<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Multiscale temporal neural dynamics predict performance in a complex sensorimotor task</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-07-04">July 4, 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wojciech</forename><surname>Samek</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Machine Learning Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Fraunhofer Heinrich Hertz Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Duncan</forename><forename type="middle">A J</forename><surname>Blythe</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Machine Learning Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Berlin Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Gabriel</forename><surname>Curio</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Neurophysics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité University Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Bernstein Center for Computational Neuroscience</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Klaus-Robert</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Machine Learning Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Berlin Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Brain and Cognitive Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Korea University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Benjamin</forename><surname>Blankertz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Neurotechnology Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Berlin Institute of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Vadim</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Nikulin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Neurophysics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité University Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for Cognition and Decision Making</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">National Research University Higher School of Economics</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="RU">Russian Federation</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Multiscale temporal neural dynamics predict performance in a complex sensorimotor task</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-07-04">July 4, 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">26968F944793F34E7E66B8C3AEDB4453</idno>
					<note type="submission">Preprint submitted to Elsevier</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:09+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Ongoing neuronal oscillations are pivotal in brain functioning and are known to influence subjects' performance.</s><s>This modulation is usually studied on short time scales whilst multiple time scales are rarely considered.</s><s>In our study we show that Long-Range Temporal Correlations (LRTCs) estimated from the amplitude of EEG oscillations over a range of time-scales predict performance in a complex sensorimotor task, based on Brain-Computer Interfacing (BCI).</s><s>Our paradigm involved eighty subjects generating covert motor responses to dynamically changing visual cues and thus controlling a computer program through the modulation of neuronal oscillations.</s><s>The neuronal dynamics were estimated with multichannel EEG.</s><s>Our results show that: (a) BCI task accuracy may be predicted on the basis of LRTCs measured during the preceding training session, and (b) this result is spatially specific, since we find that LRTCs measured over the sensorimotor areas were most predictive of the task performance.</s><s>Our results provide direct empirical evidence in addition to previous theoretical work suggesting that scale-free neuronal dynamics are important for optimal brain functioning.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p><s>While many neuronal operations occur over specific and often limited time scales, there is growing consensus that in order to develop a complete picture of neuronal functioning, brain activity should be viewed simultaneously over a range of time scales <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>, an approach which is justified by recent work suggesting that the brain operates at a "critical" state.</s><s>The theory of criticality implies that neuronal firing occurs in the form of avalanches <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> consisting of bursts of simultaneous neuronal firing of variable size and duration.</s><s>The duration and the size of such avalanches at criticality follow a power law distribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, implying scale free behavior of neuronal activation which results from the system being poised at a phase transition.</s><s>In the case of neural systems, its position close to a phase transition implies a balance between excitation and inhibition <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s><s>A number of theoretical and empirical studies indicate that the functional $ WS and DAJB contributed equally to this work * Corresponding author at: Fraunhofer Heinrich Hertz Institute, Machine Learning Group, Einsteinufer 37, 10587 Berlin, Germany.</s><s>E-mail address: wojciech.samek@hhi.fraunhofer.de.</s><s>Telephone/Fax number: +49(0)30 31002 417/190.</s><s>implications of such a critical state include maximizing dynamic range <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>, information transfer <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> and information capacity <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> in brain functioning.</s></p><p><s>Criticality manifests itself not only in the presence of aperiodic avalanches but also in slowly decaying autocorrelations in the amplitude dynamics of neuronal oscillations <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>.</s><s>Correlations such as these are often referred to as Long-Range Temporal Correlations (LRTCs) with the corresponding spectra of the amplitude envelopes having 1/f α shape.</s><s>Importantly, avalanche dynamics and LRTCs in neuronal oscillations have been found to occur simultaneously <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>; this connection between LRTCs in the ampltiude envelopes of oscillations and critical dynamics, coupled with the fact that such dynamics have been shown to be important for optimal neuronal processing, suggests that measuring LRTCs of neuronal oscillations (such as alpha/ mu oscillations) could prove to be an important measure of how close the networks under study are to the "theoretical optimum" at criticality.</s><s>These considerations motivated our empirical study of the relationship between LRTCs estimated from the amplitude envelopes of oscillations and task performance.</s></p><p><s>The physiological implications of LRTCs were elucidated by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> where it was shown that LRTCs and critical dynamics arise simultaneously in networks in which excitation and inhibition are balanced; such a balance causes oscillations to arise spontaneously, but not to spiral out of control and likewise not to be completely extinguished by inhibitory neurons-this leads to optimal signal propagation through the network as shown by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>As a measure of multi-scale dynamics LRTCs are particularly attractive for the study of the human brain.</s><s>They can be assessed with non-invasive recordings such as EEG and MEG.</s><s>Due to the continuous nature of EEG/MEG, a separation of the time-series into avalanches and inactivity is often not feasible <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>, whereas LRTCs may be estimated directly from continuous time-series.</s><s>Interesting is that LRTCs have been observed not only in electrophysiological recordings but also in behavioral measures such as reaction times <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s><s>Moreover, recent studies have shown that LRTCs in the amplitude dynamics of neuronal oscillations correlate with LRTCs in motor tapping <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> and with LRTCs in perceptual hit rate <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</s><s>However, given the predictions from previous studies regarding the relevance of power-law dynamics for brain functioning, the most important question remains open: whether LRTCs in neuronal oscillations directly predict cognitive performance and whether this predictive power extends to activities involving distributed brain areas.</s></p><p><s>In the present study we used BCI on the basis of motor imagery (MI) which is known to effectively modulate sensorimotor oscillations.</s><s>MI is defined as mental simulation of an action without the activation of effectors <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref>.</s><s>In the context of BCI subjects perform specific MI depending on the type of visual stimuli, requiring them to move the cursor to a designated part of the screen.</s><s>Thus performance in BCI depends on complex neuronal activations including processing of the visual stimuli, selection and generation of the appropriate MI, and the following assessment of the intended result according to the actual position of the cursor on the screen.</s><s>While BCI commands are conventionally generated on the basis of activity lasting a few hundreds of milliseconds <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>, it remains open whether cortical states, extending over time-scales up to tens of seconds, may be helpful in the prediction of BCI performance.</s><s>In order to address this question we use LRTCs, which are consistent with the presence of criticality in neuronal dynamics, in order to predict subjects' performance in sensorimotor BCI.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Materials and Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Data set</head><p><s>We study the Vital BCI data set <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, which comprises the EEG recordings of 80 subjects performing motor imagery with the left hand, right hand or feet.</s><s>Motor imagery is defined as the mental simulation of a specific action, e.g., the kinesthetic imagination of a movement with the left hand, without any corresponding motor output <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</s><s>All participants (41 female, age 29.9±11.5years; 4 left-handed) were BCI-novices and had not been diagnosed at the time of the experiment with any neurological diseases.</s><s>The experiment consisted of a training and a subsequent feedback session which were recorded on the same day with a break of about 10-15 minutes.</s><s>The experimental procedures were approved by the local ethics committee and all subjects gave informed consent.</s></p><p><s>Participants were positioned seated in a comfortable chair with arms on armrests.</s><s>Electroencephalography (EEG) signals were recorded from the scalp using an extended 10-20 electrode system with 119 Ag/AgCl electrodes (EasyCap, Munich, Germany) and multi-channel amplifiers (BrainAmp DC by Brain Products, Munich, Germany).</s><s>The sampling rate was set to 1000 Hz with a band-pass filter of 0.05 Hz to 200 Hz and the reference was at nasion.</s><s>The BCI experiment started with one run of real movements and three training runs of imagined movements, each containing 25 trials each of: left hand, right hand, and right foot or feet movements.</s><s>Each trial lasted 8 seconds with a baseline period of 2 sec, a 4 sec motor imagery period and a 2 sec rest period.</s><s>The motor task to perform was indicated by visual cues being arrows pointing left, right or down.</s><s>After every 20 trials there was a break of 15 sec.</s><s>In total 225 motor imagery trials were recorded during the training session indicating left, right or foot imagery, respectively.</s><s>Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> summarizes the experimental protocol.</s></p><p><s>After training the two motor imagery classes yielding highest classification accuracy were selected using cross-validation <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</s><s>Out of 80 subjects analyzed, the optimal pair chosen was left/ right hand for 30 subjects, left hand/ foot for 34 subjects and right hand/ foot for 16 subjects.</s><s>Subsequently three online BCI feedback runs, each of 100 trials, were performed with these two classes.</s><s>For some participants only one or two runs were recorded due to fatigue (N = 3) or lack of time (N = 7).</s><s>A bias adaptation technique <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> based on the first 20 trials was adopted.</s><s>During feedback, as in the training stage, each trial began with a baseline period of 2 sec where a black fixation cross was presented in the center of a grey screen.</s><s>The arrow indicating the target motor imagery class, i.e., the type of movement (left, right hand or feet) the user was asked to imagine in this particular trial, appeared for 1 sec; then the cross turned purple and moved according to the classifier output.</s><s>After 4 sec of cursor movement the cross froze at the final position and turned black again.</s><s>Two seconds later the cross was reset to the central position and the next trial began.</s></p><p><s>The classification score was indicated during the 15 second break between every block of 20 trials.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Preprocessing &amp; BCI classification</head><p><s>The preprocessing steps consist of spectral filtering, extraction of informative time segments and artifact removal.</s><s>For each of the 80 subjects first we downsampled the signal to 100 Hz and selected 62 electrodes densely covering the sensorimotor cortices.</s><s>Noisy electrodes were then removed using the method proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</s><s>The EEG was filtered in a restricted frequency range with a 5th order Butterworth filter and cut into epochs.</s><s>In order to reduce the impact of EEG artifacts on BCI training, we removed outlier trials <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Then we selected subject-specific frequency ranges and time segments by cross-validation on the training data <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>For dimensionality reduction spatial filtering is performed using Common Spatial Patterns (CSP) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>.</s><s>This method is a popular preprocessing approach, because it improves the signal to noise ratio by enhancing the amplitude changes relating to event-related synchronization and desynchronization (ERS/ERD) <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>.</s><s>These effects are induced by motor imagery and reflect sensorimotor brain activity resulting in an amplitude decrease (ERD) or increase (ERS) of oscillatory components, typically in the alpha or beta frequency range.</s></p><p><s>Applied to band passed signals CSP finds spatial filters that maximize the band power differences between motor imagery classes.</s><s>Technically, CSP solves the generalized eigenvalue problem</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Σ 1 w j = λ j Σ 2 w j<label>(1)</label></formula><p><s>where Σ 1 and Σ 2 are the average covariance matrices estimated for the two motor imagery classes.</s></p><p><s>CSP filters are sorted according to their ability to separate motor imagery conditions.</s><s>Throughout this paper we refer to the most discriminative CSP component as 1st CSP, to the second most discriminative CSP component as 2nd CSP and so on.</s><s>These transient ERDs were the basis for the BCI classification <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>After applying the CSP filters W = [w 1 . . .</s><s>w d ] ∈ R D×d to the data, each trial i was brought into the form of a feature vector:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_1">f i = log diag W X (i) (X (i) ) W<label>(2)</label></formula><p><s>The logarithmic transformation was applied in order to render the features approximately normally distributed <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</s><s>diag[ • ] denotes the operator extracting the diagonal of a matrix.</s><s>In the final step of BCI training a classifier y = h(x) separating the two motor imagery classes was computed.</s><s>We used Linear Discriminant Analysis (LDA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> for this task, which classifies trials x according to the decision criterion:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_2">h(x) = sign(v x + b)<label>(3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">with v = Σ −1 f (µ 2 − µ 1 ) and b = − 1 2 v (µ 1 + µ 2 )</formula><p><s>where µ 1 and µ 2 denote the mean feature vectors of class 1 and 2, respectively, Σ f stands for the covariance matrix of the features and sign(x) is a function with +1 for x ≥ 0 and -1 otherwise.</s></p><p><s>We computed the out-of-sample classification accuracy acc = number of correctly classified trials total number of trials</s></p><p><s>on the online feedback data for each of the 80 subjects recorded in the experiment.</s><s>More methodological details are included in the appendix.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Performance predictors</head><p><s>We use signal-to-noise ratio and Hurst exponents, both computed on the training data, to predict the performance of the subjects in the separate online feedback session.</s><s>Both predictors are computed on the six most discriminative CSP components.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1.">Signal-to-noise ratio estimation</head><p><s>In order to compute the signal-to-noise ratio (SN R) in a frequency range [f − ∆, f + ∆] we spatially filter the data by applying a CSP filter and compute the power spectrum P[f ] with Welch's method <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> using 2 sec windows.</s><s>We considered narrow frequency bins of width 5 Hz, with lower limit f −∆ = 1, 2, . . .</s><s>,40 Hz and ∆ = 2.5 Hz.</s><s>After discarding the 15 sec pause periods and outliers windows (see description in appendix) we compute SN R as the degree to which a spectral peak at f stands above the 1/f α background neural noise,</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_5">i.e., SN R(f ) = max {log(P[f ]) − q(f ) | f ∈ [f − ∆, f + ∆]}<label>(5)</label></formula><p><s>where q(•) is the linear polynomial which intercepts log(P[•]) at f − ∆ and f + ∆.</s><s>Large values correspond to pronounced peaks in the spectrum at a given frequency f (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref> middle panel), while for small SN R there are usually no peaks in the spectrum 1</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.2.">Hurst exponent and their estimation with Detrended Fluctuation Analysis</head><p><s>The Hurst exponent H, quantifies the fluctuations in a stochastic process.</s><s>For a stationary process, H may be defined formally via the auto-covariance function of the process X(t):</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_6">E(X(t)X(t + s)) − E(X(t)) 2 ∼ 1 s 2−2H ,<label>(6)</label></formula><p><s>which holds for 1 &gt; H &gt; 1 2 .</s><s>In this case the process is said to be long-range temporally correlated (LRTC) 2 .</s><s>Note that there are several Hurst exponents associated with a process X(t).</s><s>These include the Hurst exponent of X(t) but also the Hurst exponent of time-series obtained from X(t) by narrowband filtering in some frequency range.</s><s>It is exactly these narrowband exponents which we study in the following: we obtain one exponent per frequency range, using the same frequency ranges as for SN R estimation.</s></p><p><s>Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> displays amplitude dynamics of sensorimotor mu oscillations from a typical CSP component over a range of time scales.</s><s>The upper panel displays several minutes of the training run, on the basis of which H was calculated.</s><s>One observes "bursts" of alpha oscillations lasting for a few minutes, although closer inspection at a higher temporal resolution reveals that in fact within these larger bursts, transient bursts occur interleaved with periods of relative quiescence-behaviour which continues towards increasingly higher temporal resolutions (lower panel).</s></p><p><s>In order to quantify these fluctuations we estimated the Hurst exponent of a time-series by Detrended Fluctuation Analysis (DFA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref>, using a window spanning over a range of time-scales.</s><s>Using our outlier detection procedure (see appendix) DFA epochs containing outliers and scales with insufficient data were rejected.</s><s>The advantage over covariance analysis or analysis of the power-spectrum are its robustness to trends contaminating the empirical time-series and its desirable convergence properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32]</ref>.</s><s>Robustness to trends implies that if the data is contaminated by shifts in voltage then these be ignored by the DFA estimation.</s><s>The steps involved in DFA <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30]</ref> are as follows.</s><s>First one forms the aggregate sum of the empirical time-series Y (t): in our case Y (t) is the amplitude envelope of the narrowband filtered EEG obtained with the Hilbert transform.</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_7">X(t) = t i=1 Y (i)<label>(7)</label></formula><p><s>Analysis of the fluctuations in X(t) is then performed by measuring the variance of X(t) in windows of varying size n after linear detrending, i.e., X(t) is split into windows of length n, X</s></p><p><s>n , . . .</s><s>, X</s></p><p><s>n , . . .</s><s>, X</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_10">( N/n ) n</formula><p><s>and the average variance after subtracting the linear fit to the data</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_11">X (j)</formula><p><s>n in these windows is formed; i.e. let P X (j) n be the least-squares estimated linear fit of X (j) n , then the DFA coefficients or detrended variances are:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_12">F 2 DF A (n) = 1 N/n • n j X (j) n − P X (j) n X (j) n − P X (j) n =: 1 N/n • n j f 2 DF A (n, j)<label>(8)</label></formula><p><s>Crucially, in the limit of data the slope of log(F 2 DF A (n)) against log(n), the DFA estimate of the Hurst exponent H, converges to H. Thus notice that there is a distinction between the estimate H using DFA and H itself; in the limit of data these converge, however, for finite data, there will always be a difference which depends on the amount of data.</s><s>For simplicity and due to the absence of any ambiguity in the interpretation, we use simply H instead of H throughout the paper.</s><s>In Appendix D.1 we show how H can be affected by decimation and filtering of the EEG.</s><s>In Appendix D.2 linearity of the least-squares fit in DFA is assessed.</s></p><p><s>In Appendix D.3 we provide information on the effect of the window length on the estimation of H.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">BCI task performance and classification</head><p><s>The mean accuracy computed was acc = 72 ± 2% (standard deviation estimated from 500 bootstrap iterations) (median acc = 75 ± 3%).</s><s>In particular, we find that 59 of the 80 subjects performed significantly above chance according to the threshold (acc &gt; 56%) determined by a binomial test.</s><s>Notice, however, that we include all 80 subjects in the subsequent analysis because we aim at predicting a wide range of individual performances.</s></p><p><s>The spatial distribution of the topographies correspond to neuronal generators located in the sensorimotor cortices; a grand-average of the individual inverse solutions (weighted minimum norm <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref>) of CSP components confirmed the presence of maxima in the left and right sensorimotor cortices for the right and left hand motor imagery, respectively, while in a more symmetric medial location for foot motor imagery (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>).</s><s>The median ranges of the lower and higher frequencies were 9.5 Hz and 13.5 Hz, respectively, indicating that alpha oscillations were most relevant for classification, which was further confirmed by the calculation of biserial-R 2 values (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Signal-to-noise ratio</head><p><s>SN R was most pronounced in the alpha frequency range, especially for the first, most discriminative CSP component.</s><s>For all frequency ranges, we report in Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref> the grand-average values for the first and last CSP component out of the six CSP components as well as the average value over all six CSP components (denoted 'Average CSP').</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Hurst exponent values and statistics</head><p><s>Based on the criterion that a time-scale should display at least 10 epochs of outlier free data, for 99% of the Hurst exponents estimated on the first CSP filter, the largest window size lay between 29 and 55 seconds long.</s><s>Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref> displays typical DFA plots for different CSP components for a representative subject in the alpha/ mu frequency range.</s><s>Note a highly accurate linear relationship between the length of the window n (logarithmically scaled on the x-axis) and the fluctuations measured by the logarithm of DFA coefficients log(F DF A (n)) (see Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_12">8</ref>for the definition of F DF A ), thus indicating the presence of LRTC extending for at least 50 seconds in the amplitude dynamics of sensorimotor alpha oscillations.</s><s>We found that the goodness of fit (based on R 2 ) across all subjects was on average &gt; 91% and in the alpha/mu frequency range &gt;99%.</s><s>To avoid confusion with other goodness-of-fit measures used in this paper, we refer to the goodness of the linear fit of the log-DFA coefficients with the log-scale as DFA-R 2 .</s><s>In a manner similar to the SN R analysis, we calculated the dependency of Hurst exponents on the frequency of neuronal activity.</s><s>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8</ref> shows that the largest Hurst exponents are detected for alpha and beta oscillations, especially for the most discriminative CSP component.</s><s>All six CSP components displayed significant LRTC behavior (H &gt; 0.5) for all frequencies (p 0.001; Wilcoxon sign rank test on exponent values), see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Dependency between signal-to-noise ratio and Hurst exponent values</head><p><s>We computed correlations between signal-to-noise ratio and Hurst exponents (SN R and H).</s><s>As already noted by <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref>, SN R confounds the measurement of Hurst exponents-a higher SN R results in the measurement of larger Hurst exponents than in the presence of higher noise levels.</s><s>We find indeed that H and SN R are positively correlated (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">9</ref>), with the most pronounced correlations in the alpha range (r = 0.56, p 0.001; Student t approximation to distribution of Spearman's correlation coefficient).</s><s>After a Bonferroni correction <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref> controlling for multiple testing the correlation is significant (p &lt; 0.001, number of tests=40 (number of frequency bands)).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.">Sensorimotor Cortex Hurst exponent values predict task performance</head><p><s>We calculated Spearman correlations between Hurst exponents, H, and BCI task performance, acc.</s><s>This correlation analysis was performed for all frequencies between 1-40 Hz in analogy to the analysis performed for H and SN R statistics.</s><s>For the comparison we measured correlations between SN R and acc.</s></p><p><s>Traces of Hurst exponent values over frequencies for the first CSP component are plotted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref> as an image, when sorted in an ascending order with respect to BCI performance, acc.</s><s>The image clearly shows that higher exponents correspond to improved performance, which is especially visible for oscillations in the alpha frequency range.</s><s>Less pronounced but still visible is the peak in the beta frequency range.</s><s>Interestingly, these peaks resemble the location of the peaks in the biserial-R 2 distribution (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>) showing which frequencies were most discriminative for classification (see Appendix C.2 for the definition of biserial-R 2 values-these should be distinguished from the DFA-R 2 values).</s><s>This may be explained as follows: since we require variability in H to predict performance and since a larger mean in a frequency band also coincides with greater variability, then the mean exponent per frequency also coincides with predictive power (i.e.</s><s>biserial-R 2 ).</s><s>The left panel of Figure <ref type="figure">10</ref> displays a scatter-plot between Hurst exponents and BCI performance, acc, for the first CSP component (r = 0.56, p &lt; 0.001; frequency band 10-15 Hz).</s><s>The right panel of Figure <ref type="figure">10</ref> displays a corresponding scatter-plot between SN R and acc (r = 0.52, p &lt; 0.001).</s><s>When training a linear regression model on N − 1 subjects using their H (or SN R) and acc values and using it to predict the performance of a new subject (leave-one-subject-out approach), we found that H and SN R explains 28%</s></p><p><s>and 27% of the variance of acc, respectively.</s><s>Even when H was averaged across frequencies (for the first CSP component), we found it remains predictive of acc (r = 0.45, p &lt; 0.001).</s><s>Finally we found these results to be robust even to removing subjects who did not perform significantly above the chance level, 56% (r = 0.35, p &lt; 0.01; frequency band 10-15 Hz).</s><s>We also tested whether the correlation between H and acc can be explained in a binary way, i.e. depending on whether a subject performed above chance or not.</s><s>For that we constructed a binary variable by dividing subjects into two groups on the basis of their performance: acc ≤ 56% and acc &gt; 56% (56% is the significantly-above-chance performance level).</s></p><p><s>The partial correlation between H and acc remains significant when regressing out this binary variable (r = 0.30, p &lt; 0.01; frequency band 10-15 Hz).</s><s>Also bootstrapping and application of Wilcoxon signed-rank test confirmed that the correlation between continuous acc values and H is significantly larger (p 0.001) than the correlation between H and the binary variable (the latter calculations were based on point-biserial correlation).</s></p><p><s>A comprehensive overview of the correlation between H and acc by frequency bin is displayed in the first column of Figure <ref type="figure">11</ref>.</s><s>We found that correlations peak in the mu/alpha range are particularly pronounced for the first and average CSP components, where the correlations are significant even after a very conservative Bonferroni correction.</s><s>We found that the peak is negligible for the last (i.e.</s><s>sixth most discriminative) CSP component.</s></p><p><s>The correlation between SN R and acc by frequency is displayed in the second column of Figure <ref type="figure">11</ref>.</s><s>The figure demonstrates that SN R values are also predictive of BCI performance in the alpha frequency range.</s></p><p><s>Likewise, we found that there is a significant correlation between average SN R over frequencies and acc (r = 0.32, p &lt; 0.01); however the correlation is much weaker than the correlation between H and acc.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6.">Hurst exponent predictions cannot be explained in terms of signal-to-noise ratio</head><p><s>Since we observed that SN R and Hurst exponents are cross-correlated, and that SN R also predicts performance, we used partial correlations to determine whether the predictive power of H is independent of the predictive power of SN R values; see appendix for a review of partial correlation analysis.</s></p><p><s>We found that even after controlling for SN R, the predictive power of Hurst exponents of BCI performance is significant.</s><s>For the average H over frequencies on the first CSP component we found that after controlling for the effect of the average SN R, a significant correlation remains (r = 0.42, p &lt; 0.001).</s><s>The same analysis performed for SN R, controlling for H yields a much weaker correlation (r = 0.24, p &lt; 0.05).</s></p><p><s>Partial correlations for individual frequency bands are displayed in the third and fourth columns of Figure <ref type="figure">11</ref>.</s><s>In order to rigorously check whether the correlations between frequency-wise H values and acc do not depend on SN R, we controlled not only for SN R and H values in the same frequency range (for each bin in the range 1-40 Hz) but also for separate frequencies.</s><s>To do this for each pair of frequency bins (i, j) for i, j ∈ { 1 Hz, 2 Hz, . . .</s><s>, 40 Hz }, we calculated a partial correlation</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_13">r i,j = corr(H i , acc | SN R j )<label>(9)</label></formula><p><s>The most stringent control for correlation between H i and acc is given by r * i = min j {r i,j }. r * i may be thought of as the lowest partial correlation which results from controlling for the potentially confounding effect of SN R in all frequencies.</s></p><p><s>Having performed this analysis for the first CSP filter we found that the largest worst case partial correlation for individual frequency bands is nevertheless highly significant (r * = 0.37, p &lt; 0.001).</s><s>After a Bonferroni correction controlling for multiple testing this result is still significant (p = 0.005, n = 40, number of frequency bands).</s><s>An analogous result also holds for the average H across all CSP components.</s><s>On the other hand, after controlling for H, we found that after multiple testing correction SN R over frequencies is not significantly predictive of performance for any of the CSP components considered (p &gt; 0.05).</s></p><p><s>To make sure that the correlations are not due to a binary effect we performed similar analysis on the subjects who performed significantly above the chance level (acc &gt; 56%).</s><s>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">12</ref> shows the partial correlation between BCI classification accuracy and H or signal-to-noise ratio with the effects of SN R or H respectively being removed.</s><s>As before after controlling for SN R, the Hurst exponent is significantly (after multiple testing correction, p &lt; 0.05) predictive of the performance; this is not the case for SN R.</s><s>This result not only holds for the average CSP, but also for the first CSP component.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p><s>Using multichannel EEG, we showed that the performance in a complex sensorimotor task can be predicted on the basis of the neuronal dynamics of neuronal oscillations.</s><s>This prediction is frequency specific and involves oscillations generated in the Rolandic brain area.</s><s>Below we discuss the robustness of the results obtained and provide a tentative neurophysiological explanation for this predictive power, emphasizing the role of power-law dynamics in neuronal information processing.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Task performance and classifiers</head><p><s>We trained a classifier for each of 80 subjects, obtaining a median accuracy of 75%, which corresponds closely to the performance of state-of-the-art classification procedures for naïve BCI subjects <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>.</s><s>The classifiers were based on well-tested standards for sensorimotor BCI <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref> and included optimization of spatial filters, frequency ranges and feature selection.</s><s>CSP patterns could be modeled with sources located in the sensorimotor areas of the cortex, which is in agreement with previous BCI studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38]</ref> and demonstrated a somatotopy relating to hand and foot activations.</s><s>While LRTCs were systematically calculated for all frequency ranges, we found that Hurst exponents in the alpha-frequency range have the highest predictive power, with the second best frequency window in the beta range; this finding relates to the central role of mu oscillations in sensorimotor processing <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref>.</s><s>Note that, although for the evaluation of LRTCs we used data from the training condition, requiring subjects to perform motor imagery, the temporal scales of DFA analysis far exceeded (Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref>) the time scale over which the transient modulation of oscillations ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_4">4</ref>seconds) due to the performance of motor-imagery occurred, with DFA windows extending up to 55 seconds.</s><s>Such estimation of LRTCs during task conditions has also been performed in other studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42]</ref> leading to the insight that transient modulation of neuronal dynamics does not abolish LRTCs.</s><s>In fact, task-related performance may even allow subjects to remain more vigilant, preventing them from drowsiness, which is a risk factor during purely resting-state conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Task prediction on the basis of SNR and LRTCs</head><p><s>We showed that the predictive power of Hurst exponents cannot be explained by the confounding effect of SN R. The authors of <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[34]</ref> showed that the estimation of Hurst exponents may be biased by SN R: smaller SN R leads to an attenuation of exponents, moving estimates closer to the 0.5 value characteristic of white noise.</s><s>Thus it might be argued that Hurst exponents are predictive of the BCI performance only due to their correlation with SN R, which has been shown to predict BCI performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44]</ref>.</s><s>As an estimator for SN R we used the amplitude of the spectral peaks relative to the 1/f α noise floor.</s><s>Importantly, however, such a prediction does not carry neurophysiological information since it may be reduced to how well neuronal oscillations may be extracted from the background neuronal noise.</s><s>Figure <ref type="figure">11</ref> in fact shows that when SNR from all CSP components is taken into account (third column, third row), the task accuracy can still be predicted from the Hurst exponents, while when the Hurst exponents from all CSP components are taken into account, no prediction could be obtained between SNR and task accuracy (third column, fourth row).</s><s>This provides a strong evidence for the task-performance prediction not being explained in terms of SNR.</s><s>This furthermore implies that the predictive power gained by the Hurst exponents cannot be simply due to the signal quality on the scalp and that the exponents rather reflect neurophysiological aspects of dynamic neuronal activity which predict performance.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Neuronal oscillations predict task performance</head><p><s>A number of previous studies showed that the performance in different tasks might relate to the amplitude <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46]</ref> or phase <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref> of ongoing oscillations immediately preceding the stimulus requiring behavioral response.</s></p><p><s>The usual interpretation of such dependencies is based on changes of cortical excitability or in general on a neuronal propensity to respond given a neuronal state directly preceding the stimulus.</s><s>In the present study, however, we were interested instead in how the task performance can be predicted from the neuronal dynamics recorded in a separate experimental session, thus relating performance with subject-specific persistent features of neuronal activation.</s><s>BCI systems, which use sensorimotor oscillations, require the monitoring of visual stimuli and continuous generation of covert motor activity depending on the position of the cursor on the screen.</s><s>An advantage of the BCI paradigm is that it allows for the study of motor behavior without the confounding factors associated with overt movements, such as proprioceptive feedback, which can strongly modulate ongoing neuronal oscillations <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>.</s><s>Successful BCI performance is thus primarily based on the ability of subjects to quickly generate the appropriate modulation of ongoing oscillations in response to the visual cues.</s><s>Thus, in the case of BCI, performance is directly defined by very specific neuronal events, which, in our case, correspond to event-related desynchronization (ERD) of the sensorimotor rhythms <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48]</ref>.</s><s>This in turn allows us to be specific in interpreting the factors defining performance.</s><s>ERD of sensorimotor oscillations has long been associated with the active participation of a given cortical area in the task <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>, while an increase in the amplitude of oscillations (event-related synchronization) is thought to correspond to active inhibition <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46]</ref>.</s><s>Preventing a cursor moving in one direction and immediately moving it in another direction requires swift switching between ERD in one somatotopic cortical location to the subsequent generation of an ERD response in another location.</s><s>In neurophysiological terms this translates to rapidly alternating states of cortical excitation and inhibition leading to a selective modulation of neuronal activity.</s><s>Such coordination between excitation and inhibition is likely to benefit from the underlying neuronal networks moving fluently from one state to the other.</s><s>Interestingly, it has recently been shown in a computational study <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, that stronger LRTCs in neuronal oscillations may relate to a balance between excitation and inhibition.</s><s>Thus stronger LRTCs may represent a suitable background condition for the rapid modulation of neuronal oscillations.</s><s>This in turn provides a possible explanation for the positive correlation between LRTCs and BCI performance which requires rapid switching between the cortical states.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">Implications for BCI Practioners</head><p><s>For BCI researchers the question arises how to make use of the results presented in this paper in practice.</s></p><p><s>Since Hurst exponent estimates were shown to correlate with performance, one possible practical application would be to use these predictors for subject pre-screening.</s><s>This would save time as poorly performing subjects would be identified and excluded from the experiment and a different experimental paradigm could be used in their case.</s><s>Another possible field of application of the presented results is the improvement of the BCI signal processing methods.</s><s>For instance, one might apply the Hurst exponent for selecting the number of spatial filters by only selecting filters with H values larger than a predefined threshold.</s><s>Alternatively the CSP algorithm could be regularized towards sources exhibiting large H values, similar to the approach in <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50]</ref> where CSP was regularized towards stationarity.</s><s>Hurst exponents could also be used for selecting the most informative frequency band for each subject.</s><s>In addition to these technical applications, Hurst exponents combined with neurofeedback techniques could be used to improve the subjects capability to perform BCI.</s></p><p><s>More precisely, on the basis of our findings we conjecture that if subjects were to learn how to optimize their neuronal states leading to increased Hurst exponents, then they could potentially improve in control of a BCI.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5.">Effect Size</head><p><s>The strength of the correlation reflects the effect size and in our study even after the most stringent control for the possible confounding effect of SNR, the strength of the correlation between H and the task performance was at least 0.37.</s><s>The interpretation of the effect size may vary from discipline to discipline, but it is not uncommon to refer to the correlation of 0.3 or higher as moderate <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref>.</s><s>Given the noninvasive character of the recordings, the correlation values obtained in the present study are not insubstantial.</s></p><p><s>Clearly temporal dynamics are not the only factor determining the task performance; however, the obtained correlation establishes a link between LRTCs in neuronal oscillations and task performance.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.6.">Are dynamics genuinely scale-free?</head><p><s>The time-scales studied in this paper ranged between 4 seconds and 1 minute.</s><s>On this basis alone we may not be able to claim that the dynamics studied are scale-free.</s><s>Due to the nature of the task, we were unable to use longer time-scales in all subjects, because of the occasional outliers in EEG activity induced by task performance.</s><s>However, in Appendix D.3, we in addition estimated Hurst exponents in the range 0.5-81 seconds (in subjects where this data was available) and found that they were strongly correlated (r = 0.90) with the exponents estimated in the 4-54 seconds range.</s><s>The range 0.5-81 seconds covers two orders of magnitude reflecting a similar range of magnitudes reported for alpha oscillations elsewhere in the literature (for example <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref>).</s><s>However, as we show in Appendix D.1, using very short windows may introduce a small positive bias in the estimation of Hurst exponents and that is why we rather considered time windows starting from 4 seconds.</s><s>Moreover, it is known from studies at rest that alpha/ mu oscillations are scale-free over at least two orders of magnitude <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref> and remain so even during sensory stimulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref>.</s><s>Discussion of the limitations of finite-size data for the estimation of Hurst exponents can also be found in other studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55]</ref>.</s><s>While acknowledging these limitations, the authors in the abovementioned studies argue that shorter time segments may allow the extrapolation of neuronal dynamics over longer scales.</s><s>While unequivocal demonstration of the scale-free dynamics requires very long time series, DFA is known to reliably estimate scaling exponents when using even short data segments <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Moreover in Appendix D.2 we analyse whether the scaling analysed with DFA is scale-free or non-linear over the range of magnitudes studied.</s><s>We find that there is a small systematic departure from genuine monofractal scaling.</s><s>However the increase in DFA-R 2 is less than 0.005, thus not yielding a large increase in explanatory power.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.7.">Task performance and power-law dynamics</head><p><s>Although the presence of LRTCs does not constitute conclusive proof of the existence of criticality in a neural system, it is nonetheless consistent with this hypothesis <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>.</s><s>The main finding of our study is that LRTCs are advantageous for brain function, as has been conjectured, for critical dynamics.</s><s>Previous research has revealed that Hurst exponents in the amplitude dynamics of ongoing oscillations correlate with Hurst exponents in motor tapping <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> and with Hurst exponents of subliminal-stimulus detection <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</s><s>These studies, however, did not provide direct evidence that the presence of LRTCs predicts task performance as shown in our study.</s><s>Indeed, it is exactly performance itself not its variability which is most important for understanding the functional significance of LRTCs.</s><s>In general our work contributes to growing evidence that power-law neuronal dynamics might be beneficial for brain functioning as shown previously for dynamic stimulus range <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>, information capacity <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> and information transmission <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s>The fact, that we could predict task performance from LRTCs determined during the training session, indicates that power-law dynamics are subject-specific.</s><s>This is in line with findings that LRTCs are genetically defined <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref> and have significant test-retest reliability <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref> showing stability of individual LRTCs across many days.</s><s>In addition, the existence of subject-specific LRTCs is further confirmed by demonstrating that LRTCs are sensitive biomarkers of pathological neuronal activity in a variety of diseases such as Schizophrenia <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[57]</ref>, Parkinson's <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[58]</ref> and Alzheimer Disease <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[59]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In conclusion, we have shown that power-law dynamics in the amplitude of neuronal oscillations, estimated collectively over a range of time scales, predict subjects' performance in a complex sensorimotor task.</s><s>This finding provides a direct demonstration for the functional relevance of scale-free critical organization of neuronal activation in the human brain.</s><s><ref type="figure">3</ref>: The scale free nature of oscillation amplitudes.</s><s>The time-series are amplitude envelopes from a typical CSP component, where single trials are marked in red at the smallest time scale.</s><s>On the time scales of minutes bursts of neuronal activity are clearly distinguishable (top row).</s><s>Within these bursts finer bursts lasting less than a minute can be identified (second row).</s><s>Furthermore within these finer bursts one can observe bursts of activity on the time scale of single trials (bottom row).</s><s>These scale-free dynamics of neural activity indicate that the signal contains information on multiple time-scales.</s><s><ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">12</ref>: Partial correlation between BCI classification accuracy and Hurst exponents or signal-to-noise ratio with the effects of SN R or H respectively being removed for subjects who performed significantly above the chance level.</s><s>In each case the black line denotes the p = 0.05 threshold; the green line, p = 0.01; the dotted purple line, the FDR corrected p = 0.05 threshold; and the red line, the Bonferroni corrected p = 0.05 threshold for n = 40.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Left Foot Right</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2 displays typical topographies of the two most discriminative CSP [23] components which define the features on which the final classification is performed.</s><s>The middle panel of Figure 2 also displays powerspectral densities of CSP components with typical peaks in the alpha (∼ 10 Hz) and beta (∼ 20 Hz) frequency ranges.</s><s>The lower panel of the figure displays time-resolved event-related desynchronization (ERD) of the amplitude of alpha oscillations during left/right hand motor imagery: note stronger attenuation of the oscillations in the left and right hemispheres for the imagery of right and left hand movements, respectively.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2: An example of EEG patterns relating to the task performance: the top panels display two sensorimotor CSP topographies, the middle panels their corresponding power-spectra during training epochs, with blue and green lines indicating left and right hand imagery, respectively, and the bottom row displays event related desynchronization (ERD) responses.</s><s>For left hand motor imagery (left column) the CSP pattern shows an activation over the right sensorimotor cortex and the power spectrum (blue line) displays a strong power decrease in the alpha and beta band.</s><s>The event related desynchronization response of the alpha band filtered signal depicts the time course of the power decrease.</s><s>For right hand motor imagery (right column, green lines) the responses are analogous.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure3: The scale free nature of oscillation amplitudes.</s><s>The time-series are amplitude envelopes from a typical CSP component, where single trials are marked in red at the smallest time scale.</s><s>On the time scales of minutes bursts of neuronal activity are clearly distinguishable (top row).</s><s>Within these bursts finer bursts lasting less than a minute can be identified (second row).</s><s>Furthermore within these finer bursts one can observe bursts of activity on the time scale of single trials (bottom row).</s><s>These scale-free dynamics of neural activity indicate that the signal contains information on multiple time-scales.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4: Grand-average weighted minimum norm inverse solutions for the most discriminative CSP patterns from each class: left, foot, and right hand motor imagery.</s><s>The results confirm the sensorimotor origin of the most discriminative CSP components considered.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="24,215.75,129.78,170.17,188.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5: Sorting frequency-specific Hurst exponents according to individual BCI performance.</s><s>The left panel displays Hurst exponents H (in color) for each frequency bin of the first CSP component.</s><s>Subject-specific components are sorted according the BCI performance (y-axis).</s><s>The right panel depicts the average biserial-R 2 in the explanation of acc by H values for a range of frequency bands of the first CSP component.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="24,100.51,441.93,168.57,168.57" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6 :Figure 7 :</head><label>67</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure6: Grand-average signal-to-noise ratios for CSP components for each frequency.</s><s>Left: The most discriminative CSP component; middle: the sixth CSP component; right: the average across the six most discriminative CSP components.</s><s>The results show that signal-to-noise ratio is highest in the mu/alpha range ≈ 10 Hz).</s><s>For the most discriminative CSP component the SN R value is close to 1 whereas for the last CSP component it is significantly smaller and not frequency specific.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 8: Grand-average Hurst exponents for the first CSP component at each frequency (left), the last CSP component (middle) and the average across CSP components (right).</s><s>The results show that Hurst exponents are highest in the mu/alpha range, but are also elevated in the beta range.</s><s>For the last CSP component the H values do not show discernible peaks in these frequency ranges.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Freq</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 9 :</head><label>9</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 9: Correlations between signal-to-noise ratio and Hurst exponents for the first CSP component at each frequency (left), the last CSP component (middle) and the average across CSP components (right).</s><s>In each case the black line denotes the p = 0.05 threshold; the green line, p = 0.01; the dotted purple line, the FDR corrected p = 0.05 threshold; and the red line, the Bonferroni corrected p = 0.05 threshold for n = 40.</s><s>The results show that Hurst exponents and signal-to-noise ratio are significantly correlated in the alpha range but not outside this range.</s><s>For the last CSP component significant correlation is lacking for all frequencies.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 10 :Figure 11 :Freq</head><label>1011</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 10: Prediction of BCI classification accuracy.</s><s>The figure displays scatter plots of Hurst exponents, H, BCI classification accuracy acc and signal-to-noise ratio, SN R. The H and SN R values were estimated in the 10-15 Hz range on the first (most discriminative) CSP component, whereas acc was computed on multiple CSP components and a subject-specific frequency band.</s><s>The results show that both H and SN R are highly correlated with classification accuracy.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure12: Partial correlation between BCI classification accuracy and Hurst exponents or signal-to-noise ratio with the effects of SN R or H respectively being removed for subjects who performed significantly above the chance level.</s><s>In each case the black line denotes the p = 0.05 threshold; the green line, p = 0.01; the dotted purple line, the FDR corrected p = 0.05 threshold; and the red line, the Bonferroni corrected p = 0.05 threshold for n = 40.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="1,42.47,354.31,518.77,241.03" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1">Note that negative values correspond to troughs in the power-spectrum. In practice, however, we find that significant troughs do not occur.2 An instance of a process with H ∈ (0, 1) is fractional Gaussian noise, which is defined as the increments of fractional Brownian motion<ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29]</ref>.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgement</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A. Selection of Spatial Filters</head><p><s>We selected three filters with the lowest and highest median variance scores s j , which we then sorted according to discriminativity max(s j , 1 − s j ) in decreasing order.</s><s>Note that the median variance score s j of the jth CSP filter was computed as s j = median i (var(w j X (i) )) D k=1 median i (var(w k X (i) ))</s></p><p><s>where X (i) denotes the band-pass filtered signal of ith trial and var(•) stands for the variance operator.</s><s>We preferred the median score over using the eigenvalues λ j (mean score) in virtue of its greater robustness to outliers.</s><s>We used the heuristic of <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> to choose the optimal number of filters; note that despite this variable number of filters for computation of the optimal classifier, we always compute six CSP filters using fix parameters (i.e., frequency range, time segment) for computation of SN R and H values.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix B. Outlier Removal</head><p><s>In our subsequent analysis we estimate Hurst exponents on the amplitude envelope time-series of oscillations during execution of a training session.</s><s>Although transient modulations of oscillations occur during motor imagery, we consider ongoing EEG activity over long time periods of about 30-50 seconds which allows the estimation of amplitude variations over a range of time scales.</s><s>Estimation of LRTC during tasks have also been previously performed in a number of studies.</s><s>It is also important to note that Hurst exponents were estimated in the training session, while we estimated BCI performance in the subsequent feedback phase of the experiment.</s></p><p><s>We applied the following outlier detection procedure prior to the DFA:</s></p><p><s>1. Find all outlier time-points X(t i ) s.t.</s><s>|X(t i ) − µ| &gt; 4σ where σ is the standard deviation and µ the mean of X(t).</s></p><p><s>2. Remove these outliers and repeat 1. recursively until no outliers remain.</s></p><p><s>3. Record all outliers obtained from every step of the recursion.</s></p><p><s>The motivation for the recursive step was that, since outliers may be present on a range of scales, the less pronounced outliers may be missed during the first iteration.</s><s>After this outlier detection step, we rejected all DFA epochs f 2 DF A (n, j) which spanned time indices including outliers.</s><s>In order to avoid frequent exclusion of large segments, we restrict DFA estimation to a range n such that there are at least 10 segments per scale available after outlier rejection.</s><s>This approach to outlier rejection for DFA was necessary to ensure that the time-series structure of the data was preserved; simply cutting out portions of data may have introduced spurious autocorrelations which might bias the DFA procedure.</s><s>We dealt with pauses in the experimental session in a similar manner by requiring that all DFA epochs f 2 DF A (n, j) should range over time-indices from a continuous stretch of the experiment's duration, i.e. not spanning stretches separated by pauses.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix C. Mathematical Details</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix C.1. Partial correlation analysis</head><p><s>Several steps of our analysis require the estimation of a partial correlation between two variables (X, Y ) but controlling for the effect of additional variables Z.</s><s>This amounts to measuring the correlation between the residuals R X and R Y of regression fits between resp.</s><s>X and Z and Y and Z.</s><s>Under the null hypothesis H 0 that X and Y are correlated only through Z, R X and R Y are uncorrelated.</s><s>In other words, partial correlation is a test for conditional independence (dependence measured by correlation) of X and Y given Z. Formally, under H 0 we assume that, for uncorrelated random variables 1 , 2 :</s></p><p><s>So these residuals are independent in the limit of data points.</s><s>In our calculations we use partialcorr.m in MATLAB, which allows for the control of correlation over an arbitrary number of variables.</s></p><p><s>Because we do not wish to assume the presence of Gaussian or linear relationships between the variables we measure, we consider non-parametric Spearman correlations.</s><s>These are related to Pearson partial correlations in exactly the same manner as the standard Spearman correlation is related to a Pearson correlation.</s><s>Thus, one considers the Pearson correlation between the residuals resulting from regressing the ranks of the values of X and Y respectively against the ranks of Z. See <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref> for further details.</s></p><p><s>The biserial-R 2 value is a general measure indicating how well data fit a statistical model.</s><s>Here we use this quantity to measure of how much variance of the joint distribution can be explained by class membership.</s></p><p><s>In this case the biserial-R 2 value is equivalent to the squared bi-serial correlation coefficient</s></p><p><s>where µ 1 and µ 2 denote the mean value of class 1 and 2, respectively, σ represents the overall standard deviation and n 1 and n 2 stand for the number of samples in the respective class.</s><s>Note that the biserial-R 2 value should be distinguished from the DFA-R 2 value.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix D. Supplementary Analyses</head><p><s>Appendix D.1.</s><s>The effect of filtering on Hurst exponent estimation</s></p><p><s>Here we present a simulation which aims at checking the size of the bias induced by the temporal smoothing yielded by decimation, filtering the signal using Butterworth filter and calculating amplitude envelope.</s><s>This corresponds to the same pipeline as applied to the EEG data for Hurst exponent estimation.</s></p><p><s>To this end, we simulate 1000 uncorrelated Gaussian noise time-series in MATLAB of length 2 × 10 6 .</s></p><p><s>We then decimate the signals to 1/10th of their sampling rate, filter using Butterworth filters of order 5 in a frequency range corresponding to 8-10 Hz assuming the sampling rate of the signal is now 100 Hz (corresponding to the signal analyzed) and calculate the amplitude envelope using the Hilbert transform.</s></p><p><s>We then estimate Hurst exponents using DFA with log-spaced window lengths between 4 and 30 seconds and between 4 and 220 seconds.</s></p><p><s>We find that the mean Hurst exponent estimated in the range 4 to 30 seconds is 0.52 and the standard deviation over estimates is σ = 0.020.</s><s>Over the range 4 to 220 seconds we find the mean estimate is 0.51 and the standard deviation over estimates is σ = 0.022.</s></p><p><s>Since the simulated noise is uncorrelated, the true Hurst exponent of its amplitude envelopes is 0.5.</s><s>This simulation shows that there is a small positive bias in estimation induced by our preprocessing pipeline but which is not large enough to explain the values of Hurst exponents we observe in our data analysis (H often larger than 0.6).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix D.2. Systematic non-linearity in the DFA fluctuation plot</head><p><s>Here we present additional data analysis to investigate whether there is a significant systematic departure from monofractal (linear log-log) scaling over the range of time-scales analysed using DFA.</s><s>If the log-log plot is significantly non-linear, then a quadratic polynomial fit should provide a substantially better fit than a linear fit.</s><s>Moreover, if the non-linearity consists of a saturation of scaling (lower-gradient at larger scales) then the x 2 coefficient in the quadratic fit should be negative.</s><s>To this end we fit quadratic polynomials to the DFA log-log plot, i.e. we fit log(F 2 (n)) as a function of log(n) in the alpha frequency range <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>We find that there is indeed a systematic saturation of scaling towards larger time-scales, as we find that the quadratic coefficient of the polynomials fitted has mean less than zero (p &lt; 0.001; Wilcoxon sign-rank).</s></p><p><s>However, we find that there is not a large change in the explained variance between the quadratic fit (mean DFA-R 2 = 0.99 ± 7.6 × 10 −4 ) and the linear fit (mean DFA-R 2 = 0.99 ± 0.0011).</s></p><p><s>Thus we conclude that while there is indeed a small systematic saturation for large time-scales, this saturation does not lead to a substantially better model-fit over the linear model.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix D.3. The effect of largest window length on Hurst exponent estimation</head><p><s>Due to the presence of outliers in the data, the longest window length available for Hurst exponent estimation is approximately one minute.</s><s>We show here, however that Hurst exponents measured over a wider range of time-scales correlate with Hurst exponents measured over a longer range of time-scales.</s></p><p><s>To this end, we estimate Hurst exponents in the alpha range (8-13Hz) between 0.5 and a maximum window length of 81 seconds and between 4 and 54 seconds respectively for all subjects.</s><s>We find a Spearman correlation of 0.90 (p &lt; 0.001) between the two estimates.</s><s>However, due to the positive bias introduced by the filtering (see Appendix D.1) we performed our main analysis using DFA analysis with time windows starting at 4 seconds.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neuronal avalanches in neocortical circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Beggs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Plenz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11167" to="11177" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Psychophysics: Are our senses critical?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Chialvo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="301" to="302" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Criticality in large-scale brain fmri dynamics unveiled by a novel point process analysis, Networking of Psychophysics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Barbieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shimono</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychology and Neurophysiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">61</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spontaneous cortical activity in awake monkeys composed of neuronal avalanches</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Petermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Thiagarajan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lebedev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nicolelis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Chialvo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Plenz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15921" to="15926" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Information capacity and transmission are maximized in balanced cortical networks with neuronal avalanches</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Shew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Plenz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-organized criticality: An explanation of the 1/f noise</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wiesenfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical review letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">381</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Critical-state dynamics of avalanches and oscillations jointly emerge from balanced excitation/inhibition in neuronal networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-S</forename><surname>Poil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hardstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mansvelder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Linkenkaer-Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9817" to="9823" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal dynamical range of excitable networks at criticality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Kinouchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Copelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature physics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="348" to="351" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neuronal avalanches imply maximum dynamic range in cortical networks at criticality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Shew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Petermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Plenz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15595" to="15600" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long-range temporal correlations and scaling behavior in human brain oscillations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Linkenkaer-Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Nikouline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Palva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ilmoniemi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1370" to="1377" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship of fast-and slow-timescale neuronal dynamics in human meg and seeg</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zhigalov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Arnulfo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Nobili</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Palva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Palva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5385" to="5396" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Blythe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Nikulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1502.07885</idno>
		<title level="m">Meta-universality classes at criticality</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scaling laws in cognitive sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ferrer-I Cancho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Holden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Linkenkaer-Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Rhodes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Van Orden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends in cognitive sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long-range temporal correlations in resting-state alpha oscillations predict human timing-error dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Smit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Linkenkaer-Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>De Geus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11212" to="11220" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neuronal long-range temporal correlations and avalanche dynamics are correlated with behavioral scaling laws</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Palva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zhigalov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hirvonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Korhonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Linkenkaer-Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Palva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3585" to="3590" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Do imagined and executed actions share the same neural substrate?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Decety</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Cognitive brain research</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="93" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The representing brain: Neural correlates of motor intention and imagery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jeannerod</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behavioral and Brain sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">02</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural simulation of action: a unifying mechanism for motor cognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jeannerod</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="S103" to="S109" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimizing spatial filters for robust EEG single-trial analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Blankertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tomioka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lemm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kawanabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-R</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Signal Processing Magazine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neurophysiological predictor of SMR-based BCI performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Blankertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sannelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Halder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kübler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-R</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Curio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dickhaus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1303" to="1309" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brain activity during visual versus kinesthetic imagery: an fmri study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Guillot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Collet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Malouin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Richards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Doyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human brain mapping</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2157" to="2172" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward unsupervised adaptation of LDA for brain-computer interfaces</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Vidaurre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kawanabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bünau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Blankertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-R</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Biomedical Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="587" to="597" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal spatial filtering of single trial EEG during imagined hand movement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ramoser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Müller-Gerking</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pfurtscheller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Rehabilitation Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="441" to="446" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Event-related EEG/MEG synchronization and desynchronization: basic principles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pfurtscheller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Lopes Da</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Silva</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical Neurophysiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1842" to="1857" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introduction to machine learning for brain imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lemm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Blankertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dickhaus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-R</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neu-roImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="387" to="399" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The use of fast fourier transform for the estimation of power spectra: a method based on time averaging over short, modified periodograms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Welch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on audio and electroacoustics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="1967">1967</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fractional brownian motions, fractional noises and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mandelbrot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Van Ness</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="422" to="437" />
			<date type="published" when="1968">1968</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Physiological time series: distinguishing fractal noises from motions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Eke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Herman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bassingthwaighte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Raymond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Percival</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Balla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ikrényi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pflügers Archiv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">439</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="415" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fractal characterization of complexity in temporal physiological signals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Eke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Herman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kocsis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kozak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiological measurement</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">R1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mosaic organization of dna nucleotides</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-K</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Buldyrev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Havlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Simons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Stanley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Goldberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physical Review E</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1685</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymptotic properties of the detrended fluctuation analysis of long-range-dependent processes, Information Theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-M</forename><surname>Bardet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kammoun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2041" to="2052" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimators for long-range dependence: an empirical study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Taqqu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Teverovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Willinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fractals</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">04</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="785" to="798" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Continuous probabilistic solutions to the biomagnetic inverse problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ioannides</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bolton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Clarke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inverse Problems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">523</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of linear mixing in the eeg on hurst exponent estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Blythe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Haufe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-R</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Nikulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="377" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple significance tests: the bonferroni method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Altman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">310</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6973</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">170</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The non-invasive berlin brain-computer interface: fast acquisition of effective performance in untrained subjects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Blankertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dornhege</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Krauledat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-R</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Curio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="550" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Localization of classrelated mu-rhythm desynchronization in motor imagery based brain-computer interface sessions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Haufe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tomioka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dickhaus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sannelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Blankertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Nolte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-R</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">32nd Annual International Conference of the IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society (EMBC)</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5137" to="5140" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale eeg/meg source localization with spatial flexibility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Haufe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tomioka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dickhaus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sannelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Blankertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Nolte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-R</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="851" to="859" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patterns of cortical activation during planning of voluntary movement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pfurtscheller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Berghold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electroencephalography and clinical neurophysiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="250" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quasi-movements: A novel motor-cognitive phenomenon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Nikulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Hohlefeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jacobs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Curio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuropsychologia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="727" to="742" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cued spatial attention drives functionally relevant modulation of the mu rhythm in primary somatosensory cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kerr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Wan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pritchett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hämäläinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13760" to="13765" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modulation of cortical neural dynamics during thalamic deep brain stimulation in patients with essential tremor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Hohlefeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ehlen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Krugel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kühn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Curio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Klostermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Nikulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroreport</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="751" to="756" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The amsterdam resting-state questionnaire reveals multiple phenotypes of resting-state cognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Diaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Der</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sluis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Moens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Benjamins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Migliorati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stoffers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-S</forename><surname>Braber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Poil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hardstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Van't Ent</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in human neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">446</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting bci subject performance using probabilistic spatio-temporal filters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-I</forename><surname>Suk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fazli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mehnert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-R</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-W</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS one</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e87056</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Now you&apos;ll feel it, now you won&apos;t: Eeg rhythms predict the effectiveness of perceptual masking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Haufe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Blankenburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Villringer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Curio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of cognitive neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2407" to="2419" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Somatosensory anticipatory alpha activity increases to suppress distracting input</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Haegens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Luther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cognitive Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="677" to="685" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spontaneous eeg oscillations reveal periodic sampling of visual attention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Busch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Vanrullen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16048" to="16053" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Current trends in graz brain-computer interface (bci) research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pfurtscheller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Neuper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Guger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Harkam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ramoser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schlogl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Obermaier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pregenzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on Rehabilitation Engineering</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Palva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Palva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">New vistas for α-frequency band oscillations</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="158" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stationary common spatial patterns for brain-computer interfacing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Samek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Vidaurre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-R</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kawanabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Neural Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">26013</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Model selection for identifying power-law scaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Daffertshofer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>NeuroImageIn press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stimulus-induced change in longrange temporal correlations and scaling behaviour of sensorimotor oscillations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Linkenkaer-Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Nikulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Palva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kaila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ilmoniemi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="218" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic contributions to long-range temporal correlations in ongoing oscillations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Linkenkaer-Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Smit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Barkil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Van Beijsterveldt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Brussaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Boomsma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Ooyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>De Geus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13882" to="13889" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Breakdown of long-range temporal dependence in default mode and attention networks during deep sleep</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tagliazucchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wegner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Morzelewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Brodbeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Jahnke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Laufs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15419" to="15424" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long-range temporal correlations in alpha and beta oscillations: effect of arousal level and test-retest reliability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Nikulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Brismar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical neurophysiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1896" to="1908" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attenuation of long-range temporal correlations in the amplitude dynamics of alpha and beta neuronal oscillations in patients with schizophrenia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Nikulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Jönsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Brismar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="162" to="169" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Longrange temporal correlations in the subthalamic nucleus of patients with parkinson&apos;s disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hohlefeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huebl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Huchzermeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G.-H</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Schönecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kühn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Curio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Nikulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2812" to="2821" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Altered temporal correlations in parietal alpha and prefrontal theta oscillations in early-stage alzheimer disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Montez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-S</forename><surname>Poil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Manshanden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Verbunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Van Dijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Brussaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Van Ooyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Stam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Scheltens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1614" to="1619" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
