<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Calcified Liver Metastases from a Neuroendocrine Tumor of the Lung (Atypical Carcinoid) -A Case Report ▶Fig. 1 Ultrasound of the liver showing hyperechoic calcified liver metastases with posterior acoustic shadowing. Authors</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Rolf</forename><surname>Reiter</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Radiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jochen</forename><surname>Maul</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Interdisciplinary Ultrasound Unit</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><forename type="middle">Christian</forename><surname>Preis</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Gastroenterology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hendrik</forename><surname>Blaeker</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zarko</forename><surname>Grozdanovic</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Radiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Calcified Liver Metastases from a Neuroendocrine Tumor of the Lung (Atypical Carcinoid) -A Case Report ▶Fig. 1 Ultrasound of the liver showing hyperechoic calcified liver metastases with posterior acoustic shadowing. Authors</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">E2991E1F85FE3923F024F161BB679647</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1055/s-0043-100504</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:10+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Pulmonary neuroendocrine tumors (NETs) are rare tumors with an incidence rate of 0.2-2/100 000 population/year in Western countries (M.</s><s>E. <ref type="bibr">Caplin et al. Ann Oncol 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">26:1604-20)</ref>.</s><s>They account for 1-2 % of all neoplasms of the lung and constitute one-fourth to one-third of all NETs.</s><s>Atypical carcinoids are far less common than typical carcinoids and predominantly occur in male smokers aged 50 -70 years.</s><s>Most pulmonary NETs are asymptomatic due to their peripheral location.</s><s>Surgical resection is the treatment of choice.</s><s>Medical management should take hormone-related symptoms into account.</s></p><p><s>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report of a pulmonary NET with unusual calcified liver metastases.</s><s>Diagnostic workup of the patient included ultrasound, computed tomography (CT), magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), and ultrasound-guided biopsy of the liver lesions.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case Description</head><p><s>A 75-year-old woman with visual impairment of the right eye was admitted to the Department of Ophthalmology of our hospital.</s><s>She had a history of type II diabetes mellitus, partial strumectomy and arterial hypertension.</s><s>The clinical examination and complete blood count were normal.</s><s>Her medications included levothyroxine, triamterene, hydrochlorothiazide, and pantoprazole.</s><s>Optical coherence tomography revealed a choroidal lesion in the right eye.</s><s>The appearance was highly suspicious for choroidal melanoma.</s></p><p><s>A chest radiograph and abdominal ultrasound were performed as part of the routine staging of choroidal melanoma.</s><s>The chest radiograph demonstrated a nodule in the middle lobe of the right lung.</s><s>The abdominal ultrasound examination revealed multiple hyperechoic non-vascularized lesions in both hepatic lobes (Siemens Acu-son S2000, 4C1 transducer).</s><s>In segment III, the lesions were up to 4 cm in size and had hypoechoic margins, partially with posterior acoustic shadowing (▶ Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>).</s><s>For further workup of the pulmonary nodule and the calcified liver lesions, a CT of the chest and abdomen and MRI of the upper abdomen were performed (▶Fig.</s><s>2; CT: Toshiba Aquilion Prime 80; MRI: Siemens Magnetom Aera 1.5 Tesla).</s><s>CT demonstrated a single mass with smooth margins (16 × 20 mm) in the lung, suggesting malignancy, and additionally revealed liquefied and partially calcified lymph node metastases below the carina and in the right hilum.</s><s>T2-weighted MR images revealed high-signal-intensity lesions in both liver lobes with early arterial ring enhancement (▶ Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>), characterizing the calcified liver lesions as metastases.</s><s>In summary, imaging workup showed malignant lesions of the choroid, lung, and liver as well as metastatic hilar and mediastinal lymph nodes (▶Fig.</s><s>3).</s></p><p><s>For further clarification, an ultrasoundguided percutaneous biopsy of the liver metastases was performed (Bard TruCut biopsy needle, 18 G, 160 mm) after obtaining written informed consent.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathology</head><p><s>No melanin production was demonstrated in the biopsy tissue.</s><s>Histology revealed liver metastases from an NET (G2 according to WHO), most likely from a primary in the lung (atypical carcinoid).</s><s>The differential di-agnosis included choroidal and gastrointestinal NET.</s><s>However, the pattern of metastatic spread made these primary tumor sites unlikely.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report of a pulmonary NET with unusual calcified liver metastases.</s><s>A PubMed database search (search terms: calcified metastases, pulmonary NET, calcified liver metastases, hepatic calcifications) revealed no case of pulmonary NET with calcified liver metastases.</s><s>Our search revealed only a single case of a patient with pancreatic NET and calcified liver metastases (T.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Kawamoto et al. Clin J Gastroenterol 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">7:460-4)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The sonographic appearance of the liver lesions did not allow definitive characterization as benign or malignant.</s><s>Their appearance was consistent with hepatic metastases, calcified adenomas, and hepatic tuberculosis.</s><s>Further workup with CT and MRI allowed definitive classification of the lesions as calcified metastases.</s><s>The ultrasound -guided liver biopsy was crucial for identifying the primary tumor.</s><s>Otherwise multiple calcified liver metastases would primarily suggest metastatic spread from a mucin-producing primary tumor, for example in the colon, breast, stomach, or ovaries <ref type="bibr">(C. Stoupis et al. Radiographics 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr">18:675-85)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>We did not perform contrast-enhanced ultrasound (CEUS) in our patient because of the multiplicity of liver lesions and acoustic shadowing due to calcification of the lesions.</s><s>It is known from previous studies that the detection and characterization of hepatic lesions, e. g., metastases from colorectal cancer, can be significantly improved by CEUS compared to non-enhanced ultrasound (V.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Cantisani et al. Ultraschall Med 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">31:500-5, M. D'Onofrio et al. Radiol Med 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">113:76-86)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In the case presented here, imaging findings and liver biopsy ruled out the initially suspected choroidal melanoma, leading instead to the diagnosis of a pulmonary NET with metastatic spread to the liver, choroid and lymph nodes.</s><s>Workup was initiated based on this diagnosis.</s></p><p><s>However, the cause of calcification of liver and lymph node metastases in our pati ent remains unclear.</s><s>At the time of diagno sis, no hypercalcemia was apparent (Ca 2 + = 2.4 mmol/l, n = 2.2-2.5 mmol/l).</s><s>Therefore, metabolic causes or a paraneoplastic syndrome with calcification seems unlikely.</s><s>We hypothesize that rapid growth of the metastases led to necrosis with subsequent dystrophic calcification.</s></p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of Interest</head><p><s>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
