<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Necroptosis controls NET generation and mediates complement activation, endothelial damage, and autoimmune vasculitis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-10-24">October 24, 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Adrian</forename><surname>Schreiber</surname></persName>
							<email>adrian.schreiber@charite.de.</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Experimental and Clinical Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Delbrück Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Helmholtz Association</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Nephrology and Medical Intensive Care</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anthony</forename><surname>Rousselle</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Experimental and Clinical Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Delbrück Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Helmholtz Association</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><forename type="middle">Ulrich</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital of Cologne</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>50937</postCode>
									<settlement>Cologne</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anne</forename><surname>Von Mässenhausen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Nephrology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Internal Medicine III</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Carl Gustav Carus at the Technische Universitat Dresden</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>01307</postCode>
									<settlement>Dresden</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Linkermann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Nephrology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Internal Medicine III</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Carl Gustav Carus at the Technische Universitat Dresden</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>01307</postCode>
									<settlement>Dresden</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ralph</forename><surname>Kettritz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Experimental and Clinical Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Delbrück Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Helmholtz Association</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Nephrology and Medical Intensive Care</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Karin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">University of California San Diego School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>La Jolla</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Necroptosis controls NET generation and mediates complement activation, endothelial damage, and autoimmune vasculitis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2017-10-24">October 24, 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">898CE8F06EC46358C52D249E989FB36D</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.1708247114</idno>
					<note type="submission">and approved September 28, 2017 (received for review May 18, 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:10+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibody (ANCA)-associated vasculitis (AAV) constitutes life-threatening autoimmune diseases affecting every organ, including the kidneys, where they cause necrotizing crescentic glomerulonephritis.</s><s>ANCA activates neutrophils and activated neutrophils damage the endothelium, leading to vascular inflammation and necrosis.</s><s>Better understanding of neutrophilmediated AAV disease mechanisms may reveal novel treatment strategies.</s><s>Here we report that ANCA induces neutrophil extracellular traps (NETs) via receptor-interacting protein kinase (RIPK) 1/ 3-and mixed-lineage kinase domain-like (MLKL)-dependent necroptosis.</s><s>NETs from ANCA-stimulated neutrophils caused endothelial cell (EC) damage in vitro.</s><s>This effect was prevented by (i) pharmacologic inhibition of RIPK1 or (ii) enzymatic NET degradation.</s><s>The alternative complement pathway (AP) was recently implicated in AAV, and C5a inhibition is currently being tested in clinical studies.</s><s>We observed that NETs provided a scaffold for AP activation that in turn contributed to EC damage.</s><s>We further established the in vivo relevance of NETs and the requirement of RIPK1/3/MLKL-dependent necroptosis, specifically in the bone marrow-derived compartment, for disease induction using murine AAV models and in human kidney biopsies.</s><s>In summary, we identified a mechanistic link between ANCA-induced neutrophil activation, necroptosis, NETs, the AP, and endothelial damage.</s><s>RIPK1 inhibitors are currently being evaluated in clinical trials and exhibit a novel therapeutic strategy in AAV.</s></p><p><s>ANCA | NETs | necroptosis | complement | glomerulonephritis S ystemic necrotizing autoimmune vasculitis is characterized by circulating antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibody (ANCA) that recognizes either proteinase 3 (PR3) or myeloperoxidase (MPO).</s><s>Both antigens are exclusively expressed by neutrophils and monocytes <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(5)</ref>.</s><s>In vitro studies characterized various ANCA-induced neutrophil effector functions that participate in endothelial damage, such as adhesion, granule protein release, respiratory burst, and cytokine generation (reviewed in refs.</s><s>6 and 7).</s><s>Subsequently, animal studies provided mechanistic insights under complex in vivo conditions.</s><s>Activation of the alternative complement pathway (AP) together with C5a receptor blockade is one such example that was primarily derived from animal studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(8)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(9)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(10)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(11)</ref>.</s><s>A more recently described neutrophil effector function is the release of neutrophil extracellular traps (NETs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(12)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(13)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(14)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(15)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(16)</ref>. Mechanisms controlling NET formation and the clinical relevance of NETs are intensively studied.</s><s>NETs are lattice-like structures containing DNA, histones, and neutrophil granule proteins, including the ANCA antigens MPO and PR3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">18)</ref>.</s><s>ANCA-stimulated neutrophils were shown to release NETs in vitro, and circulating as well as glomerular deposited NETs were detected in AAV patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(19)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(20)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(21)</ref>.</s><s>It was suggested that NETs are immunogenic and participate in the tolerance breakdown toward the ANCA autoantigens <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">23)</ref>.</s><s>In addition, it is conceivable that ANCA-induced NETs participate in the vascular injury process that culminates in necrotizing vasculitis.</s><s>However, neither the signaling pathways by which ANCA induces NETs nor the potential mechanism(s) by which NETs affect the endothelium are fully understood.</s><s>We hypothesized that receptor-interacting protein kinases (RIPKs) 1/3, involved in the necroptosis signaling pathway, control ANCA-induced NET generation, and studied NET-mediated endothelial cell (EC) damage mechanisms.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>ANCA Stimulation Causes NET Formation, and the RIPK1/3-and Mixed-Lineage Kinase Domain-Like Protein-Dependent Necroptosis Pathway Mediates This Effect.</s><s>Both monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) to the ANCA antigens PR3 and MPO and ANCA-IgG from AAV patients induced NET formation in TNFα-primed human neutrophils (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1 A-F</ref>).</s><s>Using the cell-impermeable DNA dye propidium iodide, we detected extracellular DNA with the typical filiform NET structures when samples were paraformaldehyde (PFA)-fixed (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>), and observed typical extracellular DNA circles that surround neutrophils when unfixed samples were stained with Sytox green (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>).</s><s>Recently, critical NET-related issues</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Significance</head><p><s>In this report, we provide evidence of a mechanistic link between antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibody (ANCA)-induced neutrophil activation, regulated necrosis (necroptosis), generation of neutrophil extracellular traps, complement activation, and endothelial cell damage with consecutive vasculitis and glomerulonephritis in autoimmune ANCA-induced vasculitis (AAV).</s><s>We now show that inhibition of necroptosis-inducing kinases completely prevents ANCA vasculitis and establish a link to activation of the complement system.</s><s>We suggest that these findings significantly extend our understanding of the pathogenesis of AAV and especially the tight regulation of neutrophil cell death therein.</s><s>In addition, specific necroptosis inhibitors are currently being evaluated in clinical studies and can possibly complement existing therapeutic strategies in AAV.</s></p><p><s>were raised, including the need to define NETs by their characteristic composition, use observer-independent quantification methods, identify the upstream pathways that control NET formation in response to a given stimulus, determine the ways by which NETs cause tissue damage, and use physiologic stimuli with clinical relevance rather than artificial phorbol ester <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(24)</ref>.</s><s>ANCA provides such a disease-relevant NET inducer, and ANCA-induced NETs show the characteristic composition of DNA, histones, and human neutrophil elastase (HNE) (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref>).</s><s>Quantitative assessment of NETs using an automated and observer-independent method described by Papayannopoulos et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(25)</ref> indicated that ANCA increased both the percentage of NET-producing cells and the DNA areas surrounding the neutrophils (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1D</ref>).</s><s>While analyzing NET formation at 1-h intervals up to 4 h, we observed that up to 40% of neutrophils produced NETs in response to anti-PR3 and anti-MPO mAbs by the end of the observation period (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1E</ref>).</s><s>Incubation of polymorphonuclear neutrophil with IgG purified from patients with active AAV resulted in NET formation, whereas control IgG isolated from healthy controls did not (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1F</ref>).</s></p><p><s>The pathway(s) that controls ANCA-induced NET formation is not known.</s><s>NET formation may occur in vital neutrophils <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(26)</ref> or as a consequence of regulated necrosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28)</ref>.</s><s>Necroptosis, the best-studied form of regulated necrosis, depends on RIPK1/ 3 activation and subsequent phosphorylation of the pseudokinase mixed-lineage kinase domain-like (MLKL) (reviewed in ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29)</ref>.</s><s>Activation of RIPK3 is prevented by an inactivating conformation of RIPK1 that is maintained by the small molecule necrostatin-1 (Nec-1) or its derivatives (necrostatins) <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(30)</ref>.</s><s>We tested the hypothesis that necroptosis represents the upstream stimulus that drives ANCA-mediated NET formation.</s><s>Increasing Nec-1 concentrations decreased NET production, as assessed by microscopy (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1G</ref>) and automated quantification (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1 H  and I</ref>).</s><s>Significant reduction of NET generation was also observed with the highly specific pharmacologic RIPK1 inhibitor Nec-1s as well as with the downstream MLKL inhibitor necrosulfonamide (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> A and B).</s><s>Using a genetic approach, neutrophils from RIPK3-deficient mice exhibited reduced NET generation in response to polyclonal anti-MPO IgG (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> C and D).</s><s>Finally, we observed a clearly positive p-MLKL signal in anti-MPO antibody-stimulated human neutrophils that was absent in control antibody-stimulated cells (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2 E-H</ref>).</s><s>Together, these data indicate that RIPK3-dependent necroptosis functions as an upstream activator of ANCA-induced NET generation.</s></p><p><s>NETs Cause Endothelial Cell Damage, and NET-Dependent Alternative Complement Pathway Activation Contributes to This Effect.</s><s>EC damage by ANCA-activated neutrophils is a hallmark of AAV.</s><s>To test whether or not NETs damage the endothelium directly, we incubated NETs isolated from anti-MPO mAb-treated neutrophils with EC monolayers in the presence of serum.</s><s>Using albumin flux across the EC monolayer as an indicator of EC damage, we observed increased albumin permeability with NETs from anti-MPO mAb-treated neutrophils (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3 A and B</ref>).</s><s>We evaluated the capability of NETs to damage EC by two different approaches: either by NETs degradation with DNAse I (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A</ref>) or by specific necroptosis inhibition with Nec-1.</s><s>Both of these approaches strongly protected EC from NETs-induced damage (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3B</ref>).</s></p><p><s>We and others showed recently that AP activation caused necrotizing crescentic glomerulonephritis (NCGN) in murine AAV disease models <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(8)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(9)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(10)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(11)</ref>.</s><s>C5a was characterized as an important mediator, and an oral C5a receptor blocker was subsequently established and is currently being evaluated as a treatment target in clinical studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(31)</ref>.</s><s>We argued that NETs provide a scaffold for complement activation.</s><s>We therefore activated TNFα-primed neutrophils with mAbs to MPO or an isotype control for 3 h in HBSS before addition of human serum as a complement source for the last hour of the experiment.</s><s>After 4 h, NETs were isolated, and the NET components were released by DNase I and subjected to C5a ELISA.</s><s>We detected C5a generation in anti-MPO mAb-induced NETs that was abrogated by DNase I (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3E</ref>).</s><s>As an alternative approach, we visualized complement activation by C3d staining and observed that anti-MPO mAb-induced NETs showed strong C3d staining with DNA colocalization in the presence of normal serum.</s><s>This effect was reversed upon addition of serum and upon DNA degradation by DNase I (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C</ref>).</s><s>We then characterized the serum complement components that were required for NETmediated complement activation and EC damage using sera with defined complement deficiencies.</s><s>We observed again strong C3d staining in anti-MPO mAb-induced NETs that colocalized with DNA under normal human serum conditions but strongly diminished C3d staining when C3-deficient or factor B-deficient sera were used (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>).</s><s>In contrast, C1q deficiency had no effect on C3d staining.</s><s>Thus, NETs provide a scaffold for AP activation but not for the classical complement pathway.</s><s>Importantly, anti-MPO mAb-induced NETs that were generated in C3-or factor B-deficient sera provoked significantly less EC damage compared with NETs produced in normal or C1qdeficient sera (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3F</ref>).</s><s>In summary, these data identify the in-terconnection between ANCA-induced neutrophil activation, NETs, the AP, and EC damage.</s></p><p><s>ANCA-Induced NETs Mediate Anti-MPO-Induced Glomerular Damage.</s></p><p><s>Finally, we tested the key events from our in vitro observations in two murine AAV disease models.</s><s>First, we used a passive anti-MPO Ab transfer model to induce NCGN and evaluate the effect of DNase I treatment.</s><s>IgG was prepared from MPO-deficient mice that were immunized with murine MPO and transferred into wild-type (WT) mice.</s><s>After 7 d, all vehicle-treated mice showed proteinuria, erythrocyturia, and leukocyturia by dipstick (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4A</ref>) as well as glomerular crescents and necrosis by histology (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4 B,  C</ref>, and E).</s><s>Importantly, i.v.</s><s>DNase I treatment, started 24 h after anti-MPO Ab transfer, protected mice from the disease (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref> A, B, D, and F), supporting the notion that NETs contribute to glomerular endothelial injury in vivo.</s><s>However, we cannot rule out that DNase had additional effects independent of NET degrada- tion.</s><s>Thus, we used a different intervention by genetically interfering with the necroptosis pathway.</s><s>We induced disease in WT and RIPK3-deficient mice by passive anti-MPO Ab transfer and found that RIPK3 deficiency prevented NCGN by renal pathology (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4 H-L</ref>).</s><s>To exclude nonnecroptotic functions of RIPK3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">33)</ref>, we added another approach and induced disease in WT and MLKL-deficient mice.</s><s>We observed that MLKL deficiency protected from NCGN, thereby definitively implicating necroptosis as an important disease mechanism (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4 M-R</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Urine analysis showed less protection with RIPK3 compared with MLKL deficiency, suggesting RIPK3-independent effects on MLKL that may contribute to the pathogenesis.</s><s>However, to the best of our knowledge, no other kinase has been demonstrated to be capable of phosphorylating MLKL.</s><s>From these data, we conclude that RIPK3-mediated MLKL phosphorylation contributes to necroptosis as a central pathophysiological contributor of AAV, but cannot rule out RIPK3independent effects.</s><s>The passive transfer model did not allow us to specifically study the effect of RIPK3 deficiency in bone marrow (BM)derived cells that harbor the NET-producing neutrophils.</s><s>Thus, we generated chimeric mice that lacked RIPK3 only in BMderived cells.</s><s>MPO-deficient mice were immunized with murine MPO, irradiated, and transplanted with BM from either WT or RIPK3-deficient mice.</s><s>After 8 wk, mice that had received WT BM showed urine abnormalities (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5A</ref>) and NCGN by histology (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5 B, C, and E</ref>), whereas mice transplanted with RIPK3-deficient BM were protected (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5 A, B,  D, and F</ref>).</s><s>RIPK3 deficiency did not interfere with BM engraftment (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1</ref>).</s><s>Thus, our in vitro data together with the animal data obtained in two models using different genedeficient mice are in line with an important role of myeloid RIPK1/3, MLKL, and NETs in anti-MPO antibodymediated NCGN.</s></p><p><s>In keeping with these data, human kidney biopsy stainings obtained from anti-MPO AAV patients with highly active NCGN exhibited a remarkably specific p-MLKL staining in glomerular neutrophils.</s><s>Neutrophils were the only glomerular cells found positive for p-MLKL, and there was a notable absence of positivity in parietal epithelial cells, crescents, glomerular endothelial cells, mesangial cells, and mononuclear cells in the ANCA-associated NCGN biopsies and the controls.</s><s>Out of 12 anti-MPO antibody-associated NCGN biopsies with a total of 174 glomeruli (63 with active crescents, 57 with necrosis), we found 2 p-MLKL-positive glomerular neutrophils (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5 G-K</ref>).</s><s>Five biopsies with anti-PR3 antibody-associated NCGN did not show glomerular neutrophils with p-MLKL positivity.</s><s>Biopsies from disease control NCGN did not show any p-MLKL-positive neutrophils.</s><s>However, this does not exclude the possibility of a role for necroptosis in cells other than neutrophils, because necroptosis is a rapid form of cell death which is inevitably associated with plasma membrane rupture.</s><s>Therefore, we expect to lose the p-MLKL signal in tissue sections.</s><s>Together with the in vivo findings of RIPK3-and MLKL-deficient mice, these data suggest that RIPK3-mediated phosphorylation of MLKL and necroptosis in neutrophils play a central role in inducing disease activity in AAV in mice and humans.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>In summary, we used complementary methods, including quantitative operator-independent analyses, to show that NETs with their characteristic constituents were formed in response to a disease-relevant stimulus, namely ANCA.</s><s>We provide data supporting the notion that ANCA-induced NET formation is controlled by RIPK1/3 and MLKL, key mediators of the necroptosis pathway.</s><s>Moreover, we observed that NETs damage the endothelium in vitro and that this effect is, at least in part, mediated by NET-associated AP activation.</s><s>Finally, we used pharmacologic and genetic approaches in murine disease models and provide AAV patient data supporting the concept that necroptosis and NET formation are relevant for in vivo contribution to anti-MPO antibody-mediated NCGN.</s><s>Various infectious and noninfectious mediators were shown to induce NETs.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Kessenbrock et al. (12)</ref> were the first to demonstrate that ANCA triggers NET formation and deposition in affected glomeruli in AAV patients.</s><s>NET production by ANCAactivated neutrophils <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">35)</ref> and kidney biopsies from AAV patients with NETs containing citrullinated histones, MPO, and peptidyl arginine deiminase 4 at sites of glomerular fibrinoid necrosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(36)</ref> were subsequently reported by others as well.</s><s>Recently, critical NET-related issues were raised, including the need to define NETs by their characteristic composition, use observer-independent quantification methods, identify the upstream pathways that control NET formation in response to a given stimulus, determine the ways by which NETs cause tissue damage, and use physiologic stimuli with clinical relevance rather than artificial phorbol ester, to name a few <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(24)</ref>.</s><s>In an attempt to address some of these issues, we studied ANCAinduced NETs in vitro and in murine AAV disease models.</s><s>We found that ANCA triggers NET formation in vitro and detected the typical NET components with extracellular DNA, histones, and human neutrophil elastase in close proximity.</s><s>This composition characterized the formation of true NETs and distinguished them from any cell-free DNA that could be released after cell lysis.</s><s>Furthermore, an observer-independent method was introduced by Papayannopoulos et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(25)</ref> that allowed us to quantify NET formation with respect to the percentage of NETproducing cells and NET area.</s></p><p><s>The pathway(s) that controls NET formation in response to ANCA is not known.</s><s>In general, NET formation may occur in vital neutrophils <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(26)</ref> or as a consequence of regulated necrosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28)</ref>.</s><s>The intracellular signal transduction events that control the regulated necrotic cell death leading to NET formation are not yet clear and may differ between different NET inducers.</s><s>Necroptosis is a death pathway of regulated necrosis and is currently defined by its caspase independence and its dependence on receptor-interacting protein kinase 1, RIPK3, and the mixed-lineage kinase domain-like protein <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">37)</ref>.</s><s>Necroptosis was shown to control crystal-induced NET formation <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(38)</ref>, whereas the role of necroptosis in phorbol-12-myristat-13acetate (PMA)-induced NET formation is controversial <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(38)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(39)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(40)</ref>.</s><s>We observed that pharmacologic RIPK1 and MLKL inhibitors as well as RIPK3 deficiency reduced NET formation in response to ANCA, suggesting that necroptosis is upstream of ANCA-induced NET production.</s><s>Automated quantification indicated that both the percentage of NET-forming cells and the NET area decreased with RIPK1 and MLKL inhibition.</s><s>The cellular mechanism as to how ANCA induces NETs is currently unclear.</s><s>It is conceivable that MPO-ANCA interferes with MPO activity.</s><s>We observed abrogated NET generation in MPO-deficient neutrophils in response to PMA, indicating the importance of MPO for NET generation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2</ref>).</s><s>In addition, downstream of p-MLKL, necroptosis may be regulated by the endosomal sorting complex required for transport (ESCRT)-III complex.</s><s>Thus, we cannot rule out the possibility that additional regulation of the necrotic cell death pathway is involved <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(41)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Multiple implications of NETs in AAV are conceivable.</s><s>NETs contain the ANCA antigens MPO and PR3 and present these antigens in an immunogenic way that promotes autoimmunity <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">42)</ref>.</s><s>It is also conceivable that ANCA-induced NETs participate in endothelial injury.</s><s>In fact, NET-associated histones were recently shown to damage glomerular ECs in vitro and in an antiglomerular basement membrane glomerulonephritis model <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(43)</ref>.</s><s>Moreover, NET-associated matrix metalloproteinases had toxic EC effects in vitro, possibly contributing to vascular injury in systemic lupus erythematosus <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(44)</ref>.</s><s>We observed that isolated NETs induced by ANCA damaged ECs in vitro.</s><s>DNase and necrostatin-1 reduced EC damage, underscoring the biological importance of necroptosis-induced NET formation in the context of endothelial injury.</s><s>We made an additional observation, namely that NETs formed not only a scaffold for the activation of the alternative complement pathway but, in turn, contributed to endothelial damage.</s><s>Thus, NETs may provide a mechanistic link between ANCAinduced neutrophil activation, complement, and endothelial injury.</s><s>We believe that these findings provide an additional rationale for complement blockade as a therapeutic principle in AAV.</s></p><p><s>To test key events of our in vitro findings in complex in vivo conditions, we studied AAV disease models and selected two intervention strategies for proof of principle.</s><s>First, we used a short-term anti-MPO antibody model for NCGN and administered DNase I to degrade NETs.</s><s>This intervention reduced glomerular necrosis and crescent formation, supporting the notion that NETs contribute to glomerular endothelial injury in vivo.</s><s>However, we cannot rule out that DNase had additional effects, independent of NET degradation.</s><s>Second, we used RIPK3-and MLKL-deficient mice to evaluate the need of the necroptosis machinery for NCGN induction by anti-MPO antibodies.</s><s>We observed protection in RIPK3-and MLKL-deficient mice, but were not able to differentiate the importance of necroptosis in NET-producing BM-derived cells from necroptosis in other cells, including ECs.</s><s>Therefore, we used a BM transplantation model to generate mice that were RIPK3-deficient in BM-derived cells only.</s><s>Anti-MPO antibody-mediated NCGN was strongly attenuated in mice that had received RIPK3deficient BM compared with WT BM.</s><s>Thus, our in vivo data are in agreement with the importance of necroptosis-controlled NET formation for anti-MPO antibody-mediated NCGN.</s><s>However, prospective clinical trials are now possible, and should allow the prognostic potential of p-MLKL staining in AAV patients.</s><s>In summary, in addition to complement, necroptosis pathway elements may represent molecular targets for therapeutic interventions in AAV.</s><s>Pharmacologic RIPK1 inhibitors are currently in phase II clinical trials for the treatment of inflammatory bowel diseases, ulcerative colitis, psoriasis, rheumatoid arthritis (GSK2982772), and other indications <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(45)</ref>.</s><s>Repurposing these drugs for the treatment of AAV seems reasonable.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials and Methods</head><p><s>Preparation of Neutrophils, IgG, and Human Umbilical Vein Endothelial Cells, NET Production, and Coincubation of Human Umbilical Vein Endothelial Cell Monolayers with NETs.</s><s>Neutrophils, human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs), and IgG were prepared as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(46)</ref>.</s><s>NETs were isolated by detachment using low DNase I concentrations and coincubated with HUVECs.</s><s>BSA-FITC permeability was assessed as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(47)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Visualization and Quantification of NET Formation.</s><s>To visualize NETs, neutrophils were stained with either Sytox or propidium iodide.</s><s>For NET quantification, Sytox images of unfixed neutrophils were analyzed using ImageJ processing software (NIH) as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(25)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Mice, Immunization, NCGN Models, and DNase I Treatment Protocol.</s><s>Ripk3 −/− mice were kindly provided by V. Dixit and K. Newton, Genentech, South San Francisco, CA <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(48)</ref>, and Mlkl −/− mice were kindly provided by James Murphy, Walter and Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research, Parkville, Australia <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(45)</ref>.</s><s>Male and female mice were used both as BM donors and recipients with equal gender distribution.</s><s>BM engraftment was assessed 5 wk after bonemarrow transplantation.</s><s>Passive NCGN was induced in female WT, Ripk3 −/− , or Mlkl −/− mice.</s><s>Local authorities approved all animal experiments, which followed the Animal Research: Reporting of In Vivo Experiments (ARRIVE) guidelines.</s></p><p><s>p-MLKL Staining of Human Renal Tissue.</s><s>Sections from 12 renal biopsies with anti-MPO NCGN, 5 anti-PR3 NCGN, 2 anti-glomerular basement membraneassociated GN, and 3 biopsies with focal necrotizing IgA-GN were stained for p-MLKL.</s><s>Neutrophils from healthy human donors and HUVECs were obtained after approval by Charité and governmental authorities and after written informed consent.</s></p><p><s>Statistics. Results are given as means ± SEM.</s><s>Comparisons were made using t test or ANOVA; *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01.</s><s>See SI Materials and Methods for a detailed description.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1.</s><s>ANCA induces NET generation in human neutrophils by RIPK1dependent necroptosis signaling.</s><s>Isolated human neutrophils were primed with 2 ng/mL TNFα and subsequently stimulated with different monoclonal antibodies (ctrl, isotype control; αPR3 mab, monoclonal antibody to PR3; αMPO mab, monoclonal antibody to MPO).</s><s>(A) PFA-fixed cells were stained with propidium iodide (PI) to detect NETs.</s><s>(B) Viable cells were stained with Sytox green to detect NETs.</s><s>(C) A typical example of anti-MPO mAb-induced NETs with strong staining for DNA (blue; DAPI), histone H3 (green), and HNE (red) is depicted.</s><s>(D) Automated quantification of NET generation in response to mAbs to MPO and PR3, PMA, and isotype control mAb (ctrl) (one representative experiment is shown).</s><s>The dashed line marks the threshhold for definition of NETs generation.</s><s>(E) Time course of NET formation in response to mAbs to MPO and PR3, PMA, and isotype control mAb; n = 4 experiments with different neutrophil donors.</s><s>(F) Stimulation of TNFα-primed neutrophils with two different human control IgG preparations for 4 h (ctrl), two different human PR3-ANCA IgG preparations, and two different human MPO-ANCA IgG preparations (125 μg/mL); n = 4 experiments with different neutrophil donors.</s><s>(G) αMPO mAb-induced NET generation by microscopy was dose dependently reduced by necrostatin-1 preincubation.</s><s>(H) Depiction of the percentage of NET-producing neutrophils and NET area.</s><s>(I) Statistical analysis of the percentage of NET-producing neutrophils from four independent experiments with different neutrophil donors as in H. Error bars indicate means ± SEM.</s><s>Comparisons were made using t test or ANOVA; *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 2. ANCA induces NET generation in human and murine neutrophils by RIPK1-and MLKL-dependent necroptosis signaling.</s><s>(A) Isolated TNFα-primed human neutrophils were stimulated with a monoclonal antibody to MPO (αMPO mab) or an isotype control (ctrl).</s><s>NETs were detected by Sytox green staining.</s><s>NET generation was reduced by both necrostatin-1s and necrosulfonamide (NAS) preincubation.</s><s>(B) Corresponding statistical analysis of the percentage of NET-producing neutrophils from three independent experiments with different neutrophil donors.</s><s>(C) Isolated TNFα-primed murine neutrophils from WT or Ripk3 −/− mice were stimulated with murine polyclonal anti-MPO IgG, and NET generation was quantified by Sytox green staining.</s><s>Neutrophils from Ripk3 −/− mice displayed reduced NET generation.</s><s>(D) Corresponding statistical analysis of the percentage of NET-producing neutrophils from three independent experiments.</s><s>(E-H) p-MLKL immunohistochemistry on isolated human neutrophils.</s><s>αMPO mAb-stimulated TNFα-primed neutrophils displayed a strong p-MLKL signal that was absent in isotype control-stimulated cells; E and F show 63× magnification.</s><s>G and H depict higher digital magnification of the marked areas in E and F. Error bars indicate means ± SEM.</s><s>Comparisons were made using t test or ANOVA; *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,160.73,68.37,229.10,382.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 3. Endothelial damage and complement activation by ANCA-induced NET generation.</s><s>(A) HUVECs were coincubated with NETs isolated from either TNFα-primed human neutrophils without further stimulation (unstim), isotype mAb-stimulated (ctrl), or αMPO mAb-stimulated (αMPO) neutrophils.</s><s>Permeability of the EC monolayer was measured after 1 h using albumin-FITC.</s><s>NET degradation by DNase protected from endothelial damage.</s><s>(B) Human neutrophil preincubation with Nec-1 protected from NET-induced endothelial damage.</s><s>(C) NETs were coincubated in the absence (w/o) or presence of human serum and stained after PFA fixation with PI (DNA; red) and αC3d antibody (FITC; green).</s><s>Unstimulated cells and isotype-stimulated neutrophils displayed no NETs and no C3d deposition, whereas αMPO mAbstimulated cells coincubated with serum showed NET formation with strong C3d costaining.</s><s>DNase pretreatment prevented C3d staining.</s><s>A typical example is depicted.</s><s>(D) NETs were coincubated with different human sera as indicated and stained after fixation with PI (DNA; red) and αC3d antibody (FITC; green).</s><s>Isotype-stimulated neutrophils displayed no NETs and no C3d deposition; αMPO mAb-stimulated neutrophils displayed NET formation and-when coincubated with serum-C3d deposition.</s><s>C3d deposition was not affected by C1q deficiency but strongly reduced in both C3-deficient (C3-def) and complement factor B-deficient (FB-def) sera.</s><s>(E) αMPO mAbinduced NETs that were coincubated with human serum caused complement activation with C5a generation.</s><s>The effect was prevented by NET degradation using DNase I. (F) Increased EC permeability by αMPO mAb-induced NETs is mediated by the alternative complement pathway, as both C3-deficient and complement factor B-deficient sera provided protection whereas C1q deficiency did not.</s><s>Error bars indicate means ± SEM.</s><s>Comparisons were made using t test or ANOVA; *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01.</s><s>ns, not significant.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,56.93,147.21,226.22,218.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 4. ANCA-stimulated necroptosis-dependent NET generation induces NCGN.</s><s>(A-F) NCGN was induced by passive αMPO IgG transfer; NETs were degraded in vivo by twice daily i.p.</s><s>DNase injections, which resulted in protection from (A) urine pathology and less crescent and necrosis formation by (B) histology.</s><s>Depicted are typical renal sections with (C) low (10×) and (E) high magnification (40×) from vehicle-treated mice as well as (D) low and (F) high magnifications from DNase-treated mice.</s><s>(G-L) NCGN was induced by passive αMPO IgG transfer into WT or RIPK3-deficient (Ripk3 −/− ) mice.</s><s>Urine pathology was similar in both groups (G), whereas RIPK3 deficiency resulted in less crescent and necrosis formation (H). (I-L) Representative glomeruli with (I) low and (K) high magnifications from WT mice, whereas J shows low and L shows high magnifications from RIPK3-deficient mice.</s><s>(M-R) NCGN was induced by passive αMPO IgG transfer into WT or MLKL-deficient (Mlkl −/− ) mice.</s><s>Urine pathology showed less leukocyturia and erythrocyturia (M) and less crescent and necrosis formation in MLKL-deficient mice (N).</s><s>(O-R) Representative glomeruli with low (O) and high (Q) magnifications from WT mice, whereas P shows low and R shows high magnifications from MLKL-deficient mice.</s><s>Error bars indicate means ± SEM.</s><s>Comparisons were made using t test or ANOVA; *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,263.33,57.21,217.58,544.82" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 5. ANCA-stimulated necroptosis in circulating BM-derived cells induces NCGN.</s><s>(A-F) NCGN was induced in MPO-deficient mice immunized with murine MPO that were subsequently irradiated and transplanted with either WT or RIPK3-deficient (Ripk3 −/− ) BM. (A-F) RIPK3 deficiency significantly reduced urine pathology (A) and resulted in strong protection from crescent and necrosis induction (B).</s><s>Depicted are typical renal sections with (C) low and (E) high magnifications from WT mice, whereas D shows low and F shows high magnifications from RIPK3-deficient mice.</s><s>(G-K) Exemplary micrograph from a biopsy with active anti-MPO-ANCA-associated NCGN shows fibrinoid necrosis and a cellular crescent; the Insets (G) shows the extent of the crescent in blue, necrosis in red, and tuft in green color.</s><s>No resident mesangial cells, endothelial cells, podocytes, or intracapillary or infiltrating leukocytes are positive (brown) for p-MLKL.</s><s>(H) Some of the few tubular segments with epithelial positivity for p-MLKL.</s><s>(I) Biopsy with active anti-MPO-ANCA-associated NCGN and cytoplasmic positivity for p-MLKL in two neutrophils, recognizable by their typical segmented nuclei (short arrows).</s><s>The colors in the Left Inset are as above.</s><s>The neutrophil in the Top Right Inset (arrow) is adjacent to a fibrinoid necrosis area (arrowhead) (I and J).</s><s>The neutrophil in the Bottom Right Inset is adjacent to a fresh, cellular crescent (long arrows).</s><s>Both neutrophils in the Right Insets are magnified in the corresponding two frames (J and K) to better appreciate nuclear morphology.</s><s>Error bars indicate means ± SEM.</s><s>Comparisons were made using t test or ANOVA; *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,92.57,65.61,395.42,560.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">E9620 | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.1708247114 Schreiber et al.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">E9622 | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.1708247114 Schreiber et al.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">E9624 | www.pnas.org/cgi/doi/10.1073/pnas.1708247114 Schreiber et al.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS.</s><s>We thank Sylvia Lucke and Susanne Rolle for excellent technical assistance.</s><s>This work was supported in part by DFG Grants SCHR 771/6-1 and KE 576/7-1, the Heisenberg Professorship program (LI 2107/2-1), and an ECRC grant.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Segmental necrotising glomerulonephritis with antineutrophil antibody: Possible arbovirus aetiology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Moran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Niall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br Med J (Clin Res Ed)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">285</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">606</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Autoantibodies against neutrophils and monocytes: Tool for diagnosis and marker of disease activity in Wegener&apos;s granulomatosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Der Woude</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="425" to="429" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic autoantibodies with specificity for myeloperoxidase in patients with systemic vasculitis and idiopathic necrotizing and crescentic glomerulonephritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Falk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jennette</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">318</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1651" to="1657" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hilhorst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Van Paassen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jwc</forename><surname>Tervaert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proteinase 3-ANCA vasculitis versus myeloperoxidase-ANCA vasculitis</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Limburg Renal Registry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2314" to="2327" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>J Am Soc Nephrol</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reactivity of antineutrophil cytoplasmic autoantibodies with mononuclear phagocytes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Charles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Falk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jennette</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Leukoc Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic autoantibodies activate neutrophils</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kettritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Exp Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">169</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="220" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of neutrophils in causing antineutrophil cytoplasmic autoantibody-associated vasculitis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schreiber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Hematol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="66" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">C5a receptor mediates neutrophil activation and ANCAinduced glomerulonephritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schreiber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Soc Nephrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="298" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inhibition of complement factor C5 protects against antimyeloperoxidase antibody-mediated glomerulonephritis in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Huugen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Kidney Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="646" to="654" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternative complement pathway in the pathogenesis of disease mediated by anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic autoantibodies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schreiber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Heeringa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Falk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jennette</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Pathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">170</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">C5a receptor (CD88) blockade protects against MPO-ANCA GN</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Soc Nephrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="231" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Netting neutrophils in autoimmune small-vessel vasculitis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kessenbrock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="623" to="625" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracellular DNA traps promote thrombosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15880" to="15885" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impairment of neutrophil extracellular trap degradation is associated with lupus nephritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hakkim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9813" to="9818" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil extracellular traps sequester circulating tumor cells and promote metastasis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cools-Lartigue</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3446" to="3458" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Peptidylarginine deiminase inhibition reduces vascular damage and modulates innate immune responses in murine models of atherosclerosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Knight</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circ Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="947" to="956" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil extracellular traps kill bacteria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Brinkmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">303</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1532" to="1535" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global substrate profiling of proteases in human neutrophil extracellular traps reveals consensus motif predominantly contributed by elastase</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>O'donoghue</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e75141</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhanced formation and disordered regulation of NETs in myeloperoxidase-ANCA-associated microscopic polyangiitis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nakazawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Soc Nephrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="990" to="997" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophils from vasculitis patients exhibit an increased propensity for activation by anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic antibodies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ohlsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Exp Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">176</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="372" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increased levels of neutrophil extracellular trap remnants in the circulation of patients with small vessel vasculitis, but an inverse correlation to anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic antibodies during remission</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Söderberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rheumatology (Oxford)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2085" to="2094" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil extracellular traps mediate transfer of cytoplasmic neutrophil antigens to myeloid dendritic cells toward ANCA induction and associated autoimmunity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sangaletti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3007" to="3018" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Peptidylarginine deiminase inhibitor suppresses neutrophil extracellular trap formation and MPO-ANCA production</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kusunoki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">227</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pondering neutrophil extracellular traps with healthy skepticism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nauseef</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kubes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1349" to="1357" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil elastase and myeloperoxidase regulate the formation of neutrophil extracellular traps</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Papayannopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Metzler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hakkim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zychlinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">191</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="677" to="691" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel mechanism of rapid nuclear neutrophil extracellular trap formation in response to Staphylococcus aureus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Pilsczek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">185</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7413" to="7425" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Novel cell death program leads to neutrophil extracellular traps</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">176</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="241" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular definitions of cell death subroutines: Recommendations of the Nomenclature Committee on Cell Death</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Galluzzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Death Differ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Linkermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">370</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="455" to="465" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of RIP1 kinase as a specific cellular target of necrostatins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Degterev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Chem Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="321" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Randomized trial of C5a receptor inhibitor avacopan in ANCA-associated vasculitis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Drw</forename><surname>Jayne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Soc Nephrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2756" to="2767" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>CLEAR Study Group</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RIPK1 and RIPK3 kinases promote cell-death-independent inflammation by Toll-like receptor 4</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Najjar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinase activities of RIPK1 and RIPK3 can direct IFN-β synthesis induced by lipopolysaccharide</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Saleh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">198</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4435" to="4447" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Autophagy is induced by anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic Abs and promotes neutrophil extracellular traps formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L-L</forename><surname>Sha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Innate Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="658" to="665" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-mobility group box 1 potentiates antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibody-inducing neutrophil extracellular traps formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y-H</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Res Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil extracellular trap components in fibrinoid necrosis of the kidney with myeloperoxidase-ANCA-associated vasculitis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yoshida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sasaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sugisaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yamaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Kidney J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="308" to="312" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulated cell death and inflammation: An auto-amplification loop causes organ failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Linkermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Stockwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Krautwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H-J</forename><surname>Anders</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="759" to="767" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PMA and crystal-induced neutrophil extracellular trap formation involves RIPK1-RIPK3-MLKL signaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Desai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="229" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil extracellular trap cell death requires both autophagy and superoxide generation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Remijsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="290" to="304" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NET formation can occur independently of RIPK3 and MLKL signaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Amini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="178" to="184" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ESCRT-III acts downstream of MLKL to regulate necroptotic cell death and its consequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y-N</forename><surname>Gong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">169</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="286" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>e16</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Abnormal conformation and impaired degradation of propylthiouracil-induced neutrophil extracellular traps: Implications of disordered neutrophil extracellular traps in a rat model of myeloperoxidase antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibody-associated vasculitis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nakazawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3779" to="3787" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil extracellular trap-related extracellular histones cause vascular necrosis in severe GN</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Svr</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Soc Nephrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2399" to="2413" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil extracellular traps induce endothelial dysfunction in systemic lupus erythematosus through the activation of matrix metalloproteinase-2</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Carmona-Rivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yalavarthi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kaplan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Rheum Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1417" to="1424" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics, and efficacy of repeat doses of GSK2982772 in subjects with psoriasis (Natl Inst Health, Bethesda), ClinicalTrials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Clinicaltrials</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ID NCT02776033</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bone marrow-derived cells are sufficient and necessary targets to mediate glomerulonephritis and vasculitis induced by anti-myeloperoxidase antibodies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schreiber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Falk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jennette</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Soc Nephrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3355" to="3364" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil serine proteases exert proteolytic activity on endothelial cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Jerke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Kidney Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="764" to="775" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinase RIP3 is dispensable for normal NF-kappa Bs, signaling by the B-cell and T-cell receptors, tumor necrosis factor receptor 1, and Tolllike receptors 2 and 4</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Newton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dixit</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1464" to="1469" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
