<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Survey of e-learning implementation and faculty support strategies in a cluster of mid-European medical schools</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">Alexander</forename><surname>Back</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dieter Scheffner Center for Medical Education and Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Traumatology and Orthopedics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Bundeswehr Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Scharnhorststrasse 13</addrLine>
									<postCode>10115</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dieter Scheffner Center for Medical Education and Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Florian</forename><surname>Behringer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dieter Scheffner Center for Medical Education and Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dieter Scheffner Center for Medical Education and Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tina</forename><surname>Harms</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dieter Scheffner Center for Medical Education and Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dieter Scheffner Center for Medical Education and Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Joachim</forename><surname>Plener</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dieter Scheffner Center for Medical Education and Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dieter Scheffner Center for Medical Education and Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Kai</forename><surname>Sostmann</surname></persName>
							<email>kai.sostmann@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dieter Scheffner Center for Medical Education and Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dieter Scheffner Center for Medical Education and Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Harm</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dieter Scheffner Center for Medical Education and Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Dieter Scheffner Center for Medical Education and Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Survey of e-learning implementation and faculty support strategies in a cluster of mid-European medical schools</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3D3123192B10F63050B4987323CD042B</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12909-015-0420-4</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 5 March 2015 Accepted: 14 August 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:40+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Background: The use of electronic learning formats (e-learning) in medical education is reported mainly from individual specialty perspectives.</s><s>In this study, we analyzed the implementation level of e-learning formats and the institutional support structures and strategies at an institutional level in a cluster of mid-European medical schools.</s><s>Methods: A 49-item online questionnaire was send to 48 medical schools in Austria, Germany and Switzerland using SurveyMonkey®.</s><s>Data were collected between February and September of 2013 and analyzed using quantities, statistical and qualitative means.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results:</head><p><s>The response rate was 71 %.</s><s>All schools had implemented e-learning, but mainly as an optional supplement to the curriculum.</s><s>E-learning involved a wide range of formats across all disciplines.</s><s>Online learning platforms were used by 97 % of the schools.</s><s>Full-time e-learning staff was employed by 50 %, and these had a positive and significant effect on the presence of e-learning in the corresponding medical schools.</s><s>In addition, 81 % offered training programs and qualifications for their teachers and 76 % awarded performance-oriented benefits, with 17 % giving these for e-learning tasks.</s><s>Realization of e-learning offers was rewarded by 33 %, with 27 % recognizing this as part of the teaching load.</s><s>97 % would use curriculum-compatible e-learning tools produced by other faculties.</s><s>Conclusions: While all participating medical schools used e-learning concepts, this survey revealed also a reasonable support by institutional infrastructure and the importance of staff for the implementation level of e-learning offerings.</s><s>However, data showed some potential for increasing tangible incentives to motivate teachers to engage in further use of e-learning.</s><s>Furthermore, the use of individual tools and the distribution of e-learning presentations in various disciplines were quite inhomogeneous.</s><s>The willingness of the medical schools to cooperate should be capitalized for the future, especially concerning the provision of e-learning tools and concepts.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p><s>In parallel with the technological revolution of the past decades, digitally supported learning tools and formats (elearning) have become an important component in many medical curricula <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>An increasing number of e-learning tools has been developed and is now employed in various settings according to the subject and intention of the educational endeavor <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s>Today´s medical students have grown up mostly in an already technologically supported learning environment.</s><s>In general, they positively rate the integration of e-learning <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and e-learning is frequently integrated with face-to-face teaching as blended learning format <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s>The production of e-learning materials is often time-consuming and competes with the more and more compressed work-schedules of medical doctors and their limited time resources <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</s><s>In addition, most teachers need technical and expert support when it comes to the production and implementation of e-learning <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>International recommendations state that a facultywide use of electronic learning scenarios should be a central part in the strategic development of medical programs <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s><s>In the literature, there are a number of reports on e-learning in medical education, but mainly from discipline-specific perspectives <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>.</s><s>Analyses and research on the faculty's application of e-learning formats and supporting infrastructure in medical schools can only rarely be found <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</s><s>Medical faculties can take hold of a wide range of potential structures and strategies to facilitate and foster the use of e-learning in their medical curricula.</s><s>These range from the provision of Learning Management Systems (LMS) as internetbased software programs for the delivery and tracking of e-learning across a medical school <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> authoring tools, up to permanent e-learning staff, qualification programs and training courses for the implementation of e-learning <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, quality assurance programs for the production and implementation of e-learning <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>, funding of e-learning projects and performance-orientated payments or awards <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The aim of this study was to systematically analyze the implementation level for e-learning in medical education from a medical school institutional perspective.</s><s>We took advantage of an existing working group "New Media" within the Gesellschaft für Medizinische Ausbildung (Society for Medical Education) that brings together representatives from medical schools of the three mid-European countries Austria, Germany and Switzerland <ref type="bibr">[20]</ref>.</s><s>In addition to the level of implementation, we analyzed the currently operating institutional support structures and strategies for the provision of elearning and asked for e-learning issues that should be approached in the near future.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p><s>The target group of the survey consisted of all existing 48 medical schools in Austria (n = 4), Germany (n = 36) and Switzerland (n = 8).</s><s>Contact persons of the survey were members of the working group New Media of the Society for Medical Education and faculty members at the deaneries of student affairs responsible for e-learning.</s><s>An itembased questionnaire was constructed on the bases of literature search and according to methods of empirical social research <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[21]</ref>.</s><s>The items were grouped into the following three main areas:</s></p><p><s>-General information about the medical school and provision of e-learning -Information about the infrastructural conditions of e-learning supporting measures -Information about requirements of and incentives for staff in the field of e-learning</s></p><p><s>The initial questionnaire was validated through a peer review approach online according the pre-test method <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[22]</ref> during the winter semester 2012/13.</s><s>Peer reviewers (n = 4) were both faculty staff members responsible for e-learning in their medical school, and members of the Society for Medical Education <ref type="bibr">[20]</ref>.</s><s>The returned comments were collected and the questionnaire adapted accordingly.</s><s>The local responsible ethical committee of the university was informed about this survey and gave its written consent (Ethikkommission Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Ethikausschuss 4, Campus Benjamin Franklin, Berlin, Germany).</s><s>The survey followed the directives of the Helsinki declaration.</s></p><p><s>The final questionnaire for this study contained a total of 49 items, with 27 closed questions and 22 questions for free text answers (Additional file 1).</s><s>The questionnaire was delivered to the 48 medical schools in Austria, Switzerland and Germany using the online program SurveyMonkey® (SurveyMonkey, Oregon, USA).</s><s>Access to the questionnaire was provided by an email link.</s><s>Through electronic pre-determination of the response options supplied by SurveyMonkey®, users were offered the option of skipping or omitting certain questions.</s><s>The survey started in February 2013 and after 4 reminders, data collection ended in September 2013.</s><s>Reminders consisted of reminder emails to the correspondent involved.</s><s>In cases where an answer was still missing, we tried to contact assistants of the deaneries of student affairs by email.</s><s>In a last attempt the deanery was called by phone.</s></p><p><s>Quantitative analysis was undertaken where results of the closed questions (mainly yes/ no) were expressed as percentage of their relative occurrence per item and were calculated by the SurveyMonkey® program.</s><s>Spear-man´s rank-order correlations were applied by using the SPSS® 17.0 statistics software (SPSS Inc., Chicago, USA) in order to analyze potential coherences between the indicated size of a medical school and its financial means or the number of employees for an e-learning department.</s><s>Additionally, the chi-square test was used to analyze if the presence of e-learning staff predicted the use of any modalities, indicated by the medical schools in the closed questions.</s><s>Alternatively, the Mann-Whitney U test was performed to analyse the implementation level of e-learning in the existing disciplines at the medical schools, and that of e-learning tools both in general and in dependence of the presence of e-learning staff.</s></p><p><s>The individual responses to the free text were quantitatively and independently analyzed by two of the authors for repetitive themes and then summarized.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>A total of 34 out of the 48 online questionnaires was returned (71 %).</s><s>After analysis of all data, seven questions for free text answers were excluded due to a low return rate (n ≤ 5) or due to ambiguous responses (Additional file 1).</s><s>The responses (16 entries) came from e-learning staff (n = 8), dean's office (n = 4) and quality management, exam coordination, IT and didactics (n = 1 each).</s><s>The sizes of the various institutions varied from 100-500 students (n = 1), 500-1500 (n = 6), 1500-3000 (n = 19), 3000-6000 (n = 4), up to 6000-9000 students (n = 2).</s><s>Nine universities voluntarily provided their names (seven German, one Austrian and one Swiss).</s></p><p><s>General information about the provision of e-learning at the faculty level is given in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</s><s>At all medical schools, e-learning was an integrated element in their undergraduate medical education curricula.</s><s>The majority of e-learning tools are used as optional tools for students' education.</s><s>Between 60 and 70 % of the medical schools answering used blended learning formats or computer-based trainings as a mandatory part of their curriculum.</s><s>While an optional use of discussion forums was indicated by more than 75 %, mandatory integration of this tool was noted by less than 10 %. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref> shows the relative distribution of various e-learning formats with high levels for e-learning as an addition to face-to-face teaching, and low levels for the use of Wikis and Webinars.</s><s>Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> documents the percentage of e-learning offerings in various disciplines.</s><s>There were no 100 % or 0 % scores.</s><s>High scores were found for Anatomy, Internal Medicine and Emergency Medicine, while Chemistry, Human Genetics and Gerontology had relatively low scores.</s></p><p><s>On the average, medical schools had two permanent staff members working on e-learning (median 1, range 1-5), as well as three assisting students (varying from 0-4 at most places, whereas one university reported eight, and another one 23).</s><s>Fifty percent employed permanent staff almost exclusively in charge for e-learning (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref>).</s><s>The budget for the implementation of elearning each year varied from "no budget" (n = 5) through €10,000-50,000 (n = 4) and €50,000-100,000 (n = 2) up to €100,000-250,000 (n = 2).</s><s>There was a weak negative correlation trend that was not statistically significant for the size of the medical school and their financial means (r(10) = -0.39,</s><s>p = 0.20).</s><s>A weak positive correlation trend which was not statistically significant could be observed for the size of medical school and the number of employees within an elearning department (r(14) = 0.17, p = 0.53).</s></p><p><s>Concerning the impact of the presence of e-learning staff, a significant correlation could be shown for the existence of recommendations for the application of elearning by a medical school (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</s><s>Also, the evaluation of students on the subject of e-learning was performed significantly more often when e-learning staff was present (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref>).</s><s>There were also significantly higher implementation levels of the provided total amount of e-learning items (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>), as well as of the general existence of e-learning offers in the disciplines of medical schools (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Information about the infrastructural support for elearning provision by the medical schools is given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">2</ref>. Out of the responding medical schools, 81 % (n = 26) used a single LMS, 16 % (n = 5) used more than one and only 3 % (n = 1) did not use any at all.</s><s>Twentyfive medical schools provided details of the programs they used for the creation of e-learning contents and 20 listed programs that they used for the recording of lectures (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">3</ref>).</s><s>Special rewards associated with the commitment of teachers to e-learning provision differed in between the medical schools (11 responses).</s><s>The most common rewards were performance-based grants (n = 6) and the awarding of prizes (n = 5) such as Table <ref type="table">1</ref> General information about e-learning provision at medical schools (n = 34; results are expressed as percentage of total answers per item).</s><s>The symbol * indicates a significant difference between medical schools with (34.4 %) and without e-learning staff (9.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>The survey presented here showed that e-learning has reached a high implantation level in the cluster of analyzed mid-European medical schools.</s><s>However, the use of single tools and the distribution of e-learning offerings in individual disciplines were seen to be inhomogeneous among the institutions.</s><s>The results also highlight that there is a potential for improvements regarding motivational incentives for the teaching staff which is dealing with the development and implementation of e-learning scenarios.</s></p><p><s>Concerning the level of e-learning implementation, it can be stated that all of the addressed schools did use e-learning proposals to some extent.</s><s>E-learning is also established in its basic use as a means to offer support to classic teaching of face-to-face courses.</s><s>Among these offers, non-collaborative formats (such as podcasts or lecture recordings) are predominantly used as mandatory supplements.</s><s>Future developments should consist of an integration of mandatory collaborative e-learning tools as a holistic approach that includes digitally driven assessment-formats as well <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[23]</ref>.</s><s>In this study, gender issues were taken into account for developing e-learning activities in general by less than half of the participating medical schools.</s><s>The survey did not go into any details, for instance into the use of gender-neutral language, avoiding gender stereotypes or gender medicine as a topic itself.</s></p><p><s>Among such methods of teaching, many formats seem to be well-known and widely implemented, while tools that focus on online collaboration are less presented especially as mandatory didactic elements.</s><s>As there can be found successful usage of these-like that of wiki-in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[24]</ref>, it can be assumed that their implementation depends both on the familiarity of teachers with the tools as curricular implementation and instructional design of the course <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[25]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>There was an inhomogeneous representation of elearning offers for the single medical disciplines in this survey.</s><s>However, the individual number of medical schools which provided offers was also inhomogeneous for every particular discipline, an observation which has already been reported e.g. for radiology <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[26]</ref>.</s><s>The presented results suggest that there is a lower level of implementation in smaller disciplines, such as otorhinolaryngology or human genetics.</s><s>Here, implemented examples of successful projects in small disciplines <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[27]</ref> Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref> Relative distribution of e-learning offerings in various disciplines at medical schools.</s><s>The numbers of the medical schools answering these items are shown in brackets.</s><s>The main question asked was: "Which of the following disciplines at your medical school offer e-learning?" (Individual disciplines and their grouping into preclinical/clinical/ other disciplines were given).</s><s>The graph shows also the relative implementation level of all disciplines in relation to where e-learning staff was present or not.</s><s>There was a statistically significant higher implementation level of the general existence of e-learning offers in the individual disciplines when e-learning staff was present (40.0 +/−8.5 %) or not (26.2</s><s>+/−6.6 %) in the medical schools (p &lt; 0.001, Mann-Whitney U test)  can be seen as great potential for sharing successful formats between medical schools in the future.</s><s>Regarding infrastructure and staff, all participating medical schools had faculty members as responsible contact persons for e-learning matters.</s><s>For the technological infrastructure it can be stated that LMS were firmly established, with open source platforms predominantly used by the majority of the participants <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>It is remarkable that the majority of the medical schools observed here preferred an in-house open source model to outsourcing their LMS.</s><s>Although the use of open source systems is related to altered in-house costs, this might be acceptable to realize a higher flexibility in customizing the systems to the medical school's needs <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[28]</ref>.</s><s>Consequently, it can be assumed that a high proportion of the named e-learning staff capacities are allocated to host the LMS.</s><s>However, it could also be shown that the existence of e-learning staff is positively correlated with the presence of e-learning offers at a medical school.</s><s>This stresses the use of employing personnel merely dedicated to managing a medical schools' e-learning portfolio.</s></p><p><s>Teachers could make use of different programs for the development of contents in the context of their didactic teaching scenarios, depending on the medical school.</s><s>The vast majority offer trainings or qualification programs for teachers.</s><s>That this is important was also postulated by Cook and Triola as well as by <ref type="bibr">Kowalczyk and</ref> Copley, who stressed the need for faculty development in the use of current tools and ongoing training in emerging technologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">26]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Alongside existing infrastructural services, motivational incentives will be important to encourage especially clinical teachers to deal with the provision of e-learning offers, as this is often time and resource-intensive <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[30]</ref>.</s><s>In the study presented here, less than one-third of the participating medical schools rewarded the creation or implementation of e-learning tools/courses, and less than one fifth awarded funds or prizes for tasks undertaken in the field of e-learning.</s><s>A further problematic aspect was that an evaluation of opinions, attitudes and experiences of teachers who are involved in the development of elearning seems rarely to be taken into account <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</s><s>Although a small proportion of participating centers recognized the implementation of e-learning activities as an additional achievement when looking at admission to a tenure scheme, a larger number planned to adopt their practices in this field-a promising approach, as already reported in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[31]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Quality assurance protocols for e-learning scenarios <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> were in place at only a handful of medical schools.</s><s>As such a standardization is intended to ensure the maintenance of medical standards and the attainment of curricular learning goals <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, addressing this backlog would help to create certified e-learning tools which could be of use for a larger number of medical schools <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[27]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Altogether, the findings of this study can be seen as part of a detailed strategy of most of the medical schools to increase the scope and quality of their e-learning programs in the next years.</s><s>Future challenges for a wide use and cooperation in e-learning aspects among medical schools can in fact build on the high willingness of the medical schools to use and exchange e-learning offerings of other universities when it comes to the education of students and also the training of teachers themselves.</s><s>An interesting approach for the future might here be the development of a central-maybe even international-database of e-learning contents for medical schools, where an exchange or common use of data could take place <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">27]</ref>.</s><s>The majority of the faculties stated that professional societies, academic institutions or ministries should support the development of e-learning activities.</s></p><p><s>Here, an inter-faculty discussion platform supported by these institutions could be helpful to answer many of the questions that the individual medical schools have in the field of e-learning-e.g.</s><s>copyright or financial issues or the establishment of blended learning concepts.</s></p><p><s>Limitations of the validity of the present documentation which must be highlighted include the finding that responses were not collected from all of the medical schools addressed.</s><s>Therefore, the results shown here provide insight into the current status of the field of elearning but cannot be used for definitive statements.</s><s>This could also contribute to a bias that potential regulatory differences in curricular uses of e-learning between individual countries and federal states were not captured by this survey.</s><s>In addition, the option of leaving certain questions blank meant that there was variation in the numbers of answers collected.</s><s>Also, the faculty positions of the addressees were seen to be inhomogeneous, and this may have influenced their understanding and perceptions as a confounding variable in answering the questions.</s><s>Finally, the questions used can only provide a brief representation of the different situations in individual disciplines at the various universities.</s></p><p><s>As this evaluation focused only on the status and elearning supporting strategies at mid-European medical schools, in future studies the focus of analysis should be expanded to meet the conditions in more countries and regions of the world.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p><s>This survey shows that e-learning has gained a firm place in the curricula of those mid-European medical schools addressed.</s><s>Many institutions have grasped the potential and value of a good infrastructure in this field.</s><s>However, the distribution and promotion of e-learning is inhomogeneous.</s><s>Also, teachers' commitments should be given a better incentive.</s><s>Aims for the next years should include fostering a network with a constant dialog between the medical schools for addressing common problems, and development of a database with different quality-tested tools that can be accessed on-demand by all schools.</s><s>This survey should be repeated to document further developments and even extended internationally to compare more countries and to discover potential for future cooperation.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>4 %) with a p &lt; 0.01 (chi-square test of independence) Question Yes (%) General information about e-learning at the medical schools Do e-learning tools for the education of students exist at your medical school?</s><s>Is there a specific set of recommendations for the application of e-learning by your medical school from the academic board or deanery?</s><s>43.8 % * Do they stipulate the use of a quality assurance code for your e-learning activities?</s><s>-If so, are these quality criteria designed to comply with the standards stipulated by the German Medical Association or similar (please see the PDF file attached for details) 48.4 % 20.0 % Is there a faculty-wide strategy for increasing the scope and quality of e-learning tools over the coming years in your medical school?</s><s>58.1 % Do you take gender criteria into account when developing e-learning activities?</s><s>39.3 % Do you wish more support from relevant discipline societies (GMA/GMDS etc.) and academic institutions or public agencies (DFG/BMBF/ State Ministries) for the development of e-learning activities?</s><s>75.9 % "Teacher of the Year".</s><s>Furthermore, support was provided with student assistants or specific teaching projects for e-learning.</s><s>Two medical schools included requirements for the development of e-learning resources as part of their tenure scheme.</s><s>Eight medical schools reported about certification schemes associated with the preparation and implementation of e-learning tools.</s><s>The following solutions were put forward: summary on the basis of semester hours as part of the teaching responsibility (n = 3), regular implementation as a learning format in the course regulations, tenure scheme regulations or federal state teaching regulations (n = 1 for each).</s><s>Two schools did not name any particular arrangement.</s><s>With regards to a question about challenges for the future in the field of e-learning, the 21 responses (Additional file 2) could be crystallized into the following themes: 1. Improvement of the infrastructure and implementation in the curriculum (especially blended learning; reinforced mandatory, less optional use) 2. Creation of a faculty-wide strategy on e-learning 3. Improvement of personal resources and general financing 4. Construction of a system for teachers to encourage the creation of e-learning opportunities, as well as improved integration of teachers into e-learning concepts 5. Intensification of training measures for teachers in e-learning 6. Increased incorporation of smartphones, tablets and social media 7. Improvement of e-learning opportunities (portfolio extension, more interactivity and realism, research on benefits of e-learning and new potentials) 8. Clarification of copyright issues</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig.1Relative use of various e-learning formats at medical schools.</s><s>The numbers of medical schools answering these items are shown in brackets.</s><s>The graph shows the relative implementation level of each item in relation to where e-learning staff was present or not.</s><s>There was a statistically significant higher implementation level of the provided total amount of e-learning items when e-learning staff was present (35.9 +/−13.1 %) versus not present (26.1 +/−13.3</s><s>%) in the medical school (p &lt; 0.05, Mann-Whitney U test)</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,127.28,96.27,340.76,242.65" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,127.28,96.27,340.76,350.31" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Infrastructural information about e-learning provisions at medical schools (n = 34; results are expressed as percentage of total answers per item).</s><s>The symbol * indicates a significant difference between medical schools with (44.8 %) and without e-learning staff (17.2 %) with a p &lt; 0.01 (chi-square test of independence)</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Questions</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Software programs used for the creation of e-learning contents recording of lectures.</s><s>The questions were: "What is/are the name/s of the LMS you are using at your medical school?",</s><s>"Which programs do you offer your teachers for the development and creation of e-learning contents?",</s><s>"Which programs are used alongside those you offer by your teachers on their own initiative (as far as you know of?)", "If you record lectures-which tools do you use?"</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Program type</cell><cell>Product examples</cell></row><row><cell>Authoring systems</cell><cell>Docendo, Mediabird, Mediasite, Articulate, Lectora</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Wondershare (4x), Mediator Authoring Software</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Case-based learning systems CAMPUS (4x), Casus (3x), Inmedea Simulator, Casetrain</cell></row><row><cell>Learning management</cell><cell>Moodle (14x), Ilias (12x), OLAT (3x), Stud.IP (3x), Blackboard (2x), ALMA WEB (1x), Metacoon (1x), MedPol (1x), ILKUM</cell></row><row><cell>systems</cell><cell>(1x)</cell></row><row><cell>Microsoft Office Products</cell><cell>Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Access</cell></row><row><cell>Apple Products</cell><cell>iTunes U, Onyx Mac</cell></row><row><cell>Other products</cell><cell>Adobe Collection (Acrobat, Photoshop, Premiere, E-Learning Suite, CreativeSuite) (2x), Raptivity, Zoomify Image</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Viewer, Primal Pictures, Mediscript Online, Camtasia Studio (11x), WebKit</cell></row><row><cell>Programs for the recording of</cell><cell>Camtasia Studio (10x), Lecturnity (3x), Adobe (Adobe Connect, Adobe Premiere) (3x), WOWZA Streaming Server,</cell></row><row><cell>lectures</cell><cell>RUBcast, Vilea, LifeSize</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>We thank Mrs. Nicole Haberstroh for her technical support in data analysis.</s><s>We also thank Miss Paula S. Wendler for her support in data collection, especially when it came to contacting the correspondence partners at the universities.</s><s>Finally, we thank Mrs. Ellis Rea for her support in English editing of the text.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional files</head><p><s>Additional file 1: The questionnaire, which served as a survey instrument (the text was translated from German into English).</s><s>It was made available to the addressed medical schools in Austria, Germany and Switzerland with the online program SurveyMonkey® (SurveyMonkey, Oregon, USA).</s><s>The survey consisted of 49 items, with 27 closed questions and 22 questions for free text answers.</s><s>(DOCX 30 kb) Additional file 2: Original answers (n = 21) of the participating medical schools to the question "Which challenges do you see in the field of e-learning for your medical school in the next years?"</s><s>(This was translated from German into English.)</s><s>Each number represents commentaries of one medical school (anonymous).</s><s>(DOCX 23 kb)</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Competing interests</head><p><s>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Authors' contributions</head><p><s>DAB and KS designed the study.</s><s>DB, TH, JP and KS collected the data.</s><s>DAB, FB, TH, KS and HP analyzed and interpreted the results.</s><s>DAB drafted the article with substantial support by KS and HP.</s><s>FB, TH, JP, HP and KS revised the paper critically.</s><s>All authors approved the submitted version to be published.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of E-learning in medical education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mintzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leipzig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acad Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="212" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Teaching suturing and knot-tying skills to medical students: a randomized controlled study comparing computer-based video instruction and (concurrent and summary) expert feedback</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Xeroulis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Moulton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Reznick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Leblanc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dubrowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surgery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="442" to="449" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From lecture theatre to portable media: students&apos; perceptions of an enhanced podcast for revision</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shantikumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Teach</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="535" to="538" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A radiological case collection with interactive character as a new element in the education of medical students</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Heye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kurz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eiers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kauffmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schipp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rofo</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">180</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="344" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CAMPUS-a flexible, interactive system for web-based, problem-based learning in health care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ruderich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bauch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Haag</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Leven</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Singer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stud Health Technol Inform</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="921" to="925" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introducing an online community into a clinical education setting: a pilot study of student and staff engagement and outcomes using blended learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tobin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Med Educ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surgical e-learning: validation of multimedia web-based lectures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Ridgway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sheikh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sweeney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Evoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mcdermott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Felle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Educ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="168" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Blended learning positively affects students&apos; satisfaction and the role of the tutor in the problem-based learning process: results of a mixed-method evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Woltering</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Herrler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Spitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Spreckelsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv Health Sci Educ Theory Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="725" to="738" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High efficacy and students&apos; satisfaction after voluntary vs mandatory use of an e-learning program in traumatology and orthopedics-a follow-up study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Back</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Haberstroh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sostmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Schmidmaier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Putzier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Perka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Surg Educ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="353" to="359" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Blended learning: The Magic Is in the Mix</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Masie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Rossett A</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="58" to="63" />
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>The ASTD E-Learning Handbook</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Physicians in traumatology. Critically endangered? Results of an inquiry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Matthes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rixen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tempka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Schmidmaier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wolfl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ottersbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Unfallchirurg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="218" to="222" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An efficient approach to improve the usability of e-learning resources: the role of heuristic evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Davids</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chikte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Halperin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv Physiol Ed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="242" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A systematic review of faculty development initiatives designed to improve teaching effectiveness in medical education: BEME Guide No</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Steinert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Centeno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dolmans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Spencer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gelula</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Teach</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="497" to="526" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">German dental faculty attitudes towards computer-assisted simulation systems correlated with personal and professional profiles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Welk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Splieth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Seyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rosin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Siemer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Dent Educ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leadership&apos;s role in support of online academic programs: implementing an administrative support matrix</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Barefield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perspect Health Inf Manag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quality criteria eLearning of the German Medical Association -Qualitätskriterien eLearning der Bundesärztekammer</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.bundesaerztekammer.de/fileadmin/user_upload/downloads/KritElearningV8.01.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">German Medical Association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014-11">Nov 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Medical education in Korea: the e-learning consortium</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Park</forename><surname>Ie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Teach</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="e397" to="401" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Quality seal eLearning Charité</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Charité</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://elearning.charite.de/services/qualitaetssicherung/qualitaetssiegel_elearning/.2014" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-01">Jan 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">University of Toronto, Faculty of Medicine, eLearning task Force</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>St</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Amant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fechtig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://elearning.innovatingedu.ca/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/Structures-Finances-and-HR-WG-Final-Report.pdf.Accessed29" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Structure, Finances and Human Resources&apos; Working Group Report</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-05">2015. May 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Methoden der empirischen Sozialforschung</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Schnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Esser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Oldenbourg Wissenschaftsverlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Munich</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>9th ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pretesting survey instruments: an overview of cognitive methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Qual Life Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">e-Learning in medical education Part 1: Learning, teaching and assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ellaway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Masters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Amee Guide</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Teach</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="455" to="473" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The application of wiki technology in medical education</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rasmussen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Teach</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discussing patient management online: the impact of roles on knowledge construction for students interning at the paediatric ward</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Wever</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Van Winckel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Valcke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv Health Sci Educ Theory Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Online course delivery modes and design methods in the radiologic sciences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kowalczyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Copley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Radiol Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Case based e-learning in occupational medicine-a European approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kolb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wengenroth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hege</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Praml</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nowak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cantineau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Occup Environ Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="647" to="653" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Key Advantage of Open Source is Not Cost Savings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Scavo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.computereconomics.com/article.cfm?id=1043" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-12-14">2005. 14 Dec 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What is the role of e-learning? Looking past the hype</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Triola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Educ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="930" to="937" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The use of elearning in medical education: a review of the current situation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Choules</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Postgrad Med J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="212" to="216" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">E-learning as evidence of educational scholarship: a survey of chairs of promotion and tenure committees at U.S. medical schools</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Candler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Qadri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Roos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acad Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
