<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">ASSeSSment of DentAl StAtuS AnD PercePtion towArDS orAl HeAltH Among PHArmAcy StuDentS in QuettA, PAkiStAn</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lloyd</forename><surname>Aj</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Balochistan</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Quetta</settlement>
									<country key="PK">Pakistan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">ICON PRO</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Oxford</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Whipps Cross University Hospital &amp; the Royal London Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Celgene Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Uxbridge</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">ICON Epidemiology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Vancouver</settlement>
									<region>BC</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Celgene Corporation</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Warren</settlement>
									<region>NJ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">ASSeSSment of DentAl StAtuS AnD PercePtion towArDS orAl HeAltH Among PHArmAcy StuDentS in QuettA, PAkiStAn</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">AA578998EAA7A0A84C6F5904F5CB7F7C</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:40+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Treatment options continue to emerge for managing psoriasis, with different risk:benefit profiles and routes of administration.</s><s>This study was designed to elicit UK patients' relative strength of preference regarding treatment effectiveness, risks of side effects, and mode/frequency of administration.</s><s>MethOds: A stated preference survey (using a discrete choice experiment [DCE]) was designed to present participants with hypothetical treatment choices.</s><s>Treatments were described in terms of reducing the body surface area (BSA) affected by psoriasis, mode of administration, increase in risk of diarrhea or nausea in the short-term, and 10-year risk of melanoma, tuberculosis, or serious infection (e.g., pneumonia).</s><s>Standard DCE Methodswith an orthogonal design were used; the survey was pilot-tested in 6 participants.</s><s>Results: Psoriasis patients (n= 292; mean age= 48.5 years; mean BSA= 9.3%; mean Dermatology Life Quality Index= 10.5; 25.7% with prior biologic experience and 34.9% with psoriatic arthritis) were recruited in the UK.</s><s>Participants strongly preferred to avoid increasing their risk of melanoma (odds ratio [OR]= 0.44/5% increased 10-year risk), tuberculosis, and serious infections (OR= 0.73/5% increased 10-year risk for both) and preferred twice-daily tablets to weekly injections (OR= 0.74) or injections every 2 weeks (OR= 0.86).</s><s>Participants preferred to avoid treatments with a risk of diarrhea or nausea in the first few weeks after initiation (OR= 0.87/5% increase) and preferred treatments that effectively resolve plaque lesions (OR= 0.93 for each hand palm area still affected).</s><s>All ORs were statistically significant.</s><s>Biologic-naïve participants were more likely to prefer oral tablets to injections and were less risk-tolerant for serious adverse events.</s><s>cOnclusiOns: All attributes of treatment considered were found to be significant predictors of choice.</s><s>Patients showed strong preferences for avoiding treatments with risk of serious toxicities and avoiding injectable therapy, and a lower preference for treatments with greater efficacy.</s><s>These preferences were consistently stronger in biologic-naïve patients.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Objectives: This study is design to assess the dental status and perception towards oral health among pharmacy students.</s><s>MethOds: The study is questionnaire bases cross sectional study.</s><s>Study is conducted in Faculty of Pharmacy, University of Balochistan, Quetta by using convenient sampling.</s><s>The descriptive statistics was used to present the demographic and disease related information.</s><s>Inferential statistics was used to the evaluation relationship among study variables.</s><s>All analyses were performed using SPSS 20.0.</s><s>Results: Out of 197 participants 196 (66.0%) were male.</s><s>Majority of participants 267 (89.9%) having age ranges between 18-24 years.</s><s>One hundred ninety one (64.3%)</s><s>describe that they have no problem in chewing and 172 (53.9%) are satisfied with their teeth appearance which shows the satisfaction of participants concerning their oral dental health.</s><s>Majority of respondents 120 (40.4%) were satisfied with their teeth.</s><s>One hundred and sixty one (54.2%)</s><s>respondents were having minor teeth problems.</s><s>Score for self-rating of dental health in majority of participants 121 (40.7%) was excellent.</s><s>When discussing the self-rating score no significance difference was found in participants having dental problem, broken filling, broken tooth, cavities, bleeding gums, bad breath, stained teeth, aches and broken denture.</s><s>cOnclusiOns: Present Study concluded that although the participant were satisfied with their oral dental health, yet they are not aware about the proper hygiene and oral dental health.</s><s>Awareness program must be initiated for students, focusing primarily on dental/oral health.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PSS58 cHArActeriSticS of Acne VulgAriS in euroPeAn ADoleScentS AnD PAtientS PercePtionS</head><p><s>Delarue A 1 , Zkik A 2 , Berdeaux G 2 1 Pierre Fabre DermatoCosmétique, Lavaur, France, 2 Pierre Fabre, Boulogne Billancourt, France Objectives: Acne vulgaris is one of the most common skin conditions, affecting primarily the adolescents.</s><s>The psychological impact associated with the condition could be explained by the predominance of lesions in the face.</s><s>The objective of the present study was to describe the characteristics of the disease and its management in Europe considering the patients' perspective.</s><s>MethOds: A cross-sectional survey was conducted in a sample of individuals residing in Europe and aged 15 to 24.</s><s>To ensure representativeness, the quota method was applied considering age, sex, residence location and occupational status of the reference person.</s><s>Study participants were asked to complete an online questionnaire specifically developed for the study and Resultswere analysed descriptively.</s><s>Results: A total of 3099 study participants declared currently having acne.</s><s>Outside of the face, the back was affected by lesions in 61.05% of individuals on average (65.95% of men and 56.22% of women).</s><s>Most patients (27.03%) reported their general physician or dermatologist as the main source of information on acne.</s><s>However, advices were also often sought from relatives and internet.</s><s>In addition, whereas the diagnosis of acne is generally made by a dermatologist (29.69%), most patients, reporting acne in our study, declared that no medical diagnosis was ever made (39.3%).</s><s>This can explain why most individuals (28.65%) reported using anti-acne cosmetics advised by their pharmacists instead of prescribed treatments.</s><s>Finally, according to patients' perspective, acne is generally considered a minor issue however, for 21.3% of individuals it represents a major problem and 1.9% lives it as a real burden.</s><s>These Resultsare consistent across the selected European countries.</s><s>cOnclusiOns: Acne is a common disease considered a minor issue by most adolescent patients and commonly self-managed using anti-acne cosmetics.</s><s>However, patients often sought information and advices from healthcare professionals such as general practitioners, dermatologists or pharmacists.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PSS59 imPAct of AlexitHymiA AnD DiSeASe cHArActeriSticS on work ProDuctiVity AnD ActiVity in PSoriASiS PAtientS witH SHort DiSeASe DurAtion: ePiDePSo multicentre StuDy</head><p><s>Paul C 1 , Girolomoni G 2 , Radtke MA 3 , Sampogna F 4 , Spuls P 5 , Kirby B 6 , Brunori M 7 , Smirnov P 8 , Bergmans P 9 , Rundle J 10 , Lavie F 7 , Puig L 11</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PSS54 firSt reAl-worlD StuDy ASSeSSing HeAltH utility VAlueS for cHronic SPontAneouS/iDioPAtHic urticAriA uSing tHe eQ-5D</head><p><s>McBride D 1 , Chambenoit O 2 , Chiva-Razavi S 2 , Lynde C 3 , Sussman G 4 , Chapman-Rothe N 5 , Weller K 6 , Maurer M 6 , Koenders J 7 , Knulst AC 8 , Elberink JN 9 , Halliday A 10 , Alexopoulos ST 10 , Nakonechna A 11 , Abouzakouk M 11 , Sweeney C 12 , Radder C 12 , Wolin D 13 , Hollis K 12 , Tian H 14 , Balp M 15 , Grattan C 16 1 RTI Health Solutions, Manchester, UK, 2 Novartis Pharmaceuticals Canada Inc., Dorval, QC,   Canada, 3 Lynderm Research Inc., Toronto, ON, Canada, 4  Objectives: Although chronic spontaneous (idiopathic) urticaria (CSU/CIU) is not life threatening, it can significantly impact a patient's life when not adequately controlled by medication.</s><s>Patients experience disturbing itch, intermittent pain, lack of sleep, occupational disabilities and social isolation with high impact on healthrelated quality of life (HRQoL).</s><s>However, data on the humanistic burden associated with symptomatic persistent CSU/CIU is scarce.</s><s>Here we present data on utility values from the first international burden of illness study in CSU/CIU.</s><s>MethOds: ASSURE-CSU is an observational, non-interventional study which included a 1-year retrospective medical record abstraction and a cross-sectional patient-reported outcomes survey.</s><s>Adult CSU/CIU patients aged &gt; 18 years with disease persisting for ≥ 12 months despite treatment were assessed.</s><s>Utility values and domain scores from EQ-5D-3L were described for Canada, Germany, UK and the Netherlands.</s><s>Results: A total of 88, 98, 79 and 99 patients completed the patient survey which included the EQ-5D-3L in Canada, Germany, UK and the Netherlands, respectively.</s><s>The mean (SD) EQ-5D-3L utility score was 0.71 (0.30) for Canada; 0.71 (0.25) for Germany; 0.72 (0.31) for UK and 0.76 (0.27) for the Netherlands.</s><s>Among the different dimensions of EQ-5D-3L, pain/discomfort was the most affected with 62.0%, 70.5%, 61.5% and 56.6% of patients reporting moderate to extreme problems, respectively.</s><s>The second most affected dimension was anxiety/depression for Canada, Germany and UK with 41.8%, 51.6% and 45.6% of patients reporting moderate to extreme problems, respectively.</s><s>For the Netherlands, usual activities (44.4%) was the second most affected dimension.</s><s>Impact across all dimensions increased with disease severity and correspondingly utility values decreased.</s><s>cOnclusiOns: This is the first real-world study to assess utility values in CSU/CIU using EQ-5D.</s><s>Utility scores were similar among the countries and ranged from 0.71 to 0.76, suggesting that CSU/CIU have significant impact on the patients' health status.</s><s>Pain/discomfort was the most affected dimension across countries.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PSS55 DiSeASe BurDen, outcomeS AnD coStS Among ADultS ADmitteD to HoSPitAl in tHe uniteD kingDom (uk) Due to PlAQue or erytHroDermic PSoriASiS</head><p><s>Schaefer C 1 , Mamolo C 2 , Cappelleri JC 2 , Le C 3 , Daniel S 4 , Mallbris L 5 , Griffiths CE 6 1 Covance Market Access Services Inc., Gaithersburg, MD, USA, 2 Pfizer Inc., Groton, CT, USA, 3 Covance Market Access Services Inc., San Diego, CA, USA, 4 Covance Market Access Services   Inc., Conshohocken, PA, USA, 5 Pfizer Inc., Collegeville, PA, USA, 6 University of <ref type="bibr">Manchester and Manchester Academic Health Science Centre and Salford Royal NHS Foundation Trust, Salford, UK</ref> Objectives: To evaluate disease burden, clinical and patient-reported outcomes and healthcare costs of patients admitted to hospital for management of plaque or erythrodermic psoriasis.</s><s>MethOds: This observational study enrolled 61 eligible patients from 107 hospital stays across 9 UK hospitals.</s><s>Sites recorded Psoriasis Area Severity Index (PASI) at admission and discharge, psoriasis treatments, and length of stay (LOS).</s><s>Patients reported psoriasis-related symptoms, health status (SF-12v2, EQ-5D-3L), mood (HADS), productivity (WPAI), and dermatology-related quality of life (DLQI) at admission, and also reported psoriasis-related symptoms, EQ-5D-3L, and DLQI at discharge.</s><s>An algorithm assigned cost/hospital stay.</s><s>Descriptive statistics are based on those responding to each item.</s><s>Statistical significance evaluated at the 0.05 level.</s><s>Results: Mean age was 45.5 years; 50.8% were male.</s><s>Mean time since psoriasis diagnosis was 20.0 years.</s><s>Most (78.7%) had ≥ 1 previous psoriasis-related hospitalization.</s><s>Mean number of physician-diagnosed co-morbid conditions was 2.5.</s><s>At admission, mean SF-12v2 Physical and Mental component summary scores were 35.4 and 32.1, respectively; mean HADS scores were 9.7 (anxiety) and 9.6 (depression) indicating substantial impairment.</s><s>Forty-five percent reported changing job, role, or position at work due to psoriasis.</s><s>Mean WPAI activity impairment at admission was 68.7%; among the 35.1% employed for pay, mean WPAI work impairment was 79.2%.</s><s>Mean PASI improved from admission to discharge (25.2→ 12.1; p&lt; 0.0001).</s><s>Also, improvement was seen at discharge for EQ-5D-3L (0.34 → 0.60), DLQI total score (20.1→ 12.0), and psoriasis symptom scores (all p&lt; 0.05).</s><s>Mean (range) LOS was 17.0 (2,71) days; for 8 patients achieving a 75% reduction in PASI (PASI75), mean LOS was 18.1 vs. 13.1 days for 27 patients not achieving PASI75 (p= 0. 11).</s><s>Mean (SD) cost/hospital stay was £4,875 (±£3,096).</s><s>cOnclusiOns: Disease burden, LOS and cost are substantial among patients hospitalized for psoriasis.</s><s>On average, patients improved during their hospital stay.</s><s>Nonetheless, they reported suboptimal clinical and patientreported outcomes at discharge.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>1St Michael's Hospital,University  of Toronto, Toronto, ON, Canada, 5 Novartis Pharma GmbH, Nuernberg, Germany, 6Charite -Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany, 7 Novartis Pharma B.V., Arnhem, The Netherlands, 8 University Medical Center Utrecht, Utrecht, The Netherlands, 9 Unviersity Medical Center Groningen, Groningen, The Netherlands, 10 Novartis Pharmaceuticals UK Limited, Surrey,UK,  11 Hull and East Yorkshire NHS Hospital Trust, Hull, UK, 12 RTI Health Solutions, Research</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Triangle Park, NC, USA, 13 RTI Health Solutions, Ann Arbor, MI, USA, 14 Novartis Pharmaceuticals</cell></row><row><cell>Corporation, East Hanover, NJ, USA, 15 Novartis Pharma AG, Basel, Switzerland, 16 Norfolk and</cell></row><row><cell>Norwich University Hospital, Norwich, UK</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
