<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Dataset on the activation of Müller cells through macrophages upon hypoxia in the retina</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-11-22">22 November 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Christina</forename><surname>Nürnberg</surname></persName>
							<email>christina.nuernberg@med.uni-heidelberg.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ophthalmology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Freie Universität Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Berlin Institute of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Leibniz Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Norbert</forename><surname>Kociok</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ophthalmology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Freie Universität Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Berlin Institute of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Leibniz Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Claudia</forename><surname>Brockmann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ophthalmology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Freie Universität Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Berlin Institute of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Leibniz Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Timo</forename><surname>Lischke</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">German Rheumatism Research Center Berlin</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sergio</forename><surname>Crespo-Garcia</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ophthalmology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Freie Universität Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Berlin Institute of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Leibniz Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nadine</forename><surname>Reichhart</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ophthalmology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Freie Universität Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Berlin Institute of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Leibniz Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Susanne</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cellular Neuroscience</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Max Delbrück Center in the Helmholtz Society</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ria</forename><surname>Baumgrass</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">German Rheumatism Research Center Berlin</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sabine</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Eming</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Dermatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cologne</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sandra</forename><surname>Beer-Hammer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pharmacology and Experimental Therapy and Interfaculty Center of Pharmacogenomics and Drug Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Tübingen</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Antonia</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Joussen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ophthalmology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Freie Universität Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Berlin Institute of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Leibniz Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Dataset on the activation of Müller cells through macrophages upon hypoxia in the retina</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2017-11-22">22 November 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F39409E4C7D39169071754E1F516D1BA</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.dib.2017.11.062</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 14 October 2017 Received in revised form 15 November 2017 Accepted 16 November 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:40+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>The dataset presented in this article complements the article entitled "Myeloid cells contribute indirectly to VEGF expression upon hypoxia via activation of Müller cells" (C.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Specifications Table</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subject area</head><p><s>Biology More specific subject area Medicine -Ophthalmology.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Type of data</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Value of the Data</head><p><s>These data give an overview of the relative Cre mRNA expression in the retina as well as the genomic recombination efficiency in brain and bone marrow and the Cre and VEGF-A mRNA expression in brain, bone marrow and lung as part of the validation of the VEGF fl/fl LysMCre (here named VEGF mcko ) knockout mouse model.</s><s>These data are important for the use of the same knockout mouse in other studies.</s></p><p><s>Flow cytometric data providing an overview of T memory cells, natural killer (NK) cells, and natural killer-T (NKT) cells as percentage of CD45 positive cells in the retina of knockout and control retinas under normoxic and hypoxic conditions are presented.</s></p><p><s>The presented pathological retinal features in the model of oxygen-induced retinopathy in clodronate-liposome treated mice is of interest for similar studies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Data</head><p><s>Seven-day-old pups and the nursing dam were exposed to a 75% oxygen containing environment for five days before replacement in normal housing conditions causing a neovascular stimulus via relative hypoxia until further analysis on postnatal days 14 and 17.</s><s>The oxygen box was opened daily for a very short period to check on pups and mother.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Experimental design, materials, and methods</head><p><s>The experimental procedures are described in the related research article: Nürnberg et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>).</s><s>A more detailed description of some of the methods used in this article as followed Figs.</s><s>1-8:</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Material and methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Mouse model of oxygen induced retinopathy</head><p><s>Oxygen Induced Retinopathy (OIR) was induced as described in the main text with few modifications (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>The nursing dam as well as the offspring was kept under normal housing conditions from day P0 to P7.</s><s>On day P7 the animals were exposed to a 75% oxygen containing environment for five days using a special oxygen chamber (Model THF3384, EHRET Labor-u.</s><s>Pharmatechnik GmbH, Emmendingen, Germany).</s><s>In contrast to the original protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, the oxygen chamber was opened once daily for a few minutes to check on dam and pups.</s><s>On P12 the mice were transferred back into normal housing conditions until P14 or P17 for analysis.</s><s>A surrogate dam was provided if the nursing dam passed awaya very rare occurrence though.</s><s>Room air controls were kept under normal housing conditions at all times.</s><s>All non-liposome treated mice were genotyped twice: on P12 ear punch tissue was used for DNA isolation.</s><s>All animals were re-genotyped after completion of the experiment by tail tip biopsy.</s><s>For the VEGF-A flox PCR the following primers were used: muVEGF419.F (5′-CCTGGCCCTCAAGTACACCTT-3′); muVEGF567.R (5′-TCCGTACGACGCATTTCTAG-3′).</s><s>In the presence of a loxP-1 site these primers generated a 168 bp long fragment, and an approximately 100 bp long band in the wildtype.</s><s>Evidence of the LysMCre transgene was shown using the following primers: IMR3066 (5′-CCCAGAAATGCCAGATTACG-3′); IMR3067 (5′-CTTGGGCTG CCAGAATTTCTC-3′); IMR3068 (5′-TTACAGTCGGCCAGGCTGAC-3′).</s><s>Presence of the transgene was indicated by a 700 bp long band and the presence of a wildtype allele by a 350 bp long band.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Mouse organ dissection</head><p><s>Organs of mice were dissected for various reasons including genomic PCR, mRNA expression level analysis, histological analysis and flow cytometry.</s><s>All mice were first narcotized using a mixture of 10 mg/g bodyweight ketamine (Ketamine-Actavis®, Actavice Group PTC ehf., Hafnarfjördur, Island) and 0.015 mg/g bodyweight xylazine (CP-Pharma, Burgdorf, Germany) and then euthanized by cervical dislocation, and the tail tip was cut off for the second confirmation of the genotype.</s><s>Both the femoral and the tibial bone were extracted from the leg, the bone marrow flushed out with a 20G syringe needle (B.</s><s>Braun, Melsungen, Germany) into the tube with PBS, and centrifuged at 1400 rpm for five minutes.</s><s>The thorax was cut open and thyme, spleen as well as the lungs were dissected and cleaned from blood as best as possible.</s><s>The eyes were enucleated and dissected under microscopic control.</s><s>Cornea and lens were removed and the retina carefully dissected out of the eyecup removing vitreous body and RPE cells as best as possible.</s><s>Finally, the skull was cut open, the brain extracted and cut into halves.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">DNA isolation for genotyping</head><p><s>For purification of total genomic DNA from different mouse tissues, the DNeasy Blood and Tissue Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) was used and the manufacturer's instructions were followed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">mRNA expression levels</head><p><s>For reverse transcription of cDNA, the "High-Capacity cDNA Reverse Transcription Kit" (Applied Biosystems, Darmstadt, Germany) was used and the manufacturer's instructions were followed.</s><s>In this experimental setup, β-Actin was chosen as the housekeeping gene for control since oxygen treatment influences the expression levels of glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) in vitro <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s>Transcripts of interest were cDNAs encoding Cre and VEGF-A in the retina, bone marrow or brain.</s><s>SensiFAST SYBR (BIOLINE, Luckenwalde, Germany) was used for quantitative Real-Time PCR purposes, and the manufacturer's instructions were followed.</s><s>The following primers were used: VEGF-A fwd (5′-CAGCTATTG CCGTCCGATTGA GA-3′) and VEGF-A rev (5′-TGC TGG CTT TGG TGA GGT TTG AT-3′) amplifying a 201 bp long product; Cre fwd (5′-GATTTCGACCAGGTTCGTTC-3′) and Cre rev (5′-GCT AACCAGCGTTTTCGTTC-3′); β-Actin fwd (5′-AAGGCCAACCGTGAAAAGAT-3′) and β-Actin rev (5′-GTGGTACGACCAGAGGCATAC).</s><s>The samples were analyzed in a LightCycler 480 and calculations were performed using the LightCycler software (Roche, Basel, Switzerland).</s><s>All samples were run in triplicates and the melting curve of each product was monitored and probes with unspecific melting curves were excluded from the analysis.</s><s>In order to verify the specificity of the primers that were Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref>. Primer specificity analysis in the retina and cell culture Cre and VEGF-A mRNA expression analysis in relevant tissues and cells.</s><s>(A) Left panel: Primer specificity in the retina was monitored by separation of the amplification product in the retina of VEGF mcko and control mice under normoxic und hypoxic conditions through a 2% agarose gel.</s><s>The β-Actin primers amplified a 110 bp long product, the VEGF-A primers 201 bp product and the Cre primers a 195 bp long product.</s><s>Right panel: Primer specificity in human MIO-M1 cells was monitored by separation of the amplification products through a 2% agarose gel.</s><s>β-Actin primers amplified a 206 bp long product and the VEGF-A primers a 76 bp product.</s><s>(B) After separation through an agarose gel, primer specificity was further verified by purification and subsequent sequencing of the amplification product.</s><s>The graph shows the transcript sequence for the amplification product for each primer pair (β-Actin, VEGF-A, Cre).</s><s>(C) Relative Cre mRNA expression levels in the brain.</s><s>Measurement of relative Cre mRNA expression levels of VEGF mcko and control mice on P14 and P17 under normoxic and hypoxic conditions in the brain (animal numbers per group are indicated in the figure on each bar) (P14: control normoxia 2.18×10 −7 76.53×10 −7 , VEGF mcko normoxia 7.76×10 −5 79.83×10 −5 , control hypoxia 070, VEGF mcko hypoxia 070; P17: control normoxia 2.07×10 −6 71.07×10 −6 , VEGF mcko normoxia 0.003870.0078,</s><s>control hypoxia 1.52×10 −6 72.91×10 −6 , VEGF mcko hypoxia 0.0002470.00021).</s><s>(D) Relative Cre mRNA expression levels in the bone marrow.</s><s>Measurement of relative Cre mRNA expression levels of VEGF mcko and control mice on P14 and P17 under normoxic and hypoxic conditions in the bone marrow (animal numbers per group are indicated in the figure on each bar) (P14: control normoxia 7.89×10 −5 70.00017, VEGF mcko normoxia 0.01270.0089,</s><s>control hypoxia 070, VEGF mcko hypoxia 0.0170.0028;</s><s>P17: control normoxia 2.47×10 −6 73.95×10 −6 , VEGF mcko normoxia 0.01470.0071,</s><s>control hypoxia 0.0001170.00023,</s><s>VEGF mcko hypoxia 0.00770.0016).</s><s>(E) Relative VEGF-A mRNA expression levels in the brain (microglia cells).</s><s>Measurement of relative VEGF-A mRNA expression levels of VEGF mcko and control mice on P14 and P17 under normoxic and hypoxic conditions in the brain (animal numbers per group are indicated in the figure on each bar) (P14 VEGF mcko normoxia 0.01570.015;</s><s>P17 VEGF mcko normoxia 0.08670.049).</s><s>(F) Relative VEGF-A mRNA expression levels in the bone marrow.</s><s>Measurement of relative VEGF-A mRNA expression levels of VEGF mcko and control mice on P14 and P17 under normoxic and hypoxic conditions in the bone marrow (animal numbers per group are indicated in the figure on each bar) (P14: control normoxia 0.009370.0037,</s><s>VEGF mcko normoxia 0.005670.0018,</s><s>control hypoxia 0.01370.0046,</s><s>VEGF mcko hypoxia 0.008270.004;</s><s>P17: control normoxia 0.004870.0013,</s><s>VEGF mcko normoxia 0.004670.0007,</s><s>control hypoxia 0.008370.0069,</s><s>VEGF mcko hypoxia 0.003470.0006).</s><s>(G) Relative VEGF-A mRNA expression levels in the lungs.</s><s>Measurement of relative VEGF-A mRNA expression levels of VEGF mcko and control mice on P14 and P17 under normoxic and hypoxic conditions in the bone marrow (animal numbers per group are indicated in the figure on each bar).</s><s>The lungs served as positive control organs for VEGF-A mRNA analysis.</s><s>(P14 control normoxia 0.2170.072,</s><s>VEGF mcko normoxia 0.18370.068,)</s><s>control hypoxia 0.14970.031,</s><s>VEGF mcko hypoxia 0.14870.017;</s><s>P17 control normoxia 0.24470.031,</s><s>VEGF mcko normoxia 0.22170.067,</s><s>control hypoxia 0.2370.037).</s><s>used, amplification products were separated on a 2% agarose gel, the DNA bands were purified from the agarose using QIAquick Gel Extraction Kit (Qiagen) and the manufacturer's instructions were followed before sequencing.</s><s>Due to a very high amount of mRNA yield, the beta-Actin primers bound at a second binding site within the beta-Actin sequence, causing double peak melting curve.</s><s>Sequencing of both peaks revealed that both products were beta-Actin products.</s><s>Also the other products were primer specific.</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">% Ly6C þ CD3 þ of CD45 þ</formula><p><s>cells): P14 hypoxia: VEGF mcko n ¼ 8; 2.0 71.14%; control n ¼ 9; 1.56 7 0.64%; P17 hypoxia: VEGF mcko n ¼5; 1.23 7 0.78%; control n ¼7; 1.16 70.38%.</s><s>P14 normoxia: VEGF mcko n ¼ 15; 0.55 7 0.48%; control n ¼6; 0.417 0.41%; P17 normoxia: VEGF mcko n ¼10; 0.2 7 0.08%; control n ¼7; 0.13 70.07%.</s><s>(B) NK cells as percentage of CD45 positive cells (% NK1.1 þ CD3of CD45 þ cells): P14 hypoxia: VEGF mcko n ¼6; 2.36 7 2.61%; control n ¼ 7; 0.8 7 1.71%.</s><s>P14 normoxia VEGF mcko n ¼ 12; 0.32 7 1.67%; control n ¼ 6; 0.26 70.27%.</s><s>P17 hypoxia VEGF mcko n ¼5; 0.247 0.11%; control n ¼7; 0.477 0.17%.</s><s>P17 normoxia VEGF mcko n ¼10; 0.12 7 0.05%; control n ¼ 7; 0.12 70.07%.</s><s>(C) NKT cells as percentage of CD45 positive cells (% NK1.1 þ CD3 þ of CD45 þ cells): P14 hypoxia: VEGF mcko n ¼ 8; 13.917 11.24%; control n ¼9; 13.02 7 4.92%.</s><s>P17 hypoxia: VEGF mcko n ¼ 5; 5.117 1.35%; control n ¼ 7; 4.53 7 1.47%.</s><s>P14 normoxia: VEGF mcko n ¼ 15; 6.7 74.43%; control n¼ 8; 4.83 7 3.93%.</s><s>P17 normoxia: VEGF mcko n ¼10; 0.36 7 0.23%; control n ¼ 7; 0.12 70.07%.</s><s>Oberländer for embedding and cutting the paraffin sections, and to Gabriele Fels for support in conducting some immunostainings.</s></p><p><s>This study was funded by DFG Jo 324/10-2 (AMJ) and SFB 829 (SAE), a grant from the Christian and Emmy Sörensen Stiftung (CN), the Ilse-Palm Stiftung (AMJ), Bayer HealthCare AG, O_006_CHO (AMJ), a Marie Curie grant from the European Commission in the framework of the REVAMMAD ITN (Initial Training Research network), Project number 316990 (SC-G), and LOM of Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin.</s><s>Dr. Claudia Brockmann is participant in the BIH-Charité Clinical Scientist Program funded by the Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin and the Berlin Institute of Health.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Transparency document. Supporting information</head><p><s>Transparency data associated with this article can be found in the online version at https://doi.org/</s><s>10.1016/j.dib.2017.11.062.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1.</s><s>Oxygen-induced retinopathy mouse model.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 2. Validation of the VEGF fl/fl LysMCre mouse model in the retina.</s><s>(A) Relative Cre mRNA expression levels in the retina.</s><s>Measurement of relative Cre mRNA expression levels by quantitative Real-Time PCR in VEGF mcko and control mice under normoxic and hypoxic conditions (animal numbers per group are indicated in the figure on each bar) as an indirect indication of the occurrence of recombination in the retina on P14 (VEGF mcko hypoxia 5.48×10 −4 7 5.56×10 −4 ; VEGF mcko normoxia 6.63×10 −4 710.06×10 −4 ) and on P17 (VEGF mcko hypoxia 6.46×10 −4 7 6.85×10 −4 ; VEGF mcko normoxia 11.13×10 −4 718.58×10 −4 ).</s><s>(Cre mRNA expression in the control tissues brain and bone marrow Fig. 3C, D). (B) Genomic recombination efficiency in various murine tissues.</s><s>Detection of the length of the VEGF-A gene in thyme (A), brain (B), spleen (C) and bone marrow (D) in three mice per group of VEGF mcko (VEGF fl/fl Cre tg/ þ ) and two types of control animals through genomic PCR analysis.</s><s>DNA from the bone marrow and spleen was isolated after magnetic cell sorting of CD11b positive cells.</s><s>A 420 bp fragment in VEGF mcko mice (VEGF fl/fl Cre tg/ þ ) indicates the occurrence of recombination, a 1934 bp long fragment was found in the floxed and a 1866 bp long fragment in the wildtype control animals.</s><s>(C) Screen for Pdeb rd1 mutation.</s><s>Genomic PCR screen for a Pdeb rd1 mutation causing postnatal photoreceptor degeneration in three VEGF mcko (VEGF fl/fl Cre tg/ þ ) and three control animals (VEGF fl/fl Cre þ / þ ).</s><s>A 400 bp long fragment was proof of the presence of a wildtype allele and ruled out the presence of the mutation, which would have been indicated by a 550 bp long band.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,41.95,66.73,376.82,195.99" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 3. (continued)</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,47.40,66.33,378.47,423.21" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 5. Histochemistry of CD11b positive cells in spleen sections.</s><s>Representative staining of CD11b positive cells in spleens of control mice kept under hypoxic conditions.</s><s>Clodronate injection (right) led to a depletion of CD11b positive cells whereas sections of PBS injected controls (left) still showed a considerable amount of CD11b positive cells (dark staining).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,74.67,328.25,324.00,155.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 6.</s><s>Presence of mononuclear phagocytes (MPs) in close proximity to blood vessels.</s><s>Representative images for mononuclear phagocytes (CD11b in red) and vessels (AF488-Isolectin-IB4 in green) of retinal flatmount preparations on P14 and P17 under hypoxic conditions in control mice.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 7. Water control for vimentin and GFAP stainings for Müller cell activation.</s><s>Representative images of water controls for vimentin (rabbit anti mouse-IgG-Alexa488 as secondary antibody) and GFAP (goat anti rabbit-IgG-Cy3 a secondary antibody) staining of Müller cells on P17 under hypoxic conditions in VEGF mcko mice.</s><s>The primary antibodies were omitted.</s><s>Nuclei are costained with DAPI.</s><s>Primary antibodies used: rabbit anti-GFAP (DAKO, Glostrup, Denmark) and monoclonal mouse anti-Vimentin antibody (Santa Cruz, Dallas, Texas, USA).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,122.97,66.73,180.00,303.14" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,41.95,66.73,378.03,345.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Table, text file, graph, figure fl/fl LysMCre tg/ þ (here named VEGF mcko ) and C57Bl/6J were used as experimental animals.</s><s>VEGF-A fl/fl LysMCre þ / þ (here named controls) were used as controls Experimental features qPCR: RNA-isolation was conducted with the NucleoSpin RNA Mini Kit (Machery Nagel, Düren, Germany) For reverse transcription of cDNA, the "High-Capacity cDNA Reverse Transcription Kit" (Applied Biosystems, Darmstadt, Germany) was used.</s><s>FACS: Spleen, bone marrow and retina samples were mashed through cell strainer (70 μm for spleen and bone marrow and 40 μm for the retina).</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>How data was</cell><cell>PCR processor (LightCycler 480, Roche, Basel Switzerland),</cell></row><row><cell>acquired</cell><cell>FACS (LSRFortessa flow cytometer (BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ, USA)),</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>data analyzed with FlowJo software (version 9.8.1; Treestar, Ashland, OR, USA),</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Microscope (Axio Imager.M2 microscope (Zeiss, Jena, Germany)</cell></row><row><cell>Data format</cell><cell>Analyzed</cell></row><row><cell>Experimental factors</cell><cell>VEGF-A Afterwards, the cells were re-suspended in PBS, centrifuged and used for FACS</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>analysis.</cell></row><row><cell>Data source</cell><cell>Berlin, Germany</cell></row><row><cell>location</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Data accessibility Data are with this article</cell></row><row><cell>Related research</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>article</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>Christina Nürnberg, Norbert Kociok, Claudia Brockmann, Timo Lischke, Sergio Crespo-Garcia, Nadine Reichhart, Susanne Wolf, Ria Baumgrass, Sabine A. Eming, Sandra Beer-Hammer, and Antonia M. Joussen.</s><s>Myeloid cells contribute indirectly to VEGF expression upon hypoxia via activation of other cell types Müller cells.</s><s>Exp.</s><s>Eye Res.</s><s>2017.</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Antibodies used.</s></p></div></figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p><s>We thank Dr. Napoleone Ferrara for kindly providing the VEGF-A flox line and Dr. Irmgard Förster for providing the LysMCre line.</s><s>We thank Dr. Olaf Strauß for constructive discussion.</s><s>Special thanks go to Dr. Fee Schmitt and Claudia Müller for her support in conducting the qPCR data, to Karin</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Myeloid cells contribute indirectly to VEGF expression upon hypoxia via activation of Müller cells Exp</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nürnberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kociok</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Brockmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lischke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Crespo-Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Reichhart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Baumgrass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Eming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Beer-Hammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Joussen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eye Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxygen-induced retinopathy in the mouse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Wesolowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mclellan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kostyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Amato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sullivan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>D'amore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Invest. Ophthalmol. Vis. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct comparison of GAPDH, beta-actin, cyclophilin, and 28S rRNA as internal standards for quantifying RNA levels under hypoxia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Simons</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">259</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="523" to="526" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
