<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Petruschke</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of General Practice &amp; Family Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jena University Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Jena</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ramsauer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Vivantes Klinikum Neukölln</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Obstetrics Department]</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Klinik für Geburtsmedizin [Vivantes Hospital Neukölln</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Borde</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Alice Salomon University of Applied Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Gynaecology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow Clinic</addrLine>
									<settlement>Charité, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Schlüsselwörter</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">"</forename><surname>Geburt</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">"</forename><surname>Schwangerschaft</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">"</forename><surname>Entbindung</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">"</forename><surname>Schmerz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">"</forename><surname>Wehen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">"</forename><surname>Geburtsschmerz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Prof</roleName><forename type="middle">Matthias</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin Campus Virchow-Klinikum Klinik für Gynäkologie Augustenburger Platz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">0016-5751</idno>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">C90EAC7FA43974D42EFD096E1554D8C0</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1055/s-0042-109397</idno>
					<note type="submission">received 11. 1. 2016 revised 27. 5. 2016 accepted 29. 5. 2016</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:40+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction:</head><p><s>The starting point of this study was the considerably lower rate of epidural analgesia use among women of Turkish origin in Germany compared to non-immigrant women in the German Research Foundation (DFG)-funded study entitled "Perinatal Health and Migration Berlin".</s><s>The study aimed to identify possible differences in the womenʼs attitudes towards epidural analgesia.</s><s>Methods: Exploratory study with semi-structured interviews, interviews lasting 17 minutes on average were conducted with 19 women of Turkish origin and 11 non-immigrant women at a Berlin hospital.</s><s>The interviews were subjected to a qualitative content analysis.</s><s>Results: Immigrant women of Turkish origin in Germany more frequently ascribe meaning to the pain associated with vaginal delivery.</s><s>They more frequently categorically reject the use of epidural analgesia, 1) for fear of long-term complications such as paralysis and back pain and 2) based on the view that vaginal delivery with epidural analgesia is not natural.</s><s>Information on epidural analgesia is frequently obtained from a variety of sources from their social setting, in particular, by word of mouth.</s><s>The women in both groups stated that they would take the decision to use epidural analgesia independent of their partnerʼs opinion.</s><s>Discussion: The differences in epidural analgesia use rates observed correspond to the womenʼs attitudes.</s><s>For the immigrant women of Turkish origin in Germany, the attitude towards using epidural analgesia is based in part on misinformation.</s><s>In order to enable the women to make an informed decision, epidural analgesia could receive a stronger focus during childbirth courses.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Einleitung: Ausgangspunkt der hier vorliegenden Studie war die deutlich niedrigere Periduralanästhesie-(PDA-)Rate bei Schwangeren mit Migrationshintergrund (MH) Türkei im Vergleich zu Schwangeren ohne MH in der DFG-geförderten Studie "Perinatale Gesundheit und Migration in Berlin".</s><s>Es sollte geklärt werden, ob und wie sich die Einstellungen der Schwangeren bez.</s><s>PDA unterscheiden.</s><s>Methodik: Anhand einer explorativen Studie mit leitfadengestützten Interviews wurden dazu durchschnittlich 17-minütige Interviews mit 19 türkeistämmigen und 11 deutschen Schwangeren in einem Berliner Krankenhaus geführt, die einer qualitativen Inhaltsanalyse unterzogen wurden.</s><s>Ergebnisse: Dem Schmerz einer vaginalen Entbindung messen Schwangere mit MH Türkei häufiger eine sinnvolle Bedeutung zu.</s><s>Eine PDA wird von ihnen häufiger von vornherein abgelehnt: 1) aus Angst vor langfristigen Komplikationen wie Lähmung und Rückenschmerzen und 2) aufgrund der Ansicht, dass eine vaginale Entbindung mit PDA nicht natürlich sei.</s><s>Informationen zur PDA werden häufiger aus vielfältigen, vor allem mündlichen Quellen aus dem sozialen Umfeld bezogen.</s><s>Die Schwangeren beider Gruppen gaben an, die Entscheidung bez.</s><s>einer PDA unabhängig von der Meinung ihres Partners zu treffen.</s><s>Diskussion: Die beobachteten Unterschiede in den PDA-Raten entsprechen den Einstellungen der Schwangeren.</s><s>Diese beruht bei den Schwangeren mit MH Türkei gegenüber der PDA z. T. auf Fehlinformationen.</s><s>Um den Schwangeren eine informierte Entscheidung zu ermöglichen, könnte die PDA während der Geburtsvorbereitung stärker thematisiert werden.</s></p><p><s>Differences in the Frequency of Use of Epidural Analgesia between Immigrant Women of Turkish Origin and Non-Immigrant Women in Germany -Explanatory Approaches and Conclusions of a Qualitative Study Häufigkeitsunterschiede der Periduralanästhesienutzung zwischen türkeistämmigen Migrantinnen und Nichtmigrantinnen -Erklärungsansätze und Schlussfolgerungen einer qualitativen Studie Introduction !</s><s>Epidural analgesia is the gold standard for pain management during childbirth.</s><s>Regional analgesic procedures are used in around 20 to 30% of all births in Germany today <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>).</s><s>In the process of tissue damage, pain perception and pain expression, psychological processes are activated that are influenced by cognitive and emotional elements.</s><s>Biological, social and cultural-ethnic factors contribute to further modification of this "pain cascade".</s><s>Pain perception and response to pain vary interculturally <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s>The fact that pregnant immigrants undergo epidural analgesia significantly less often than non-immigrants has also been reported in the United States <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>), Canada <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and Spain <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s><s>Studies focusing particularly on the use of epidural analgesia by immigrant women with a Turkish background were conducted in Sweden <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, Austria <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and Germany <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s>There are a variety of explanations for this.</s><s>One study conducted in the United States, which investigated the lower rate of epidural analgesia use in Hispanic women demonstrated a correlation with the womenʼs linguistic proficiency <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</s><s>This result could point to a language barrier when the patient requests epidural analgesia or to communication gaps when presenting information or during patient consent.</s><s>A qualitative study from the United States concluded that Hispanic womenʼs decision not to use epidural analgesia was primarily due to misconceptions about the intervention and its risks <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s><s>Furthermore, in addition to the already mentioned sociocultural differences in pain perception <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, the partnerʼs attitude <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>, the attitude of the medical personnel towards immigrant women <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, the womenʼs educational level <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref> and religious background (secular vs. religious) <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> have also been discussed as influencing factors.</s></p><p><s>In Germanyʼs currently largest study on perinatal health and migration, significant differences were also observed in the use of epidural analgesia and combined spinal-epidural anaesthesia (together referred to as "epidural analgesia" below) among immigrant women of Turkish origin and non-immigrant women.</s><s>In the group of women with vaginal delivery, epidural analgesia was used in 28.2 % of immigrant women of Turkish origin and in 44.4 % of German women (p &lt; 0.001) <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>.</s><s>There are no indications, either in clinical routine or in the published literature, that women of Turkish origin present to the labour ward at a too advanced stage of labour so that the use of epidural analgesia is precluded.</s><s>Based on the available research results, it is only possible to speculate about the reasons for the significant differences in the rate of epidural analgesia use among pregnant women of Turkish origin and non-immigrant women.</s><s>The study presented here aimed to identify possible reasons on the part of the women for the different epidural analgesia rates.</s><s>To this end, the following questions were raised: Do attitudes towards epidural analgesia differ between women of Turkish origin and non-immigrant women?</s><s>Which factors influence the attitudes towards epidural analgesia?</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>Since quantitative studies have not provided any answers to this question to date, we elected to use an explorative-qualitative approach that allows attitudes and their logical framework to be elucidated.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</head><p><s>The inclusion criteria were as follows: pregnant women at least 18 years old who consented to complete an interview during antenatal care, at the admissions area of the delivery room and on an obstetrics ward.</s><s>The exclusion criteria were as follows: women in an advanced stage of labour or those assessed by the personnel as being in a physically or emotionally difficult situation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Interviews</head><p><s>The interviews aimed to ascertain whether the observed differences in the epidural rates of the immigrant women of Turkish origin and those of non-immigrant women were based on differences in attitude.</s><s>To this end, after their consent was obtained, the women were interviewed at a Berlin hospital.</s><s>The interviews were designed as focused (semi-structured) interviews and were tested in a pretest and subsequently modified slightly <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>.</s><s>Additionally, a brief questionnaire was used to obtain data on the pregnancy and on sociodemographic and immigration background.</s><s>In the interviews, the women were asked to describe their attitudes towards epidural analgesia during childbirth as well as about the causal framework underlying the attitude.</s><s>All of the documents used were translated into Turkish by qualified translators.</s><s>An interpreter was used as needed to simultaneously interpret the interview.</s><s>The interviews were recorded on a dictaphone.</s><s>The field notes on the interview context (setting, brief description of the interviewee, rapport, highlights, difficult moments, surprises) were written up in condensed form.</s><s>All of the interviews were conducted by 1 person (I.</s><s>P.).</s><s>After transferring the audio file from the dictaphone to a digital text document, the audio file was deleted from the dictaphone.</s><s>The data was then pseudonymised.</s><s>The interviews were transcribed according to the recommendations of <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Kuckartz et al. (2008)</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref> and qualitative content analysis was performed based on the design proposed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Mayring (2002)</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>.</s><s>Categorisation was undertaken inductively, i.e. using the material provided by the interviews.</s><s>Within the group of women of Turkish origin the comparison was broken down in more detail with regard to immigrant generation (first vs. second/third), educational level (none/primary vs. secondary/university degree) and parity (nulliparous vs. all others) when appropriate.</s><s>Due to the high correlation between immigrant generation and German proficiency, no comparisons were undertaken between women with various levels of German proficiency.</s><s>The interviews were conducted on 12 days from June to August 2015.</s><s>Among the women of Turkish origin, 9 were interviewed with an interpreter because they preferred the interview in Turkish.</s><s>Care was taken to ensure that the interviews did not prolong waiting time or delay planned examinations or consultations.</s><s>The interviewees were selected randomly.</s><s>Only 25 % of the women who were approached did not agree to be interviewed.</s><s>When planning the study, it was assumed that around 50 interviews per group would be required to obtain sufficient information.</s><s>However, among the non-immigrant women, a content-related "saturation" was achieved after 10 interviews, so that interviews of this subgroup were discontinued after the 11th interview.</s><s>In the interviews with the immigrant women of Turkish origin, content-related "saturation" was achieved after 19 interviews.</s><s>Due to the interpreting required in some cases, the interviews with the women of Turkish origin took longer than the interviews with the non-immigrant women (average 21 minutes compared to 13 minutes, respectively).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistics and vote of the Ethics Committee</head><p><s>The descriptive statistical analysis of the brief questionnaire was undertaken using the SPSS statistics software (Version 23.0, IBM).</s><s>A positive vote of the Ethics Committee is in place for the overall project, the German Research Council (DFG)-funded study "Perinatal Health and Migration in Berlin" (FKZ EA1/235/08).</s><s>The project presented here was separately approved by the Charité Data Protection Officer.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>In total, after the interviews 552 minutes of audio material was available, with transcription of the material requiring around 64 hours altogether.</s><s>The interviewees were 30 pregnant women, 19 of them women of Turkish origin and 11 non-immigrant women.</s><s>The sociodemographic data are presented in l " Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s><s>The content analysis encompassed 18 interviews of immigrant women of Turkish origin and 10 interviews of non-immigrant women.</s><s>In the brief questionnaire, the interviewees were asked to name the most important people for them in the event of questions on pregnancy and childbirth.</s><s>For the women of Turkish origin, this was the obstetrician, followed by the midwife and the womanʼs mother.</s><s>For the non-immigrant women, the most important people were the obstetrician, the midwife and the partner.</s><s>In the section below, the results of the interviews with respect to labour pain (feelings and meaning), attitudes towards and sour-ces of information on epidural analgesia and the role of the partner are presented.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Labour pain</head><p><s>Feelings arising at the thought of labour pain included a) fear, b) fear mixed with confidence, c) serenity and d) other (e.g.</s><s>uncertainty).</s><s>These items were mentioned equally often in both groups.</s><s>The women were also asked, "Do you think labour pain is meaningful?"</s><s>Non-immigrant women responded more frequently that they did not think that labour pain is meaningful (5 out of 9 vs. 1 out of 12).</s><s>However, they were often of the opinion that "childbirth without pain is not possible" or that pain belongs to childbirth as a "necessary evil".</s><s>Immigrant women of Turkish origin more frequently said that the pain was meaningful or had explanatory models for it (11 out of 12), such as the separation or detachment of the child: "Yes, itʼs natural for it to be that way, because a child becomes detached from the woman.</s><s>Thatʼs way it has to be (…) connected with pain.</s><s>A part becomes separated from the body".</s><s>(Inter.</s><s>28, Turkish origin) and "Labour pain as a signal".</s><s>In this respect there were no differences between the immigrant generations.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Attitudes towards epidural analgesia</head><p><s>The responses to the question "What is your position regarding epidural analgesia?"</s><s>were categorised into a) agreement, b) agreement if necessarydefined as both the necessity from the perspective of the personnel and the necessity from the perspective of the pregnant womanand 3) rejection.</s><s>There were significant differences in the acceptance of epidural analgesia from the beginning.</s><s>Non-immigrant women had a much more positive at- The results were the same for women of different parity.</s><s>Multiparous women rejected the use of epidural analgesia as often as nulliparous women (4 out of 9 vs. 3 out of 8).</s><s>However, there were differences in the attitudes towards epidural analgesia with respect to immigrant generations.</s><s>First-generation immigrant women more frequently categorically rejected epidural analgesia (6 out of 8 vs. 1 out of 9), while second-generation immigrant women more frequently considered epidural analgesia to be an option ("if needed") (6 out of 9 vs. 0 out of 8).</s></p><p><s>The immigrant women of Turkish origin frequently justified their (negative) attitudes with their concerns about the placement of the epidural analgesia (4 out of 16 vs. 1 out of 9) and about complications (8 out of 16 vs. 1 out of 9): "Iʼm afraid of it, because I have friends who have had back pain ever since they had the epidural".</s><s>(Inter.</s><s>29, Turkish origin).</s><s>Both women with lower education levels (secondary school not completed, primary school) and those with higher education levels (Realschule, school-leaving exam [Abitur], university studies) had these concerns (3 out of 6 vs. 5 out of 10).</s><s>The information and consent consultation, the scope of the information and consent sheet and the requirement for a signature all contributed to fears with respect to the risks of epidural analgesia: "But then I wonder why you have to give your signature while you are in labour.</s><s><ref type="bibr">[…]</ref>.</s><s>Three or four pages, Iʼve heard.</s><s>You donʼt have to give your signature for other pain relievers, like laughing gas or whatever".</s><s>(Inter.</s><s>17, Turkish origin)</s></p><p><s>The opinion that vaginal delivery with epidural analgesia no longer constitutes natural childbirth was expressed only by pregnant women of Turkish origin (5 out of 16 vs.</s><s>0 out of 9): "For me, when it comes down to it, natural childbirth means doing it without an epidural".</s><s>(Inter.</s><s>17, Turkish origin).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sources of information on epidural analgesia</head><p><s>Equal numbers of immigrant and non-immigrant women stated that their sources of information on epidural analgesia were books/internet and a previous childbirth.</s><s>However, differences were also observed: Immigrant women of Turkish origin obtained their information on epidural analgesia more frequently from their social environment (5 out of 14 vs. 0 out of 7) and from friends and relatives (4 out of 14 vs. 0 out of 7): "In our community, they say that youʼll have back pain later or permanent damage or […] you even have the risk that you […] will be paralysed …" (Inter.</s><s>13, Turkish origin).</s><s>In the group of pregnant women of Turkish origin, this was especially true for nulliparous women compared to multiparous women (6 out of 6 vs. 3 out of 8).</s><s>As expected, the latter group obtained information on epidural analgesia frequently through a previous childbirth.</s><s>Non-immigrant women more frequently used other sources to obtain information on epidural analgesia: obstetrician, antenatal course, job-related health care setting, television (6 out of 7 vs. 2 out of 14).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Role of the partner</head><p><s>The interviewees were asked about the partnerʼs attitude towards epidural analgesia and the role of his opinion in electing to use epidural analgesia or not.</s><s>The majority of both groups of women reported that they took this decision themselves, as reflected by the following statements: "He respects my decision.</s><s>He says he will adjust to it".</s><s>(Inter.</s><s>6, Turkish origin) and "He supports me in the way I decide and wouldnʼt have much chance to disagree".</s><s>(Inter.</s><s>16, non-immigrant) l " Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> presents a summary of the pregnant womenʼs attitudes and opinions and presents differences and commonalities between the 2 surveyed groups.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>In principle, all women should have all options for pain management during labour available to them after they have received adequate information.</s><s>There should be no discrepancies in pain relief provision either on the part of the hospital or due to the patientʼs social or insurance status.</s><s>Considering that adequate options are available for pain-free childbirth, the question arises as to why some women elect to use these options while other women choose to tolerate the labour pain.</s><s>The interview-based qualitative study presented here aimed to identify factors behind</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Immigrants of Turkish origin Non-immigrant women</head><p><s>Commonalities " There are no differences among the groups with respect to feelings at the thought of labour pain.</s><s>" The pregnant women in both groups reported with equal frequency that they obtained information on epidural analgesia from the internet/books or from a previous childbirth, if applicable.</s><s>" The majority of the women take the decision for or against epidural analgesia without regard for their partnerʼs attitude.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Differences</head><p><s>Significance of labour pain " Labour pain is often considered to be meaningful.</s></p><p><s>" Labour pain is not considered to be meaningful.</s></p><p><s>Attitudes towards epidural analgesia " The use of epidural analgesia is more frequently categorically rejected.</s></p><p><s>" More frequent categorical acceptance of epidural analgesia.</s><s>Reasons for rejecting epidural analgesia " There are more often concerns about the procedure and the complications (paralysis, back pain).</s><s>" For one-third of the women, a vaginal delivery with epidural analgesia is no longer a natural childbirth.</s></p><p><s>" Over half the women expected that epidural analgesia would provide pain relief.</s></p><p><s>Sources of information on epidural analgesia " Information on epidural analgesia is frequently obtained from the social setting.</s></p><p><s>the womenʼs decision to agree to epidural analgesia or reject it.</s><s>A qualitative study is particularly well-suited for investigating this question.</s><s>There were significant differences in the attitudes of the 2 interviewed groups of women towards epidural analgesia.</s><s>In contrast to the non-immigrant women, the majority of the pregnant women of Turkish origin categorically rejected the use of epidural analgesia.</s><s>The study identified 3 main reasons for this: 1. concerns regarding the direct placement of epidural analgesia 2. concerns regarding long-term sequelae (back pain, paralysis) and 3. the desire for natural childbirth.</s><s>Identical concerns were expressed by Hispanic women in a study performed in the United States <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s><s>In another study conducted in the United States, 54 % of the women surveyed stated that they rejected the use of epidural analgesia due to their concern about possible risks to their own health.</s><s>In this population, Hispanic women constituted the largest ethnicity and also constituted the largest group that did not use epidural analgesia <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</s><s>The desire to experience an unmedicated birth as grounds for rejecting epidural analgesia has also been reported in other studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>.</s><s>The pregnant women of Turkish origin surveyed obtained information about epidural analgesia from their social environment (relatives, neighbours, friends, acquaintances) more frequently than non-immigrants.</s><s>While the women were not asked about their current state of knowledge about epidural analgesia, similar to a study performed in the United States, statements such as "Thatʼs what I heard" or "Thatʼs what they say" suggest that the rejection of epidural analgesia is not based on an informed decision and may actually be based on misunderstandings <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s><s>Another study performed in the United States described a similarly diverse range of sources of information about epidural analgesia.</s><s>However, there was no correlation between the source of information and the actual use of epidural analgesia <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Strengths of the study</head><p><s>1.</s><s>This study offers approaches for explaining the lower rate of use of epidural analgesia among immigrant women of Turkish origin compared to non-immigrants, as they were documented both in an analysis of data from the 1990s <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> and of current data <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> in Berlin.</s><s>The results can most likely also be transferred to pregnant women of Turkish origin in Austria, where a lower rate of use of epidural analgesia has also been reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</s><s>2. The explorative-qualitative methodology allows to identify differences in the attitudes of the 2 groups of women.</s><s>3. Using an interpreter allowed to include and evaluate the attitudes of women with limited German proficiency.</s><s>4. The study was conducted with 1 method, at 1 location and by 1 (female) interviewer.</s><s>Therefore there is no interobserver bias.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations</head><p><s>This study considered only the womenʼs perspective.</s><s>Other possible reasons, such as the attitude of the obstetric personnel towards the two groups of women or towards the intervention were not investigated.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p><s>1. Based on the results of this study, it can be concluded that the attitudes towards epidural analgesia among pregnant women of Turkish origin are based on misconception and fear of com-plications.</s><s>Since obstetricians and midwives are among the most important persons for women of Turkish origin, members of these 2 professions could make an effort during their antenatal care to mitigate existing fears of long-term sequelae due to epidural analgesia.</s><s>For women whose German proficiency is insufficient, it would be a good idea to offer printed materials in Turkish on the subject.</s><s>For illiterate patients, providing a professional interpreter and/or care by German-and Turkishspeaking obstetricians and midwives during antenatal care would be desirable.</s><s>Women making an informed decision can also elect not to have epidural analgesia, for example, if they wish to experience an unmedicated birth.</s><s>This decision should be respected whether or not the woman is an immigrant.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Sociodemographic data on the interviewees (n = 30).</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>All (n = 30)</cell><cell>Immigrant women</cell><cell>Non-immigrant</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>of Turkish origin (n = 19)</cell><cell>women (n = 11)</cell></row></table><note><p><s>titude towards epidural analgesia, which is reflected by the following statement: "To be honest, if itʼs possible to have something like that, why not use it?"</s><s>(Inter.</s><s>22, non-immigrant).</s><s>Women of Turkish origin expressed rejection more often: "Even if itʼs unbearable, I wouldnʼt have the injection".</s><s>(Inter.</s><s>27, Turkish origin)</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Summary and overview of the interview statements.</s></p></div></figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Petruschke I et al. Differences in the … Geburtsh Frauenheilk 2016; 76: 972-977</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">"  The obstetrician, childbirth course, etc. are frequent sources of information.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2">. For non-immigrant women, the study results show that the higher rate of epidural analgesia use corresponds with their attitudes and desires.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflicts of interest</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>No conflicts of interest indicated.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anästhesie in der Geburtshilfe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hunsicker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Birkholz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eine Kurzübersicht. Klinikarzt</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="190" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ethnocultural influences on variation in chronic pain perception</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anderson</forename><surname>Ko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pain</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Racial differences in the use of epidural analgesia for labor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Glance</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wissler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Glantz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anesthesiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Racial and ethnic disparities in the provision of epidural analgesia to Georgia Medicaid beneficiaries during labor and delivery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rust</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Nembhard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nichols</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">191</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="456" to="462" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Racial and ethnic disparities in neuraxial labor analgesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Toledo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Grobman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anesth Analg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="172" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social disparity and the use of intrapartum epidural analgesia in a publicly funded health care system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Manual</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">202</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="e274" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>e8</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ethnic differences in the use of intrapartum epidural analgesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jiménez-Puente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Benítez-Parejo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Del</forename><surname>Diego-Salas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Health Serv Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">207</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epidural analgesia during labor among immigrant women in Sweden</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ekéus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cnattingius</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hjern</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="243" to="249" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Migrants and obstetrics in Austria-applying a new questionnaire shows differences in obstetric care and outcome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Oberaigner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Leitner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Oberaigner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Wien Klin Wochenschr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perinatal outcome in Berlin (Germany) among immigrants from Turkey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pachaly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Vetter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch Gynecol Obstet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">274</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="278" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preferred spoken language mediates differences in neuraxial labor analgesia utilization among racial and ethnic groups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Caballero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Butwick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Carvalho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Obstet Anesth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="167" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A qualitative analysis of parturientsʼ perspectives on neuraxial labor analgesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Toledo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Peralta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Obstet Anesth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The pain of childbirth: perceptions of culturally diverse women</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Callister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Khalaf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Semenic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pain Manag Nur</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Survey of the factors associated with a womanʼs choice to have an epidural for labor analgesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Harkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Carvalho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Evers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1155/2010/356789</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anesth Res Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Theyʼre more like ordinary stroppy British women&apos;: attitudes and expectations of maternity care professionals to UK-born ethnicity minority women</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Puthussery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Twamley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Harding</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Health Serv Res Pol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="201" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predictors of recommendation and acceptance of intrapartum epidural analgesia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sheiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sheiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Shoham-Vardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anesth Analg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="113" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of perinatal data of immigrant women of Turkish origin and German women -results of a prospective study in Berlin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Borde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brenne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geburtsh Frauenheilk</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="441" to="448" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Eine qualitative Befragung schwangerer Frauen mit und ohne Migrationshintergrund Türkei</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Petruschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>School of Public Health</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Master of Public Health (MPH). eingereicht</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Qualitative Evaluation: Der Einstieg in die Praxis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Kuckartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Dresing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rädicker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Verlag für Sozialwissenschaften</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Wiesbaden</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Einführung in die qualitative Sozialforschung</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mayring</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Eine Anleitung zu qualitativem Denken. 5 Aufl. Wiesbaden: Beltz Studium</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">US nulliparasʼ perceptions of roles and of the birth experience as predictors of their delivery preferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Arcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Midwifery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="885" to="894" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Womenʼs preference for a cesarean section: incidence and associated factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gamble</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Creedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Birth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perinatal outcome in Berlin (Germany) among immigrants from Turkey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pachaly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Vetter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch Gynecol Obstet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">274</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="278" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
