<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weiland</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Northern Institute for Cancer Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Newcastle Cancer Centre</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Newcastle University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newcastle upon Tyne</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Hematology, Oncology, Hemostaseology, and Stem Cell Transplantation</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">RWTH Aachen University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Aachen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Pal</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Northern Institute for Cancer Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Newcastle Cancer Centre</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Newcastle University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newcastle upon Tyne</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Case</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Northern Institute for Cancer Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Newcastle Cancer Centre</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Newcastle University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newcastle upon Tyne</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Irving</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Northern Institute for Cancer Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Newcastle Cancer Centre</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Newcastle University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newcastle upon Tyne</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ponthan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Northern Institute for Cancer Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Newcastle Cancer Centre</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Newcastle University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newcastle upon Tyne</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Koschmieder</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Hematology, Oncology, Hemostaseology, and Stem Cell Transplantation</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">RWTH Aachen University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Aachen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Heidenreich</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Northern Institute for Cancer Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Newcastle Cancer Centre</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Newcastle University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newcastle upon Tyne</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Von Stackelberg</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Paediatric Oncology/Haematology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Eckert</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Paediatric Oncology/Haematology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vormoor</surname></persName>
							<email>josef.vormoor@newcastle.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Northern Institute for Cancer Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Newcastle Cancer Centre</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Newcastle University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newcastle upon Tyne</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Great North Children&apos;s Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Newcastle upon Tyne Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newcastle upon Tyne</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Elder</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Northern Institute for Cancer Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Newcastle Cancer Centre</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Newcastle University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Newcastle upon Tyne</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F277F4AF781089269F0D24596321EFDF</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1038/leu.2016.64</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:40+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Outcomes of nonmyeloablative HLA-haploidentical blood or marrow transplantation with high-dose post-transplantation cyclophosphamide in older adults.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>OPEN</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BCP-ALL blasts are not dependent on CD19 expression for leukaemic maintenance</head><p><s>Leukemia (2016) 30, 1920-1923; doi:10.1038/leu.2016.64</s></p><p><s>2]<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> The rationale behind targeting CD19 in BCP-ALL is primarily its homogenous cell surface expression and B-lineage specificity. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref></s><s>Thus, the entire malignant cell population should be targeted and eradicated by anti-CD19-directed immunotherapies.</s><s>]<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> However, the effects of CD19 depletion on BCP-ALL cells have not been investigated.</s><s>Hence, we examined the role of CD19 in leukaemic maintenance by silencing its expression in BCP-ALL cell lines and primograft samples using RNA interference.</s></p><p><s>First, we explored the effects of CD19 knockdown in CD19 + BCP-ALL cell lines reflecting three maturation stages of BCP-ALL: pro-B-ALL SEM (CD10 − CD19 + ), common B-ALL REH (CD10 + CD19 + ) and pre-B-ALL 697 (CD10 + CD19 + cyIgM + ).</s><s>BCP-ALL cell lines were transduced with two different lentiviral constructs targeting CD19.</s><s>A short hairpin RNA (shRNA) that specifically targets the fusion gene RUNX1/ETO without affecting endogenous RUNX1 was used as a control, 10 as this fusion is not found in any of the cell lines or primografts used (see Supplementary Methods for further details).</s><s>We chose the pTRIPZ system, which allows doxycycline-mediated induction of shRNA) expression and puromycin selection of successfully transduced cells.</s><s>Five days after induction, CD19 surface expression was reduced 15-fold in SEM cells, sixfold in REH cells and 14-fold in 697 cells by the best construct (shCD19II) compared to the geometric mean of expression in the control (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>The CD19 depletion was maintained over several time points (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</s><s>None of the cell lines showed any impairment in proliferation over 23-26 days (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>) or doubling times: SEM (control: 34 h vs shCD19: 33 h), REH (control: 38 h vs shCD19: 34 h) and 697 (control: 30 h vs shCD19: 29 h).</s><s>This suggests that, at the level of knockdown achieved, CD19 is not essential for the proliferation of BCP-ALL cell lines in suspension culture.</s></p><p><s>We next considered that CD19 could be important for niche interactions, so we used a murine stromal cell feeder layer to mimic this.</s><s>Cells were grown on M2-10B4 cells in medium containing 2% fetal bovine serum, which was the level at which the SEM and 697 cells developed dependence on the feeder layer for growth at low cell densities (10 4 cells/ml) (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>).</s><s>REH cells did not develop feeder dependence to the same extent as the other cell lines.</s><s>Next, we performed a competitive assay under these conditions.</s><s>We seeded equal mixtures of transduced and un-transduced cell populations to determine whether CD19-depleted cells were at a competitive disadvantage to wild-type cells.</s><s>The ratio of RFP + (shRNAexpressing) to RFP − (wild-type) cells was used to assess changes in the proportions of each population.</s><s>We did not observe any substantial differences in the ratio of CD19 − to wild-type cells for any of the three cell lines studied (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>), indicating that CD19 expression does not give cells a competitive growth advantage when adherent on stroma cells.</s></p><p><s>We also studied the effects of CD19 silencing in a high-risk pre-B-ALL t(17;19) primograft, L707, achieving a threefold reduction in Accepted article preview online 17 March 2016; advance online publication, 8 April 2016 CD19 expression using a constitutively active pGIPZ-shCD19 construct (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>).</s><s>L707 cells were cultured on a human mesenchymal stem cell feeder layer and assessed for cell proliferation after puromycin selection.</s><s>CD19-depleted L707 cells did not exhibit impaired growth compared to control cells (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>) and were not at a competitive disadvantage compared to control cells (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1d</ref>).</s><s>This suggests that CD19 is not required for leukaemic maintenance in primary blasts.</s></p><p><s>In support of our in vitro data, we obtained a patient sample taken at relapse (LK194), which presented as CD19 + BCP-ALL but relapsed as CD19 − BCP-ALL after treatment with blinatumomab (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a  and b</ref>, Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>).</s><s>To investigate if these CD19 − cells could engraft and reconstitute leukaemia and if the CD19 − phenotype is stable in vivo, we injected 1 × 10 6 CD19 − primary cells each into three NOD/LtSz-scid IL-2Rγ null (NSG) mice.</s><s>All mice presented enlarged spleens (0.56-1.05 g, compared to o0.1 g for non-engrafted mice) and histological analysis showed leukaemic infiltration of the bone marrow (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>).</s><s>Fluorescence-activated cell sorting analysis of harvested spleen samples showed that CD19 − blasts were able to engraft and reconstitute the leukaemia, and that the phenotype appeared stable (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2c-e</ref>, Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref>).</s><s>In one mouse (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2d</ref>), a CD19 + population also emerged.</s><s>These cells were also evident in CD19-stained histological sections (Supplementary Figures <ref type="figure">6C and D</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To investigate the relative repopulating ability of these populations, we re-transplanted the primograft into secondary recipients.</s><s>In three secondary mice, the CD19 + peak appeared to increase in size relative to the CD19 − cells, suggesting the CD19 + blasts have a slight advantage in repopulating ability in vivo (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2f</ref>, Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>).</s><s>However, a defined CD19 + population did not emerge in a secondary transplant of one of the CD19 − primografts (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2g</ref>), demonstrating that the blasts are not dependent on CD19 for  <ref type="figure">(c-e</ref>) CD19 expression in spleen samples from mice transplanted with LK194, harvested 10 weeks post transplant.</s><s>The green line shows cells labelled with B-cell surface markers CD10, CD34, CD58, human-specific CD45 and mousespecific CD45.</s><s>This acts as a control for the pink histogram, which shows cells labelled with these same cell surface markers but with the addition of CD19.</s><s>Only human cells are shown.</s><s>See also Supplementary Figures <ref type="figure">5 and 7</ref>. (f, g) CD19 expression in spleens of mice transplanted with samples from Mouse 2 (f) or Mouse 3 (g).</s><s>See also Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure">8 (h)</ref>.</s><s>Gel electrophoresis image of PCR products to detect the expression of CD19 exons 1-3, using cDNA from LK194 mouse samples.</s><s>Arrows show expression of CD19 transcript containing exons 1-3 (403 bp) and absence of the variant that skips exon 2 (expected size 137 bp).</s><s>SEM cells were used as a CD19 + control.</s><s>NTC, non-template control.</s></p><p><s>survival in vivo.</s><s>It is unclear whether the CD19 + cells grew from a preexisting minor CD19 + subclone in the relapsed sample, or arose from the CD19 − population through re-expression of CD19.</s><s>A recent study has demonstrated exon 2 skipping as a mechanism of resistance to anti-CD19 therapeutics, whereby cells express a truncated CD19 protein to evade detection by anti-CD19 CAR T cells. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref></s><s>Analysis of LK194 primograft using reverse transcriptase-PCR demonstrated expression of a transcript containing exons 1-3, with no evidence of exon 2 skipping (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2h</ref>).</s><s>Moreover, sequencing confirmed that the CD19 cDNA from LK194 was fully intact, compared with both a reference transcript and cDNA from the SEM cell line (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure">9</ref>).</s><s>The presence of full-length CD19 transcript in these cells, but absence of protein, demonstrates evidence of an alternative mechanism of resistance to T-cell therapies to that previously described. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref></s><s>Further investigation of the mechanisms by which this occurs will be important for understanding how to circumvent the development of resistance to anti-CD19 therapies in patients.</s></p><p><s>In summary, we have shown that BCP-ALL cell lines and primary blasts are not dependent on CD19 for survival and propagation in both in vitro and in vivo settings.</s><s>This is contrary to the expectation given the functions of CD19 in pre-BCR and PI3K signalling and suggests that CD19-independent pathways play an important role in BCP-ALL development.</s><s>Further investigation of the differences between CD19 + and CD19 − ALL blasts will be important to understand these pathways.</s><s>Our data are consistent with other studies reporting CD19 − leukaemias <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> and demonstrating the emergence of CD19 − BCP-ALL clones following therapies targeting CD19. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>imilarly, immature CD34 + /CD19 − cells from primary high-risk paediatric ALL samples have previously been shown to engraft and maintain leukaemia in immunodeficient mice. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref></s><s>It is therefore evident that leukaemic blasts that lose expression of the CD19 antigen will be able to survive and escape CD19targeted therapies, increasing the risk of CD19 − relapse.</s><s>It remains to be seen how big an impact this will have on the longterm efficacy of CD19 immunotherapies.</s><s>Thus, in the future it will be vital to identify how best to integrate these immunotherapies into standard treatment protocols <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> and develop combination therapies to eliminate emergent CD19 − blasts.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>CD19 knockdown in BCP-ALL cell lines and high-risk BCP-ALL primograft does not affect cell growth.</s><s>(a) Cell growth of BCP-ALL cell lines transduced with two different shRNA constructs targeting CD19 or RUNX1/ETO (control) in suspension culture.</s><s>(b) CD19-depleted cells are not disadvantaged in a competitive setting.</s><s>Populations of untransduced BCP-ALL cell lines and cells transduced with a pTRIPZ shRNA construct were mixed at low cellular density under serum-starved conditions on feeder cells.</s><s>Relative tRFP expression represents the proportion of cells expressing the construct.</s><s>The graph shows the mean of two independent experiments.</s><s>(c) Cell growth of BCP-ALL primograft (L707) transduced with pGIPZ shRNA constructs against CD19 or RUNX1/ETO on human mesenchymal stem cell (hMSC) feeder cells in comparison with untransduced cells.</s><s>Cell numbers were equalised at the first timepoint to allow comparison of growth rates.</s><s>(d) Competitive assay of BCP-ALL primograft transduced with CD19 or RUNX1/ETO constructs mixed with untransduced BCP-ALL primograft on hMSC feeder cells.</s><s>The graph shows the change in proportion of GFP-positive to -negative cells over the time course.</s><s>The GFP-positive cells correspond to the fraction expressing the construct.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,43.14,58.00,499.58,461.42" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. The CD19 − BCP-ALL sample is able to engraft NSG mice.</s><s>Histogram showing CD19 expression in a relapsed CD19 − sample LK194 (a) compared to a typical ALL diagnostic sample (b).(c-e)</s><s>CD19 expression in spleen samples from mice transplanted with LK194, harvested 10 weeks post transplant.</s><s>The green line shows cells labelled with B-cell surface markers CD10, CD34, CD58, human-specific CD45 and mousespecific CD45.</s><s>This acts as a control for the pink histogram, which shows cells labelled with these same cell surface markers but with the addition of CD19.</s><s>Only human cells are shown.</s><s>See also Supplementary Figures5 and 7. (f, g) CD19 expression in spleens of mice transplanted with samples from Mouse 2 (f) or Mouse 3 (g).</s><s>See also Supplementary Figure8 (h).</s><s>Gel electrophoresis image of PCR products to detect the expression of CD19 exons 1-3, using cDNA from LK194 mouse samples.</s><s>Arrows show expression of CD19 transcript containing exons 1-3 (403 bp) and absence of the variant that skips exon 2 (expected size 137 bp).</s><s>SEM cells were used as a CD19 + control.</s><s>NTC, non-template control.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,90.65,59.75,423.50,488.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Leukemia (2016) 1909 -1962 © 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited, part of Springer Nature.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">© 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited, part of Springer Nature.Leukemia (2016) 1909 -1962</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p><s>We are grateful for support from CRUK programme grant C27943/A12788 and from Leukaemia and Lymphoma Research grant 13067.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</head><p><s>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</s><s>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</s><s>The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material.</s><s>To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ by/4.0/</s><s>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on the Leukemia website (http://www.nature.com/leu)</s><s>Letters to the Editor</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chimeric antigen receptor T cells for sustained remissions in leukemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Maude</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Frey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Aplenc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Barrett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bunin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">371</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1507" to="1517" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">T cells expressing CD19 chimeric antigen receptors for acute lymphoblastic leukaemia in children and young adults: a phase 1 dose-escalation trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Kochenderfer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stetler-Stevenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Delbrook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Feldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">385</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="517" to="528" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chimeric antigen receptor-modified T cells for acute lymphoid leukemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Grupp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kalos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Barrett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Aplenc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Porter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rheingold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">368</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1509" to="1518" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phase II trial of the anti-CD19 bispecific T cell-engager blinatumomab shows hematologic and molecular remissions in patients with relapsed or refractory B-precursor acute lymphoblastic leukemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Topp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Gokbuget</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zugmaier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Klappers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stelljes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Neumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4134" to="4140" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Therapeutic targeting of CD19 in hematological malignancies: past, present, future and beyond</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Herishanu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Leuk Lymphoma</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="999" to="1006" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ifitm3 (CD225) mediates CD19-dependent survival and proliferation during normal B cell development and in Ph+ ALL</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Geng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Klemm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bailey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2505</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CD19 is a major B cell receptor-independent activator of MYC-driven B-lymphomagenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Psathas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Thomas-Tikhonenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2257" to="2266" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CD19 function in early and late B cell development. II. CD19 facilitates the pro-B/pre-B transition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Otero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Rickert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">171</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5921" to="5930" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CD19: a multifunctional immunological target molecule and its implications for Blineage acute lymphoblastic leukemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Weiland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Elder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Forster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Heidenreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Koschmieder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vormoor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatr Blood Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1144" to="1148" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AML1/MTG8 oncogene suppression by small interfering RNAs supports myeloid differentiation of t(8;21)-positive leukemic cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Heidenreich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Krauter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Riehle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hadwiger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>John</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Heil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3157" to="3163" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Convergence of acquired mutations and alternative splicing of CD19 enables resistance to CART-19 immunotherapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sotillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Barrett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Black</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bagashev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Oldridge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Discov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1282" to="1295" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CD19 expression in acute leukemia is not restricted to the cytogenetically aberrant populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Francis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Dharmadhikari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Sait</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Deeb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Leuk Lymphoma</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1517" to="1520" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CD19-negative B-lymphoblastic leukemia associated with hypercalcemia, lytic bone lesions and aleukemic presentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hussein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Pinkney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Jobanputra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bhagat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Alobeid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Leuk Lymphoma</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1533" to="1537" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In childhood acute lymphoblastic leukemia, blasts at different stages of immunophenotypic maturation have stem cell properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Le Viseur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hotfilder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bomken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rottgers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schrauder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immune-based therapies for childhood cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mackall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Merchant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Clin Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="693" to="703" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
