<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Upregulation of Transient Receptor Potential Vanilloid Type-1 Channel Activity and Ca 2þ Influx Dysfunction in Human Pterygial Cells</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Fabian</forename><surname>Garreis</surname></persName>
							<email>fabian.garreis@fau.de.</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Anatomy II</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Friedrich Alexander University Erlangen-Nürnberg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Antje</forename><surname>Schröder</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Anatomy II</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Friedrich Alexander University Erlangen-Nürnberg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Reinach</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Ophthalmology and Optometry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Wenzhou Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Wenzhou</settlement>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stefanie</forename><surname>Zoll</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ophthalmology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Hospital</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Noushafarin</forename><surname>Khajavi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ophthalmology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Hospital</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Priyavathi</forename><surname>Dhandapani</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Gastroenterology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Hospital</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexander</forename><surname>Lucius</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ophthalmology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Hospital</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Uwe</forename><surname>Pleyer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ophthalmology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Hospital</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Friedrich</forename><surname>Paulsen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Anatomy II</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Friedrich Alexander University Erlangen-Nürnberg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stefan</forename><surname>Mergler</surname></persName>
							<email>stefan.mergler@charite.de.</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ophthalmology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Hospital</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Friedrich</forename><surname>Alexander</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Ophthalmology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Clinic, Augustenburger Platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University Erlangen-Nürnberg</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">De-partment of Anatomy II</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Uni-versitätsstraße 19</addrLine>
									<postCode>91054</postCode>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Upregulation of Transient Receptor Potential Vanilloid Type-1 Channel Activity and Ca 2þ Influx Dysfunction in Human Pterygial Cells</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F4DC8B928397A97C590FF26045CAFE29</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted: January 18, 2016 Accepted: March 26, 2016</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>pterygium</term>
					<term>human conjunctival epithelium</term>
					<term>transient receptor potential vanilloid 1 channel</term>
					<term>VEGF</term>
					<term>EGF</term>
					<term>intracellular Ca 2þ</term>
					<term>planar patch-clamp technique</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>The heat-sensitive transient receptor potential vanilloid type-1 (TRPV1) channel (i.e., capsaicin [CAP] receptor) is upregulated in numerous cancers.</s><s>This study determined if this response occurs in fresh and cultured hyperplastic human pterygial epithelial tissues.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS.</head><p><s>Reverse transcriptase PCR and quantitative real-time PCR, along with immunohistochemistry and Western blotting, characterized TRPV1 expression patterns in pterygial and healthy conjunctival tissue, primary and immortalized pterygial cells (hPtEC), and primary and immortalized conjunctival epithelial cells (HCjEC).</s><s>Imaging of Ca 2þ and planar whole-cell patch-clamping evaluated TRP channel activity.</s><s>An MTS assay measured cell metabolic activity and a cell growth assay monitored proliferation.</s></p><p><s>RESULTS.</s><s>Capsaicin (20 lM) and elevating bath temperature above 438C activated Ca 2þ transients more in hPtEC than HCjEC.</s><s>Capsaicin induced corresponding changes in inward currents that were inhibited by 20 lM capsazepine (CPZ).</s><s>Vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) also increased Ca 2þ -influx and induced corresponding inward currents more in hPtEC than in HCjEC, whereas CPZ (20 lM), BCTC (20 lM), or La 3þ (500 lM) reduced these responses, respectively.</s><s>Whereas epidermal growth factor (EGF) increased proliferation more in hPtEC than in HCjEC, VEGF had no effect on this response.</s><s>Capsazepine suppressed hPtEC proliferation induced by EGF and VEGF, whereas it was cytotoxic to HCjEC.</s></p><p><s>CONCLUSIONS.</s><s>Mitogenic responses to EGF and VEGF are mediated through TRPV1 transactivation.</s><s>Only in hPtEC do the increases in proliferation induced by EGF exceed those in HCjEC.</s><s>Therefore, TRPV1 is a potential drug target whose clinical relevance in treating pterygium warrants further assessment.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>P terygium (conjunctivae) is a common ocular surface hyperproliferative tumorous disorder.</s><s>Its risk factors include not only dust, wind, heat, dryness, and smoke, but also chronic UV-B light exposure, which is the main risk factor.</s><s>In addition, viral infection and genetic factors contribute to initiating and promoting this disease. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref></s><s>4]<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> Surgical resection is the only option for reducing visual impairment caused by a pterygium-related disturbance.</s><s>Because of its high recurrence rate (10%-70%), often repeated surgery may be needed, which heightens the likelihood of regrowth, inflammation, and scar formation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">7</ref></s><s>Advanced pterygium frequently leads to precorneal tear film dysfunction and dry eye disease (DES).</s><s>In the long term, it often results in reduced vision due to astigmatism, tear film alterations, and movement restriction of the bulbus. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s>]<ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref> Reten-tion of the pterygial cell phenotype appears to be location specific, as this tissue does not infiltrate into the cornea, suggesting that the corneal milieu is not supportive of this process. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref></s><s>ransient receptor potential (TRP) channels constitute a superfamily of ligand-gated, nonselective cation channels subdivided into seven subfamilies according to differences in amino acid sequence homology (reviewed by <ref type="bibr">Ramsey et al. 11</ref> ).</s><s>The heat-sensitive TRP vanilloid receptor 1 (TRPV1, capsaicin [CAP] receptor) channel is the most investigated TRP channel and it is the only one whose three-dimensional structure was determined. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">13</ref></s><s>5]<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref> Furthermore, changes of TRPV1 expression (in human skin) can be detected after UV irradiation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">17</ref></s><s>ransient receptor potential V1 mediates heat shock-induced matrix metalloproteinase-1 (MMP-1) expression in human keratinocytes. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">18</ref></s><s>However, diverse TRPV1 activation mechanisms induced through various (physical) stimuli have not yet iovs.arvojournals.org</s><s>j ISSN: 1552-5783 been elucidated.</s><s>High-resolution analysis of TRPV1 structure identified conformational changes in an outer pore domain and lower gate domain through ligand-binding.</s><s>Allosteric coupling between both domains is responsible for a broad physiological range of stimuli activating TRPV1 and other TRP channels. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">20</ref></s><s>gawa et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21</ref></s><s>showed that the oxidative status of Cys residues in the TRPV1 sequence modulated by reactive oxygen species triggers TRPV1 activation through changes in the redox environment.</s><s>Additionally, TRP channels are mechanically activated directly or by signaling cascades that alter lipid composition, change conformation of plasma membrane and open TRPs by mechanical force (reviewed in Liu and Montell <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">22</ref> ).</s><s>In Drosophila, photoreceptors and mammalian photosensitive retinal ganglion cell phototransduction is mediated by G protein-activated phospholipase C (PLC), which generates a force in the lipid-bilayer opening TRP-Canonical channels. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">24</ref></s><s>ransient receptor potential V1 is expressed in human conjunctival epithelial cells (HCjEC), <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">25</ref> human corneal endothelial cells, <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">26</ref> corneal fibroblasts, <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">27</ref> and corneal epithelial cells (HCEC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29</ref> (reviewed in Ref. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">30</ref> ).</s><s>Cellular constituent release caused by a severe chemical injury also induces TRPV1 activation, followed by corneal opacification and chronic dysregulated inflammation during wound healing. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">32</ref></s><s>As increases in cell proliferation in cancer are associated with rises in functional TRPV1 expression and activity, <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">34</ref> we hypothesized that this change is associated with conjunctival hyperplasia in pterygium.</s></p><p><s>We show here that TRPV1 channel expression is upregulated in human PT.</s><s>This upregulation is associated with dysfunctional Ca 2þ influx.</s><s>Furthermore, the mitogenic responses to EGF and VEGF are dependent on their respective cognate receptors transactivating TRPV1, as suppression of TRPV1 activation by capsazepine (CPZ) inhibited the increases in proliferation induced by these cytokines in human pterygial cells (hPtECs).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MATERIALS AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials</head><p><s>Capsazepine (CPZ) and icilin were obtained from Cayman Chemical Company (Ann Arbor, MI, USA).</s><s>N-(4-tert.butylphenyl)-4-(3-chloropyridin-2-yl)</s><s>tetrahydro-pyrazine-1(2H)-carboxamide (BCTC) and fura-2/AM were obtained from TOCRIS Bioscience (Bristol, UK).</s><s>Vascular endothelial growth factor was purchased from ThermoFisher Scientific (Waltham, MA, USA).</s><s>Medium and supplements for cell culture came from Life Technologies Invitrogen (Karlsruhe, Germany) or Biochrom AG (Berlin, Germany).</s><s>All other reagents were purchased from Sigma (Deisenhofen, Germany).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tissue and Cell Preparation</head><p><s>Human PT was obtained after surgical removal from 21 patients with primary pterygium conjunctivae (no recurrent lesions and no bilateral pterygia were included in the study) by the Department of Ophthalmology, Charité University Medicine Berlin, according to the tenets of the Declaration of Helsinki.</s><s>All patients provided written consent, which was approved by the ethics committee of Charité, University Medicine Berlin, Germany.</s><s>For RT-PCR and Western blot analysis, eight different PT samples were used and eight others for immunohistochemistry analysis.</s><s>For functional studies, PT from another five patients was mechanically reduced to small aggregates, incubated with 0.1 mg/mL collagenase type IV for 1 hour at 378C, 5% CO 2 , 21% O 2 ).</s><s>After rinsing with 13 PBS, aggregates were incubated again with 0.01 mg/mL collagenase IV for another 24 hours.</s><s>Cells were rinsed again in 13 PBS and isolated by centrifugation (5 minutes, 145 g).</s><s>Afterward, cells were transferred and cultivated in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM)/Ham's F12 containing 10% fetal calf serum, 1 lg/mL insulin, 5 lg/mL hydrocortisone, and 100 U/mL penicillin/streptomycin mix.</s><s>After two to four passages, cells were used for functional studies.</s><s>In two of these cell preparations, primary hPtEC underwent spontaneous immortalization after several cell passages.</s><s>Primary conjunctival epithelial cells obtained from healthy individuals were grown under the same conditions only for two to four passages and then discarded to avoid possible passage-dependent electrophysiological changes.</s><s>In addition, an immortalized HCjEC line, was used and cultivated as previously reported. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29</ref></s><s>Furthermore, an SV40-immortalized human cornea epithelial cell line (HCEC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">35</ref> was cultured according to our previous study. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">25</ref></s><s>verse Transcriptase PCR Surgically removed PT was stored in RNAlater (Invitrogen, Karlsruhe, Germany) at 48C and later lysed in 1 mL peqGOLD TriFast reagent (Peqlab, Erlangen, Germany) in an innuSPEED Lysis Tube placed in a SpeedMill plus homogenizer (both Analytik Jena AG, Jena, Germany).</s><s>After centrifugation (10 minutes, 15,000 g), supernatants were used for RNA isolation.</s><s>Pterygium tissue DNA contamination was eliminated by digestion with RNase-free DNase I (30 minutes, 378C).</s><s>DNase was heat inactivated for 10 minutes at 658C.</s><s>Reverse transcription of RNA samples to first-strand cDNA was performed by RevertAidTM H Minus M-MuL V Reverse Transcriptase Kit (Fermentas, St. Leon-Rot, Germany) according to manufacturer's protocol.</s><s>Two micrograms total RNA and 10 pmol Oligo (dT) 18 primer (Fermentas) were used for each reaction.</s><s>Each PCR reaction contained 2 lL cDNA in 2.5 lL 103 PCR buffer, 1 lL 50 mM MgCl 2 , 1 lL 10 mM dNTP mix (Fermentas), 0.5 lL 10 pmol forward primer, 0.5 lL 10 pmol reverse primer, 0.2 lL (5 U/lL) Taq DNA Polymerase (Invitrogen) diluted with RNase-free diethylpyrocarbonatetreated water.</s><s>Polymerase chain reaction amplification underwent an initial cycle at 958C for 5 minutes followed by 35 cycles at 958C for 30 seconds, primer-specific annealing temperature for 30 seconds, 728C for 30 seconds, and a final elongation at 728C for 5 minutes as well as a temperature hold at 48C.</s><s>Gene-specific intron-spanning primer sequences, annealing temperatures, cycle numbers, and product sizes are shown in the Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">.</ref></s><s>Primers were synthesized at Metabion International AG (Steinkirchen, Germany).</s><s>Polymerase chain reaction products were resolved by electrophoresis in a 1.5 % agarose gel and visualized via fluorescence.</s><s>Base pair (bp) values were compared with Genbank data.</s><s>Reverse transcriptase PCR product identity was confirmed by sequencing and sequence alignment (data not shown).</s><s>Genomic contamination was prevented by omission of reverse transcriptase.</s><s>Housekeeping b-actin gene expression assessed integrity and stability of the reverse transcribed cDNA.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Real Time RT-PCR</head><p><s>Each reaction was performed in a final volume of 20 lL containing 10 lL LightCycler 480 SYBR Green Mastermix (Roche, Penzberg, Germany), 0.5 lL gene-specific primer mix (10 pmol), 7.5 lL nuclease-free water, and 2 lL sample cDNA.</s><s>Each plate was run at 958C for 2 minutes, followed by 45 cycles at 958C for 10 seconds, 608C for 10 seconds, and 728C for 10 seconds, and gene-specific transcript amplification was confirmed by obtaining a melting curve profile (60-958C).</s><s>The cycle threshold (Ct) parameter was defined by second derivative maximum analysis with LightCyler480 software v1.5 (Roche).</s><s>To standardize mRNA concentration, transcript levels of a reference gene in each sample, 18S rRNA was determined in parallel and relative transcript levels were corrected by normalization with the 18S Ct levels.</s><s>All real-time RT-PCRs were performed in triplicate and changes in gene expression were calculated using the delta delta Ct method. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">36</ref></s><s>Real-time RT-PCR was performed using LightCycler 480 from Roche.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Immunohistochemistry</head><p><s>Surgically removed PT fixed in 4% formalin was embedded in paraffin, sectioned (7 lm) and deparaffinized.</s><s>Immunohistochemistry was performed with anti-TRPV1 (ACC-030; Alomone Labs, Jerusalem, Israel), TRPM8 (HPA024117; Sigma Aldrich, Munich, Germany), cytokeratin (CK)-13 (sc-57003; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Heidelberg, Germany), CK-15 (CBL1587417; Millipore, Darmstadt, Germany), and CK-19 (sc-53003; Santa Cruz Biotechnology) antibodies, as previously described in detail. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">37</ref></s><s>Transient receptor potential V1 and -M8 antibody specificity was confirmed based on elimination of antibody reactivity by antibody preadsorption with 1 lg of a respective blocking peptide per lg antibody.</s><s>Furthermore, control sections were incubated with nonimmune IgG to determine possible nonspecific binding of IgG.</s><s>The slides were examined with a Keyence BZ 9000 microscope (Keyence Germany, Neu-Isenburg, Germany).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Western Blot Analysis</head><p><s>Cells were lysed with 1% Triton X-100 for 30 minutes on ice and centrifuged at 17,950 g for 5 minutes.</s><s>Pterygium tissue was lysed with peqGOLD TriFast reagent (Peqlab).</s><s>Total protein was isolated from phenol/chloroform phase as described in the manufacturer's protocol.</s><s>Protein pellet was dissolved in 10 M urea/50 mM dithiothreitol and sonicated (HTU Soni130; G. HEINEMANN, Schwäbisch Gmünd, Germany) for 3 seconds.</s><s>Supernatant protein concentration was determined with the Bradford assay.</s><s>For Western blot analysis, 20 lg total protein was boiled for 5 minutes with a reducing buffer containing b-mercaptoethanol and loaded onto 12% SDS-PAGE, separated by electrophoresis and transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane by blotting.</s><s>Blots were blocked in 5% nonfat milk/TBST (1 mL Tween 20/1 L Tris-buffered saline)</s></p><p><s>for 1 hour and probed with the primary antibody (1:100 dilution) overnight at 48C.</s><s>Washing with TBST was followed by incubation with horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody (dilution 1:5000, 2 hours at room temperature).</s><s>Signal readout was determined by chemiluminescence with an enhanced chemiluminescence substrate (Millipore) in Biorad Universalhood II (Munich, Germany).</s><s>Furthermore, every blot was stripped with b-mercaptoethanol, 20% SDS, 1M Tris-HCl pH 6.8 containing buffer at 708C for 30 minutes.</s><s>Afterward, glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase detection for normalization was performed.</s><s>Blots were analyzed and quantified by Quantity One Software v4.6.9 (Biorad).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proliferation Assay</head><p><s>Spontaneously immortalized hPtEC as well as HCjEC cells were seeded at 10 5 cells/mL in 24-well cell culture plates.</s><s>Cells were cultivated under aforementioned standard conditions in 10% fetal calf serum-containing DMEM/Ham's F12 medium (Control).</s><s>Cells were cultivated with 10 ng/mL epidermal growth factor (EGF), 10 ng/mL VEGF in the presence and absence of 10 lM CAP and/or 10 lM capsazepine (CPZ).</s><s>Medium with/ without additives was replaced every 48 hours.</s><s>At the indicated time points, cells were trypsinized and counted under a phase-contrast microscope (Axiovert 40 CFL; Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany) using a Neubauer improved-hemocytometer (BRAND, Wertheim, Germany).</s><s>At every time point and for each cell line, four different wells were counted.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Metabolic Cell Viability Assay</head><p><s>Using the CellTiter 96 AQueous MTS Assay System (Promega, Mannheim, Germany) according to manufacturer's protocol, cells were cultured in serum-free medium supplemented with either 10, 20, or 100 lM CAP as well as 10 or 20 lM CPZ, respectively.</s><s>Metabolic cell viability was measured after 24 hours by photometry in a plate reader (MWG, Ebersberg, Germany) at 490 nm.</s><s>Human pterygium epithelial cells and HCjEC without additives were used as controls.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fluorescence Calcium Imaging</head><p><s>Cells were seeded on sterile glass cover slips and loaded with fura-2/AM (2 lM) for 20 to 50 minutes at 378C.</s><s>Loading was</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">RT-PCR b-actin 5 0 -GATCCTCACCGAGCGCGGCTACA-3 0 5 0 -GCGGATGTCCACGTCACACTTCA-3 0 60 298 CK-3 5 0 -TGTACCAGACCAAGTTGGGG-3 0 5 0 -CGCCGTAACCTCCTCCATAG-3 0 58 456 CK-13 5 0 -CGGGATGCTGAGGAATGGT-3 0 5 0 -GGGAAACCAATCATCTTGGCG-3 0 62 392 CK-15 5 0 -ACTGAGGAGCTGAACAAAGAGG-3 0 5 0 -CAAGCAGCATCTTGTACTCCT-3 0 58 280 Ki-67 5 0 -TATCAAAAGGAGCGGGGTCG-3 0 5 0 -TTGAGCTTTTCTCATCAGGGTCA-3 0 58 388 MMP7 5 0 -GTTTAGAAGCCAAACTCAAGG-3 0 5 0 -CTTTGACACTAATCGATCCAC-3 0 64 100 MUC5AC 5 0 -CCAAGGAGAACCTCCCATAT-3 0 5 0 -CCAAGCGTCATTCCTGAG-3 0 61 282 TRPV1 5 0 -CTCCTACAACAGCCTGTAC-3 0 5 0 -AAGGCCTTCCTCATGCACT-3 0 63 285 TRPV2 5 0 -CTCTGGTGGCTAGCCTGTCCTGACA-3 0 5 0 -TGGGATCCCGGAGCTTCTTCTCA-3 0 63 228 TRPV3 5 0 -GCTGAAGAAGCGCATCTTTGCA-3 0 5 0 -TCATAGGCCTCCTCTGTGTACT-3 0 65 288 TRPV4 5 0 -TACCTGTGTGCCATGGTCATCT-3 0 5 0 -TGCTATAGGTCCCCGTCAGCTT-3 0 60 379 TRPM8 5 0 -CCTGTTCCTCTTTGCGGTGTGGAT-3 0 5 0 -TCCTCTGAGGTGTCGTTGGCTTT-3 0 65 621 Real-time RT-PCR 18S rRNA 5 0 -TGCCAGAGTCTCGTTCGTTA-3 0 5 0 -GGTGCATGGCCGTTCTTA-3 0 60 92 TRPM8 5 0 -ACACTCAGTGAACAGCTCAACAG-3 0 5 0 -GCCAAAGTGAAGAACGACATC-3 0 60 93 TRPV1 5 0 -CCTGCAGGAGTCGGTTCA-3 0 5 0 -CAGCAGCGAGACCCCTAA-3 0 60 65</formula><p><s>stopped by replacing the dye containing culture medium with a Ringer-like (control) solution optimized for TRP detection <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">38</ref> whose composition was in mM: 150 NaCl, 6 CsCl, 1 MgCl 2 , 10 glucose, 10 HEPES, and 1.5 CaCl 2 at pH 7.4.</s><s>Washed cover slips were put into a bath chamber containing the aforementioned Ringer-like solution on the stage of a microscope (Olympus BW50WI; Olympus Europa Holding GmbH, Hamburg, Germany) in conjunction with a digital imaging system having UV excitation capability (TILL Photonics, Munich, Germany).</s><s>Cells were alternately excited at 340 and 380 nm and fluorescence emission was detected from cell clusters every 500 ms at 510 nm.</s><s>The ratio (f 340nm /f 380nm ) is a relative index of intracellular Ca 2þ ([Ca 2þ ] i ) levels. <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">39</ref></s><s>The 340-and 380-nm signals were always detectable and did not distort the ratio.</s><s>The measuring field was adapted to the number of cells (TILL Photonics viewfinding system).</s><s>Before the experiments, stable control baseline levels were obtained for 8 to 10 minutes.</s><s>The control traces are designated with open circles in the figures.</s><s>All experiments were performed at a constant room temperature (» 208-238C) because experiments performed at higher temperatures led to increased Ca 2þ levels due to increased open probability of thermosensitive-TRPs in ocular surface cells. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29</ref></s><s>Stock solutions of drugs were prepared in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO).</s><s>Dimethyl sulfoxide concentrations below 0.1% had no detectable effect on intracellular Ca 2þ regulation (data not shown). <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">40</ref></s><s>anar Patch-Clamping</s></p><p><s>The whole-cell mode (''Port-a-Patch''; Nanion, Munich, Germany) was used in combination with an EPC 10 patch-clamp amplifier (HEKA, Lamprecht, Germany) and PatchMaster software (Version 2.4; HEKA). <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">40</ref></s><s>In brief, the standard intracellular solution contained in mM: 50 CsCl, 10 NaCl, 60 CsF, 20 EGTA, and 10 HEPES-acid at pH of approximately 7. mV. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">41</ref></s><s>The holding potential was set to 0 mV to eliminate any possible contribution of voltage-dependent Ca 2þ channels.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Analysis</head><p><s>Student</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Validation of hPtEC Phenotype</head><p><s>Reverse transcriptase PCR documented biomarker gene expression of pterygium (MMP7 and Ki-67) and conjunctiva (MUC5AC, CK-13 and -15) <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">42</ref> in spontaneously immortalized hPtECs and in PT (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1A</ref>).</s><s>Western blot analysis shows increased protein levels of CK-13, -15, and -19 in hPtEC compared with HCjECs.</s><s>In hPtECs, there was a 2.9-fold increase in CK-13, 11.4-fold increase in CK-15 and 96.9-fold</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Temperature-Sensitive TRP Channel Expression</head><p><s>In hPtEC, PT, immortalized HCEC, HCjEC, and limbal epithelial cells, there was TRPV1, 2, 3, and 4 and TRPM8 gene expression (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2A</ref>).</s><s>The TRP gene expression profiles were similar to one another and the b-actin control PCR (298 bp) products were invariant in all samples.</s><s>Real-time RT-PCR analysis revealed significant TRPV1 gene expression upregulation (P ¼ 0.042) in hPtEC compared with HCjEC.</s><s>In the no template controls (NTC), contaminating genomic DNA was absent.</s><s>Transient receptor potential V1 protein expression levels were approximately 2-fold and 4.8-fold higher in hPtEC and PT, respectively, than those in HCEC and HCjEC (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2B</ref>).</s><s>In addition, there was TRPV1 and TRPM8 localized expression in FFPE sections of pterygia (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2C</ref>).</s><s>Transient receptor potential V1 and weaker TRPM8 intracytoplasmic reactivity was evident in pterygial epithelial cells in all epithelial layers.</s><s>Transient receptor potential V1 immunoreactivity was also present in vascular endothelial cells of the lamina propria.</s><s>There was less intense intracellular TRPM8 immunoreactivity in PT sections, but none was detected in the lamina propria.</s><s>In all cases, no reactivity was detected with each preadsorbed primary antibody.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Functional Heat-Sensitive TRPV1 Expression</head><p><s>In hPtEC expanded from five patients, the f 340nm /f 380nm ratio irreversibly increased after heating (&gt;438C) from  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">, 3C</ref>).</s><s>However, there was a sustained increase in intracellular Ca 2þ after heat stimulation only in hPtEC.</s><s>This was not obvious in HCjEC and HCEC and the Ca 2þ transients were not significantly different shortly after heat stimulation.</s><s>Specifically, after heat stimulation for 4 minutes, the duration of the TRPV1 response was longer in hPtEC than in HCjEC and HCEC (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3D</ref>).</s><s>Moreover, the transient decline was more gradual in hPtEC than HCEC (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3A</ref> versus Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3C</ref>).</s><s>With hPtEC at 320 seconds, the f 340nm /f 380nm ratio rose to  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">, 4B</ref>).</s><s>Subsequent to reaching a peak, it partially declined to 1.315 6 0.012 in HCjEC (n ¼ 11; *P &lt; 0.05, paired tested).</s><s>Although the Ca 2þ transient peaks were not different from one another in HCjEC and hPtEC (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref>), at 480 seconds intracellular Ca 2þ level remained at a higher level in hPtEC (480 seconds; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3D</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Using instead primary freshly isolated hPtEC and comparing its heat-induced [Ca 2þ ] i transient with that measured in healthy HCjEC, the difference was larger than obtained with immortalized hPtEC (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>).</s><s>Taken together, the larger and less reversible heat-induced Ca 2þ influx in primary passaged hPtEC indicates a longer and greater TRPV1 open probability than in the normal healthy HCjECs.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TRPV1-Induced Currents in Immortalized hPtEC</head><p><s>To validate that the heat-induced Ca 2þ transients are attributable to TRPV1 activation, they were compared with the underlying currents induced by 20 lM CAP.</s><s>It increased outwardly rectifying currents (þ130 mV) from 81 6 13 pA/pF up to 199 6 44 pA/pF (*P &lt; 0.05; n ¼ 16, paired tested) (Figs.</s><s><ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5C, 5D</ref>).</s><s>This change was   not significantly different from that in immortalized HCjECs (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5H</ref>).</s><s>On the other hand, CAP increased inward currents in hPtEC (À60 mV) from À12 6 1 pA/pF up to À31 6 6 pA/pF (**P &lt; 0.01; n ¼ 16) (Figs.</s><s>5C, 5D), which was slightly larger than that occurring in healthy HCjECs (À16 6 2 pA/pF; Figs.</s><s><ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5F-H</ref>).</s><s>The TRPV1 channel blocker CPZ caused these currents in hPtEC to fall by À15 6 1 pA/pF more than in HCjEC.</s><s>This difference more definitively reflects larger functional TRPV1 activity in immortalized hPtEC than immortalized HCjEC.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Heightened Functional TRPV1 Behavior in hPtEC</head><p><s>To validate that the difference in inward currents is accountable for larger Ca 2þ influx in immortalized hPtEC than HCjEC, we compared the magnitudes of the Ca 2þ transients induced by CAP.</s><s>Results shown in Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6D-F</ref> indicate that the CAPinduced Ca 2þ transients were at higher levels in immortalized hPtEC than in HCjEC.</s><s>Specifically, the f 340nm /f 380nm ratio increased from 1.201 6 0.002 to 1.231 6 0.045 after CAP application (20 lM) in immortalized hPtEC (n ¼ 31; ***P &lt; 0.005, paired tested; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6D</ref>), whereas in HCjEC, this ratio increased less from 1.200 6 0.0003 to 1.209 6 0.003 (n ¼ 12; ##P &lt; 0.01, unpaired tested; Figs.</s><s><ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6D, 6F</ref>).</s><s>These increases were smaller than those induced by heating to 438C, as heating is less specifically activating TRPV1 than CAP.</s><s>A difference in selectivity also is apparent between exposure to CAP and a hypertonic stress because the latter condition induced larger CPZ inhabitable intracellular Ca 2þ transients (Figs.</s><s><ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6A-C</ref>).</s><s>This difference among the effects of CAP, hypertonicity, and heating are not attributable to baseline variations, because in the absence of CAP, the baseline levels remained constant and were identical to one another in HCjEC and hPtEC (Figs.</s><s><ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6D-F</ref>; n ¼ 13-19; open circles).</s><s>Taken together, these results suggest that functional TRPV1 expression in hPtEC is at higher levels in immortalized hPtEC than in HCjEC.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dependence of VEGF-Induced Ca 2þ Influx on TRPV1 Transactivation in hPtEC</head><p><s>As shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7B</ref>, VEGF increased the f 340nm /f 380nm ratio from 1.202 6 0.002 to 1.225 6 0.006 (t ¼ 480 seconds) in hPtEC (n ¼ 6; *P &lt; 0.05, paired tested), whereas the VEGF effect was smaller in HCjEC (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7A</ref>).</s><s>On the other hand, in hPtEC, 20 lM CPZ as well as a mixed TRPV1/TRPM8 antagonist, 20 lM BCTC, <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">43</ref> both caused the Ca 2þ transients to even fall below their baseline (Figs.</s><s><ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7C, 7D</ref>).</s><s>Corresponding effects of 10 ng/mL VEGF on inward currents indicate that they increased from À18 6 2 pA/pF to À54 6 11 pA/pF (n ¼ 6-12; ***P &lt; 0.005; unpaired tested in hPtEC; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8H</ref>), whereas rises in outward currents were smaller (Figs.</s><s><ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8D, 8H</ref>).</s><s>Notably, 20 lM CPZ inhibited the inward currents (À20 6 4 pA/pF; n ¼ 8; **P &lt; 0.01; unpaired tested), whereas 500 lM La 3þ only partially decreased these currents (Figs.</s><s><ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8A-D</ref>).</s><s>This agreement between the suppressive effects of CPZ on VEGF-induced rises in inward currents and Ca 2þ transients supports the notion that the Ca 2þ transients induced by VEGF are mediated through TRPV1 transactivation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Human Pterygium Epithelial Cells and HCjEC Proliferation Behavior</head><p><s>As functional TRPV1 activity is larger in immortalized hPtEC than in HCjEC, we hypothesized that hyperplastic hPtEC activity is dependent on enhanced TRPV1 channel activity mediating larger Ca 2þ influx.</s><s>To test this hypothesis, timedependent increases in cell proliferation were compared between spontaneously immortalized hPtEC and HCjEC.</s><s>The results shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">9A</ref> indicate that the number of cultivated hPtECs was significantly greater at all time points examined (*P 24 &lt; 0.05, **P 48 &lt; 0.01, ***P 72-240 &lt; 0.001).</s></p><p><s>During the long exponential growth phase extending from 24 to 168 hours, the population-doubling time of immortalized hPtEC was 39.09 hours compared with 54.27 hours for HCjEC, which showed no exponential growth phase.</s><s>Furthermore, we determined if this increase in immortalized hPtEC proliferation was associated with rises in metabolic activity.</s><s>In HCjEC 5 lM (*P &lt; 0.05) and 100 lM (***P &lt; 0.001) CAP significantly decreased metabolic cell activity after 24 hours of cultivation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">9B</ref>).</s><s>On the other hand, in immortalized hPtEC, both 5 and 20 lM CAP (***P &lt; 0.001) increased metabolic activity.</s><s>Cultivation with CPZ (10 lM) maximally increased immortalized hPtEC metabolic cell activity (**P &lt; 0.01), because at 20 lM its effect was indistinguishable from that at the lower concentration.</s><s>On the other hand, it had no effect after 24 hours in HCjEC.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Capsazepine Suppresses EGF-Induced Cell Proliferation in hPtEC</head><p><s>The mitogenic responses by hPtEC and HCjEC to 10 ng/mL EGF were compared to determine if they corresponded with differences in TRPV1 channel activity between these cell types.</s><s>Epithelial growth factor-induced mitogenic responses were larger in hPtEC than in HCjEC.</s><s>(Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">10A, 10C</ref>).</s><s>After 96 hours, cocultivation of hPtEC with EGF/CPZ cell amount was higher compared with that with CPZ alone ( ## P &lt; 0.01).</s><s>This partial inhibitory effect of CPZ suggests that other pathways besides TRPV1 contribute to mediating a rise in Ca 2þ influx needed to induce an increase in proliferation.</s><s>Capsaicin (10 lM) did not affect proliferation in HCjEC until 96 hours when it began to instead inhibit this response (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">10A</ref>).</s><s>Similarly, CPZ inhibited HCjEC cell proliferation and became cytotoxic (Figs.</s><s><ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">10B, 10D</ref>; ### P 72/96 &lt; 0.001).</s><s>After another 48 hours of exposure to CPZ, there were no remaining viable HCjECs.</s><s>Taken together, these results suggest that larger functional TRPV1 activity in hPtEC than HCjEC is sufficient to induce hyperplastic pterygial epithelial cell behavior.</s><s>Nevertheless, TRPV1 activation con-  ) and after addition of La 3þ (labeled as [C]).</s><s>Data were obtained from the data shown in (A).</s><s>Notable, there was a partial decrease of VEGF-induced in-and outward currents in the presence of La 3þ .</s><s>(C) Maximal negative current density induced by a voltage step from 0 mV to À60 mV are depicted in percent of control values before application of VEGF and La 3þ respectively (left).</s><s>Vascular endothelial growth factor-induced inward currents could be partially suppressed in the presence of La 3þ (500 lM).</s><s>Same analyses are shown on the right, but of steps from 0 mV to 130 mV.</s><s>(D) Summary of the experiments with VEGF and La 3þ .</s><s>The asterisk (*) indicates a statistically significant difference of whole-cell inward currents with and without VEGF (n ¼ 5; *P &lt; 0.05; paired tested).</s><s>(E) Similar recordings as shown in (A), but with CPZ (20 lM) from approximately 250 seconds.</s><s>(F) Similar traces as shown in (B) but with CPZ instead of La 3þ .</s><s>Notable, there was a clear decrease of VEGF-induced inward currents in the presence of CPZ (lower trace).</s><s>(G) Similar diagrams as shown in (C) but with CPZ instead of La 3þ .</s><s>(H) Summary of the experiments with VEGF and CPZ.</s><s>The asterisks (*) indicate statistically significant differences of VEGF-induced increases of inward currents with and without CPZ (n ¼ 6-8; **P &lt; 0.01 at the minimum; unpaired tested).</s><s>tributes to these mitogenic responses because CPZ always had an inhibitory effect on cell proliferation in hPtEC.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>By comparing TRPV1 characteristics in clinical pterygial samples and a spontaneously immortalized pterygial epithelial cell line (hPtEC) with those in freshly isolated conjunctival tissue and an immortalized HCjEC counterpart, our results indicate that hyperplastic pterygial cell activity is associated with heightened TRPV1 channel expression levels and functional activity.</s><s>This association suggests that larger TRPV1 activation may support an increased cell proliferation as a consequence of increased Ca 2þ influx.</s><s>Such an effect may more fully activate the mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) signaling pathways mediating growth factor receptor control of proliferation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">44</ref></s><s>unctional TRPV1 activity was characterized in these different tissue preparations by contrasting the effects of raising the bath temperature above 438C (specific for TRPV1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">15</ref> ) with those induced by CAP on Ca 2þ transients and underlying ionic currents.</s><s>The involvement of TRPV1 in inducing these changes was validated by showing that these responses were suppressed during exposure to either La 3þ or CPZ.</s><s>6]<ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[47]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[48]</ref> Because TRPV1 expression and activity are elevated in cancerous tissue, it is conceivable that TRPV1 and possible endogenous modulators may be a potential drug target to suppress proliferation not only in malignant tumors but also in benign hyperplastic tumors, such as pterygium (reviewed by Santoni et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">49</ref> ).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TRPV1 Expression and Functional Relevance</head><p><s>An association between increases in functional TRPV1 activity and proliferation in immortalized hPtEC relative to that in HCjEC is similar to what was described in retinoblastoma cells and in various other tumorous tissues. <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">46</ref></s><s>Increased functional TRPV1 expression in immortalized hPtEC (Figs.</s><s>4-6) suggests that reducing its activity may resolve tumor progression if increases in its activity precede or occur as a consequence of pterygial development.</s><s>Dysregulated TRP channel activation contributes to also triggering, aberrant differentiation, and resistance to apoptotic cell death leading to uncontrolled tumor invasion (spread) (reviewed by Santoni et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">49</ref> ).</s></p><p><s>Transient Receptor Potential V1 (also classically known as a pain receptor <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[50]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[51]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[52]</ref> ) is a nociceptor that is a potential drug target for inhibiting cancer pain in bone metastases, pancreatic cancer, and most likely in other cancers (reviewed in Refs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">53</ref></s><s>).</s><s>Additionally, TRPV1 is also expressed at a multitude of nonneuronal sites, which is prompting many studies probing for their possible involvement in disease progression.</s><s>Besides TRPV1, our RT-PCR results indicate that there is also TRPV2 and TRPM8 gene expression in PT.</s><s>It is noteworthy that TRPV2 mRNA level in PT appears to be higher than in HCjEC (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>).</s><s>Similar to TRPV1, TRPV2 is also elevated in cancerous cells compared with their healthy counterparts. <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">54</ref></s><s>Furthermore, TRPV2 expression may be relevant for supporting the pterygial phenotype, because activation of TRPV2 is associated with release of VEGF in RPE cells. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">45</ref></s><s>Similarly, TRPM8 expression may contribute to the pterygial transition, as this channel plays a role in cancer diseases concerning by modulating proliferation and cell cycle progression. <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">55</ref></s><s>Notably, TRPM8 is functionally expressed at higher levels in hPtEC (data not shown) compared with human corneal epithelial cells and conjunctival epithelial cells, <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">56</ref> whereas TRPM8 mRNA expression was not significantly different (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>).</s><s>These disconnects show that there is not always an association between changes in TRP mRNA expression and their functional expression.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TRPV1 Characteristics</head><p><s>Inducing TRPV1 activation by a thermal stress led to continuous larger sustained intracellular Ca 2þ increases after initiating heating in primary hPtEC (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3A</ref>) than in immortalized HCjEC or HCEC (Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3B, 3C</ref>).</s><s>This difference in the Ca 2þ response patterns suggests a possible Ca 2þ signal remodeling in tumorigenic from that in nontumorigenic cells. <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">57</ref></s><s>More specifically, the time-dependent Ca 2þ transient recovery subsequent to reducing the bath temperature back to 228C was different between hPtEC and HCjEC.</s><s>In primary hPtEC, there was no reversal, whereas in HCjEC, temperature restoration to 228C caused a partial recovery toward its baseline level (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3B</ref>).</s><s>This limited baseline restoration in HCjEC is somewhat similar to the complete recovery that occurred in immortalized HCEC <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29</ref> (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3C</ref>).</s><s>Even though these are immortalized cell lines, their similar recovery patterns indicate that Ca 2þ extrusion mechanism activation is sufficient to offset Ca 2þ influx.</s><s>In primary HCjEC, the recovery pattern was similar to that in immortalized HCjEC (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4A</ref>, open circles).</s><s>Another suggestion of Ca 2þ regulation remodeling in hPtEC is that the intracellular Ca 2þ level was always higher in primary hPtEC than in normal tissues (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4A</ref>, filled circles).</s><s>Such remodeling may involve TRPV1 upregulation along with overexpression.</s><s>This suggestion of Ca 2þ signal remodeling is based on similar differences in Ca 2þ transients between other hyperproliferative cancerous and normal tissues. <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">57,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">58</ref></s><s>For example, Stewart et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">57</ref> suggested, in their hypothetical remodeling of Ca 2þ signaling, that lack of recovery is linked with a sustained increase in intracellular Ca 2þ tumorigenic cells.</s><s>Notably, this indication of Ca 2þ remodeling may account for the lack of recovery in both immortalized pterygial cells and in uveal melanoma cells. <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">47</ref></s><s>The more prolonged Ca 2þ transient in tumor cells suggests that TRPV1 open probability time is longer than in healthy controls.</s><s>Another possibility for the lack of recovery is that calcium extrusion mechanism functional behavior (i.e., Na þ /Ca 2þ exchanger and/or plasma membrane calcium ATPase) may be reduced in pterygial cells.</s></p><p><s>The correspondence between the heat-induced Ca 2þ transients and underlying ionic currents was validated by showing that CAP and CPZ had similar modulatory effects on TRPV1 activity.</s><s>Another result reflective of TRPV1 involvement is that the reversal potential was always near 0 mV, which is consistent with behavior of a nonselective cation channel.</s><s>On the other hand, any possible contributions by Cl À channel currents are unlikely because isosmotic substitution of NaCl with Na-gluconate Ringers did not change whole-cell currents. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29</ref></s><s>The CAP-induced inward current densities were larger in hPtEC than in HCjEC, whereas the outward current densities were not significantly different from one another (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>).</s><s>This larger inward current indicates that Ca 2þ influx is greater in hPtEC due to TRPV1 activation eliciting larger Ca 2þ influx along a favorable bath to cell electrochemical Ca 2þ gradient.</s><s>However, the outward currents involve other ions than Ca 2þ , which do not permeate against an unfavorable electrochemical gradient from cell to bath.</s><s>Such a difference between the effects of CAP on the inward and outward currents supports the notion that the larger inward currents in cultivated hPtEC are attributable to greater functional TRPV1 activity in hyperplastic immortalized pterygial cells than in HCjEC.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Differential Responses by Cell Types to TRPV1 Channel Modulators</head><p><s>Capsaicin induced larger Ca 2þ transients and whole-cell currents in immortalized hPtEC than in HCjEC, which were blocked by CPZ and BCTC (Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7A-D, 8E-H</ref>).</s><s>As this difference may be associated with hyperplastic activity in immortalized PT, we determined if mitogenic responses to EGF were dependent on Ca 2þ influxes induced by TRPV1 activation.</s><s>As CPZ had corresponding inhibitory effects on increases in Ca 2þ influx and immortalized hPtEC proliferation, EGF receptor activation transactivates TRPV1.</s><s>Another indication that larger TRPV1 activity provides the needed Ca 2þ influx to support immortalized hPtEC hyperplastic behavior is that transient recovery in HCEC and HCjEC recovery was evident, whereas in immortalized hPtEC it was delayed.</s><s>The correspondence between enhanced cell proliferation in fresh clinical pterygial samples and hPtEC shows that results obtained with immortalized hPtEC are relevant for gaining insight into the pathogenesis of this disease. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref></s><s>Another indication of the suitability of hPtEC as a model is that CAP increased metabolic activity in this cell type, but it was cytotoxic in HCjEC (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">10</ref>).</s><s>This difference may be attributable to differences in multidrug efflux resistance (i.e., MDR) behavior between hyperplastic pterygial cells and healthy cells.</s><s>If there is functional MDR activity in immortalized hPtEC, extrusion by this MDR transporter of CAP may prevent it from accumulating to cytotoxic levels, whereas in HCjEC, such a protective effect may be diminished.</s><s>On the other hand, CPZ increased metabolic activity in immortalized hPtEC, suggesting that suppressing TRPV1 activity improved cell viability.</s><s>The lack of an inhibitory effect by CPZ on proliferation in HCjEC may indicate that functional TRPV1 activity is at a much lower level than in immortalized hPtEC (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">9B</ref>).</s><s>Heparin-bound EGF as well as EGF levels rise in pterygium during UV-B exposure <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> and contribute to mediating increases in cell proliferation.</s><s>Transient receptor potential V1 transactivation seems to be involved in inducing this response, as EGF-induced increases in cell proliferation were suppressed in hPtEC after a 48-hour exposure to 10 lM CPZ.</s><s>In contrast, CAP (10 lM) had no effect on hPtEC cell proliferation, suggesting that transient increases in Ca 2þ are inadequate to induce an increase in cell proliferation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">10</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations of Current Therapeutic Options</head><p><s>3]<ref type="bibr" target="#b66">[64]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b67">[65]</ref> In many cases, if it is at all effective, it only delays recurrence. <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">62,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b68">66</ref></s><s>This limitation may be due to the short half-life of anti-VEGF agents at the ocular surface and to the difficulty in determining the ideal dose and treatment regimen to prevent pterygia over an extended period.</s><s>Moreover, Peng et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">67</ref> showed that VEGF gene polymorphism contributes to the variable effectiveness of anti-VEGF agents, as their antibody complexation with VEGF targets specific isoforms that are not expressed in all patient populations.</s><s>Transient receptor potential V1 inhibitors instead may be an alternative approach to suppress VEGF-induced Ca 2þ increases, which are at higher levels in pterygium cells (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref>).</s><s>However, the efficacy and safety of TRPV1 inhibitors as possible drugs for adjuvant pterygium therapy awaits clarification.</s><s>Another possibility for future studies may be to determine if TRPV1 inhibition can be induced by targeting another receptor besides VEGF, whose control of neovascularization elicits TRPV1 activation through transactivation.</s><s>Such a strategy is tenable, as TRPM8 activation by a thyroid hormone analogue (3-T 1 AM) inhibited through crosstalk CAP-and hypertonic-induced increases in TRPV1 channel activity in both HCjEC and HCEC. <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">56</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p><s>Both TRPV1 gene and protein expression and its functional activity are at higher levels in hyperplastic immortalized hPtEC than in normal HCjEC.</s><s>This difference is associated with larger mitogenic responses to EGF in the transdifferentiated hPtEC than in the nontumorous parental control tissue.</s><s>Such differences in TRPV1 characteristics may contribute to the hyperplastic behavior of hPtEC.</s><s>This is tenable because growth factor receptor control of proliferation is dependent on TRPV1 transactivation leading to increases in Ca 2þ influx and in turn MAPK signaling activation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">44</ref></s><s>Furthermore, VEGF induced larger Ca 2þ increases in hPtEC than in HCjEC, which is indicative of larger functional TRPV1 activity in hPtEC than in HCjEC.</s><s>On the other hand, the cause-and-effect relationship between increases in functional TRPV1 activity and pterygium pathogenesis is unclear.</s><s>Finally, the feasibility of noninvasively inhibiting pterygial cell proliferation in a clinical setting by drug-targeting TRPV1 with eye drops awaits the outcome of further studies.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>2 and approximately 288 mOsM, which was applied to the inner side of the microchip.</s><s>The external solution contained in mM: 140 NaCl, 4 KCl, 1 MgCl 2 , 2 CaCl 2 , 5 D-glucose monohydrate, and 10 HEPES (pH » 7.4 and osmolarity » 298 mOsM) was present on the external side of the microchip (resistance of 2.5-3.0</s><s>MX).</s><s>A single cell was held in place in the aperture by applying negative pressure (software-controlled pump).</s><s>The mean membrane capacitance of HCjEC was 13 pF 6 1 pF.</s><s>Mean access resistance was 11 6 1 MX (both n ¼ 26).</s><s>For hPtEC, the corresponding values were 9 pF 6 1 pF and 37 6 4 MX (both n ¼ 26), respectively.</s><s>Series resistances, and fast and slow capacitance transients were compensated by the patchclamp amplifier.</s><s>Current recordings were all leak-subtracted and cells with leak currents above 100 pA were excluded from analysis.</s><s>The I-V response patterns were generated by imposing voltages in 10 mV steps from À60 mV to þ130</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FIGURE 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 1. Characterization of spontaneously immortalized hPtECs.</s><s>(A) Reverse transcriptase PCR analysis revealed gene expression of MMP7, Ki-67, Muc5AC, and CK-13, -15, and -3 in cultivated hPtEC as well as PT.</s><s>Limbal stem cells (LSCs) as well as HCECs and HCjECs were used as controls and show a similar expression profile.</s><s>(B) Detection of CK-13, -15, and -19 proteins in cultivated HCjEC and hPtEC by Western blot analysis.</s><s>(C) Statistical analysis of Western blots shows increased CK-15 and -19 protein levels in cultivated hPtEC compared with HCjEC.</s><s>Results presented as mean 6 SEM of three independent experiments (n ¼ 3).</s><s>*P &lt; 0.05 (2-tailed Student's t-test).</s><s>(D) Localization (red staining) of CK-13, -15, and -19 in formalin-embedded paraffin section of pterygia by immunohistochemistry. Pterygium epithelial cells (Ep), lamina propria (Lp), and blood vessels (arrow) are marked.</s><s>Nuclei (blue) counterstained with hemalaun.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,124.21,63.04,363.52,180.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>FIGURE 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 2. Gene and protein expression of temperature-sensitive TRP channels in pterygia.</s><s>(A) Reverse transcriptase PCR analysis revealed gene expression of TRPV1, 2, 3, and 4 and TRPM8 in hPtECs and PT.</s><s>Limbal stem cells, HCECs, and HCjECs show a similar thermo-TRP gene expression.</s><s>(B) Western blot analysis revealed increased TRPV1 protein expression in cultivated hPtEC (2-fold) as well as PT (4.8-fold) compared with HCjEC.</s><s>(C) Intracytoplasmic immunoreactivity (red staining) of TRPV1 and TRPM8 antibody in formalin-embedded paraffin section of pterygia.</s><s>Pterygium Ep, Lp, and blood vessels (arrow) are marked.</s><s>Nuclei (blue) counterstained with hemalaun.</s><s>(D) Real-time RT-PCR revealed upregulation of TRPV1 gene expression in cultivated hPtEC compared with HCjEC.</s><s>Results presented as mean 6 SEM of three independent experiments (n ¼ 3).</s><s>*P &lt; 0.05 (2-tailed Student's t-test).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,124.21,63.04,363.57,243.38" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>FIGURE 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 3. Increase in Ca 2þ entry through heat-sensitive TRPs caused by heat exposure in hPtEC, HCjEC, and HCEC.</s><s>The thermal changes were inflicted at the time points indicated by arrows.</s><s>Data are mean 6 SEM of 4 to 22 experiments.</s><s>(A) Rise of bath solution temperature from room temperature (» 228C) to over 438C resulted in an irreversible Ca 2þ elevation in hPtEC (n ¼ 22; left).</s><s>In the presence of La 3þ (100 lM), the heatinduced Ca 2þ increase was clearly suppressed (n ¼ 18; right).</s><s>(B-C) Same set of experiments as shown in (A), but with HCjEC (B) and HCEC (C), respectively.</s><s>The heating effect was at lower levels between HCEC and hPtEC at 480 seconds.</s><s>(D) Summary of the experiments with heat stimulation and La 3þ in hPtEC, HCjEC, as well as HCEC.</s><s>The asterisks (*) indicate significant differences between controls (Ca 2þ base levels before heating) and heat-induced Ca 2þ increase on [Ca 2þ ] i (n ¼ 18-22) (paired Student's t-test).</s><s>The hash marks (#) between the filled bars indicate significant differences between Ca 2þ influx with and without La 3þ (unpaired Student's t-test) and heat-induced Ca 2þ influx between hPtEC and HCEC (n ¼ 10-22).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>FIGURE 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 4. Increased heat-induced Ca 2þ influx in primary cultivated hPtEC.</s><s>The thermal change was carried out at the time point indicated by an arrow.</s><s>Data from five patients with pterygium are mean 6 SEM of 22 experiments.</s><s>Data from one healthy individual are mean 6 SEM of 11 experiments.</s><s>(A) Rise of bath solution temperature from room temperature (228C) to over 438C resulted in Ca 2þ elevation in healthy primary cultivated HCECs from one healthy individual and hPtECs from patients with pterygium.</s><s>Traces show intracellular Ca 2þ measured of several neighboring healthy HCjECs (open circles) (n ¼ 11) and primary cultivated hPtECs from patients with pterygium (filled circles) (n ¼ 22) (control base line; f 340nm /f 380nm ¼ 1.2).</s><s>In hPtEC from patients with pterygium, the heat-induced Ca 2þ influx was clearly increased (##P &lt; 0.01; n ¼ 11-22).</s><s>(B) Summary of the experiments with healthy HCjEC from a healthy patient and hPtEC from five patients with pterygium.</s><s>The asterisks (*) indicate significant differences between controls (Ca 2þ base levels; n ¼ 11-22) and heat-induced Ca 2þ increase on [Ca 2þ ] i (n ¼ 11-22) (paired Student's ttest).</s><s>The hash marks (#) between the filled bars indicate significant differences between healthy HCjEC and hPtEC from patients with pterygium (unpaired Student's t-test).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>FIGURE 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 5. Capsaicin-induced increases of whole-cell currents in immortalized HCjEC and in hPtEC.</s><s>(A) Simplified scheme of whole-cell configuration of the planar-patch clamp technique.</s><s>(B) Voltage stimulation protocol.</s><s>Holding potential was set to 0 mV to avoid any voltagedependent ion channel currents.</s><s>(C) Whole-cell channel currents induced by depolarization from À60 mV to þ130 mV after establishing the wholecell configuration (with leak current subtraction) under control conditions.</s><s>(D) Whole-cell channel currents in the presence of 20 lM CAP.</s><s>(E) Whole-cell channel currents in the presence of 10 lM CPZ.</s><s>(F) Effect of CAP and CPZ in HCjEC is shown in a current/voltage plot (I-V plot).</s><s>For the I-V plot, maximal peak current amplitudes were plotted against the voltage (mV) and normalized to cell membrane capacity (current density; pA/ pF).</s><s>The upper trace (filled quadrangles) was obtained in the presence of 20 lM CAP and the trace below (hash marks) in the presence of 10 lM CPZ.</s><s>The third (lower) trace (open circles) was obtained under control conditions.</s><s>(G) Same plot as shown in (F) but data are from hPtEC and taken from (C), (D) and (E).</s><s>(H) Comparison of whole-cell current densities of HCjEC and hPtEC from a patient with pterygium.</s><s>The inward currents of hPtEC were at higher levels compared with those of HCjEC.</s><s>The asterisks (*) indicate significant differences between controls (Ca 2þ base levels; n ¼ 11-22) and CAP-induced whole-cell currents (n ¼ 11-22) (paired Student's t-test).</s><s>The hash marks (#) between the filled bars indicate significant differences between HCjEC and hPtEC from a patient with pterygium (unpaired Student's t-test).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>FIGURE 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 6. Capsaicin and hypertonic challenge induce Ca 2þ entry in hPtEC.</s><s>Data are mean 6 SEM of 6 to 31 experiments.</s><s>(A) Hypertonic challenge (450 mOsM) resulted in Ca 2þ elevation in hPtEC.</s><s>Traces show intracellular Ca 2þ measurements with hypertonic challenge (n ¼ 6) and without hypertonic challenge (n ¼ 10) (control Ca 2þ baseline).</s><s>(B) Similar experiments as shown in (A).</s><s>The trace shows intracellular [Ca 2þ ] i measurements with hypertonic challenge in the presence of CPZ (n ¼ 11).</s><s>(C) Summary of the experiments with hypertonic challenge and CPZ.</s><s>The hypertonicinduced Ca 2þ increase could be clearly suppressed by CPZ.</s><s>The asterisks (*) indicate significant differences between controls (Ca 2þ base levels; n ¼ 6) and hypertonic stress-induced Ca 2þ increases on [Ca 2þ ] i (n ¼ 11) (paired Student's t-test).</s><s>The hash marks (#) between the filled bars indicate significant differences of hypertonic stress-induced Ca 2þ response with and without CPZ (unpaired Student's t-test).</s><s>(D) Application of 20 lM CAP resulted in Ca 2þ elevation in HCjEC.</s><s>Traces show intracellular Ca 2þ measurements with CAP (n ¼ 12) and without CAP (n ¼ 13) (control Ca 2þ base line).</s><s>(E) Similar experiments as shown in (A).</s><s>Traces show intracellular [Ca 2þ ] i measurements with CAP (n ¼ 31) and without CAP (n ¼ 19) (control Ca 2þ baseline).</s><s>(F) Comparison of Ca 2þ entries in HCjEC and immortalized hPtEC.</s><s>The Ca 2þ entry in hPtEC was at higher levels compared with those of HCjEC.</s><s>The asterisks (*) indicate significant differences between controls (Ca 2þ base levels; n ¼ 12-31) and CAP-induced Ca 2þ increases on [Ca 2þ ] i (n ¼ 12-31) (paired Student's t-test).</s><s>The hash marks (#) between the filled bars indicate significant differences between HCjEC and immortalized hPtEC (unpaired Student's t-test).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>FIGURE 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 8. Vascular endothelial growth factor-induced increases of whole-cell currents in hPtEC.</s><s>(A) Time course recording showing the current increases by 10 ng/mL VEGF and current density levels after adding La 3þ (500 lM).</s><s>(B) Original traces of VEGF-induced current responses to voltage ramps.</s><s>Current densities are shown before application (labeled as [A]), during application of VEGF (labeled as [B]) and after addition of La 3þ (labeled as [C]).</s><s>Data were obtained from the data shown in (A).</s><s>Notable, there was a partial decrease of VEGF-induced in-and outward currents in the presence of La 3þ .</s><s>(C) Maximal negative current density induced by a voltage step from 0 mV to À60 mV are depicted in percent of control values before application of VEGF and La 3þ respectively (left).</s><s>Vascular endothelial growth factor-induced inward currents could be partially suppressed in the presence of La 3þ (500 lM).</s><s>Same analyses are shown on the right, but of steps from 0 mV to 130 mV.</s><s>(D) Summary of the experiments with VEGF and La 3þ .</s><s>The asterisk (*) indicates a statistically significant difference of whole-cell inward currents with and without VEGF (n ¼ 5; *P &lt; 0.05; paired tested).</s><s>(E) Similar recordings as shown in (A), but with CPZ (20 lM) from approximately 250 seconds.</s><s>(F) Similar traces as shown in (B) but with CPZ instead of La 3þ .</s><s>Notable, there was a clear decrease of VEGF-induced inward currents in the presence of CPZ (lower trace).</s><s>(G) Similar diagrams as shown in (C) but with CPZ instead of La 3þ .</s><s>(H) Summary of the experiments with VEGF and CPZ.</s><s>The asterisks (*) indicate statistically significant differences of VEGF-induced increases of inward currents with and without CPZ (n ¼ 6-8; **P &lt; 0.01 at the minimum; unpaired tested).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>FIGURE 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 7. Vascular endothelial growth factor-induced increases of intracellular Ca 2þ in immortalized HCjEC and in hPtEC.</s><s>Data are mean 6 SEM of 4 to 11 experiments.</s><s>(A) Application of 10 ng/mL VEGF resulted in Ca 2þ elevation in HCjEC.</s><s>Traces show intracellular Ca 2þ measurements with VEGF (filled circles, n ¼ 11) and without VEGF (n ¼ 4) (control Ca 2þ baseline).</s><s>(B) Similar experiments as shown in (A) but with hPtEC.</s><s>Traces show intracellular [Ca 2þ ] i measurements with VEGF (filled circles, n ¼ 6) and without VEGF (n ¼ 4) (control Ca 2þ baseline).</s><s>(C) Similar experiments as shown in (B) but in the presence of 20 lM CPZ (left) or 20 lM BCTC (right).</s><s>The VEGF-induced Ca 2þ entry was completely abolished in the presence of CPZ or BCTC.</s><s>(D) Comparison of Ca 2þ entries in HCjEC and immortalized hPtEC.</s><s>The Ca 2þ entry in hPtEC was at higher levels compared with those of HCjEC (480 seconds).</s><s>The asterisks (*) indicate significant differences between controls (Ca 2þ base levels; n ¼ 12) and VEGF-induced Ca 2þ increases on [Ca 2þ ] i (n ¼ 31) (paired Student's t-test).</s><s>The hash marks (#) between the filled bars indicate significant differences between HCjEC and immortalized hPtEC and VEGF effect with and without CPZ/BCTC (unpaired Student's t-tests).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>FIGURE 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 9. Cell proliferation and metabolic cell activity in HCjEC and hPtEC.</s><s>(A) Human pterygial cells showed an increased cell proliferation compared with HCjEC.</s><s>Total numbers of cells were counted at the indicated time points.</s><s>Human conjunctival epithelial cells, as well as hPtECs, were cultivated under standard conditions.</s><s>All data presented as mean 6 SEM of four independent experiments (n ¼ 4).</s><s>For statistical evaluation of cell counts, 2-way ANOVA and Bonferroni posttests were performed.</s><s>(B) Metabolic cell activity is affected by TRPV1 agonist CAP in both cell lines, whereas TRPV1 antagonist CPZ affected only hPtEC.</s><s>Human conjunctival epithelial cells and hPtECs were incubated with 5, 20, and 100 lM CAP, as well as 10 and 20 lM CPZ for 24 hours.</s><s>Metabolic cell activity was colorimetric analyzed by MTS assay.</s><s>Cells cultivated in standard medium containing DMSO were used as controls and set to 100%.</s><s>Values represent mean 6 SEM of eight independent experiments (n ¼ 8).</s><s>Statistical significance was calculated by 1-way ANOVA and Dunnet's posttests and indicated by asterisks (*P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; ***P &lt; 0.001) and hashtags ( ### P &lt; 0.001).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,124.27,63.04,363.40,133.46" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>FIGURE 10 .</head><label>10</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 10. Cell proliferation in hPtEC and HCjEC with and without TRPV1 modulators as well as pterygium-associated growth factors.</s><s>Capsazepine (10 lM) suppressed EGF-but not VEGF-induced cell proliferation in hPtEC at long-term cultivation.</s><s>Capsaicin (10 lM) did not affect cell proliferation of hPtEC.</s><s>Both TRPV1 modulators had a cytotoxic effect in HCjEC.</s><s>(A-D) Cell proliferation assays.</s><s>Human pterygial cells (A, C), as well as HCjEC (B, D), were cocultivated with CAP (10 lM), CPZ (10 lM), EGF and VEGF (each 10 ng/mL), and CPZ together (EGF/CPZ and VEGF/ CPZ) as well as without additives (control) up to 96 hours.</s><s>Total numbers of cells were counted every 24 hours.</s><s>(E-H) Detailed statistical analysis of cell proliferation in hPtEC (E, G) and HCjEC (F and H).</s><s>All data are presented as mean 6 SEM of four independent experiments (n ¼ 4).</s><s>For statistical evaluation of cell counts, 1-way ANOVA and Bonferroni posttests were performed.</s><s>Statistical significance is indicated by asterisks (*P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; ***P &lt; 0.001) and hashtags ( ## P &lt; 0.01; ### P &lt; 0.001).</s><s>n.d., no detectable cells.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="11,150.46,63.04,311.02,503.09" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE .</head><label>.</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Gene-Specific Intron-Spanning Primer Sequences, Annealing Temperatures, Cycle Numbers, and Product Sizes of Biomarkers and TRPs</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>A t ,</cell><cell>Size,</cell></row><row><cell>Gene</cell><cell>Forward Primer</cell><cell>Reverse Primer</cell><cell>8C</cell><cell>bp</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>1.556 6 0.045; n ¼ 22 and fell slightly to 1.478 6 0.059; n ¼ 22 at 480 seconds.</s><s>On the other hand, with HCjEC, the f 340nm /f</s></p></div></figDesc><table /><note><p><s>380nm ratio rose less, from 1.200 6 0.001 to 1.370 6 0.022 (n ¼ 11; ***P &lt; 0.005, paired tested; Figs.</s><s>4A</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License. Downloaded From: https://iovs.arvojournals.org/ on 08/27/2018</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Downloaded From: https://iovs.arvojournals.org/ on 08/27/2018</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p><s>The authors thank Ersal Türker and Gabriele Fels for the technical assistance, as well as Olaf Strauß, PhD (all Charité, Department of Ophthalmology), for helpful discussions.</s><s>Furthermore, we appreciate very much the technical assistance provided by the fellow students Anna Santaella, Sahana Srinivasan, Lilly Brankova, Katherina Riffel, Nina Ljubojevic, Anja Lude, Martin Straßenburg, and Leticia Barcelos Picado during their laboratory internships, as well as Sylvia Dyczek in the translation and proof reading of the</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pterygium: prevalence, demography and risk factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Saw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ophthalmic Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The science of pterygia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Reid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Schwab</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Ophthalmol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="815" to="820" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The prevalence and risk factors for pterygium in an adult Chinese population in Singapore: the Tanjong Pagar survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Foster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Seah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Ophthalmol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="176" to="183" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pterygium in Indonesia: prevalence, severity and risk factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gazzard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Saw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Farook</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Ophthalmol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1341" to="1346" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prevalence of and racial differences in pterygium: a multiethnic population study in Asians</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ophthalmology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1509" to="1515" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Etiology, clinical aspects and novel adjuvant therapies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Heindl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cursiefen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Pterygium</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>in German</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ophthalmologe</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="517" to="514" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The treatment of pterygium</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hirst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surv Ophthalmol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="180" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Angiogenesis in pterygium: study of microvessel density, vascular endothelial growth factor, and thrombospondin-1. Eye (Lond)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aspiotis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tsanou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gorezis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1095" to="1101" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immunohistochemical analysis of vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) and p53 expression in pterygium from Tunisian patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Khalfaoui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mkannez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Colin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pathol Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential expression of vascular endothelial growth factor implies the limbal origin of pterygia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gebhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mentlein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Schaudig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ophthalmology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1023" to="1030" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An introduction to TRP channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ramsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Delling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Clapham</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Rev Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="619" to="647" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capsaicin receptor: TRPV1 a promiscuous TRP channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Pingle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Matta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ahern</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Handb Exp Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">179</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="171" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single particle electron cryomicroscopy of a mammalian ion channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julius</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Struct Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and function of TRPV1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tominaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Tominaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pflugers Arch</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">451</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="150" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermosensation and pain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tominaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Caterina</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurobiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pharmacology of vanilloid transient receptor potential cation channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vriens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Appendino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Nilius</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1262" to="1279" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increased expression of TRPV1 channel in intrinsically aged and photoaged human skin in vivo</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="436" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transient receptor potential vanilloid-1 mediates heat-shock-induced matrix metalloproteinase-1 expression in human epidermal keratinocytes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Invest Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2328" to="2335" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TRPV1 structures in distinct conformations reveal activation mechanisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julius</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">504</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="118" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure of the TRPV1 ion channel determined by electron cryo-microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julius</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">504</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional and structural divergence in human TRPV1 channel subunits by oxidative cysteine modification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ogawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kurokawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fujiwara</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">291</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4197" to="4210" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Forcing open TRP channels: mechanical gating as a unifying activation mechanism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Montell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem Biophys Res Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">460</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Photomechanical responses in Drosophila photoreceptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hardie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Franze</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">338</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="260" to="263" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Melanopsin signalling in mammalian iris and retina</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Xue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Do</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Riccio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">479</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calcium regulation by thermo-and osmosensing transient receptor potential vanilloid channels (TRPVs) in human conjunctival epithelial cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mergler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Garreis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sahlmuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Histochem Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="743" to="761" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TRPV channels mediate temperature-sensing in human corneal endothelial cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mergler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Valtink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Coulson-Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp Eye Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="758" to="770" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional TRPV1 expression in human corneal fibroblasts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mergler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wolosin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Reinach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp Eye Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transient receptor potential vanilloid 1 activation induces inflammatory cytokine release in corneal epithelium through MAPK signaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cell Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">213</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="730" to="739" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermosensitive transient receptor potential channels in human corneal epithelial cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mergler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Garreis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sahlmuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Reinach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Paulsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Pleyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cell Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">226</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1828" to="1842" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Polymodal roles of transient receptor potential channels in the control of ocular function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Reinach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mergler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eye Vis (Lond)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TRPV1 activation is required for hypertonicity-stimulated inflammatory cytokine release in human corneal epithelial cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Reinach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="485" to="493" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TRPV1 involvement in inflammatory tissue fibrosis in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Okada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Reinach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Shirai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Pathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">178</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2654" to="2664" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Piperine, a dietary phytochemical, inhibits angiogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Doucette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hilchie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Liwski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hoskin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Nutr Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="239" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TRP channels in cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Prevarskaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Barritt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim Biophys Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1772</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="937" to="946" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An SV40-immortalized human corneal epithelial cell line and its characterization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Araki-Sasaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ohashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sasabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="614" to="621" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new mathematical model for relative quantification in real-time RT-PCR</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Pfaffl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e45</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Thermo-sensitive transient receptor potential vanilloid channel-1 regulates intracellular calcium and triggers chromogranin A secretion Thermo-Sensitive TRP Upregulation in Pterygia IOVS j</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mergler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Skrzypski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sassek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016-05">May 2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2576</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">in pancreatic neuroendocrine BON-1 tumor cells</title>
		<ptr target="https://iovs.arvojournals.org/on08/27/2018" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Signal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The principle of temperature-dependent gating in cold-and heat-sensitive TRP channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Voets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Droogmans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Wissenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Janssens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Flockerzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Nilius</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">430</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="748" to="754" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new generation of Ca2þ indicators with greatly improved fluorescence properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Grynkiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Poenie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Tsien</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">260</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3440" to="3450" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lcarnitine reduces in human conjunctival epithelial cells hypertonic-induced shrinkage through interacting with TRPV1 channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Khajavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Reinach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Skrzypski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lude</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mergler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Physiol Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="790" to="803" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thyronamine induces TRPM8 channel activation in human conjunctival epithelial cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Khajavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Reinach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Slavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Signal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="325" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transplantation of conjunctival epithelial cells cultivated ex vivo in patients with total limbal stem cell deficiency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ricardo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cristovam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Filho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cornea</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of transient receptor potential vanilloid 1 (TRPV1) receptor antagonist compounds SB705498, BCTC and AMG9810 in rat models of thermal hyperalgesia measured with an increasing-temperature water bath</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Tekus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bolcskei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kis-Varga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">641</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epidermal growth factor receptor transactivation by the cannabinoid receptor (CB1) and transient receptor potential vanilloid 1 (TRPV1) induces differential responses in corneal epithelial cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Capo-Aponte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Reinach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp Eye Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="471" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heatsensitive TRPV channels in retinal pigment epithelial cells: regulation of VEGF-A secretion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cordeiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Seyler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stindl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Milenkovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Strauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6001" to="6008" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Altered calcium regulation by thermosensitive transient receptor potential channels in etoposide-resistant WERI-Rb1 retinoblastoma cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mergler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Skosyrski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp Eye Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calcium regulation by temperature-sensitive transient receptor potential channels in human uveal melanoma cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mergler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Derckx</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Reinach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Signal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conservation of functional and pharmacological properties in the distantly related temperature sensors TRVP1 and TRPM8</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Weil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Waite</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Randall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gunthorpe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="518" to="527" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TRPV channels in tumor growth and progression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Santoni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Farfariello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Amantini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv Exp Med Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">704</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="947" to="967" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Targeting TRP channels for pain relief</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Brederson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kym</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Szallasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">716</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The functions of TRPA1 and TRPV1: moving away from sensory nerves</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Fernandes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fernandes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Keeble</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">166</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="510" to="521" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TRP channels: targets for the relief of pain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Alessandri-Haber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim Biophys Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1772</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="989" to="1003" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oncogenic TRP channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Lehen'kyi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Prevarskaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv Exp Med Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">704</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="929" to="945" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advances in transient receptor potential vanilloid-2 channel expression and function in tumor growth and progression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Liberati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Morelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Amantini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Protein Pept Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="732" to="737" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TRPM8 ion channels differentially modulate proliferation and cell cycle distribution of normal and cancer prostate cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Valero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mello De Queiroz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Stuhmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Viana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pardo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e51825</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">3-Iodothyronamine increases transient receptor potential melastatin channel 8 (TRPM8) activity in immortalized human corneal epithelial cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lucius</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Khajavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Reinach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Signal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Altered calcium signaling in cancer cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Yapa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Monteith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim Biophys Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1848</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2502" to="2511" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Remodelling of Ca2þ transport in cancer: how it contributes to cancer hallmarks?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Prevarskaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ouadid-Ahidouch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Skryma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shuba</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">369</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 20130097</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subconjunctival bevacizumab injection for corneal neovascularization in recurrent pterygium</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Bahar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kaiserman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mcallum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rootman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Slomovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Eye Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Antiangiogenic therapy for pterygium recurrence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Leippi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Grehn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Geerling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>in German</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ophthalmologe</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="413" to="419" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inhibition of corneal neovascularization by topical bevacizumab (anti-VEGF) and sunitinib (anti-VEGF and anti-PDGF) in an animal model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Perez-Santonja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Campos-Mollo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lledo-Riquelme</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Javaloy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Alio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Ophthalmol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">150</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="519" to="528" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>e511</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative study of topical mitomycin C, cyclosporine, and bevacizumab after primary pterygium surgery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Korean J Ophthalmol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="375" to="381" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does topical bevacizumab prevent postoperative recurrence after pterygium surgery with conjunctival autografting?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Karalezli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kucukerdonmez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Akova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Koktekir</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Ophthalmol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="512" to="516" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Randomized controlled trial of subconjunctival bevacizumab injection in impending recurrent pterygium: a pilot study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lekhanont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Patarakittam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Thongphiew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Suwan-Apichon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hanutsaha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cornea</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="161" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subconjunctival bevacizumab for primary pterygium excision; a randomized clinical trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Razeghinejad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Banifatemi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Ophthalmic Vis Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bevacizumab in the treatment of pterygium: a meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Qiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Nie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cornea</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="160" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vascular endothelial growth factor gene polymorphism and protein expression in the pathogenesis of pterygium</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Tung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Ophthalmol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="556" to="561" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
