<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">CART neurons in the arcuate nucleus and lateral hypothalamic area exert differential controls on energy homeostasis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-11-08">8 November 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jackie</forename><surname>Lau</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Neuroscience Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Garvan Institute of Medical Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">St. Vincent&apos;s Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2010</postCode>
									<settlement>Darlinghurst, Sydney</settlement>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Aitak</forename><surname>Farzi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Neuroscience Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Garvan Institute of Medical Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">St. Vincent&apos;s Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2010</postCode>
									<settlement>Darlinghurst, Sydney</settlement>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yue</forename><surname>Qi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Neuroscience Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Garvan Institute of Medical Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">St. Vincent&apos;s Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2010</postCode>
									<settlement>Darlinghurst, Sydney</settlement>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Regine</forename><surname>Heilbronn</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Virology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Corporate Member of Freie Universität Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Berlin Institute of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Benjamin Franklin</addrLine>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mario</forename><surname>Mietzsch</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Virology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Corporate Member of Freie Universität Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Berlin Institute of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Benjamin Franklin</addrLine>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yan-Chuan</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
							<email>y.shi@garvan.org.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Neuroscience Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Garvan Institute of Medical Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">St. Vincent&apos;s Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2010</postCode>
									<settlement>Darlinghurst, Sydney</settlement>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Herbert</forename><surname>Herzog</surname></persName>
							<email>h.herzog@garvan.org.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Neuroscience Division</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Garvan Institute of Medical Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">St. Vincent&apos;s Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>2010</postCode>
									<settlement>Darlinghurst, Sydney</settlement>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Experimental and Clinical Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Medical University of Graz</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Graz</settlement>
									<country key="AT">AUSTRIA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biochemistry &amp; Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Structural Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">The McKnight Brain Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Florida</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>32610</postCode>
									<settlement>Gainesville</settlement>
									<region>FL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">CART neurons in the arcuate nucleus and lateral hypothalamic area exert differential controls on energy homeostasis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2017-11-08">8 November 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">24960F0EA2D34DFEDB0A97BE63BC7C1B</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.molmet.2017.10.015</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received October 10, 2017 Revision received October 27, 2017 Accepted October 30, 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Objective: The cocaine-and amphetamine-regulated transcript (CART) codes for a pivotal neuropeptide important in the control of appetite and energy homeostasis.</s><s>However, limited understanding exists for the defined effector sites underlying CART function, as discrepant effects of central CART administration have been reported.</s><s>Methods: By combining Cart-cre knock-in mice with a Cart adeno-associated viral vector designed using the flip-excision switch (AAV-FLEX) technology, specific reintroduction or overexpression of CART selectively in CART neurons in the arcuate nucleus (Arc) and lateral hypothalamic area (LHA), respectively, was achieved.</s><s>The effects on energy homeostasis control were investigated.</s></p><p><s>Results: Here we show that CART neuron-specific reintroduction of CART into the Arc and LHA leads to distinct effects on energy homeostasis control.</s><s>Specifically, CART reintroduction into the Arc of otherwise CART-deficient Cart cre/cre mice markedly decreased fat mass and body weight, whereas CART reintroduction into the LHA caused significant fat mass gain and lean mass loss, but overall unaltered body weight.</s><s>The reduced adiposity in Arc CART ;Cart cre/cre mice was associated with an increase in both energy expenditure and physical activity, along with significantly decreased Npy mRNA levels in the Arc but with no change in food consumption.</s><s>Distinctively, the elevated fat mass in LHA CART ;Cart cre/cre mice was accompanied by diminished insulin responsiveness and glucose tolerance, greater spontaneous food intake, and reduced energy expenditure, which is consistent with the observed decrease of brown adipose tissue temperature.</s><s>This is also in line with significantly reduced tyrosine hydroxylase (Th) and notably increased corticotropin-releasing hormone (Crh) mRNA expressions in the paraventricular nucleus (PVN).</s><s>Conclusions: Taken together, these results identify catabolic and anabolic effects of CART in the Arc and LHA, respectively, demonstrating for the first time the distinct and region-specific functions of CART in controlling feeding and energy homeostasis.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">INTRODUCTION</head><p><s>The cocaine-and amphetamine-regulated transcript (CART) is a major neuropeptide involved in the regulation of diverse biological processes, including appetite control, maintenance of body weight, reward and addiction, psychostimulant effects, and neuroendocrine functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>Among the wide and abundant central distribution of the peptide associated with multiple neurocircuitries in mammals [2e4], CART expression shows predominance in neuroendocrine neurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, particularly in the hypothalamus at feeding-related regions <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>.</s><s>Extensive research has focused on the role of CART in modulating feeding behavior and energy homeostasis <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, thereby exploring therapeutic potentials in the treatment of obesity and other metabolic disorders.</s><s>However, identification of the hypothalamic sites of action and the mechanisms underlying CART function in homeostatic regulation remains challenging, mainly owing to the lack of information on the elusive CART receptor(s) that remain(s) unidentified <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>In addition to the ubiquitous expression and broad connection of the peptide with various neuronal networks, the biosynthesis of CART involves complex post-translational processing, including the formation of various disulfide bonds <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>, further rendering pharmacological intervention using any synthetic ex-vivo produced CART analogs difficult.</s></p><p><s>The functional importance of CART is highlighted by the strong evolutionary conservation across species <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>.</s><s>Moreover, CART expression patterns are very similar between rodents and human, with high density of expression in hypothalamic areas important for energy homeostasis regulation, including the arcuate nucleus (Arc), lateral hypothalamic area (LHA), paraventricular nucleus (PVN), and dorsomedial hypothalamic nucleus <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>.</s><s>However, studies of CART primarily conducted in rodents have so far generated inconclusive or discrepant results <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, highlighting the complexity in the physiology of endogenous CART biosynthesis and function.</s><s>In rats and mice, in addition to alternative splicing of Cart mRNA on the transcription level, the resultant CART propeptides harbor several cleavage sites that are subjected to post-translational processing by prohormone convertases, which exhibit tissue-and brain region-specific expressions and functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>.</s><s>Hence, the in vivo production of several CART isoforms also involves processing and expression in a tissue-and sitespecific manner <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>, generating at least two predicted active CART peptides, CART I (42-89/55-102) and CART II (49-89/62-102) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref>.</s><s>Accordingly, studies in rodents have suggested the differential physiological functions of CART variants across the periphery as well as the central nervous system <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s><s>In light of the multiple factors involving complex region-specific posttranslational processing, along with undetermined conformational profile and binding sites for the peptide, studies are challenged with limited targeting contacts to mimic or modulate endogenous CART expression and activity.</s><s>Although most traditional studies have classified CART as anorexigenic [14e16], orexigenic evidences also exist <ref type="bibr">[17e19]</ref>.</s><s>In mouse models, global CART knockout led to an overall increase in body weight gain and adiposity, while lacking any overt impact on food consumption <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20]</ref>.</s><s>Supporting the catabolic property of CART, mutations and polymorphisms in the human CART gene are linked to obesity and associated metabolic disorders <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>.</s><s>On the other hand, while intracerebroventricular (i.c.v.) administration of various CART isoforms in rodents consistently and dose-dependently suppressed food intake and weight gain <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23]</ref>, overexpression of CART I (55-102) in specific hypothalamic nuclei was shown to induce either stimulatory or inhibitory response on feeding and body weight <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24]</ref>.</s><s>This suggests that CART originating from different nuclei is engaged in differential functions involving discrete neurocircuitries.</s><s>Furthermore, central administrations of different CART variants, which demonstrate varying endogenous abundance in distinct brain regions, have exhibited site-specific activities and differential potencies in affecting food intake and body weight gain <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26]</ref>.</s><s>In an effort to identify the most critical hypothalamic sites of CART action in the control of energy homeostasis, the Arc and LHA have received considerable interest.</s><s>The Arc represents a pivotal structure for adiposity signal integration and metabolic modulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, where CART expression is enriched and colocalized with the anorexigenic proopiomelanocortin (POMC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29]</ref>.</s><s>The first-order CART-containing neurons at the Arc launch axonal projections to neurons at the LHA and <ref type="bibr">PVN [30e32]</ref>.</s><s>Despite implications for the Arc-LHA pathway in mediating the anorexic effects of CART <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31]</ref>, direct injection of CART into the Arc or LHA in rodents triggered overt orexigenic responses <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24]</ref>.</s><s>Differential neurochemical responses were also shown at the two regions.</s><s>For instance, while Cart mRNA levels at the Arc are markedly reduced by fasting and restored following refeeding <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34]</ref>, such correlation was not demonstrated at the LHA <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[35]</ref>.</s><s>Moreover, CART in the LHA is found to be colocalized with the orexigenic-acting melanin-concentrating hormone (MCH) <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37]</ref>, further hinting that CART in different hypothalamic areas and neurons may exhibit disparate functions.</s></p><p><s>In this study, we aimed to more specifically investigate the effects of CART in the Arc and LHA on the regulation of feeding and energy homeostasis.</s><s>For this, we developed models that allow the CART neuron-specific introduction and processing of CART by combining Cart-cre knock-in mice with a Cart adeno-associated viral vector designed using the flip-excision switch (AAV-FLEX) technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>.</s><s>The AAV vector encodes the long form of the mouse Cart cDNA CART I (55-102), which is focused herein due to wider documentation and the reported higher potency in influencing appetite and body weight compared to the CART II (62-102) isoform <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39]</ref>.</s><s>This approach allows for either reintroducing CART specifically into CART neurons in otherwise CART-deficient mice, or to overproducing CART in Arc or LHA CART neurons, avoiding off-target side-effects associated with simple ectopic delivery.</s><s>Furthermore, our viral approach also facilitates the in vivo processing and modifications of CART propeptides in a natural physiological environment, hence producing active peptides under endogenous conditions.</s><s>Mouse models generated this way were then analyzed in a comprehensive phenotyping paradigm, determining all major aspects that are involved in energy homeostasis control.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">MATERIALS AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Animals</head><p><s>All research and animal care procedures were approved by the Garvan Institute/St.</s><s>Vincent's Hospital Animal Ethics Committee and were conducted in agreement with the Australian Code of Practice for the Care and Use of Animals for Scientific Purposes.</s><s>Male mice were used for all experiments and were housed under conditions of controlled temperature <ref type="bibr">(22 C</ref>) and illumination (12:12 h lightedark cycle, lights on at 07:00 am).</s><s>Mice were provided with ad libitum access to water and standard chow diet (8% calories from fat, 21% calories from protein, 71% calories from carbohydrate, 2.6 kcal/g; Gordon's Specialty Stock Feeds, Yanderra, NSW, Australia).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Generation of inducible Cart-cre knock-in mouse model</head><p><s>To investigate the effects of CART action at particular hypothalamic regions, CART neuron-specific introduction of genetic elements was performed in an adult-onset inducible manner.</s><s>This is enabled through the use of a conditional Cart-cre knock-in mouse line, for which the detailed generating procedures were described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>.</s><s>As illustrated <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>, the inducible Cart-cre knock-in mice (Cart cre/cre ) were generated by crossing the Cart lox/lox line with mice that expressed Crerecombinase specifically in the oocytes to homozygosity, hence combining the tamoxifen-inducible Cre gene with the endogenous Cart promoter.</s><s>In this study, both the homozygous Cart cre/cre and the heterozygous Cart cre/þ mouse lines were included.</s><s>Comparison between the two groups serves to highlight the contribution of CART function in specific hypothalamic nuclei to feeding and metabolic regulation in the presence or absence of endogenous CART signaling.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Generation and expression of cre-inducible AAV-FLEX-Cart vector</head><p><s>To selectively express the bioactive CART in CART neurons, the flipexcision switch technique was employed to create a unique Crerecombinase-dependent AAV vector for delivery, which carries a double floxed inverted open reading frame (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>The FLEX strategy utilizes the recombination mechanism whereby DNA elements flanked by loxP recombination sites in the opposite orientation are inverted by Cre-recombinase <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref>.</s><s>The AAV-FLEX-Cart vector consists of a codon-optimized mouse Cart cDNA for the expression of CART I (55-102) active peptide flanked by loxP-sites as displayed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Gene expression is driven by the chicken b-actin (CBA) promoter on a self-complementary AAV vector backbone packaged in AAV capsids of serotype 1. AAV vectors are produced by plasmid cotransfection of HEK293 cells, benzonase-treatment of cell extracts and purification by high-performance liquid chromatography using AVB-Sepharose columns, as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[40]</ref>.</s><s>Within this AAV-FLEX-Cart vector, the Cart coding sequence is flanked by a set of two distinct loxP sites positioned in the opposite orientation to each other (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1Ai</ref>), where recombination only occurs between the same type of loxP sequences.</s><s>The Cart coding unit was placed in a reverse thus inactive orientation downstream of the CBA promoter, preventing expression prior to Cre-driven recombination.</s><s>Upon exposure to tamoxifen, Cre-recombinase is activated through translocation from the cytoplasm to the nucleus, thereby catalyzing the inversion of the loxP-flanked cassette in two possible ways (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1Aii</ref>).</s><s>Subsequent recombination between the same type of loxP sites placed in the same orientation would eliminate the alternative loxP site in-between, thereby generating the stable transgene with the Cart sequence in the correct orientation for further transcription and translation (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1Aiii</ref>).</s><s>In parallel, AAV-FLEX-GFP encoding the green fluorescence protein (GFP) was used as the control.</s><s>As Cre expression is driven by the endogenous Cart promoter in the Cart-cre knock-in mice, the AAV-FLEX-Cart vector and the AAV-FLEX-GFP control are targeted only to CART neurons.</s><s>Hence, production of the active form of CART or GFP is exclusive to CART neurons.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Stereotaxic delivery of AAV-FLEX-Cart to CART neurons in</head><p><s>Cart-cre knock-in mice Adult-onset central CART neuron-specific expression of CART I (55-102) in the Arc or LHA was achieved by intra-hypothalamic injection of the AAV-FLEX-Cart vector in parallel with i.c.v.</s><s>tamoxifen administration in Cart-cre knock-in mice.</s><s>At 11 weeks of age, Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice were anesthetized with intraperitoneal (i.p.) injection of 100/ 20 mg/kg ketamine/xylazine (Parke Davis-Pfizer, Sydney, Australia &amp; Bayer AG, Leverkusen, Germany) and immobilized in a stereotaxic frame (David Kopf Instruments, Tulunga, CA, USA) in the flat-skull position.</s><s>A small incision was made to expose the skull, where a small hole was opened for injection.</s><s>One microliter of the AAV-FLEX-Cart vector (titer 1.0 Â 10 12 viral particles/ml) or the AAV-FLEX-GFP control vector was injected unilaterally into the Arc or LHA at a speed of 0.1 ml/min using a 2-mL Hamilton syringe connected to a syringe infusion pump (World Precision Instruments Inc., Waltham, MA, USA).</s><s>The AAV-FLEX-Cart or AAV-FLEX-GFP was stereotaxically delivered into both Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice, such that mice from each genotype were separated into two groups, one injected at the right Arc (coordinates relative to Bregma: À2.18 mm anteroposterior, À0.25 mm mediolateral, and À5.5 mm dorsoventral), and the other injected at the right LHA (coordinates relative to Bregma: À1.94 mm anteroposterior, À1.0 mm mediolateral, and À5.25 mm dorsoventral).</s><s>Mice from each of the four groups were further divided evenly into two groups based on body weight and fat mass, one receiving the AAV-FLEX-Cart injection and the other littermate group injected with the AAV-FLEX-GFP control.</s><s>The injection needle was gently withdrawn 15 min after injection.</s><s>To activate the Cre-recombinase for mediating the transgene inversion and expression, 1 ml of the active metabolite of tamoxifen 4-OHT <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref> (20 mg/mL) (SigmaeAldrich Pty Ltd, Sydney, NSW, Australia) dissolved in absolute ethanol was then injected unilaterally into the left lateral cerebral ventricle (LV) at a rate of 0.1 ml/min using a 2-ml Hamilton syringe (World Precision Instruments Inc.).</s><s>The injection coordinates relative to Bregma were À0.34 mm anteroposterior, þ1.0 mm mediolateral, and À2.5 mm dorsoventral corresponding to the left LV <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref>.</s><s>Body temperature of the animals was maintained by placement on a heating pad throughout the surgical process and the overnight recovery period.</s><s>Mice were allowed two weeks of recovery with regular body weight assessment prior to any phenotypic characterization procedures.</s><s>According to previous experience from extensive central viral delivery experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref>, maximal expression of the transgene is estimated to be reached within two weeks and remain stable for at least 6 months.</s><s>The conditional tamoxifen-induced Cre activation and concomitant intranuclear delivery of AAV-FLEX-Cart or AAV-FLEX-GFP in the hypothalamus resulted in Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice with CART or GFP selectively expressed in CART neurons at the Arc or LHA.</s><s>For simplicity, the post-surgery subjects are referred to as Arc CART or Arc GFP ;Cart cre/cre or Cart cre/þ , and LHA CART or LHA GFP ;Cart cre/cre or Cart cre/þ mice.</s><s>At least 10 mice were included for each of the resultant 8 groups, with n ¼ 10e12 for each site of injection with either CART or GFP for each genotype.</s><s>For each targeted area and each genotype, at least two cohorts of animals were used, each cohort consisting of AAV-FLEX-Cart-injected mice run in parallel with AAV-FLEX-GFP-injected mice from the same litter.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.">Verification of the expression site of targeted AAV-FLEX-Cart by in situ hybridization and immunohistochemistry</head><p><s>To validate the injection sites at the hypothalamic Arc or LHA regions where CART was introduced to CART neurons, and to verify functionality of the AAV-FLEX-Cart construct, in situ hybridization and immunostaining for CART mRNA and protein expression were examined in brains collected from Cart-cre knock-in mice.</s><s>At the transcriptional level, efficiency of Cart reintroduction or overexpression was validated by in situ hybridization for Cart mRNA on brain cryosections from both the Arc CART/GFP and LHA CART/GFP Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice (n ¼ 5 each) following procedures as described above.</s><s>For the detection of CART-containing cells receiving AAV-FLEX-Cart delivery at the translational level, CART peptide expression was assessed by immunohistochemistry as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43]</ref>.</s><s>At the completion of study, a separate group of mice was anesthetized with i.p. injection of 100/20 mg/kg ketamine/xylazine (Parke Davis-Pfizer) and sacrificed via transcardial perfusion.</s><s>The brains were subsequently fixed by perfusion and subjected to post-fixing and cryoprotection.</s><s>Coronal brain slices (30 mm) from both the Arc CART and LHA CART Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice (n ! 5 each) were serially cryosectioned and incubated overnight with rabbit anti-mouse CART polyclonal primary antibody Ca7-OVA <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> (gift from Dr. Anna Secher, Novo Nordisk, Copenhagen, Denmark) diluted 1:1500.</s><s>Sections were then incubated with biotinylated goat anti-rabbit IgG secondary antibody (Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA, USA) diluted 1:250 for 2 h, followed by incubation with ExtrAvidin-peroxidase (SigmaeAldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA).</s><s>Immunostaining for CART expression was performed using diaminobenzidine (Dako, Carpinteria, CA, USA) as the chromogen.</s><s>Free-floating brain sections were mounted on SuperfrostÒ glass slides (Menzel-Glaser, Braunschweig, Germany) and coverslipped.</s><s>For visualization of CART immunoreactivity (IR), brain sections containing the targeted Arc or LHA regions from respective mice were investigated using a Zeiss Axiophot microscope equipped with a ProgRes 3008 digital camera (Carl Zeiss, Jena, Germany).</s><s>Bright field photomicrographs were acquired for the targeted hypothalamic regions on both the injection and contralateral sides of the brain for comparison.</s><s>An increase in CART-IR on the injection side relative to the contralateral side therefore signifies the presence of AAV-delivered   CART-expressing CART neurons that are accurately targeted and functional.</s><s>In parallel, brain sections from a portion of the Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice with AAV-FLEX-GFP targeted into the Arc or LHA (n ¼ 3 each) were prepared as described above and mounted on SuperfrostÒ slides for the detection of GFP expression by direct fluorescence microscopy.</s><s>To detect GFP expression produced by the control targeting construct, brain sections containing the targeted Arc or LHA regions from respective mice were examined using a Leica DM5500 B fluorescent microscope (Leica, Chicago, IL, USA).</s><s>Fluorescence micrographs were acquired for the visualization of GFP, indicative of successful delivery and expression of the empty control vector in CART neurons at the respective areas.</s></p><p><s>2.6.</s><s>Determination of food intake and body weight All Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice were fed a standard laboratory chow and subjected to the same experimental procedures as follows.</s><s>Body weight was measured weekly throughout the duration of studies.</s><s>Following a two-week recovery period after the brain surgery, all mice were at 13e14 weeks of age.</s><s>Mice were assessed for spontaneous food intake in the fed state as well as for fasting-induced food intake in response to 24-hr fasting.</s><s>Basal daily food intake was determined as the average of duplicate readings obtained over two consecutive 24-hr periods.</s><s>Twenty four-hr fasting-induced food intake was subsequently measured at 1, 3, 7, and 24 h after refeeding, while the corresponding body weight was recorded in parallel.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7.">Indirect calorimetry of energy expenditure and assessment of physical activity</head><p><s>All Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice with Arc CART or LHA CART together with the controls Arc GFP or LHA GFP (n ¼ 10 -12 per group) were evaluated for metabolic parameters and physical activity at 16e17 weeks of age.</s><s>For energy metabolism, metabolic rate was measured by indirect calorimetry using an 8-chamber open-circuit calorimeter (Oxymax series; Columbus Instruments, Columbus, OH, USA).</s><s>For each 24-hr run, 4 mice targeted with AAV-Cart in a specific region were matched with 4 control mice of the same genotype with AAV-GFP in the same region.</s><s>Hence, with n ¼ 10e12 per group, three runs were involved for AAV-Cart mice in parallel with AAV-GFP mice for each targeted area for each genotype.</s><s>Mice were housed individually in specially built Plexiglas cages with airflow of 0.6 L/min at a consistent ambient temperature of 22 C, following standard protocol as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref>.</s><s>Oxygen consumption (VO 2 ) and carbon dioxide production (VCO 2 ) were measured every 27-min intervals.</s><s>The respiratory exchange ratio (RER) was calculated as the quotient of VCO 2 /VO 2 , with 100% carbohydrate oxidation represented by the value of 1.0 and 100% fat oxidation the value of 0.7.</s><s>Energy expenditure (kcal heat produced) was determined as calorific value (CV) Â VO 2 , where CV is 3.815 þ 1.232 Â RER.</s><s>Data obtained for the 24-hr monitoring period were averaged at 1-hr intervals for energy expenditure and RER.</s><s>For physical activity, ambulatory activity of the mice was assessed in parallel within the Plexiglas metabolic chambers with an OPTO-M3 sensor system (Columbus Instruments).</s><s>Ambulatory counts denote the consecutive adjacent photo-beam breaks, while cumulative ambulatory counts of the X, Y and Z directions were recorded per minute and summed at 1-hr intervals.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.8.">Body composition and bone densitometry analysis</head><p><s>All mice from both Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ groups were subjected to body composition analysis using the dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA, Lunar PIXImus2 mouse densitometer; GE Healthcare, Waukesha, WI, USA) system at 16e17 weeks of age, immediately following completion of the indirect calorimetry assessment of energy metabolism and physical activity.</s><s>Animals were anesthetized with isoflurane for the scanning procedure to determine whole body bone mineral density (BMD), bone mineral content (BMC), fat and lean mass, where lean mass corresponds to non-fat and non-bone tissue content.</s><s>The head of the animal was excluded while the tail included for the analysis.</s></p><p><s>2.9.</s><s>Measurement of whole body and brown adipose tissue temperatures by infrared imaging Whole body temperature and temperature of the interscapular brown adipose tissue (IBAT) were measured for both the Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ cohorts by non-invasive high-sensitivity infrared imaging as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>.</s><s>Briefly, all 17-week-old mice were transferred from group housing to individual cages for acclimatization 2 days prior to imaging procedures.</s><s>For area-specific exposure of skin to facilitate temperature reading, all mice were shaved at the IBAT and lumbar back regions under light isoflurane anesthesia in parallel.</s><s>A high-sensitivity infrared camera (ThermoCAM T640, FLIR, Danderyd, Sweden, sensitivity ¼ 0.04 C) fixed on a tripod was placed 100 cm above the freely moving singly housed mouse, and thermographic images were taken for 1 min per mouse.</s><s>After each 1-min measurement, the camera was moved to record surface temperatures of the next mouse.</s><s>Temperature measurement was performed daily for three consecutive days.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.10.">Glucose metabolism studies</head><p><s>All mice from both Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ cohorts were examined by intraperitoneal glucose tolerance test (IPGTT) and insulin tolerance test (IPITT).</s><s>IPGTT and IPITT were conducted at 15 and 18 weeks of age, respectively.</s><s>For IPGTT, mice were subjected to 6-hr fasting; food was removed from cage hoppers at 09:00 h and injection of a dose of a 10% D-glucose solution (1.0 g/kg body weight; Astra Zeneca, North Ryde, NSW, Australia) was performed 6 h later into the peritoneal cavity.</s><s>For IPITT, mice were subjected to 5-hr fasting where food was removed from cage hoppers at 10:00 h and injection of a dose of insulin (0.5 IU/kg body weight) (Novo Nordisk Pharmaceuticals, Baulkham Hills, NSW, Australia) was performed 5 h later into the peritoneal cavity.</s><s>For both tests, tail vein blood was collected at 0, 15, 30, 60, and 90 min following glucose or insulin injection, and glucose concentrations were measured using a glucometer (Accu-Check II; Roche, Castle Hill, NSW, Australia).</s><s>For IPGTT, insulin levels were subsequently quantified using a sensitive rat insulin radioimmunoassay (RIA) kit (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA).</s><s>Glucose and insulin tolerance curves constructed for the glucose levels obtained during IPGTT and IPITT respectively are presented in terms of absolute values.</s><s>Area under the glucose (AUCglucose) or insulin (AUCinsulin) concentration curves between 0 and 90 min after glucose injection during IPGTT were plotted after subtraction of the initial concentrations prior to injection.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.11.">Tissue collection</head><p><s>Following completion of studies, all mice from both Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ groups were sacrificed at 19 weeks of age.</s><s>Animals were culled between 13:00 to 17:00 h through cervical dislocation followed by decapitation.</s><s>Brains were promptly collected and frozen on dry ice, then stored at e80 C until subsequent analysis as described below.</s><s>The brown adipose tissue (BAT) at the interscapular area and the white adipose tissue (WAT) depots from the inguinal, epididymal, retroperitoneal and mesenteric regions were removed and weighed.</s><s>Major organs including the pancreas, liver, gonads, heart, kidney, seminal vesicles, and spleen were also removed and weighed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.12.">In situ hybridization analysis of key hypothalamic neuropeptides</head><p><s>In situ hybridization was performed on brain sections of Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice from both the Arc CART/GFP and LHA CART/GFP groups (n ¼ 5 each) to determine mRNA expression of Cart, Pomc, neuropeptide Y (Npy), corticotropin-releasing hormone (Crh), Mch, orexin (Orx), tyrosine hydroxylase (Th), and thyrotropin-releasing hormone (Trh) at the hypothalamus following procedures as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Briefly, matching coronal brain sections (25 mm) collected from the Cart-cre knock-in mice were prepared from specific brain levels with respect to the Bregma to represent the hypothalamic areas involved in the regulation of energy homeostasis.</s><s>Detection of the mRNA expression was performed for Cart in the Arc and LHA, for Npy and Pomc in the Arc, for Mch and Orx in the LHA, and for Crh, Th, and Trh in the PVN.</s><s>The cryosections were hybridized with [a- 35 S]-thio-dATP (PerkinElmer, Boston, MA, USA) radiolabeled DNA oligonucleotides complementary to mouse Cart: (5 0 -TCCTTCTCGTGGGACGCATCATC-CACGGCAGAGTAGATGTCC AGG-3 0 ), Pomc: (5 0 -TGGCTGCTCTCCAGG-CACCAGCTCCACACATCTATG GAGG-3 0 ), Npy: (5 0 -GAGGGTCAGTCCACA CAGCCCCATTCGCTTG TTACCTA GCAT-3 0 ), Crh: (5 0 -CCGATAATCTC CATCAGTTTCCTGTTGCTGTGAGC TTGCTGAGCT-3 0 ), Mch: (5 0 -TTTCCTG TGTGGACTCAGCATTCTGAACTCCAT TCTCAGCTGG-3 0 ), Orx: (5 0 -CTTTCCCAGAGTCAGGATACCCGCAGCGTGGT TGCCAGCTCCGTGC-3 0 ), Th: (5 0 -CTCTAAGGAGCGCCGGATGGTGTGAGGA CTGTCCAGTACATCA-3 0 ) and Trh: (5 0 -AACCTTACTCCTCCAGAGGTTCCCT GACCCAGGCTTC-CAGTTGTG-3 0 ).</s><s>Hybridization signals on sections were visualized by exposure to BioMax MR film (Kodak, Rochester, NY, USA) for 7e10 days and digitalized images from the scanned autoradiograms were acquired.</s><s>For structural details, the brain sections were photoemulsion-dipped and superficially counterstained with hematoxylin, with which regions of interest were visualized and captured into digital images acquired by bright-field microscopy.</s><s>Quantification of the mRNA expression levels of respective genes was performed by measuring the relative optical densities (RODs) within the brain areas of interest outlined with consistent defined dimensions across corresponding sections on the photomicrographs using the National Institutes of Health ImageJ 1.61 software (written by Wayne Rasband; available at https://imagej.nih.gov/ij/).</s><s>Background labeling was considered uniform with signal levels below 5% of specific signal levels and was subtracted from the resultant signal density.</s><s>Data are evaluated and presented as percentage of ROD averaged from at least three sections per mRNA assessed per animal.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.13.">Statistical analysis</head><p><s>All data are presented as means AE SEM.</s><s>Differences among mouse groups of various genotypes and viral treatments were assessed by ANOVA or repeated-measures ANOVA combined with Bonferroni posthoc analysis where appropriate.</s><s>Energy expenditure, RER, and physical activity over the continuous 24-hr period were averaged for the whole 24-hr period, as well as the 12-hr light and dark phases individually.</s><s>Comparison of energy expenditure (kcal/hr) between groups was performed by the analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) with lean mass as the covariate.</s><s>The adjusted means of energy expenditure at a common lean mass for the comparison were generated by ANCOVA as presented.</s><s>Statistical analyses were performed with GraphPad Prism 7 for Mac OS X (GraphPad Software, Inc. CA, USA).</s><s>Statistical significance was defined as p-value 0.05.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Generation of hypothalamic CART neuron-specific reintroducing or overexpressing CART mouse models</head><p><s>To investigate the role of CART in the Arc and LHA, we employed our inducible Cart-cre knock-in lines selectively injected with AAV1-FLEX-CART vectors into these two brain areas.</s><s>Specifically we used heterozygous Cart cre/þ mice, which allow for the CART neuron-specific overexpression of CART, as well as homozygous Cart cre/cre mice with global CART ablation, thus allowing for the CART neuron-specific reintroduction of CART on an otherwise CART-deficient background <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>To demonstrate the precise delivery of the construct to the targeted brain regions, we first employed the GFP reporter for visual guidance.</s><s>Two weeks after AAV-FLEX-GFP injection, GFP expression was detected exclusively in either the Arc (Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B and S1A</ref>) or LHA (Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C and  S1B</ref>), as shown in the representative photomicrographs, validating accurate targeting of the viral vectors.</s><s>Next, to verify targeted expression and functionality of the unilaterally injected AAV-FLEX-Cart construct, which was activated through i.c.v.</s><s>tamoxifen treatment, CART neuronspecific introduction of CART expression was determined on both the transcriptional and translational levels.</s><s>Successful Cart reintroduction was confirmed by in situ hybridization in both the Arc (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1DeE</ref>) and LHA (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1FeG</ref>) of Cart cre/cre mice, where Cart mRNA expression was only observed in mice receiving AAV-FLEX-Cart while absent in control groups treated with AAV-FLEX-GFP.</s><s>In parallel, Cart cre/þ mice subjected to Arc (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1DeE</ref>) or LHA (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1FeG</ref>) CART AAV overexpression displayed significantly upregulated Cart mRNA expression in the corresponding areas compared to the respective AAV-FLEX-GFP controls of the same genotype.</s><s>Immunostaining for CART protein expression further confirmed the exclusive CART-IR shown on the injection side, but not on the contralateral control side, for both the Arc (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2A</ref>) and LHA (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2B</ref>) regions in Cart cre/cre mice receiving AAV-Cart unilaterally.</s><s>CART immunostaining at the respective local sites of delivery (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2AeB</ref>) displayed a pattern that is consistent with endogenous CART-containing neurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref>, signifying selective CART reintroduction in CART neurons only.</s><s>In contrast, lack of CART-IR on the contralateral sides (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2AeB</ref>) denotes the regional and CART neuron-specific targeting, with minimal diffusion to other areas in the brain.</s><s>No CART-IR was detected on matching sections from Arc GFP or LHA GFP ;Cart cre/cre controls (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2AeB</ref>).</s><s>Similarly, notably higher CART-IR was shown on the injection compared to the contralateral side for both the Arc (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2A</ref>) and LHA (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2B</ref>) in Cart cre/þ mice treated with AAV-CART.</s><s>Such difference was not observed in Cart cre/þ counterparts receiving Arc GFP (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2A</ref>) or LHA GFP control constructs (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">2B</ref>).</s><s>The visual guidance from CART expression further verified the correct stereotaxic injection for both Arc and LHA groups, while only data from mice identified for positive hits were used for downstream analysis.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Selective reintroduction of CART in CART neurons in the arc but not the LHA reduces body weight</head><p><s>To investigate the basic metabolic characteristics of Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice re-introduced with or overexpressing CART in the (Arc CART ) or (LHA CART ), male mice at the age of 11 weeks were unilaterally injected with AAV-FLEX-Cart or AAV-FLEX-GFP into the Arc or LHA, respectively, and body weight and other metabolic parameters were measured following the targeted brain surgery.</s><s>In Cart cre/þ mice with endogenous CART expression in place, CART overexpression targeted at either the Arc (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3A</ref>) or LHA (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3B</ref>) had no obvious effect on body weight compared with respective controls injected with the AAV-GFP control construct.</s><s>The lack of difference was seen for both absolute body weight as well as weight gain expressed as a percentage of initial body weight (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3AeB</ref>).</s><s>In contrast, in Cart cre/cre mice without endogenous CART expression, CART reintroduction into the Arc CART neurons led to a significant decrease in both absolute body weight and percentage weight gain compared to AAV-GFP controls over the entire study period (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3C</ref>).</s><s>On the contrary, no significant effect on body weight was seen after CART was reintroduced into the LHA of Cart cre/cre mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3D</ref>).</s><s>These results suggest that CART action originating from the Arc but not  the LHA is responsible for the establishment of a negative energy balance that is leading to a body weight loss.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">CART neuron-specific rescue of CART expression in the arc and LHA leads to opposite effects on adiposity</head><p><s>To elucidate the factors contributing to the differential responses in body weight to CART delivery, body composition analysis was performed.</s><s>In line with the markedly lower body weight (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3C</ref>), Cart cre/cre mice expressing Arc CART demonstrated a significant decrease in whole body fat mass compared with Arc GFP controls (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4A</ref>), as confirmed by the significantly reduced mass of dissected white adipose tissue depots (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4B</ref>).</s><s>Interestingly, whole body lean mass was unaltered following Arc CART reintroduction (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4C</ref>).</s><s>In contrast, despite similar body weight, Cart cre/cre mice with CART rescue in the LHA exhibited a significant increase in whole body fat mass (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4D</ref>) compared to the AAV-GFP controls, consistent with the markedly higher dissected fat weights (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4E</ref>).</s><s>Unlike the Arc CART reintroduction, rescue of CART in the LHA was accompanied by a significant reduction in lean mass relative to LHA GFP counterparts (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4F</ref>).</s><s>The lower lean mass may have offset the greater fat mass (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4DeE</ref>), leading to the unvaried absolute body weight observed (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3D</ref>).</s><s>It is therefore possible, while not directly involved in weight regulation, LHA CART reintroduced on an otherwise CART-negative genetic background may modulate body composition by increasing adiposity and decreasing lean body mass.</s><s>No apparent difference was seen in the weights of major organs between genotypes in either brain area (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S2 A-B</ref>).</s><s>Interestingly, investigation of Cart cre/þ mice subjected to CART overexpression in either the Arc or the LHA, which showed unaltered body weight (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3AeB</ref>), also revealed unchanged adiposity (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S2 C-F</ref>) and lean mass (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S2 G-H</ref>) compared to AAV-GFP controls.</s><s>As part of the body composition analysis, and based on the known link between CART and bone remodeling <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46]</ref>, effects of chronic CART introduction specifically into CART neurons in the Arc or LHA on bone parameters were also examined.</s><s>Interestingly, neither introduction of CART into the Arc or LHA had any significant effect on both whole body BMD and BMC for either Cart cre/cre (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S3 A-D</ref>) or Cart cre/þ (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S3 E-H</ref>) mice.</s><s>The unchanged bone mass phenotype suggests that CART neurons in these two hypothalamic regions are not directly involved in bone homeostatic control, while CART in other brain areas may be responsible for the regulation of bone metabolism.</s></p><p><s>3.4.</s><s>CART reintroduction in the arc and LHA led to differential effects on food intake and energy expenditure In order to determine which side of the energy balance equation is responsible for the altered body weight and body composition caused by the selective CART reintroduction into Arc or LHA CART neurons, we next measured spontaneous and fasting-induced food intake in Cart cre/cre mice.</s><s>Spontaneous daily food intake under fed conditions was unchanged between Arc CART and Arc GFP groups (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5A</ref>), excluding food intake alteration as a significant contributing factor to the marked decrease in body weight gain seen in Arc CART ;Cart cre/cre mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3C</ref>).</s><s>In contrast, despite unaltered body weight in Cart cre/cre mice expressing LHA CART (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3D</ref>), a trend towards higher spontaneous food intake was seen compared with LHA GFP controls (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5B</ref>), which is consistent with the significantly elevated fat mass seen in these mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4DeE</ref>).</s><s>Food intake in response to 24-hr fasting was unaffected by replenishing CART expression in Cart cre/cre mice at either the Arc (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S4 A</ref>) or LHA (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S4 B</ref>).</s><s>However, despite similar weight loss from the 24-hr fasting, Arc CART mice experienced an accelerated weight regain during refeeding compared to Arc GFP controls (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S4 C</ref>).</s><s>No significant difference in body weight loss and subsequent recovery was seen in the LHA CART mice (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S4 D</ref>).</s><s>To also investigate the other component of the energy balance equation -energy expenditure, open-circuit indirect calorimetry was employed.</s><s>Interestingly, a marked increase in energy expenditure was demonstrated in Arc CART compared to Arc GFP Cart cre/cre mice, both overall and specifically during the light phase (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5C</ref>).</s><s>The elevated energy expenditure may contribute at least in part to the substantial drop in fat mass (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4AeB</ref>) and body weight (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3C</ref>) observed.</s><s>On the other hand, LHA CART mice showed a significant reduction in energy expenditure compared to LHA GFP controls throughout the entire light cycle (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5D</ref>).</s><s>This reduction in heat dissipation, together with greater food intake (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5B</ref>), may account for the increased fat mass in LHA CART ;Cart cre/cre mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4DeE</ref>).</s><s>Prominent nuclei-specific effects of CART reintroduction in CART neurons were also demonstrated in the average energy expenditure over the total 24-hr period between Arc and LHA groups (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5E</ref>).</s><s>Interestingly, the greater energy expenditure observed in Arc CART mice was not associated with any significant increase in physical activity, albeit a trend of modest elevation during the light phase (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5F</ref>).</s><s>Similarly, despite notably lower energy expenditure no detectable difference was seen in physical activity in LHA CART mice compared to controls (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5G</ref>).</s><s>Correspondingly, the impact of CART administration on overall physical activity was minimal for either the Arc or LHA cohort (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5H</ref>), indicating that physical activity had little contribution to the alterations in energy expenditure.</s><s>Since a role of CART in thermoregulation has been implicated <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47]</ref>, along with the overt changes in energy expenditure seen above, the effects of CART reintroduction on body temperature were examined.</s><s>Despite heightened energy expenditure, infrared imaging in Arc CART ;Cart cre/cre mice detected no difference in either whole body temperature, as represented by measurements of the lumbar back area (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5I</ref>), or BAT temperature (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5J</ref>) indicative of non-shivering thermogenesis <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[48]</ref> when compared to AAV-GFP controls.</s><s>Interestingly, the pronounced reduction in energy expenditure in LHA CART ;Cart cre/cre mice is not matched with strong effects on whole body temperature which shows a trend to a reduction relative to controls (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5I</ref>).</s><s>Furthermore, significantly lower BAT temperature (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5J</ref>) and BAT weight (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5K</ref>) were seen in Cart cre/cre mice with LHA CART but not Arc CART when compared to the respective GFP controls, suggesting an involvement of LHA CART in the regulation of BAT thermogenesis.</s><s>In addition, as the tail is regarded as a major thermoregulatory organ for heat dissipation <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>, tail temperature was also examined and was demonstrated to be significantly increased in LHA CART but not Arc CART Cart cre/cre mice compared with controls (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5L</ref>).</s><s>The elevated tail heat loss possibly contributed to the reduced temperature seen in the whole body (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5I</ref>) and the IBAT region (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5J</ref>), indicating a potential involvement of CART function in the LHA to the regulation of vasodilation and vasoconstriction <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[49]</ref>.</s><s>Determination of RER, a measure for fuel source preference, revealed no significant difference between treatments for both Arc (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5M</ref>) and LHA (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5N</ref>) groups throughout the entire photoperiod as well as when averaged for 24-hr (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5O</ref>).</s><s>However, a modest increase in RER was demonstrated for Arc CART compared to Arc GFP Cart cre/cre mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5M</ref>), possibly suggesting higher relative preference for carbohydrate over fat as the metabolized fuel, which may be associated with the diminished fat availability (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4AeB</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.">CART reintroduction in the arc and LHA induced differential effects on the hypothalamic expression of key peptides in the control of energy homeostasis</head><p><s>To elucidate the neurochemical alterations and the central mechanisms underlying the phenotypes manifested following CART reintroduction into Arc or LHA CART neurons, hypothalamic expression of several neurotransmitters and hormones that are pivotal in the regulation of energy homeostasis were profiled.</s><s>As CART neurons in the Arc co-express the anorexigenic POMC and are adjacent to the orexigenic NPY neurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32]</ref>, in situ hybridization was performed to measure the transcript expression of Pomc and Npy in the Arc of Arc CART mice.</s><s>Cart cre/cre mice expressing Arc CART demonstrated a notable trend to a decrease in Pomc mRNA level (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6A</ref>) and significantly reduced Npy expression (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6B</ref>) compared to Arc GFP controls.</s><s>In contrast, no difference was observed in the Arc mRNA level for either neuropeptide in Arc CART ;Cart cre/þ mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6AeB</ref>).</s><s>Since CART has been implicated as a major regulator of CRH neurons of the hypothalamicpituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[50,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51]</ref>, and CART neurons in the Arc are known to innervate CRH neurons in the PVN <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52]</ref>, we also investigated the effects of CART targeted to the Arc on Crh mRNA expression in the PVN in either Cart cre/cre or Cart cre/þ mice.</s><s>Interestingly, neither of the genotypes showed any significant impact on Crh mRNA expression (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6C</ref>).</s><s>In the LHA of both humans and rodents, CART has been reported to have a high level of colocalization with the orexigenic neuropeptide melanin-concentrating hormone (MCH) <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37]</ref>.</s><s>Orexin, another  feeding-stimulating peptide, can also be found in the LHA <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44]</ref>.</s><s>To examine the potential of these two neuropeptides acting together with CART to control feeding and energy homeostasis, mRNA levels of Mch and Orx were evaluated.</s><s>Interestingly, CART rescue in the LHA of Cart cre/cre mice did not affect the mRNA level of either Mch (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6D</ref>) or Orx (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6E</ref>), despite the significant trend towards an increased spontaneous food intake (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5B</ref>) seen in these mice.</s><s>However, LHA CART ;Cart cre/cre mice showed significantly higher Crh levels (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6F</ref>) and a significant decrease in Th expression (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6G</ref>) in the PVN compared with GFP controls, consistent with the role of these PVN peptides in the regulation of energy expenditure and BAT thermogenesis <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53]</ref>.</s><s>The reduced Th transcript expression was also in line with the potential decrease in vasoconstriction reflected by the greater tail temperature thus heat loss in these mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5L</ref>).</s><s>In contrast, the mRNA level of Trh in the PVN, another key regulator of the HPA axis with implications in the control of energy balance and thermoregulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[54]</ref> was unchanged in LHA CART ;Cart cre/cre mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6H</ref>).</s><s>Similarly, CART reintroduction into the LHA in Cart cre/cre mice had no impact on the expression levels of Pomc (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6I</ref>) or Npy (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6J</ref>) in the Arc.</s></p><p><s>3.6.</s><s>CART neuron-specific reintroduction of CART in the LHA reduced glucose tolerance and insulin responsiveness Based on the well-established link between fat metabolism and glucose homeostasis <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[55]</ref> and given the distinctly altered fat content in Cart cre/cre mice expressing Arc CART and LHA CART , various parameters of glucose metabolism were investigated.</s><s>Following i.p. glucose challenge, blood glucose levels throughout the 90 min duration were indistinguishable between Arc CART and Arc GFP Cart cre/cre mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7A</ref>), as reflected in the unchanged AUCglucose.</s><s>In contrast, LHA CART ;Cart cre/cre mice demonstrated significant higher blood glucose levels compared with GFP controls during the course of IPGTT as shown by the increased AUC (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7B</ref>), which suggests reduced glucose tolerance.</s><s>Interestingly, despite different responses to glucose challenge between the Arc and LHA groups (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7B</ref>), serum insulin levels during IPGTT were not different compared to corresponding controls when reintroduced into either the Arc (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7C</ref>) or LHA (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7D</ref>).</s><s>Similar to the GTT, insulin responsiveness using the IP-ITT test was not altered between the Arc CART and Arc GFP mice displaying unvaried blood glucose levels in response to i.p. insulin (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7E</ref>).</s><s>However, LHA CART mice with similar initial fasted levels demonstrated significantly higher blood glucose excursion throughout the 90 min period compared to LHA GFP counterparts (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7F</ref>), as reflected by the corresponding, prominent increase in AUCglucose compared to controls (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7F</ref>).</s><s>The reduction in insulin responsiveness may be due to decreased lean mass as well as increased adiposity in these mice, which may thus contribute to the reduced glucose tolerance observed in LHA CART mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7B</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">DISCUSSION</head><p><s>This study presents the first characterization of energy homeostatic functions of CART specifically expressed in the Arc or LHA in a CART neuron-specific manner, through targeted unilateral AAV-FLEX CART delivery in either the homozygous or heterozygous version of the Cartcre knock-in mice.</s><s>Intriguingly, in Cart cre/þ mice with existing endogenous CART expression, CART overproduction in Arc or LHA CART neurons had little effect on any of the body composition and metabolic parameters measured.</s><s>On the other hand, significant and distinctive changes were demonstrated in Cart cre/cre mice subjected to CART neuron-specific reintroduction of CART into the Arc and LHA on an otherwise CART-deficient background.</s><s>In Cart cre/cre mice, CART selectively targeted to CART neurons in the Arc markedly reduced body weight and fat mass without altering lean mass, whereas CART reintroduction into the LHA led to significant fat mass gain and lean mass loss, resulting in unchanged body weight.</s><s>Although food consumption was unaltered, Arc CART ;Cart cre/cre mice showed an increase in both energy expenditure and physical activity, accompanied by a significant decrease in Npy mRNA expression in the Arc, which may have contributed to the observed reduction in adiposity.</s><s>In comparison, the elevated fat mass in LHA CART ;Cart cre/cre mice was associated with greater spontaneous food intake and lower energy expenditure, with significantly reduced Th and notably increased Crh mRNA levels in the PVN.</s><s>In line with this, the LHA CART-mediated suppression in energy expenditure was paralleled with a significant drop in BAT temperature and BAT weight, while both parameters remained unchanged in Arc CART ;Cart cre/cre counterparts.</s><s>Interestingly, glucose homeostasis was also differentially regulated in the two groups.</s><s>While LHA CART ;Cart cre/cre mice displayed reduced insulin responsiveness and reduced glucose tolerance, attributed at least in part to the higher fat and lower lean body masses, Arc CART ;Cart cre/cre mice, on the other hand, were not influenced in this aspect.</s><s>These findings demonstrate that CART neurons in the Arc and LHA play differential roles in the control of feeding behavior, body composition, and energy homeostasis.</s><s>From existing literature, CART has been classified primarily as anorectic, as summarized from i.c.v.</s><s>CART studies, as well as global CART knockout rodents <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20]</ref>, which showed an increase in body weight gain and adipose mass with unchanged feeding behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20]</ref>.</s><s>Consistent with this classic view, CART reintroduction into the Arc of otherwise CART-deficient mice leads to reduced body weight and lower fat mass, which is accompanied by increased energy expenditure and physical activity, with unaltered food intake.</s><s>This confirms the Arc as a crucial hypothalamic site for the anorexigenic potency of CART, since the limited gene dosage from the unilateral CART reintroduction was sufficient to trigger profound catabolic effects.</s><s>Mechanistically, a substantial decline in the Arc Npy level was observed in these mice, which may be responsible, at least in part, for the increased energy expenditure <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>, indicating the critical involvement of Arc NPY in CART action in regulating energy homeostasis.</s><s>As opposed to the catabolic effects displayed in Arc CART ;Cart cre/cre mice with unaffected feeding behavior, direct evidence for an orexigenic role of CART is also supported by the LHA CART -directed elevation in food intake and adiposity under CART-deficient condition.</s><s>This finding is in line with a prior study where heightened Cart expression in the LHA was associated with elevated feeding and body weight <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[56]</ref>.</s><s>More importantly, the increased adiposity in these mice may be achieved by the alterations in Th and Crh expression in the PVN, indicating the possible control function of LHA CART neurons on TH and CRH neurons in the PVN.</s><s>Additionally, the anabolic profile of LHA CART ;Cart cre/cre mice comprises a reduction in lean mass, lower energy expenditure, and reduced BAT temperature, suggesting that CART in the LHA regulates energy homeostasis through multiple mechanisms.</s><s>Furthermore, as the LHA is traditionally described as the hunger center <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[57]</ref>, and lesions in the LHA were reported to cause hypophagia and weight loss <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[58]</ref>, our results further confirm the significance of CART in the orexigenic activity of the LHA.</s><s>Moreover, since CART knockout mice showed obesogenic traits <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20]</ref>, Arc CART activity may exhibit greater baseline potency than CART in the LHA, and is therefore regarded a major contributor to the overall CART system in energy homeostasis.</s><s>Contrary to our results, previous studies in rodents subjected to intra-Arc or -LHA CART administration showed body weight gain and increased feeding <ref type="bibr">[17e19]</ref>.</s><s>The different responses to CART action are most likely due to the different techniques employed.</s><s>While the AAV-FLEX strategy employed in this work enables the endogenous processing and synthesis of endogenous CART selectively in CART neurons, previous intra-hypothalamic CART delivery by intranuclear injection or chronic infusion leads to widespread and uncontrolled action of CART peptide in these nuclei and areas.</s><s>Furthermore, when chemically synthesized CART fragments are used, it is only presumed that these peptides would represent the active form of CART produced by CART neurons.</s><s>The representativeness of such methods for replicating physiological CART function may be questionable, as evident in the discrepancy between pharmacological studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>In addition, whilst few studies have identified any impact of CART injection on energy expenditure and physical activity, the two parameters were profoundly and differentially regulated in Arc CART and LHA CART Cart cre/cre mice.</s><s>Further verifying the efficacy of this viral approach for CART expression, this study also provided the first evidence for LHA CART in the regulation of glucose metabolism.</s><s>However, the reduced glucose tolerance and insulin responsiveness resulted from CART reintroduction into the LHA could also be secondary to the higher fat and lower lean masses <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[59]</ref> in these mice.</s><s>Importantly, while hypothalamic CART has been reported to be involved in bone physiology <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46]</ref>, our data here show that CART reintroduction into CART neurons in either of the two nuclei had only a minor effect on bone mass, suggesting that other hypothalamic CART neuronal population are more critical for this CART-related control mechanism.</s><s>In addition, our study also revealed that overproducing CART in specific CART neurons in the Arc and LHA of Cart cre/þ mice does not confer any additive function compared to controls with existing endogenous CART, or enhance any effect seen in the respective Cart cre/cre mice with reintroduced CART expression.</s><s>The lack of dose response in Cart cre/þ mice could either be due to a saturation effect above a certain expression threshold for CART at the particular region or the insufficiency of unilateral CART delivery to generate any detectable physiological shift.</s><s>Future work involving bilateral targeting of CART may provide additional insights into the validity of this conjecture.</s><s>Potentially, any effects from the introduced CART in the Cart cre/þ mice may also be subject to counterbalancing actions from endogenous CART expressed locally or at other central areas.</s><s>This further highlights the usefulness of our Cart cre/cre mice as a valuable instrument for determining region-specific CART activity.</s><s>In conclusion, via CART neuron-specific reintroduction of CART in CARTdeficient mice, the catabolic and anabolic homeostatic influences of CART were demonstrated in the Arc and LHA, respectively.</s><s>This work supports the notion of an emerging, multifaceted, and nuclei-specific function of CART in appetite control and energy homeostasis regulation.</s><s>Collectively, our results consolidate the postulation that CART in discrete hypothalamic nuclei performs distinct functions [30e32].</s><s>While appetite-stimulating properties were indicated for LHA CART function, Arc CART displayed multiple catabolic impacts.</s><s>Hence, CART neuronal populations in these two regions may serve as therapeutic entry points for appetite control and body weight maintenance in the treatment of obesity.</s><s>Future work applying the same design with bilateral CART delivery may facilitate the fine-tuning of CART dosage effects in the presence and absence of endogenous CART.</s><s>In parallel, comprehensive neurochemical profiling upon CART reintroduction or overexpression in other areas may provide further invaluable insights into the elements and neuronal signaling pathways that interact with the CART system, thereby unraveling the underlying mechanisms linked to CART action in the regulation of feeding and energy homeostasis.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1: (A) Schematic representation of the AAV-FLEX-Cart vector targeted selectively to CART neurons in the Arc or LHA in Cart-cre knock-in mice.</s><s>The Cre-inducible Cart AAV vector was designed using the FLEX switch strategy.</s><s>(i) The targeting construct comprises the CBA promoter, followed by two pairs of heterotypic recombinase recognition loxP sites (here referred to as loxP-a and loxP-b) in antiparallel configuration, flanking the codon-optimized Cart coding region in the anti-sense inactive orientation relative to the promoter.</s><s>(ii) Administration of tamoxifen activates Cre expression driven by the endogenous Cart promoter to mediate inversion of the floxed element in two possible manners, whereby subsequent recombination occurs only among the same type of loxP sites.</s><s>Consequently, parallel loxP sites of the same type recombine, namely loxP-a with loxP-a, loxP-b with loxP-b, deleting the alternative loxP type in-between.</s><s>(iii) Stable transgene consisting of the Cart coding unit in an orientation parallel to the promoter is transcribed and translated into bioactive and functional CART peptide, which is expressed specifically in the targeted CART neurons in the hypothalamus.Figure 1BeC: Representative fluorescence micrographs of coronal brain sections from Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice unilaterally injected with the AAV-FLEX-GFP control, displaying the Arc (B) and LHA (C) regions where GFP expression within the targeted neurons indicates accurate stereotaxic delivery.Figure 1DeG: Confirmation of Cart reintroduction and overexpression in the Arc and LHA by in situ hybridization in Cart-cre knock-in mice.</s><s>Representative bright-field photomicrographs of coronal brain sections showing Cart mRNA at the Arc (D) and LHA (F) of Cart cre/cre and</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1: (A) Schematic representation of the AAV-FLEX-Cart vector targeted selectively to CART neurons in the Arc or LHA in Cart-cre knock-in mice.</s><s>The Cre-inducible Cart AAV vector was designed using the FLEX switch strategy.</s><s>(i) The targeting construct comprises the CBA promoter, followed by two pairs of heterotypic recombinase recognition loxP sites (here referred to as loxP-a and loxP-b) in antiparallel configuration, flanking the codon-optimized Cart coding region in the anti-sense inactive orientation relative to the promoter.</s><s>(ii) Administration of tamoxifen activates Cre expression driven by the endogenous Cart promoter to mediate inversion of the floxed element in two possible manners, whereby subsequent recombination occurs only among the same type of loxP sites.</s><s>Consequently, parallel loxP sites of the same type recombine, namely loxP-a with loxP-a, loxP-b with loxP-b, deleting the alternative loxP type in-between.</s><s>(iii) Stable transgene consisting of the Cart coding unit in an orientation parallel to the promoter is transcribed and translated into bioactive and functional CART peptide, which is expressed specifically in the targeted CART neurons in the hypothalamus.Figure 1BeC: Representative fluorescence micrographs of coronal brain sections from Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice unilaterally injected with the AAV-FLEX-GFP control, displaying the Arc (B) and LHA (C) regions where GFP expression within the targeted neurons indicates accurate stereotaxic delivery.Figure 1DeG: Confirmation of Cart reintroduction and overexpression in the Arc and LHA by in situ hybridization in Cart-cre knock-in mice.</s><s>Representative bright-field photomicrographs of coronal brain sections showing Cart mRNA at the Arc (D) and LHA (F) of Cart cre/cre and</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,97.46,81.70,380.39,524.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1: (A) Schematic representation of the AAV-FLEX-Cart vector targeted selectively to CART neurons in the Arc or LHA in Cart-cre knock-in mice.</s><s>The Cre-inducible Cart AAV vector was designed using the FLEX switch strategy.</s><s>(i) The targeting construct comprises the CBA promoter, followed by two pairs of heterotypic recombinase recognition loxP sites (here referred to as loxP-a and loxP-b) in antiparallel configuration, flanking the codon-optimized Cart coding region in the anti-sense inactive orientation relative to the promoter.</s><s>(ii) Administration of tamoxifen activates Cre expression driven by the endogenous Cart promoter to mediate inversion of the floxed element in two possible manners, whereby subsequent recombination occurs only among the same type of loxP sites.</s><s>Consequently, parallel loxP sites of the same type recombine, namely loxP-a with loxP-a, loxP-b with loxP-b, deleting the alternative loxP type in-between.</s><s>(iii) Stable transgene consisting of the Cart coding unit in an orientation parallel to the promoter is transcribed and translated into bioactive and functional CART peptide, which is expressed specifically in the targeted CART neurons in the hypothalamus.Figure 1BeC: Representative fluorescence micrographs of coronal brain sections from Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice unilaterally injected with the AAV-FLEX-GFP control, displaying the Arc (B) and LHA (C) regions where GFP expression within the targeted neurons indicates accurate stereotaxic delivery.Figure 1DeG: Confirmation of Cart reintroduction and overexpression in the Arc and LHA by in situ hybridization in Cart-cre knock-in mice.</s><s>Representative bright-field photomicrographs of coronal brain sections showing Cart mRNA at the Arc (D) and LHA (F) of Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice receiving AAV-FLEX-Cart versus AAV-FLEX-GFP injection.</s><s>Scale bar ¼ 200 mm.</s><s>Hybridization signals at the Arc (E) and LHA (G) of respective brain sections are quantified as mean labeling intensity of neurons expressed as percentage coverage of neuronal surface by silver grains (RODs) within the defined areas of interest.</s><s>3V, third ventricle; fx, fornix; Arc, arcuate nucleus; LHA, lateral hypothalamic area.</s><s>Data are means AE SEM and averaged for all mice from each group examined.</s><s>****p 0.0001 for Cart cre/cre or Cart cre/þ mice targeted with AAV-Cart versus AAV-GFP in the Arc or LHA, or for comparisons between different genotypes receiving the same treatments.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2: Validation of the site-specific reintroduction and overexpression of CART peptide in Cart-cre knock-in mice by immunohistochemistry. Representative bright-field photomicrographs of CART-immunostained matching brain sections from Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice unilaterally injected with the AAV-FLEX-GFP control or AAV-FLEX-Cart in the Arc (A) or LHA (B).</s><s>Left panel: high densities of CART immunostaining within CART neurons at the Arc or LHA were only shown on the injection side of the respective brain sections from Cart cre/cre mice receiving AAV-Cart but not AAV-GFP.</s><s>CART-IR exhibited a pattern concordant with endogenous CART-containing neurons, while lacking on the contralateral control side.</s><s>Right panel: higher CART-IR was shown in the Arc or LHA on the injection compared to the contralateral side of brain sections from Cart cre/þ mice targeted with AAV-Cart, whereas comparable CART-IR was displayed on both sides for counterparts treated with AAV-GFP.</s><s>Scale bar ¼ 200 mm.</s><s>3V, third ventricle; fx, fornix; Arc, arcuate nucleus; LHA, lateral hypothalamic are.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,80.05,81.70,454.78,512.33" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3: Specific introduction of CART expression into CART neurons in the Arc led to significant decline in body weight in homozygous Cart cre/cre but not heterozygous Cart cre/þ mice.</s><s>Absolute body weight and corresponding body weight change as a percentage of initial body weight measured weekly in Cart cre/þ (A -B) and Cart cre/cre (C -D) mice targeted with AAV-Cart or AAV-GFP in the Arc (A, C) or the LHA (B, D) (n ¼ 10 -12 per group).</s><s>Data are means AE SEM and averaged for all mice from each group examined.</s><s>*p 0.05, **p 0.01 for AAV-Cart versus AAV-GFP treatments, or for comparisons indicated by horizontal bar.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,97.23,101.54,380.84,568.06" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4: Reintroduced CART expression in CART neurons in the Arc and LHA reduces and increases fat mass respectively in Cart cre/cre mice.</s><s>Body composition analysis using dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry.</s><s>Whole body fat mass in Cart cre/cre mice injected with Arc CART versus Arc GFP (A) or LHA CART versus LHA GFP (D) (n ¼ 10 -12 per group).</s><s>Tissue mass of dissected white adipose tissue (WAT) depots after sacrifice in the corresponding Arc (B) and LHA (E) groups.</s><s>i, inguinal; e, epididymal; m, mesenteric; r, retroperitoneal; total, summed weight of i, e, m and r WAT depots.</s><s>Whole body lean mass in the corresponding Arc (C) and LHA (F) groups.</s><s>Data are means AE SEM and averaged for all mice from each group examined.</s><s>*p 0.05, **p 0.01, ***p 0.001 for AAV-Cart versus AAV-GFP treatments.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,87.19,230.51,440.59,461.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5: CART reintroduction in Cart cre/cre mice upregulates energy expenditure when targeted in the Arc while downregulating energy expenditure and BAT temperature when introduced into the LHA.</s><s>Daily spontaneous/basal food intake during fed state in Cart cre/cre mice expressing Arc CART versus Arc GFP (A) or LHA CART versus LHA GFP (B) (n ¼ 10 -12 per group).</s><s>Indirect calorimetric assessments for the 24-hr time course of energy expenditure (C, D), physical activity (F, G) and respiratory exchange ratio (M, N) to compare Arc CART against Arc GFP and LHA CART against LHA GFP treatments in Cart cre/cre mice respectively.</s><s>Corresponding average values for energy expenditure (E), physical activity (H), and respiratory exchange ratio (O) over the total 24-hr period were shown in adjacent bar graphs.</s><s>Energy expenditure was adjusted for lean mass and compared between groups by analysis of covariance.</s><s>The adjusted means of energy expenditure were presented at the common lean mass of 22.515 g (Arc) and 21.921 g (LHA) respectively.</s><s>Open and filled horizontal bars indicate the light and dark photoperiods, respectively.</s><s>Temperatures of the lumbar back region (I), the interscapular brown adipose tissue (IBAT) (J), and the tail (L) measured by high-sensitivity infrared imaging.</s><s>(K) Dissected BAT mass.</s><s>Data are means AE SEM and averaged for all mice from each group examined.</s><s>*p 0.05, ****p 0.0001 for AAV-Cart versus AAV-GFP treatments, for comparisons between mice receiving the same treatments at the Arc versus LHA, or for comparisons indicated by horizontal bar.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="11,110.21,81.70,394.56,555.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6: CART neuron-specific CART reintroduction in the Arc and LHA of Cart cre/cre mice differentially impacts mRNA expression of key hypothalamic peptides in the control of energy homeostasis.</s><s>In situ hybridization for Pomc (A) and Npy (B) mRNA expression in the Arc and Crh (C) mRNA expression in the PVN in Cart cre/cre and Cart cre/þ mice expressing Arc CART versus Arc GFP (n ! 5 per group).</s><s>In situ hybridization for Mch (D) and Orx (E) mRNA expression in the LHA, for Crh (F), Th (G), and Trh (H) mRNA expression in the PVN, and for Pomc (I) and Npy (J) mRNA expression in the Arc in Cart cre/cre mice expressing LHA CART versus LHA GFP (n ¼ 5 per group).</s><s>Bright-field photomicrographs of coronal brain sections showing mRNA expression for Pomc (A) and Npy (B) in the Arc, and for Crh (F) and Th (G) in the PVN.</s><s>Scale bar ¼ 200 mm or 100 mm.</s><s>Hybridization signals are quantified to obtain mean labeling intensity of neurons expressed as percentage coverage of neuronal surface by silver grains (RODs) within the defined areas of interest.</s><s>PVN, paraventricular nucleus; Arc, arcuate nucleus; Pomc, proopiomelanocortin; Npy, neuropeptide Y; Crh, corticotropin-releasing hormone; Mch, melanin-concentrating hormone; Orx, orexin; Th, tyrosine hydroxylase; Trh, thyrotropin-releasing hormone.</s><s>Data are means AE SEM and averaged for all mice from each group examined.</s><s>**p 0.01 for AAV-Cart versus AAV-GFP treatments.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="12,71.89,81.70,431.47,553.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 7: CART neuron-specific rescue of CART expression in the LHA of Cart cre/cre mice reduces glucose tolerance and insulin responsiveness.</s><s>Blood glucose levels during a 90min intraperitoneal glucose tolerance test (1.0 g/kg body weight) performed in 6-hr fasted Cart cre/cre mice expressing Arc CART versus Arc GFP (A) or LHA CART versus LHA GFP (B) (n ¼ 10 -12 per group).</s><s>Adjacent bar graphs showing the area under the glucose concentration curve (AUCglucose) between 0 and 90 min after glucose injection.</s><s>Corresponding serum insulin levels during the 90-min IPGTT procedure for the Arc (C) and LHA (D) groups.</s><s>Adjacent bar graphs showing the area under the insulin concentration curve (AUCinsulin) between 0 and 90 min after glucose injection.</s><s>Absolute blood glucose levels during a 90-min intraperitoneal insulin tolerance test (0.5 IU/kg body weight) performed in 5-hr fasted Cart cre/cre mice expressing Arc CART versus Arc GFP (E) or LHA CART versus LHA GFP (F).</s><s>Adjacent bar graphs showing AUCglucose between 0 and 90 min after insulin injection.</s><s>Data are means AE SEM and averaged for all mice from each group examined.</s><s>*p 0.05, **p 0.01 for AAV-Cart versus AAV-GFP treatments, or for comparisons indicated by horizontal bar.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="14,42.52,81.70,491.73,474.46" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">MOLECULAR METABOLISM 7 (2018) 102e118 Ó 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). www.molecularmetabolism.com</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="104"> MOLECULAR METABOLISM 7 (2018)  102e118 Ó 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). www.molecularmetabolism.com</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="106"> MOLECULAR METABOLISM 7 (2018)  102e118 Ó 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). www.molecularmetabolism.com</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="108"> MOLECULAR METABOLISM 7 (2018)  102e118 Ó 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). www.molecularmetabolism.com</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="110"> MOLECULAR METABOLISM 7 (2018)  102e118 Ó 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). www.molecularmetabolism.com</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="112"> MOLECULAR METABOLISM 7 (2018)  102e118 Ó 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). www.molecularmetabolism.com</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="114"> MOLECULAR METABOLISM 7 (2018)  102e118 Ó 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). www.molecularmetabolism.com</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="116"> MOLECULAR METABOLISM 7 (2018)  102e118 Ó 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). www.molecularmetabolism.com</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="118"> MOLECULAR METABOLISM 7 (2018)  102e118 Ó 2017 The Authors. Published by Elsevier GmbH. This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/). www.molecularmetabolism.com</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>The authors are grateful to Mr. Ronaldo Enriquez for providing technical assistance for the animal work.</s><s>We thank the staff of the Garvan Institute Biological Testing Facility for facilitation of these experiments.</s><s>This research was supported by the National Health and Medical Research Council of Australia (NHMRC) with grant number 1081290, a Research Fellowship to H.H., a Postgraduate Scholarship to J.L., and the Austrian Science Fund (FWF grant J-3814) to A.F.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</head><p><s>No potential conflicts of interest associated with this article were reported and there has been no significant financial support for this work that could have influenced its outcome.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>APPENDIX A. SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</head><p><s>Supplementary data related to this article can be found at https://doi.org/10.1016/j.</s><s>molmet.2017.10.015.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CART in the regulation of appetite and energy homeostasis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Herzog</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anatomy of hypothalamic CART neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Vrang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Peptides</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006. 1970e1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immunohistochemical localization of novel CART peptides in rat hypothalamus, pituitary and adrenal gland</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Koylu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Couceyro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lambert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Desouza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kuhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neuroendocrinol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="823" to="e833" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CART in the brain of vertebrates: circuits, functions and evolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Subhedar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Nakhate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Upadhya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kokare</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Peptides</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="108" to="e130" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PCR differential display identifies a rat brain mRNA that is transcriptionally regulated by cocaine and amphetamine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Douglass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mckinzie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Couceyro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2471" to="e2481" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterization of CART neurons in the rat and human hypothalamus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Elias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ahima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kuhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Saper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Comparative Neurology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">432</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="e19" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cocaine-and amphetamine-regulated transcript (CART) is colocalized with the orexigenic neuropeptide y and agouti-related protein and absent from the anorexigenic a-melanocyte-stimulating hormone neurons in the infundibular nucleus of the human hypothalamus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Menyhért</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wittmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lechan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Keller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liposits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fekete</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Endocrinology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4276" to="e4281" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tissuespecific processing of cocaine-and amphetamine-regulated transcript peptides in the rat</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Thim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kristensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wulff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Clausen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of United States of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2722" to="e2727" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The CART gene: structure and regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dominguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Peptides</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006. 1913e1918</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CART peptides as modulators of dopamine and psychostimulants and interactions with the mesolimbic dopaminergic system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hubert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Moffett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rogge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kuhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemical Pharmacology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="e62" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative distribution of cocaine-and amphetamine-regulated transcript (CART) in the hypothalamus of the capuchin monkey (Cebus apella) and the common marmoset (Callithrix jacchus)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cavalcante</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cândido</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Sita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Do Nascimento</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D S</forename><surname>Cavalcante</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S M</forename><surname>De Oliveira Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="e61" />
			<date type="published" when="1425">2011. 1425</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CART peptide analysis by western blotting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kuhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yoho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Synapse</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="e171" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biological processing of the cocaine and amphetamine-regulated transcript precursors by prohormone convertases, PC2 and PC1/3</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Xhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Carroll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Turck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Biological Chemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">278</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15007" to="e15014" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Absence of cocaine-and amphetamine-regulated transcript results in obesity in mice fed a high caloric diet</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Asnicar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Heiman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-F</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Endocrinology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4394" to="e4400" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CART knock out mice have impaired insulin secretion and glucose intolerance, altered beta cell morphology and increased body weight</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Wierup</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Richards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Bannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kuhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ahrén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sundler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Regulatory Peptides</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="e211" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leptin regulation of bone resorption by the sympathetic nervous system and CART</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Elefteriou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Takeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Starbuck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">434</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="514" to="e520" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evidence of an orexigenic role for cocaine-and amphetamine-regulated transcript after administration into discrete hypothalamic nuclei</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Abbott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stanley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Endocrinology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3457" to="e3463" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A role for arcuate cocaine and amphetamine-regulated transcript in hyperphagia, thermogenesis, and cold adaptation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Stanley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gardiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Abbott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Seth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The FASEB Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1688" to="e1690" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Orexigenic effect of cocaine-and amphetamine-regulated transcript (CART) after injection into hypothalamic nuclei in streptozotocin-diabetic rats</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D.-Z</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-Y</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-W</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical and Experimental Pharmacology and Physiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="989" to="e995" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Temperature dependence of the control of energy homeostasis requires CART signaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Herzog</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuropeptides</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutational screening of the CART gene in obese children: identifying a mutation (Leu34Phe) associated with reduced resting energy expenditure and cosegregating with obesity phenotype in a large family</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Del Giudice</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Santoro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cirillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>D'urso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Di Toro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Perrone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabetes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001. 2157e 2160</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Leu34Phe ProCART mutation leads to cocaine-and amphetamine-regulated transcript (CART) deficiency: a possible cause for obesity in humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yanik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dominguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kuhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Del Giudice</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Loh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Endocrinology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="e43" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hypothalamic CART is a new anorectic peptide regulated by leptin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kristensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Judge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Thim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Ribel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Christjansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wulff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">393</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="e76" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Overexpression of CART in the PVN increases food intake and weight gain in rats</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Gardiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obesity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2239" to="e2244" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The CART (cocaine-and amphetamineregulated transcript) system in appetite and drug addiction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vicentic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">320</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="499" to="e506" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Both neuropeptide Y knockdown and Y1 receptor inhibition modulate CARTmediated appetite control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hsieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Kuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hormones Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="e47" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic approaches to studying energy balance: perception and integration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Barsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="589" to="e600" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brain stem melanocortinergic modulation of meal size and identification of hypothalamic POMC projections</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Patterson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Phifer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-R</forename><surname>Berthoud</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Physiology -Regulatory, Integrative and Comparative Physiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">289</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="R247" to="R258" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leptin activates hypothalamic cart neurons projecting to the spinal cord</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Elias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Aschkenasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ahima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Couceyro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1375" to="e1385" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Origin of cocaineand amphetamine-regulated transcript (CART)-immunoreactive innervation of the hypothalamic paraventricular nucleus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fekete</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wittmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liposits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lechan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Comparative Neurology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">469</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="340" to="e350" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leptin differentially regulates NPY and POMC neurons projecting to the lateral hypothalamic area</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Elias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Aschkenasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ahima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bjorbaek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="775" to="e786" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leptin activates anorexigenic POMC neurons through a neural network in the arcuate nucleus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cowley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Smart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rubinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cerdan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Diano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Horvath</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">411</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="480" to="e484" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of fasting on cocaine-amphetamine-regulated transcript, neuropeptide y, and leptin receptor expression in the non-human primate hypothalamus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Van Vugt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lujan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Froats</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Krzemien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Couceyro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Reid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroendocrinology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="e93" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Time course effects of adrenalectomy and food intake on cocaine-and amphetamine-regulated transcript expression in the hypothalamus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M R</forename><surname>Germano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>De Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rorato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T C</forename><surname>Laguna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Antunes-Rodrigues</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Elias</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1166</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="e64" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cocaine-and amphetamine-regulated transcript in the arcuate nucleus stimulates lipid metabolism to control body fat accrual on a high-fat diet</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wortley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G.-Q</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Davydova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Fried</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Leibowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Regulatory Peptides</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="e99" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Melanin-concentrating hormone acutely stimulates feeding, but chronic administration has no effect on body weight</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Shea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Miyoshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ghatei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bloom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Endocrinology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="e355" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Melanin-concentrating hormone: a functional melanocortin antagonist in the hypothalamus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ludwig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mountjoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Tatro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gillette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Frederich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Flier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Physiology -Endocrinology and Metabolism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">274</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="E627" to="E633" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deconstruction of a neural circuit for hunger</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Atasoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Betley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sternson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">488</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="172" to="e177" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chronic central infusion of cocaine-and amphetamine-regulated transcript (CART 55-102): effects on body weight homeostasis in lean and high-fat-fed obese rats</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rohner-Jeanrenaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Craft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bridwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Suter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Tinsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Smiley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Obesity and Related Metabolic Disorders</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="e149" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OneBac: platform for scalable and high-titer production of adeno-associated virus serotype 1-12 vectors for gene therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mietzsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Grasse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zurawski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Weger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Agbandje-Mckenna</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Human Gene Therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="212" to="e222" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ligand-activated site-specific recombination in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Feil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Brocard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mascrez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lemeur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Metzger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chambon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of United States of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10887" to="e10890" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The mouse brain in stereotaxic coordinates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Paxinos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Franklin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier Science Publishing Co. Inc</publisher>
			<pubPlace>San Diego USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd ed.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Arcuate NPY controls sympathetic output and BAT function via a relay of tyrosine hydroxylase neurons in the PVN</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-C</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sperk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Metabolism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="236" to="e248" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recombinant CART peptide induces c-Fos expression in central areas involved in control of feeding behaviour</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Vrang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tang-Christensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Larsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kristensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">818</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="499" to="e509" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GPR88 is a critical regulator of feeding and body composition in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Farzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Enriquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Herzog</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9912</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gender-specific increase of bone mass by CART peptide treatment is ovary-dependent</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Gerrits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bakker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van De Ven-De Laat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Bourgondien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Peddemors</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Litjens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Bone and Mineral Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2886" to="e2898" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hindbrain cocaine-and amphetamine-regulated transcript induces hypothermia mediated by GLP-1 receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Skibicka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Alhadeff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Grill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6973" to="e6981" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Central neural regulation of brown adipose tissue thermogenesis and energy expenditure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shaun</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Morrison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christopher</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Madden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tupone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Metabolism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="741" to="e756" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leptin raises defended body temperature without activating thermogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hoefig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Abreu-Vieira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M A</forename><surname>De Jong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Petrovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mittag</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1621" to="e1631" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Actions of cocaine-and amphetamine-regulated transcript (CART) peptide on regulation of appetite and hypothalamo-pituitary axes in vitro and in vivo in male rats</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stanley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Small</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Abbott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Seal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">893</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="e194" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Central administration of cocaine-and amphetamine-regulated transcript increases phosphorylation of cAMP response element binding protein in corticotropinreleasing hormone-producing neurons but not in prothyrotropin-releasing hormone-producing neurons in the hypothalamic paraventricular nucleus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sarkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wittmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fekete</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lechan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">999</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="e192" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Origin of cocaineand amphetamine-regulated transcript-containing axons innervating hypophysiotropic corticotropin-releasing hormone-synthesizing neurons in the rat</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wittmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liposits</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lechan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fekete</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Endocrinology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">146</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2985" to="e2991" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The corticotropin-releasing factor family of peptides and CRF receptors: their roles in the regulation of energy balance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Richard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Timofeeva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Pharmacology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">440</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="e197" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of melanocortin signaling in the regulation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-thyroid (HPT) axis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lechan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fekete</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Peptides</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="310" to="e325" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hyperinsulinemia. A link between hypertension obesity and glucose intolerance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Modan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Halkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Almog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lusky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Eshkol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shefi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Clinical Investigation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="809" to="e817" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential expression of hypothalamic CART mRNA in response to body weight change following different dietary interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>South</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X.-F</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurochemistry International</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1422" to="e1430" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Central nervous system control of food intake</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Woods</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Porte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Seeley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Baskin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">404</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="661" to="e671" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The dorsomedial hypothalamic nucleus and its role in ingestive behavior and body weight regulation: lessons learned from lesioning studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bellinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bernardis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiology Behavior</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="e442" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lean mass inversely predicts plasma glucose levels after oral glucose load independent of insulin secretion or insulin sensitivity in glucose intolerance subjects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kwankaew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Saetung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chanprasertyothin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Leelawattana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rattarasarn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Endocrine Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="e83" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
