<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Hemodynamics of Pericardial Aortic Valves: Contemporary Stented versus Stentless Valves in a Matched Comparison</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>MD. Charité</roleName><forename type="first">Torsten</forename><surname>Christ</surname></persName>
							<email>torsten.christ@charite.de</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Sebastian</forename><surname>Holinski</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Konstantin</forename><surname>Zhigalov</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Christina</forename><forename type="middle">Barbara</forename><surname>Zielinski</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Herko</forename><surname>Grubitzsch</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">-Universi- Tätsmedizin</forename><surname>Berlin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiovascular Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Corporate Member of Freie Universität Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">and Berlin Insti-tute of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Corporate Member of Freie Universität Berlin</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiovascular Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Berlin Institute of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Hemodynamics of Pericardial Aortic Valves: Contemporary Stented versus Stentless Valves in a Matched Comparison</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BFD3B135219E9AC51FA97F7A1DA99CBE</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.5761/atcs.oa.17-00061</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: March 29, 2017; Accepted: May 21, 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:30+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>biological prosthesis</term>
					<term>valve replacement</term>
					<term>echocardiography</term>
					<term>hemodynamics</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Hemodynamic performance of aortic valve bioprostheses is essential for reliable function and durability.</s><s>So far, the supra-annularly implanted stentless Sorin Freedom Solo (SFS) demonstrated unsurpassed hemodynamic properties.</s><s>As contemporary stented and externally mounted pericardial bioprostheses, like the Labcor Dokimos Plus (LDP), also improve hemodynamic performance, these types of valves were compared in this study.</s><s>Methods: A total of 218 patients, who underwent aortic valve replacement with the LDP or the SFS, were matched retrospectively 1:1 on variables affecting hemodynamic measurements: implanted valve size, age, sex, and body surface area (BSA).</s><s>With matching tolerance for valve size and gender of 0%, for age and BSA of 5%, 57 patient-pairs were yielded.</s><s>Operative data, clinical, and hemodynamic outcome were analyzed.</s><s>Results: Except for slightly higher left ventricular function and lower procedural times in the SFS group, preoperative, operative, and postoperative characteristics of patient-pairs did not differ significantly.</s><s>Mean pressure gradients, effective orifice areas (EOAs), and indexed EOAs were comparable.</s><s>Corresponding to valve sizes of 21, 23, 25, and 27 mm, the indexed EOAs of the LDP and SFS prostheses were 1.08 ± 0.33, 0.92 ± 0.19, 0.93 ± 0.24, 0.99 ± 0.13 cm 2 /m 2 and 0.81 ± 0.13, 0.92 ± 0.28, 0.95 ± 0.20, 1.04 ± 0.27 cm 2 /m 2 , respectively.</s><s>Conclusion: Contemporary stented and stentless pericardial bioprostheses showed excellent hemodynamic properties without significant differences in EOAs and indexed EOAs.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>The hemodynamic performance of aortic valve prostheses has a relation to patients' outcome with inferior survival in patients with a patient-prosthesis-mismatch. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1)</ref> Previously, stentless aortic bioprostheses showed excellent hemodynamic properties, especially the third-generation supra-annularly implantable Sorin Freedom Solo (SFS) valve. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3)</ref></s><s>]<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> The Labcor Dokimos Plus (LDP) valve is one of these stented pericardial bioprosthesis with a low profile stent and externally mounted leaflets for the supraannular position. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7)</ref></s><s>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref> shows the geometric dimensions of both prostheses.</s><s>Technically, both types of valves (SFS or LDP) could be implanted in the same patient.</s><s>The aim of this study was to compare the hemodynamic performance of contemporary stented and stentless bovine pericardial prostheses based on a retrospectively matched comparison of the LDP and the SFS valve.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patients</head><p><s>The local Ethics Committee approved the study and waived patients' individual consent.</s><s>All patients who underwent aortic valve replacement from 2009 until 2015 with the stented LDP or the stentless SFS were evaluated regarding availability of a comprehensive echocardiographic examination at discharge.</s><s>Thus, 93 patients with LDP prostheses and 125 patients with SFS prostheses were identified.</s><s>Retrospective matching was done 1:1 on variables known to affect hemodynamic measurements: size of implanted valve, age, sex, and body surface area (BSA). <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1)</ref></s><s>LDP and SFS are equally oversized in comparison to the aortic annulus.</s><s>The size of the measured annulus matches the labeled valve size for implantation in both valves.</s><s>Therefore, sizing was done by ball sizers to assure accurate matching and avoid bias of differences in the actual size of the by the manufacturers provided sizers.</s><s>Matching tolerance for valve size and gender was 0%, whereas for age and BSA it was 5%.</s><s>Thereby, 57 matched patientpairs were yielded.</s><s>In all cases, bioprostheses were implanted after explicit patient education and informed consent according to the actual guidelines. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8)</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Operation</head><p><s>All procedures were performed using partial (isolated procedures) or complete (complex procedures) sternotomy, cardiopulmonary bypass, cardioplegic arrest (blood cardioplegia), excision of the diseased aortic valve including thorough decalcification, and sizing of the annulus using ball sizers.</s><s>The LDP valve was implanted with 12-15 horizontal Teflon felt-armed mattress sutures.</s><s>The SFS was implanted supra-annularly using three running polypropylene sutures according to the technique of Beholz to prevent a protruding flange. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9)</ref></s><s>e procedures were performed by six surgeons and operative setting did not change in the study period.</s><s>The choice of the bioprosthesis was left to the discretion of the surgeon.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical follow-up</head><p><s>Pre-, intra-, and early postoperative data were prospectively collected.</s><s>Hemodynamic performance was evaluated using transthoracic echocardiography, using a GE Vivid 7 Dimension (General Electric, Fairfield, CT, USA), at discharge.</s><s>Standard two-dimensional and Doppler transthoracic echocardiography was performed.</s><s>Mean values for each measurement were derived from three beats in sinus rhythm, and five beats in those in non-sinus rhythm.</s><s>Trans-aortic flow velocities were assessed by continuous-wave Doppler, whereas flow velocities in the left ventricular outflow tract were assessed by pulsed-wave Doppler.</s><s>Pressure gradients were calculated using the Bernoulli equation.</s><s>The effective orifice area (EOA) was calculated with the continuity equation and indexed by the BSA of the patient indexed effective orifice area (EOAI).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistics</head><p><s>All data were analyzed with SPSS Statistics version 22 (IBM Corporation, Armonk, NY, USA).</s><s>Descriptive statistics are reported as mean ± standard deviation for continuous variables and as absolute frequencies and percentages for categorical variables.</s><s>For comparison of baseline and operative characteristics independentsamples Student's t-tests and Fisher's exact tests were used, respectively.</s><s>For comparison of hemodynamic outcome and clinical outcome, paired-samples Student's t-tests and Fisher's exact tests were used, respectively.</s><s>Due to the limited number of cases, no equal variances were assumed.</s><s>All p values were two-sided.</s><s>Statistical significance was set at a p value of less than 0.05.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Matching resulted in two almost equal groups regarding baseline characteristics (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>).</s><s>There was only a dissimilarity of 3.3% in mean left ventricular ejection fraction.</s><s>This is clinically not relevant.</s><s>Additionally, there was no significant difference between the groups regarding the presence of severely impaired left ventricular function.</s><s>Operative characteristics revealed a distinct advantage in procedural times in the SFS group, whereas other procedural features were not significantly different (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>).</s><s>Clinical outcome was uneventful and similar in both groups (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Echocardiography showed no significant differences between the LDP and the SFS with respect to pressure gradients, EOA, and indexed EOA.</s><s>In none of the patients, relevant aortic regurgitation occurred.</s><s>Detailed results, corresponding to valve sizes 21, 23, 25, and 27 mm, are presented in Table <ref type="table">5</ref>.</s><s>Except for a higher maximum pressure gradient of the 27 mm LDP valve, all parameters were comparable.</s><s>Only three matched cases with valve size less than 23 mm were analyzed in the comparison.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>There is still a controversial debate about the use of stentless aortic valve prostheses.</s><s>Although they demonstrate excellent hemodynamic performance, their implantation is more demanding implantation procedure and the longterm durability remains limited. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr">11)</ref></s><s>In contrast, conventional stented valves, exhibiting a proven durability, are simple to implant, while their hemodynamic performance is limited by the stent, which narrows the orifice area.</s><s>The last generation of stentless and stented pericardial aortic bioprostheses is characterized by supra-annular implantation.</s><s>The supra-annular position together with thinner stent design of newer stented bioprostheses preserves or even enlarges the orifice area.</s><s>Additionally, externally mounted leaflets further increase the orifice area.</s><s>However, both types of prostheses are constructed from fixed pericardium, which is not as pliable as the leaflets of the native aortic valve and consequently impairs transvalvular blood flow.</s></p><p><s>The results of this study are interesting regarding several aspects.</s><s>The disadvantage of a demanding implantation procedure of the first generation of stentless valves, which resulted in prolonged procedural times, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr">11)</ref> disappeared due to the simplified single suture line implantation technique of the SFS <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9)</ref> leading to shorter procedural times.</s><s>In contrast, the LDP valves were associated with prolonged implantation time in our series.</s><s>However, these differences did not affect the clinical outcome of the patients, which was uneventful in both groups.</s><s>A repeatedly reported complication after implantation of the SFS is thrombocytopenia. <ref type="bibr">12,</ref><ref type="bibr">13)</ref></s><s>In our matched study LDP: Labcor Dokimos Plus; SFS: Sorin Freedom Solo excellent hemodynamic properties. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3)</ref></s><s>Furthermore, a significant advantage in hemodynamics of the SFS compared to Edwards Perimount stented bioprostheses (Edwards Lifesciences) could be shown. 17)</s><s>Considering the geometric dimensions of the LDP and the SFS (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>), with a higher orifice diameter of the SFS in the same labeled valve size (3 mm), one would expect a distinct advantage of the stentless valve in our study results.</s><s>However, results of our matched analysis showed no significant difference in EOA or EOAI.</s><s>Considering that the EOA is the EOA of the blood flow and not the geometric orifice area of the valve, apparently the stent of the LDP seems not to obstruct the effective blood flow.</s><s>Consequently, no difference between stentless and stented valves could be found in our data.</s><s>Due to the study population containing only three matched pairs of patients with valve size 21 mm, this finding is based on the comparison of larger valve sizes (≥23 mm).</s><s>Comprehensibly, cohort, it occurred in 11 patients of the SFS group and three patients of the LDP group.</s><s>However, it was not accompanied with bleeding complications or thromboembolic events in both groups.</s></p><p><s>The main focus of the study was the hemodynamic performance of the different valves.</s><s>]<ref type="bibr">[16]</ref> Until now, there is no data available regarding contemporary stented, externally mounted pericardial bioprostheses, and third-generation stentless valves.</s><s>]<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> Similarly, the stentless SFS showed in larger aortic annuli, the stent and sewing ring fit better in to the supra-annular aortic sinus.</s><s>In smaller annuli, this could be different because the dimension of the stent is identical in all valve sizes.</s><s>Thus, the proportion of the geometric orifice area which is reduced by the stent gets larger in smaller aortic roots.</s><s>Therefore, results might differ in smaller valves sizes.</s><s>Whether this mathematical assumption is clinical relevant or not has to be proved in further studies involving smaller valves.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>The stented LDP and the stentless SFS showed comparable hemodynamic performance.</s><s>In line with other publications, hemodynamic properties of contemporary stented pericardial bioprostheses, in particular in larger valve sizes, are not inferior to those of contemporary stentless pericardial bioprostheses.</s><s>However, further studies are necessary to confirm the hemodynamic outcome in long-term follow-up and to evaluate the outcome in smaller valve sizes.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Ann Thorac Cardiovasc Surg Vol. 23, No.6 (2017)</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Ann Thorac Cardiovasc Surg 2017; 23: 298-303</cell><cell>Online September 8, 2017</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>doi: 10.5761/atcs.oa.17-00061</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 Geometric dimensions of the Labcor Dokimos Plus and the Sorin Freedom Solo</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Labcor Dokimos Plus 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Labeled valve size</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>27</cell></row><row><cell>Sewing ring diameter (mm)</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>29</cell><cell>31</cell></row><row><cell>Orifice diameter (mm)</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>24</cell></row><row><cell>Sorin Freedom Solo 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Labeled valve size</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>27</cell></row><row><cell>Sewing ring diameter (mm)</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>29</cell></row><row><cell>Orifice diameter (mm)</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>27</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 Baseline characteristics and risk stratification</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Characteristic</cell><cell>LDP group</cell><cell>SFS group</cell><cell>p value</cell></row><row><cell>Number of patients (n)</cell><cell>57</cell><cell>57</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>• Age in years ± standard deviation</cell><cell>70.9 ± 7.2</cell><cell>71.1</cell><cell>0.64</cell></row><row><cell>Gender</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>• Male (n)</cell><cell>43</cell><cell>43</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>• Female (n)</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>14</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Body surface area ± standard deviation (m 2 )</cell><cell>1.99 ± 0.23</cell><cell>1.97 ± 0.23</cell><cell>0.11</cell></row><row><cell>Left ventricular ejection fraction</cell><cell>53.6</cell><cell>56.9</cell><cell>&lt;0.01</cell></row><row><cell>• Left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;40%</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0.32</cell></row><row><cell>Predominant cardiac rhythm</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.28</cell></row><row><cell>• Sinus rhythm (n)</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>46</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>• Atrial fibrillation (n)</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>11</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Concomitant disease</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>• Coronary artery disease (n)</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>0.13</cell></row><row><cell>• Arterial hypertension (n)</cell><cell>48</cell><cell>52</cell><cell>0.39</cell></row><row><cell>• Pulmonary hypertension (n)</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0.13</cell></row><row><cell>• Renal dysfunction (n)</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0.14</cell></row><row><cell>• Peripheral arterial disease</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>• Diabetes mellitus (n)</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>0.28</cell></row><row><cell>• Chronic lung disease (n)</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>1</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 Operative characteristics</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Characteristic</cell><cell>LDP group</cell><cell>SFS group</cell><cell>p value</cell></row><row><cell>Procedure</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Isolated aortic valve replacement (n)</cell><cell>37</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>0.25</cell></row><row><cell>Combined procedures (n)</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>27</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>• Coronary artery bypass grafting (n)</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>22</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>• Mitral valve replacement (n)</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>• Left atrial ablation (n)</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>5</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>• Ascending aorta replacement (n)</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>• Tricuspid valve reconstruction (n)</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Implanted valve sizes</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>• 21 mm (n)</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>• 23 mm (n)</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>• 25 mm (n)</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>• 27 mm (n)</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Duration of procedure (min)</cell><cell>210.6 ± 51.9</cell><cell>170.3 ± 47.3</cell><cell>&lt;0.01</cell></row><row><cell>• Isolated procedures (min)</cell><cell>193.7 ± 37.4</cell><cell>148.4 ± 36.3</cell><cell>&lt;0.01</cell></row><row><cell>• Combined procedures (min)</cell><cell>241.8 ± 60.9</cell><cell>194.6 ± 46.7</cell><cell>0.01</cell></row><row><cell>Aortic cross clamp time (min)</cell><cell>83.4 ± 51.9</cell><cell>68.9 ± 21.8</cell><cell>&lt;0.01</cell></row><row><cell>• Isolated procedures (min)</cell><cell>78.2 ± 20.1</cell><cell>61.6 ± 21.0</cell><cell>&lt;0.01</cell></row><row><cell>• Combined procedures (min)</cell><cell>93.2 ± 30.6</cell><cell>77.0 ± 20.0</cell><cell>&lt;0.05</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">LDP: Labcor Dokimos Plus; SFS: Sorin Freedom Solo</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 4 Clinical outcome</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Characteristic</cell><cell>LDP group</cell><cell>SFS group</cell><cell>p value</cell></row><row><cell>Hospital mortality (n)</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Redo valve replacement (n)</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Myocardial infarction (n)</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Stroke (n)</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Relevant bleeding (n)</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0.68</cell></row><row><cell>Thrombocytopenia (&lt;100/nL) at discharge (n)</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0.04</cell></row></table><note><p><s>LDP: Labcor Dokimos Plus; SFS: Sorin Freedom Solo</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1">Data according to Labcor Laboratories, Nova Granada, Brazil.<ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> Data according to LivaNova PLC, London, United Kingdom Ann Thorac Cardiovasc Surg Vol. 23, No.6 (2017)  </note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Ann Thorac Cardiovasc Surg Vol. 23, No.6 (2017)  </note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disclosure Statement</head><p><s>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hemodynamic and clinical impact of prosthesis-patient mismatch in the aortic valve position and its prevention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pibarot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Dumesnil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1131" to="1141" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Freedom SOLO valve for aortic valve replacement: clinical and hemodynamic results from a prospective multicenter trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Beholz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Repossini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Livi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Heart Valve Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long-term outcome of the Sorin Freedom SOLO stentless aortic valve</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Christ</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Claus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zielinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Heart Valve Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="679" to="684" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The St Jude Medical Trifecta aortic pericardial valve: results from a global, multicenter, prospective clinical study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bavaria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Desai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cheung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="590" to="597" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Carpentier-Edwards Perimount Magna valve versus Medtronic Hancock II: a matched hemodynamic comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Borger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Nette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maganti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Thorac Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2054" to="2058" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical outcome and hemodynamic behavior of the Labcor Dokimos Plus aortic valve</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Christ</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Zhigalov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Konertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cardiothorac Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">160</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The new Labcor-Santiago pericardial bioprosthesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Garcia-Bengochea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Casagrande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Gonzalez-Juanatey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Card Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="613" to="619" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines (writing Committee to revise the 1998 guidelines for the management of patients with valvular heart disease); Society of Cardiovascular Anesthesiologists, et al. ACC/AHA 2006 guidelines for the management of patients with valvular heart disease: a report of the American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines (writing Committee to revise the 1998 guidelines for the management of patients with valvular heart disease) developed in collaboration with the Society of cardiovascular anesthesiologists endorsed by the Society for cardiovascular angiography and interventions and the Society of thoracic surgeons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Bonow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Carabello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kanu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="e1" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>American College of Cardiology</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Operative technique and early hemodynamic results with the Freedom Solo valve</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Beholz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Claus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dushe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Heart Valve Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="429" to="432" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Are stentless valves superior to modern stented valves?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Halstead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cafferty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
