<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A Rare Intrascrotal Metastases From Renal Cell Carcinoma: A Case Report</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-10-23">23 October 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Essa</forename><surname>Adawi</surname></persName>
							<email>essa.adawi@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Urology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité University Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsklinikum</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Benjamin Franklin, Hindenburgdamm 30</addrLine>
									<postCode>12200</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A Rare Intrascrotal Metastases From Renal Cell Carcinoma: A Case Report</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-10-23">23 October 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">E353D29FB317E6F50E9B97362C67756C</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.eucr.2015.09.010</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 6 September 2015 Received in revised form 28 September 2015 Accepted 29 September 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Renal cell carcinoma Clear cell type Testicular metastasis Radical nephrectomy Radical orchiectomy</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Metastatic renal cell carcinoma is potentially a lethal disease with in some cases aggressive behavior.</s><s>The given fact that the patterns of metastases from RCC are not clearly identified, which may involve some rare metastatic locations.</s><s>We present a case of 58 years old male presented with painless left scrotal mass, which was discovered to be an intrascrotal metastases appeared 3 years after nephrectomy for ipsilateral renal cell carcinoma.</s><s>We believe that the rarity of the metastatic site and the intriguing possible mechanism of spread make an interesting case for clinicians and could add more follow-up measures for patients treated from renal cell carcinoma.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p><s>Almost 30% of renal cell carcinoma can metastasize to various organs at the time of diagnosis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref></s><s>The common organs of metastasis are the lungs 50%, bones 49%, lymph nodes 32%, skin 11%, liver 8%, and brain 3%. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> To date there are only 33 published cases in the literature of metastatic RCC to the testis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> To date there are only 33 published cases in the literature of metastatic RCC to the testis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref></s><s>This report presented the second case in the literature of pathologically proven scrotal metastasis from RCC with out testicular or epididymal invasion.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case report</head><p><s>A 58-years old male was presented with localized pain and swelling in the left hemi-scrotum for 2 months.</s><s>He had a past history of renal clear cell carcinoma pT3c G3 with adrenal metastasis and renal vein thrombosis from the left kidney after radical nephrectomy with adenectomy and renal vein thrombus removal 3 years prior to the current symptoms (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>The final histopathology showed a negative tumor margins but with positive intrarenal lymph and blood vessels invasion.</s><s>After surgery no adjuvant systemic therapy was given.</s><s>The routine follow-up imaging for the last 3 years did not show any relapse or metastases.</s><s>The physical examination revealed a non-tinder firm mass in the left hemi-scrotum.</s><s>The left testis was not attached to of the mass.</s><s>The blood work-up was within the normal range in clouding the testicular tumor markers (AFP 4.7 mg, LDH 4.3 U/l, b-HCG &lt;0.1 IU/l).</s><s>Ultrasound of the abdomen and the Scrotum revealed a 3 Â 4 Â 5 cm hyperdense mass with no evidence of testicular invasion.</s></p><p><s>Surgery was preformed through midline scrotal incision.</s><s>The tumor was intravaginal with three blood vessel connection, one lateral vessel originated from the left testis and tow superior vessels were from the epididymis.</s><s>There was no testicular invasion.</s><s>The tumor was resected with safe margins and was sent for histopathological examination.</s><s>No orchiectomy was preformed.</s><s>Macroscopically it was 8 Â 4 Â 3.5 cm firm specimen.</s><s>There was no involvement to the testis, tunicas, paratesticular soft tissue, or spermatic cord.</s><s>Microscopically revealed partial eosinophilia partial clear cell solid neoplasia in a fibrous soft tissue with microscopic capillary networks.</s><s>The tumor cells contain eosinophilic cytoplasm.</s><s>The nuclei were prominent and parts of the nuclear pleomorphism were matching a Fuhrman nuclear grade 4. The tumor cells did not expressed vitamins, alkaline phosphatase and were CD10 negative (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</s><s>Because of the unusual presentation, an immunopathological phenotype examination of the mass was compared with the one of the renal cell tumor diagnosed 3 years earlier that showed a good match.</s><s>Thus the final impression was a scrotal metastasis of clear cell renal carcinoma.</s><s>Three weeks post operatively the patient was readmitted with scrotal abscess, which was treated with surgical evacuation and drainage.</s><s>Again the testis was also spared from removal.</s><s>Three, six and 12 months follow-up MRI showed no evidence of recurrence or metastases.</s><s>The patient is doing well and till the date of this report no adjuvant systemic therapy was given.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Metastases to the testis are rare because of low temperature in the scrotum that theoretically might reduce the tumor cells growth. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s>Furthermore, the fact that the testis has a blood testis barrier formed by Sertoli cells adds another defense mechanism that inhibits tumor growth. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s>Prostate cancer is considered the most frequent primary tumor that can metastasis to the testis, probably because orchiectomy is a modality of treating metastatic prostate cancer that could lead to isolating more testicular metastases. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Renal cell carcinoma commonly results in metastasis to different organs, yet rarely to the testis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s>Looking to the literature, using PubMed and Google scholar, the previous reported 33 cases descried an intratesticuler invasion of the metastasis from the renal cell carcinoma.</s><s>The feature of the presented case is twofold: first we report the second case known in the literature of extra-testicular invasion, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> and the presence of renal vain thrombosis suggests the retrograde descent of tumor cells through the testicular veins as the mechanism of the metastases. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> As it is extremely rare for renal cell carcinoma to metastasis to the testes, patients are incorrectly assumed to have independent testicular mass. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref></s><s>The given fact that our patient was 58 years old and because of the ultrasound findings which exclude a direct testicular invasion the probability of a germ or non-germ cell tumors was unlikely.</s><s>Non-Hodgkin lymphoma remains the most suspected diagnoses in patients older than 50 <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> ; however, in our patient the past history of relatively advanced Renal cell carcinoma with renal vein invasion raise the possibility of metastatic disease and directed the therapy plan.</s></p><p><s>Many previous attempts tried to understand the mechanisms of spread of renal cell carcinoma to the testis but it remained unclear.</s><s>In many reports they suggests one of tow mechanisms.</s><s>The first is through retrograde descent of tumor cells through the testicular veins. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s>This theory might be justified in the left ipsilateral renal tumor.</s><s>However, given the differences in both sides anatomy, it is difficult to implement the same theory to the right side.</s><s>Researchers argued that right side or bilateral testicular metastases are observed via Batson venous complex. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> In our case the primary kidney and the scrotal metastasis are in the same left side, and therefore the spread through the testicular vein is more acceptable.</s><s>It is, therefore, directing us to include scrotal ultrasound to the routine follow-up protocol for patient with left renal vein thrombosis.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>This case represents a rare pattern of metastatic renal cell carcinoma to the Scrotum.</s><s>Nonetheless, it gives the first evidence to including a routine scrotal ultrasound examinations in our followup plans for renal cell carcinoma patients with renal vein thrombosis, especially in the left side.</s><s>Although this review is based on case report, it highlights the significance of case reporting especially in rare oncological scenarios where clinic trials or even case series are not possible.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Scrotal metastasis from renal cell carcinoma (RCC).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,30.22,50.80,239.13,192.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Abdominal MRI showing a left renal mass, (arrow) renal vein thrombosis.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,31.24,468.68,239.13,202.11" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p><s>There is no conflict of interest to declare.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simultaneous contralateral testiculer metastasis from a renal cell carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Heimbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pakos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Muller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scand J Urol Nephrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="136" to="e137" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simultaneous bilateral testicular metastases from renal clear cell carcinoma: a case report and review of the literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Moriyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Takeshit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Adachi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncol Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1273" to="e1275" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Secondary tumor of the testis: tow cases and a review of the literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Blrfari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Risi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pino</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Urol Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="469" to="e470" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Late intrascrotal metastasis from renal cell carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Selli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Woodard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Paulson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Urology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="e425" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sternberg&apos;s Diagnostic Surgical Pathology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ulbright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Greenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Oberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Philadelphia</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2168" to="e2190" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Testicular and Paratesticular Tumors. 4th ed</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
