<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Site-specific chromosomal gene insertion: Flp recombinase versus Cas9 nuclease</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Vinh</forename><surname>Quang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Phan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies (BCRT)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Föhrer Strasse 15</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biomaterial Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Helmholtz-Zentrum Geesthacht (HZG)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>14513</postCode>
									<settlement>Teltow</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jörg</forename><surname>Contzen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies (BCRT)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Föhrer Strasse 15</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biomaterial Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Helmholtz-Zentrum Geesthacht (HZG)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>14513</postCode>
									<settlement>Teltow</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Petra</forename><surname>Seemann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies (BCRT)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Föhrer Strasse 15</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Augustenburger Platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Manfred</forename><surname>Gossen</surname></persName>
							<email>manfred.gossen@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies (BCRT)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Föhrer Strasse 15</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biomaterial Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Helmholtz-Zentrum Geesthacht (HZG)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>14513</postCode>
									<settlement>Teltow</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Labor für Pädiatrische Molekularbiologie</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Site-specific chromosomal gene insertion: Flp recombinase versus Cas9 nuclease</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BA8BC2206DE897AD0ED9596365688E2F</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41598-017-17651-0</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 13 June 2017 Accepted: 24 November 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Site</head><p><s>-specific recombination systems like those based on the Flp recombinase proved themselves as efficient tools for cell line engineering.</s><s>The recent emergence of designer nucleases, especially RNA guided endonucleases like Cas9, has considerably broadened the available toolbox for applications like targeted transgene insertions.</s><s>Here we established a recombinase-mediated cassette exchange (RMCE) protocol for the fast and effective, drug-free isolation of recombinant cells.</s><s>Distinct fluorescent protein patterns identified the recombination status of individual cells.</s><s>In derivatives of a CHO master cell line the expression of the introduced transgene of interest could be dramatically increased almost 20-fold by subsequent deletion of the fluorescent protein gene that provided the initial isolation principle.</s></p><p><s>The same master cell line was employed in a comparative analysis using CRISPR/Cas9 for transgene integration in identical loci.</s><s>Even though the overall targeting efficacy was comparable, multi-loci targeting was considerably more effective for Cas9-mediated transgene insertion when compared to RMCE.</s><s>While Cas9 is inherently more flexible, our results also alert to the risk of aberrant recombination events around the cut site.</s><s>Together, this study points at the individual strengths in performance of both systems and provides guidance for their appropriate use.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>The accurate, site-specific genetic manipulation of mammalian chromosomes remains a technical challenge.</s><s>This holds true for targeted insertions, deletions or substitutions of DNA that can range in size from entire chromosomal regions to individual nucleotides.</s><s>The challenges include limiting genome alterations exclusively to the target site, to obtain reasonably high targeting efficacy in a reliable manner, and to successfully select engineered cells.</s><s>Homologous recombination solely based on extended sequence identity between the exogenous donor and the endogenous acceptor locus is widely employed.</s><s>However, this strategy is restricted to selected cell types like certain mouse embryonic stem cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> .</s><s>In contrast, site-specific targeting based on recombinases like Cre, Flp or Phi (see reference <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> for a recent review) has been used for decades without apparent cell type preferences.</s><s>While these recombinase systems are widely employed for cell line engineering, they inevitably require the prior establishment of master cell lines genetically engineered to contain suitably arranged recombinase recognition sites as chromosomal targets, also referred to as "landing pads".</s><s>Such master cell lines are the starting point for the construction of isogenic cell lines, which are genetically almost identical aside from small, defined alterations, comprising the genetic element of interest.</s><s>This can, for example, be an expression control sequences like a promoter or a gene of interest (GOI).</s><s>For the analysis of regulatory genetic elements the main conceptual advantage for the use of recombinase-mediated targeting to predetermined loci is to minimize integration site effects on the experimental readout between different isogenic lines <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> .</s><s>Such genetic elements are never truly autonomous and subject to proximal chromatin structures as well as regulatory signals located in cis.</s><s>However, comparative analyses in isogenic lines would impose the same external influences on all the regulatory elements to be analysed.</s><s>In contrast, the repeated insertion of different protein-encoding genes in the same, pre-characterised chromosomal site is frequently applied in biotechnological research, including the establishment of production cell lines for biologics.</s><s>Here, the main rational behind this strategy is that a high producer line, once identified in an often tedious and time consuming process, can be re-utilized for the production of another gene product, while the favourable characteristics of the original cell line are preserved <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> .</s><s>Such recombinase-mediated, site-specific insertion of DNA fragments in mammalian chromosomes can be achieved by integration of the entire donor vectors (DV) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> or by cassette exchange methods like RMCE <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> ).</s><s>The latter process involves the substitution of segments of the chromosomally integrated landing pad-containing vector (LPV) by matching DV segments.</s><s>This reaction requires only short recombinase recognition sites engineered properly in both, the target region on the chromosome and the incoming DV.</s></p><p><s>Several of the engineering strategies outlined so far can also be realized using the more recently developed designer nucleases <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> .</s><s>Their use for site-specific chromosomal DNA insertion provides greater flexibility in target site selection when compared to a recombinase strategy.</s><s>DNA double-strand cuts by these nucleases close to the intended insertion site facilitate a homology-driven repair (HDR) mechanism, provided that a properly designed DV that contains the insert flanked by homology arms identical to the chromosomal sequences around the actual cut site is present <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> .</s><s>Such alternative strategies, especially the use of RNA-guided engineered nucleases (RGENs) like in Clustered Regularly Interspaced Short Palindromic Repeats/CRISPR-associated protein-9 nuclease (CRISPR/Cas9) genome editing, can substantially speed up targeted insertions when no premade master cell lines are available.</s></p><p><s>Here we established a RMCE protocol in which recombination events can be monitored and isolated by following expression of fluorescent marker proteins.</s><s>This procedure proved highly efficient to obtain cell lines with homogenous, phenotypically stable transgene expression.</s><s>A side-by-side comparison to CRISPR/Cas9-mediated targeting of the same chromosomal loci showed comparable efficiencies of donor vector integration.</s><s>However, when two potential integration sites were present in a given cell, striking differences between the recombinaseand the nuclease-based genome engineering systems were observed, with CRISPR/Cas9 having a much higher capacity to simultaneously modify multiple loci at a time.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Targeted Chromosomal Transgene Integration: Vector Design Rationales.</s><s>As a general strategy to monitor site-specific donor integration in a preselected chromosomal target, the landing pad, we chose to follow the expression of two spectral distinct fluorescent proteins.</s><s>The favourable properties of stable cell lines isolated via cell sorting according to fluorescent protein gene expression are well established <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> .</s><s>Here, the switch was from the landing pad vector (LPV)-encoded green fluorescent protein (GFP) to a red fluorescent protein (RFP).</s><s>For Flp-mediated RMCE outlined in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, top, two heterospecific Flp recombination targets (FRT sites) <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> were included in the LPV.</s><s>A FRT wt site was placed 5′ within the GFP open reading frame and a FRT F3 3′ to the LPV transcription units.</s><s>Corresponding FRT sites in the donor vector for RMCE (DV RMCE ) were placed 5′ to the truncated RFP coding sequence lacking a promoter and a translation start codon (FRT wt ) and 3′ to the GOI (FRT F3 ), respectively.</s><s>This design allowed to distinguish between targeted and random chromosomal integration of the incoming RFP-derived marker construct.</s><s>Functional RFP expression will only occur after recruitment of the ATG start codon of LPV's GFP gene via in-frame targeted integration(i.</s><s>e. an ATG and promoter trap <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref> ).</s></p><p><s>Several other features to enhance the sensitivity, versatility and utility of the matched RMCE vector combination were included in the design.</s><s>(i) The expression of the GFP gene within the LPV is controlled by the human elongation factor 1 alpha (hEF1α) promoter.</s><s>We have previously shown that this promoter favours high level, homogenous transgene expression, especially long term, in the absence of antibiotic selection <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> .</s><s>(ii) A N-terminal nuclear localisation signal (NLS) is located 5′ to the GFP-embedded FRT wt .</s><s>Nuclear accumulation of the fluorescent protein makes it easier to recognize low GFP levels against the cellular auto-fluorescence background <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> .</s><s>This subcellular localisation feature will also pass on to the incoming RFP construct.</s><s>This allows to stringently assess if a given red fluorescence signal observed originates from a targeted integration event (i.e.</s><s>nuclear signal) or from the accidental acquisition of transcription/translation start signals via random integration, which in all likelihood would result in a non-localized signal.</s><s>(iii) A GFP version with a C-terminal degradation domain (d2EGFP; d2 refers to a protein half-life of 2 hours) <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> will result in faster GFP signal depletion after a DV RMCE integration event.</s><s>(iv) A PGK promoter driven positive/negative selection marker (+/−, here a puromycin/thymidine kinase gene -PuroTK) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref> is included in the LPV, in case preparative fluorescence activated cell sorting (FACS) for exchange events will not be possible or practical.</s><s>TK gene expression conveys sensitivity to Gancilovir.</s><s>Thus, addition of this nucleoside analogue can be employed to monitor the absence of the PuroTK gene expected upon RMCE, eliminating site-specific insertion events of the whole DV RMCE plasmid, which could in principle occur via recombinase action on FRT wt alone <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> , that would result in GFP − /RFP + /PuroTK + cells, or, in case integration via FRT F3 only, in GFP + /RFP − /PuroTK + cells.</s><s>(v) LoxP sites in both the LPV and DV are positioned such that the newly created RFP transcription unit, which is created upon successful RMCE, can be deleted via Cre-mediated excision <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref> .</s><s>(vi) Stop codons that immediately precede the DV RMCE 's FRT wt site are positioned in all three potential reading frames <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref> , to further preclude accidental RFP expression upon random integration in a promoter/ATG-trap constellation <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref> .</s><s>(vii) The DV RMCE also contains a transcription unit for the actual gene-of-interest (GOI) for the respective study, which in the standard configuration is driven by the hEF1α promoter for the reasons outlined above <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> .</s><s>(viii) Lastly, the LPV transcription units are integrated in a self-inactivating lentiviral backbone in opposite orientation to the LTR-directed transcription.</s><s>Recombinant lentiviral particles not only facilitate highly efficient transduction of most mammalian cell lines, they also allow a fair command over integration copy number.</s><s>In addition, the reverse orientation permits inclusion of unidirectional polyadenylation signals as well as an intron-containing hEF1α promoter in the virus, without premature termination or internal truncations of the viral genomic RNA.</s><s>The resulting drop in viral titer when compared to LTR codirectionality <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26</ref> was substantial, but manageable in our experiments.</s></p><p><s>The principle functionality of the proposed recombination scheme was initially established in an all-transient transfection experiment (i.e.</s><s>co-transfection of LPV, DV RMCE and Flp expression vectors).</s><s>Only upon Flp expression red fluorescent cells emerged, indicative of successful recombination between LPV and DV RMCE (suppl.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Characterisation of CHO RMCE master clones.</head><p><s>The utility of a RMCE system for facilitating cell line engineering depends largely on the availability of high quality LPV + master cell lines that allow the repeated insertion of highly expressed GOIs under standardized conditions.</s><s>As the cellular background we chose Chinese Hamster Ovary (CHO) cells, one of the workhorses of recombinant protein production <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> .</s><s>CHO cells were transduced with the LPV lentivirus.</s><s>Clonal LPV + isolates were obtained via preparative FACS/single cell deposition of GFP + cells.</s><s>Clones with a bright and homogenous GFP signal after initial expansion were pre-screened for a high RMCE frequency by transfection with DV RMCE /Flp expression vector, using the frequency of RFP + cells as a first readout.</s><s>A total of eleven clones that showed GFP/RFP profiles expected from RMCE occurring at either a single copy proviral LPV (two clones) or ≥ two copies proviral LPVs (nine clones) were initially identified and one clone of each of these two subgroups was characterised in more detail.</s><s>GFP/RFP profiles of the DV RMCE / Flp expression vector-transfected CHO.S15 RMCE cell pool indicated a single LPV integration event (&lt;0.1% recorded GFP + /RFP + events; suppl.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2</ref>).</s><s>By contrast, when CHO.S18 cells were transfected in the same way, the majority of RFP + cells remained positive for GFP (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2a</ref>).</s><s>Thus, more than one LPV copy must have been integrated.</s><s>Subsequent analysis via next generation sequencing confirmed two independent proviral integrations in these CHO.S18 cells (see suppl.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S3</ref> for details).</s><s>This clone also showed the highest phenotypic stability, as only very few GFP − cells emerging after prolonged culture in absence of antibiotic selection (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2a</ref>; see suppl.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2</ref>, CHO.S15, for comparison).</s><s>Aside from this stability issue, the dual LPV integration CHO.S18 line was chosen as the master clone for subsequent experiments going beyond the RMCE experiments already shown, as it allows the comparative analysis with HDR in addressing multi-loci targeting efficiency (see below).</s><s>Beyond the phenotypic selection for RFP + cells, we verified the accurate cassette exchange for a CHO.S18 subclone (CHO.</s><s>S18-R) with integrated DV RMCE by multiplex PCR specific for the expected RMCE events (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2b</ref>, left panel).</s><s>The absence of the 537 bp PCR band specific for the original LPV + master cell line locus demonstrated the successful cassette exchange in both chromosomal LPVs in the analysed clone, as expected from its GFP − /RFP + phenotype.</s><s>However, in a minority of the total events we examined, the GFP − /RFP + phenotype was attributed to mixed RMCE/transgene insertion events, where in one locus the entire DV RMCE was integrated via FRT wt .</s><s>Such recombination events leave the chromosomal PuroTK gene intact and result in continued Gancicolvir sensitivity (suppl.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S4</ref>).</s><s>As for the GFP + /RFP + cells with only one LPV targeted, results from a preliminary analysis by another multiplex PCR approach suggests that there is no pronounced bias for one of the two LPV copies as the preferred target for RMCE (suppl.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S5</ref>).</s><s>Lastly, we confirmed the possibility to eliminate the RFP transcription unit that is generated upon RMCE by Cre-mediated deletion (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Heterologous expression of hBMP-2.</head><p><s>The GOI encoded in the particular DV RMCE employed in the previous experiments, except the experiment shown in supplemental figure S1, was human Bone Morphogenic Protein-2 (hBMP-2).</s><s>BMP-2 is an osteoinductive growth factor and FDA approved for the treatment of open tibial fractures and maxillofacial bones defects as well as for the induction of spinal fusions <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> .</s><s>While we did not intend to establish a preparative experimental setting for recombinant hBMP-2 production, quantification of secretion of this growth factor was used to monitor expression of a GOI along the suggested RMCE protocol, beyond the analysis of fluorescent reporter patterns only.</s><s>Immunoblot analysis for rhBMP-2 was performed for CHO.S18 cells (rhBMP-2 − ), as well as CHO.S18-R and CHO.S18-RΔRFP cells, both rhBMP-2 + (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3a</ref>) The secreted rhBMP-2 was apparently in its biologically active, mature dimeric form, as indicated by a blot signal that corresponded to the expected molecular weight of a dimer under non-reducing conditions.</s><s>Most remarkably, when compared to CHOS18-R cells, we observed a very substantial increase of almost 20-fold in rhBMP-2 secretion for CHO.S18-RΔRFP cells, where the RFP transcription unit that preceded the hBMP-2 gene was deleted.</s><s>Of note, this Cre-mediated deletion did not alter the hBMP-2 transcription unit itself (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>This effect of strongly elevated secretion levels in CHO.S18-RΔRFP cells was also confirmed by an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3b</ref>) for rhBMP-2 in the culture supernatant.</s><s>Lastly, the biological activity of the rhBMP-2 produced by CHO.S18-RΔRFP cells was demonstrated by its ability to induce differentiation towards osteoblasts of C2C12 myoblast cells, as demonstrated by increased alkaline phosphatase (ALP) activity (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3c</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Targeting of the LPV via CRISPR/Cas9.</s><s>We identified chromosomal loci that permit high-level, continued transgene expression in mammalian cells, which can be effectively retargeted via Flp-mediated RMCE.</s><s>Such a cell line offers the opportunity to ask whether RMCE or more recently emerging technologies that allow the targeting of defined chromosomal loci with high precision have different performance characteristics.</s><s>To this end, we used a CRISPR/Cas9 approach to integrate a specially designed donor vector in the LPV of CHO.</s><s>S18 cells.</s><s>Our experimental strategy is outlined in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4a</ref>.</s><s>A sgRNA that directed efficient Cas9 cutting 3′ to the NLS of the LPV-encoded GFP was identified, monitored both by a T7E1 assay as well as the knock-out inactivation of the LPV GFP reporter gene as functional criteria (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4b,c</ref>).</s><s>The position of the actual double-strand break determined the insert-proximal ends of the left and right homology arms (HA-L and HA-R, see suppl.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6</ref> for details) in the DV HDR , which was tailor-made for this endonuclease site.</s><s>Other than DV RMCE , the DV HDR itself contains a functional transcription unit for the RFP reporter.</s><s>This is due to the requirement for rather long homology arms, which in the case of HA-L spans over the translation start site and promoter.</s><s>DV HDR together with an expression vector for Cas9 and the NLS-GFP-specific sgRNA were transfected into CHO.S18 cells.</s><s>After 9 days, dual parameter GFP − /RFP + flow cytometry single cell sorting was employed (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5a</ref>).</s><s>Twelve clones that gave a homogenous RFP signal upon microscopic inspection were otherwise randomly selected.</s><s>Site-specific integration was analysed by PCR (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5b</ref>), as random chromosomal integration of DV HDR would also result in a RFP signal.</s><s>Noteworthy, we identified in all clones analysed at least one LPV targeting event.</s><s>In 7/12 clones DV HDR was inserted in both copies of the LPV.</s><s>In 3/12 only one copy of LPV was targeted, the other apparently inactivated for GFP expression via non-homologous end joining (NHEJ).</s><s>In 2/12 clones the PCR pattern indicated an irregular integration event for one of the LPV copies.</s><s>Subsequent sequence analysis revealed sequence additions of CHO genomic DNA and a vector fragment of the transfected plasmid, respectively, both directly adjacent to the cutting site (suppl.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure">S7</ref>).</s><s>In summary, CRISPR/Cas9-directed HDR also allowed efficient targeting of LPV in CHO.</s><s>S18 cells.</s><s>Side-by-side comparison RMCE vs. HDR.</s><s>The analysis of RMCE vs. HDR conducted so far pointed at principle differences in the performance of these transgene insertion systems, which were particular evident when multiple targets were present in a cell line.</s><s>However, the experiments presented so far (Figs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">2 and 5</ref>) were based on different transfection and cell enrichment strategies.</s><s>For a more meaningful analysis of targeting efficiencies side-by-side lipofection of the CHO.S18 LPV + line was performed.</s><s>While keeping the plasmid inputs comparable, no subsequent antibiotic selection or enrichment of transfected cells by cell sorting was employed, and cells were grown out for 9 days.</s><s>As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref>, transfection of CHO.S18 cells with only DV RMCE did not yield, as expected, any RFP + cells (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6b</ref>), as DV RMCE requires Flp-mediated LPV targeting for activity.</s><s>In contrast, transfection of the intact transcription unit contained in DV HDR resulted in about 0.2% RFP + cells (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6e</ref>).</s><s>Given a transient transfection efficiency of &gt;30% in this series of experiments we observed a stable, most likely random transgene integration of less than 1% of the successfully transfected cells.</s><s>Expression of Flp alone in the CHO.S18 cells resulted in a low but distinct (&lt;0.2%) population of GFP − cells (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6c</ref>), which might reflect residual recombination between FRT wt and FRT F3 sites <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> .</s><s>As expected, in absence of DV HDR co-expression of Cas9 and the NLS-GFP-specific sgRNA resulted in a functional knockout via NHEJ of the LPV target, here in about one third to half of the actually transfected cells (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6f</ref>).</s><s>Transfection in a RMCE setting (DV RMCE + Flp) resulted in targeting events (i.</s><s>e. RFP + cells) in 4 to 5% of the total cells (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6a</ref>).</s><s>However, only in about one fifth of those cells both GFP transgenes were inactivated (GFP − /RFP + ).</s><s>In sharp contrast, whereas transfection in a HDR setting (DV HDR + sgRNA/Cas9) resulted in somewhat less efficient LPV targeting (in 1.5 to 2% of the total cells), in &gt;80% of those recorded events both of the LPV loci were hit, either by insertion or knock-out (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6d</ref>).</s><s>However, while these results provide a rough estimate of overall engineering efficacies, we also like to stress the limitations of this semi-quantitative comparative analysis.</s><s>Not only might results substantially differ when using other cell lines, but also the exact ratio of recombination donors and expression levels for recombinases/nucleases plus sgRNAs have to be taken into account.</s><s>Nevertheless, the focus on identical target sites for transgene integration in the exemplary CHO.S18 master cell line, and largely similar results for other multi-LPV clones analysed in the course of this study, provides valuable insights in performance characteristics of both the genome engineering systems analysed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Progress in genome engineering technology results in a constantly increasing choice of available tools, which often lack direct comparison, both quantitatively and qualitatively.</s><s>Given the different underlying modes of action of the enzymes employed, one would not necessarily expect one of these tools to emerge as the "one-serves-all" solution.</s><s>Here we explored a Flp recombinase-based cassette exchange mechanism and Cas9-based, HDR-mediated transgene insertion in an identical recipient cell line, in which the same insertion loci were targeted.</s><s>Initially established for a RMCE protocol, our experimental design allowed for the rapid and efficient isolation of targeting event by following a switch in fluorescent protein expression.</s><s>The strategy pursued by us works efficiently even without the use of any supportive antibiotic selection.</s><s>Cell lines created by drug selection protocols often show heterogeneous transgene expression patterns and silencing of the transgene over time <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> .</s><s>Especially in combination with a growth disadvantage for high expressing cells, this can lead to a decrease in transgene expression levels <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31</ref> .</s><s>Due to dynamic epigenetic effects that manifest themselves also in dependence of cell types, the nature of transcription signals, integration sites and other variables, these problems often persist even after isolation of cell clones with initially favourable characteristics <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33</ref> .</s><s>In this current study the donor vector contained no antibiotic selection marker.</s><s>While the design of the landing pad vector allowed for an antibiotic-based positive/negative selection scheme <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34</ref> , such a selection was not an integral part of our routine cell line engineering protocol.</s><s>Instead, desired features of transgene expression like stability of transgene expression over time and homogeneity served as integral parts of the clonal isolation strategy.</s><s>While we did not systematically analyse RMCE cell pools for genetic homogeneity and phenotypic stability, both the PCR and analytical flow cytometry results suggested that at least for some applications omission of clonal isolation would not compromise transgene expression in a major way.</s><s>Other antibiotic-free protocols for cell line engineering rely on the recombinase-mediated deletion of fluorescence markers directly linked to transgene activation.</s><s>Following this paradigm we previously generated clones and showed uniform expression patterns as well as remarkably high-level of transgene expression over a time course of 100 population doublings <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> .</s><s>Alternatively, techniques like the cold-capture selection method employ the transiently enhanced accumulation of the secreted protein of interest itself on the cell surface for isolating high-producing cell lines with good success <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36</ref> .</s><s>In the first PCR analysis (upper panel; primers P-HDR-1 and P-HDR-2, see suppl.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure">S9</ref> for details) the PCR product of 1,596 bp is indicative for successful HDR events.</s><s>In the second PCR analysis (lower panel; primers P-HDR-1 and P-HDR-3, see suppl.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure">S9</ref> for details) the entire targeted segment is amplified.</s><s>Successful homologous recombination events result in an approximately 3,702 bp PCR product, whereas parental loci as well as NHEJ indels will result in a 2,825 bp PCR product.</s><s>Irregular recombination events (red stars) could be detected in two cases.</s><s>(P: parental clone CHO.S18).</s><s>The uncropped gel pictures are shown in suppl.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S11d</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Subsequent to the analysis of the DV RMCE integration in the CHO cells we quantified the expression of hBMP-2 gene, chosen as the GOI for this study.</s><s>Most strikingly, we found a very substantial increase in GOI expression (almost 20-fold) after the loxP/Cre-mediated excision of the RFP transcription unit.</s><s>We consider implausible that under the given experimental conditions and without an observed change in growth parameters the relief from an extra consumption of metabolic resources (also referred to as "metabolic burden" <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38</ref> ) caused the increase in hBMP-2 synthesis.</s><s>Transcriptional interference in the tandem constellation of promoters before RFP deletion is likely to contribute to the observed effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39</ref> , despite the separation of the transcription units by an effective termination signal <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40</ref> .</s><s>It remains unclear, though, what other factors might influence the steep increase in GOI expression.</s><s>However, the possibility to insert modified DVs to the landing pad provides the opportunity for a mechanistic analysis of the observed effects and has to be addressed in future experiments.</s><s>Using the same transgene expression and RMCE approach in an unrelated research project, we observed that the expression of hOct4 in an macrophage precursor cell line also increased to a comparable extent when the 5′ preceding fluorescence marker gene was deleted (suppl.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure">S8</ref>).</s><s>Thus, while the magnitude of the RFP deletion-effect on hBMP-2 expression might be related to our vector design, it is neither cell type nor integration site specific.</s></p><p><s>Next we asked whether using Cas9 to facilitate HDR-mediated transgene insertion in a landing pad is able to compete in terms of efficacy with Flp in a LPV + cell line optimized for RMCE.</s><s>Obviously, RGEN technology can satisfy experimental demands that cannot be addressed by recombinases, like direct gene knock-outs or gene repair.</s><s>Also with respect to transgene insertion/replacement RGENs and other programmable nucleases could be advantageous for directed chromosomal insertions, as for several applications this strategy might allow for cell line engineering without prior establishment of master cell lines.</s><s>The targeting of the LPV loci by a CRISPR/Cas9 approach required the design of a different donor vector (DV HDR ) with suitable homology arms.</s><s>As with DV RMCE , use of this vector allowed to monitor successful integration events by loss of the GFP signal and a concomitant gain in RFP signal.</s><s>However, a random integration of DV HDR would also result in a RFP signal.</s><s>In practice though, this turned out not be a major limitation.</s><s>Under unselected experimental conditions the Cas9-facilitated HDR process was about tenfold more frequent than random integration (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref>, HDR panels: DV HDR + sgRNA/Cas9 vs. DV HDR only).</s><s>The chosen experimental setting allowed for a direct comparison, Flp vs. Cas9, of integration frequencies at the LPV loci.</s><s>According to the isolation of the LPV + master cell line we expected the fluorescent protein signals from integration sites to favour not only high and stable transgene expression but also high recombination efficiency.</s><s>This interrelation has been described in more detail before <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41</ref> .</s><s>However, it is understood that any absolute comparison in integration efficiency beyond our use of identical target sites would require a systematic experimental optimisation.</s><s>One would have to address the available nuclear amounts and ratios of donor vector and recombinase (in case of RMCE) or sgRNA-loaded Cas9 protein (in case of HDR).</s><s>Previous work demonstrated the importance of this aspect for both HDR <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43</ref> and RMCE <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45</ref> .</s></p><p><s>Contrary to the HDR reaction, Flp-mediated recombination does not require additional host factors, nor does it involve nucleolytic activities or DNA synthesis.</s><s>Thus, one might consider recombinase-mediated DNA insertion a "mild" form of genotoxic stress, whereas both NHEJ and nuclease-facilitated HDR involve the generation of DNA double-strand breaks with free DNA ends 2 .</s><s>This processing is instrumental for knockout strategies using RGENs on the one hand, but might be an issue for HDR-mediated genome engineering.</s><s>Notably, aberant recombination was observed in 2 out of 12 cell clones categorized by us as successful recombinants according to phenotypic criteria.</s><s>Both cases involved the integration of additional DNA sequences in the immediate vicinity of the sgRNA/Cas9 cut site.</s><s>Of note, in one case the additional sequence originated from an input plasmid, while in the other affected clone the extra DNA was a chromosomal hamster DNA fragment.</s><s>Such aberrant events were observed before for CRISPR/Cas-mediated gene insertions <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46</ref> .</s><s>They may have little practical implications for biotechnologically driven cell line engineering and its relative ease of validation, but are worth further attention in more complex experimental settings, including gene repair strategies.</s></p><p><s>The most striking result of the comparative part of the analysis presented here was the differences between Flpand Cas9-mediated genome engineering in targeting multiple copies of a given transgene, here the LPV present in two copies in the master cell line.</s><s>For Cas9-facilitated HDR, the majority of the bona fide integration events result in the targeting of both loci.</s><s>Note that the RFP + /GFP − phenotype was not necessarily indicative of DV HDR insertion in both transgenes (PCR analysis Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>: 7/12), but can be a mixture transgene insertion in one copy and knock-out of the other LPV copy via NHEJ (PCR analysis Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>: 3/12).</s><s>This is in sharp contrast to our results for RMCE (or in rare cases DV RMCE insertion), where the simultaneous targeting of both loci is rather the exception.</s><s>This principle difference between the two targeting technologies extended to all CHO.S-type clones with more than one LPV that were analysed by us.</s><s>A high efficiency to simultaneously engineer both alleles of a given gene in mice via Cas9 has been described, both for gene knock-outs <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47</ref> as well as HDR-modifications <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> and is mirrored by the high efficiency in multiplexing strategies that involve the simultaneous use of multiple sgRNAs at the same time <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50</ref> .</s></p><p><s>Notwithstanding the rising popularity or RGEN technology, targeted transgene insertion by site-specific recombinases like Flp remains a powerful genome engineering tool.</s><s>Recent efforts in redirecting recombinases to endogenous chromosomal sites, either via protein evolution approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52</ref> or fusion to designer DNA binding moieties <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53</ref> might develop into attractive alternatives for ever more efficient and reliable genome engineering in biotechnology and biomedicine.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p><s>Gene synthesis, cloning procedures and vector nomenclature.</s><s>Synthetic DNA fragments used for the generation of the LPV and the different DVs were provided by Entelechon GmbH and assembled using standard cloning procedures.</s><s>All restriction enzymes and cloning kits were purchased from New England Biolabs (NEB) and used accordingly to the manufacture's instruction.</s><s>As for the nomenclature, only one LPV construct and one DV HDR construct were employed in the study and are referred to accordingly.</s><s>By contrast, three different DVs were employed in the analysis of RMCE, with DV RMCE used as a generic name, and DV RMCE (MCS), DV RMCE (hBMP-2) and DV RMCE (hOct4) to specify the detailed GOI/MCS where appropriate.</s></p><p><s>Cell culture.</s><s>CHO-K1 (ATCC:CCL-61) and CHO-derived stable cell lines were cultivated in RMPI 1640 medium (Gibco) supplemented with 10% heat inactivated FCS and 100 µg/ml of penicillin/streptomycin in a humidified incubator at 37 °C with a 5% CO 2 atmosphere.</s><s>HAFTL cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54</ref> were cultured under the same conditions, but medium was further supplied with 50 mM beta-mercaptoethanol (βME).</s><s>C2C12 cells (ATCC: CRL-1772) were cultivated in DMEM supplemented with 10% FCS, 2 mM Glutamine, 100 µg/ml of penicillin/streptomycin. HEK 293TN (System Biosciences; LV900A-1) were cultivated in Advanced DMEM (Gibco) supplemented with 2% FCS, 0.01 mM cholesterol, 0.01 mM lecithin and 1:100 chemical defined lipid concentrate.</s><s>Fluorescence microscopy image acquisition was done by the Axio Observer.Z1 (Zeiss) and its imaging software AxioVision 4.7.2 (12-2008).</s></p><p><s>Analytical flow cytometry and cell sorting.</s><s>Cells for analytical flow cytometry and FACS sort were prepared as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55</ref> .</s><s>Flow cytometry analysis was done on the Becton Dickinson (BD) Accuri C6 flow cytometer (Filter: GFP 533/30 and RFP 610/20) and for preparative FACS, cells were sorted with BD FACSAria II.</s></p><p><s>Lentiviral packaging and titration.</s><s>Lentiviral vectors were packaged in HEK293TN cells and virus titer was determined as previous described <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56</ref> .</s><s>Cell culture supernatant containing recombinant virions were filtered through 0.45 µm filter and concentrated using Lenti-X (Clontech) following the manufacturer's instruction.</s></p><p><s>LPV cell line creation.</s><s>LPV cell lines were generated by lentiviral transduction.</s><s>The MOI was adjusted to 0.1 to ensure low number of integrated proviruses.</s><s>Cells were seeded in a 12-well plate with growth medium supplemented with 8 µg/ml polybrene (Sigma).</s><s>24 hours after seeding, lentiviral particles were added to the cells and incubated for 16-18 hours before medium change.</s><s>GFP positive cells were sorted using FACSAria single cell deposition <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> .</s><s>Clones were picked and analysed via flow cytometry and selected based on their strength, homogeneity and persistence of the GFP signal.</s></p><p><s>PCR and T7E1 assay.</s><s>PCRs for cloning and T7 Endonuclease I (T7E1; NEB) assay were performed with the Q5 PCR Mastermix kit.</s><s>For PCRs with amplicons longer than 3 kbp, the LongAmp Taq PCR kit was used.</s><s>Both PCR kits are distributed by NEB and optimal annealing temperatures were determined by the NEB Tm Calculator (http://tmcalculator.neb.com).</s><s>PCR programs were set according to the manufacturer's instructions.</s><s>T7E1 assays were performed as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57</ref> .</s><s>Cleaved DNA fragments were separated on a 2% agarose gel and stained with Syto60 staining solution (1:9,000) for 45 minutes while shaking.</s><s>Gels were analysed on the Odyssey infrared imaging system (Li-cor) using the manufacturer's software and the DNA concentration of each band was quantified using the ImageJ software.</s><s>Percent values of indels were calculated as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49</ref> .</s></p><p><s>Transfections.</s><s>Prior to stable RMCE experiments, the RMCE strategy was tested in transient transfections.</s></p><p><s>HEK293TN cells were co-transfected with DV RMCE , LPV, and a Flippase plasmid.</s><s>This Flp expression vector was derived from of pCAGGS-Flpe-puro (Addgene #20733) and modified by substituting the puromycin resistance gene by a blue fluorescent protein (BFP) marker, facilitating the isolation of transfected cells by preparative FACS, if desired.</s><s>One day prior to transfection, 4 × 10 5 HEK293TN cells per well were seeded in a 6-well plate.</s><s>A total of 2 µg plasmid DNA was mixed in a mass ratio of 1:1:1 in 150 mM NaCl and combined with a 7,5 mM polyethylenimine (PEI) solution, at a nitrogen/phosphate (N/P) molar ratio of 10.</s><s>The mix was incubated for 10 minutes at room temperature and added dropwise to the cells.</s></p><p><s>For stable RMCE experiments and sgRNA/Cas9 efficacy tests, CHO-K1 and HAFTL target cell lines were transfected by electroporation.</s><s>Cells were resuspended in 600 µl of antibiotic-free medium and electroporated in 0.4 cm cuvettes with the Gene Pulser Xcell from Biorad (CHO cells with square wave pulse protocol: 250 V, 15 ms, 2 pulse, 0.1 s pulse interval; HAFTL cells with exponential decay wave pulse protocol: 300 V, 950 µF capacitance).</s><s>20 µg of DV RMCE with 20 µg of Flippase vector were used.</s><s>In this experiment, transfected BFP + cells were isolated using preparative FACS.</s><s>RFP deletion was mediated by Cre recombinase.</s><s>Here, 40 µg of pPGK-Cre-bpA (gift from Klaus Rajewsky (Addgene plasmid #11543)) was electroporated into the selected CHO and HAFTL cell clone with the indicated pulse conditions.</s><s>Transfected cells were kept in subculture for 2 weeks and a RFP − population was isolated via FACS.</s></p><p><s>For sgRNA efficacy test 20 µg of pX330-sgRNA:NLS-GFP (sgRNA/Cas9 vector; derived from Addgene #42230) with 20 µg of salmon sperm DNA were used for each transfection.</s><s>For HDR transfections as well as the side-by-side comparison with RMCE, CHO cells were transfected with Lipofectamine 3000 (Invitrogen).</s><s>In a 6-well plate, 1.5 × 10 5 cells were seeded a day prior to transfection.</s><s>Either 1 µg of sgRNA/Cas9 or Flippase plasmid and the 1 µg of the appropriate DV were mixed and transfected accordingly to the manufacture's instructions.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Next generation sequencing.</head><p><s>For the library preparation, 2.5 µg genomic DNA of CHO.S18 was digested overnight with the restriction enzymes BamHI, BglII, EcoRI, MfeI, and HindIII in a total volume of 100 µl.</s><s>The digest was purified via NucleoSpin Gel and PCR Clean-up (MACHEREY-NAGEL) and linkers were ligated to the DNA ends overnight with T4 DNA Ligase.</s><s>After heat inactivation at 70 °C for 15 minutes, 1 µl of each ligation was used as the first round PCR template for amplification with one primer complementary to the linker DNA and one complementary to the 3' end LTR of the HIV provirus.</s><s>The secondary PCR added the indices needed for sequencing on the MiSeq sequencer (Illumina).</s><s>Methods are essentially as described (Genome Walker Kit, Clontech) using primers described in the supplements.</s><s>For CHO.S18, HIV-1 LTR specific reads covering the proviral integration boundary for 2 locations were obtained.</s></p><p><s>Immunoblot analyses.</s><s>Sample preparation for rhBMP-2 detection.</s><s>For immunoblot analysis of rhBMP-2, supernatants were filtered (0.45 µm) and proteins were precipitated by adding 1 volume of 100% (w/v) trichloroacetic acid (TCA) to 10 volumes of filtered supernatant, incubation on ice for 1 hour and centrifugation at 18,000 × g for 15 min at 4 °C.</s><s>Supernatants were discharged, the protein pellets washed in 1 ml ice cold acetone and centrifuged at 18,000 × g for 15 min at 4 °C.</s><s>Air-dried pellets were resuspended in RIPA buffer (50 mM HEPES-KOH, 500 mM LiCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1% NP-40, 0.7% sodium deoxycholat) by sonication with a BANDELIN SONOPULS HD 2070 at an amplitude setting of 90% for 2 minutes.</s></p><p><s>Sample preparation for hOCT-4 detection.</s><s>HAFTL cells were centrifuged at 300 × g for 5 minutes at room temperature, cell pellets resuspended in RIPA buffer and incubated on ice for 15 minutes.</s><s>Lysed cells were sonicated as described above and subsequently centrifuged at 15,000 × g for 15 minutes at 4 °C.</s></p><p><s>Immunoblotting.</s><s>Protein samples were diluted in RIPA buffer, mixed with loading buffer (10% glycerol, 50 mM Tris pH 6, 8, 2 mM EDTA, 2% SDS, 0.02% bromophenol blue, 5% βME (omitted when samples ran under non-reducing conditions)).</s><s>PAGE separation, protein transfer and detection were done as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55</ref> .</s><s>For detection of rhBMP-2 and hOCT-4, a rabbit anti-BMP-2 antibody (Dianova CYT-26591; 1:5000) and a goat anti-OCT-4 antibody (Santa Cruz sc-8628; 1:2000) were used.</s><s>Total proteins blotted onto nitrocellulose membranes were stained by colloidal gold <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">58</ref> .</s><s>hBMP-2 ELISA.</s><s>rhBMP-2 concentration in medium supernatants of CHO.S18 clones and its variants were quantified by ELISA according to the instruction of the manufacturer (Antigenix America Inc.; RHF913CKC).</s><s>Absorption was measured with a SpectraMax 340PC384 at a wavelength of 405 nm.</s><s>A standard curve was derived using recombinant hBMP-2 was and the concentration of expressed protein in the samples was determined by linear regression.</s></p><p><s>Biological activity of rhBMP-2 and ALP assay.</s><s>hBMP-2 is able to suppress myoblast differentiation in the myogenic cell line C2C12.</s><s>At the same time it promotes osteoblastic differentiation, which results in the expression of alkaline phosphatase (ALP) <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">59</ref> .</s></p><p><s>C2C12 cells were exposed to the medium supernatant of clone CHO.S18-RΔRFP containing rhBMP-2 and ALP activity was determined.</s><s>On a 96-well plate, 10.000 C2C12 cells were seeded per well and differentiation protocol was started 24 hours after seeding.</s><s>Growth medium was exchanged for depletion medium (DMEM with 2% FCS, 100 µg/ml of penicillin/streptomycin, and 2 mM L-glutamine).</s><s>Further, medium was mixed with supernatant from CHO.S18-RΔRFP to reach the end concentration of 1 nM rhBMP-2.</s><s>Human BMP-2 (InductOS) served as the positive control and was added in the same concentration.</s><s>As the negative control, supernatant from parental clone CHO.S18 was added in the same volume as for CHO.S18-RΔRFP.</s><s>Medium was changed every other day over the time course of 8 days.</s><s>Subsequently, differentiated C2C12 cells were tested for ALP activity via a colorimetric assay based on the dephosphorylation of para-Nitrophenylphosphate (pNPP) as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60</ref> .</s><s>Absorption was measured with the SpectraMax 340PC384 at a wavelength of 405 nm.</s></p><p><s>Statistical analyses.</s><s>Data are represented as mean ± standard deviation.</s><s>Unpaired t-test as well as One-way ANOVA followed by Sidak's multiple comparisons test were performed using GraphPad Prism version 6.00 for Mac, GraphPad Software, La Jolla California USA, www.graphpad.com.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>RMCE strategy.</s><s>The landing pad vector (LPV) including the GFP reporter and the PuroTK selection marker gene is integrated into the host genome by lentiviral transduction.</s><s>The donor vector (DV RMCE ) includes a non-functional RFP reporter and the GOI expression unit (upper panel).</s><s>Flp recombinase-mediated cassette exchange of the FRT-flanked DV RMCE sequences results in the functional reconstitution of the RFP reporter gene along with the insertion of the GOI (middle panel).</s><s>If desired, the fluorescent reporter can be selectively deleted via Cre recombination (lower panel).</s><s>See Results section for vector features and abbreviations.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,155.64,46.50,300.00,215.04" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>, bottom).</s><s>As shown in Fig. 2b (right panel), transient expression of Cre recombinase in CHO.S18-R cells caused the expected chromosomal deletion in the resulting CHO.S18-RΔRFP cells.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Drug selection-free RMCE.</s><s>LPV-encoded GFP reporter genes in CHO cells were replaced by the DV RMCE sequences.</s><s>(a) Representative fluorescence microscopy images and flow cytometry plots of, from left to right, the CHO.S18 master clone, the unselected RMCE pool after the RMCE transfection, an isolated RFP + clone (CHO.S18-R) and the same clone after Cre-mediated RFP gene deletion (CHO.S18-RΔRFP).</s><s>Scale bar = 100 µm.</s><s>(b) Verification of the expected RMCE (left) and deletion events (right) by PCR analysis of genomic DNA.</s><s>The nomenclature of the cell lines and pools is according to Fig. 2a, above.</s><s>Shown on the left is a multiplex PCR with 3 primers where the lower band of 537 bp is indicative of the intact LPV, whereas the upper band of 1,329 bp is indicative of the RMCE reaction.</s><s>Shown on the right is a PCR analysis of integrated DV RMCE , before (upper band of 4,571 bp) and after (lower band of 2,157 bp) Cre/loxP deletion.</s><s>For details of the PCR patterns refer to suppl.</s><s>Fig. S9.</s><s>(M: Hyperladder 1 kb).</s><s>The uncropped gel pictures are shown in S11a.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,155.64,46.50,396.00,315.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. Heterologous Expression of hBMP-2.</s><s>hBMP-2 was chosen as the GOI and clone CHO.S18 and its variants were characterised for hBMP-2 expression and processing.</s><s>(a) Immunoblot analysis of supernatants (SN) of CHO.S18 clones for rhBMP-2 (M: PageRuler; Invitrogen).</s><s>In SDS-PAGE under non-reducing conditions the mature dimer form of rhBMP-2 migrates at approximately 30 kDa, while under reducing conditions the rhBMP-2 migrates as a monomer of approximately 15 kDa.</s><s>As positive control, CHO-K1 (wt) were transiently transfected with DV RMCE (hBMP-2) and medium supernatant was harvested 2 days post transfection.</s><s>The uncropped blot pictures are shown in S11b.</s><s>(b) Quantification of rhBMP-2 in supernatants of CHO S.18 clones via ELISA reveals a 19-fold increase in rhBMP-2 expression from CHO.S18-R to its RFP excision variant CHO.S18-RΔRFP.</s><s>rhBMP-2 could not be detected in supernatants of parental clone CHO.</s><s>S18 (ND: not detected; n = 2; Sidak's post-hoc test was applied to detect significant differences in ANOVA, p &lt; 0.0001; asterisks indicate a significant difference compared with the hBMP-2 concentration in the supernatant of CHO.S18-R, ****p &lt; 0.0001).</s><s>(c) Biological activity of produced rhBMP-2 tested by ALP assay.</s><s>C2C12 cells exposed to supernatant of CHO.S18-RΔRFP containing rhBMP-2 shows an upregulation in ALP activity, suggesting a biological active form of rhBMP-2.</s><s>ALP activity of C2C12 cells exposed to DMEM supplied with 2% FCS and commercial available rhBMP-2 was set to 100 (bar graphs: mean ± standard deviation; n = 3).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,155.64,46.50,360.00,367.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. LPV-targeting via CRISPR/Cas9.</s><s>Schematic overview of LPV targeting by CRISPR/Cas9 and indel efficiency test of selected sgRNA.</s><s>(a) The chosen Cas9 cut site is located between the NLS sequence and the FRT site of the LPV.</s><s>In presence of the donor vector (DV HDR ).</s><s>These double strand breaks facilitate the DV HDRencoded GOI insertion via the cellular HDR pathway.</s><s>The integration of the donor results in the change of the fluorescence signal from GFP to RFP.</s><s>Validation of sgRNA potency: (b) T7E1 assay revealed efficient production of indels at the target site (M: HyperLadder 1 kb), in line with results obtained in a TIDE analysis (suppl.</s><s>Fig. S10).</s><s>The uncropped gel picture is shown in S11c.</s><s>(c) Flow cytometry analysis of clone CHO.S18 after transfection with the chosen sgRNA and a Cas9 expression vector, resulting in an efficient functional knockout of the GFP reporter gene via NHEJ.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,155.64,46.50,360.00,328.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. PCR characterisation of HDR events in CHO.S18.</s><s>LPV sequences in RMCE master clone CHO.S18 were targeted by a co-transfection of DV HDR and a Cas9/sgRNA expression vector.</s><s>(a) Flow cytometry plot of the cell pool after transfection.</s><s>The red rectangle indicates the gate used for single cell sorting for clonal isolation of GFP − /RFP + cells.</s><s>(b) Recombination events in 12 of the resulting clones were further characterised by PCR.In the first PCR analysis (upper panel; primers P-HDR-1 and P-HDR-2, see suppl.</s><s>Fig.S9for details) the PCR product of 1,596 bp is indicative for successful HDR events.</s><s>In the second PCR analysis (lower panel; primers P-HDR-1 and P-HDR-3, see suppl.</s><s>Fig.S9for details) the entire targeted segment is amplified.</s><s>Successful homologous recombination events result in an approximately 3,702 bp PCR product, whereas parental loci as well as NHEJ indels will result in a 2,825 bp PCR product.</s><s>Irregular recombination events (red stars) could be detected in two cases.</s><s>(P: parental clone CHO.S18).</s><s>The uncropped gel pictures are shown in suppl.</s><s>Fig.S11d.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,155.64,46.50,360.00,237.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6.</s><s>Side-by-side comparison of RMCE and HDR recombination frequencies.</s><s>Both transgene integration systems targeting the same loci in cell clone CHO.S18 in a side-by-side comparison.</s><s>The fluorescent marker protein distribution of unselected cell pools 9 days after transfection is shown.</s><s>Below each plot the plasmids used for transient transfection are listed for both the RMCE and HDR approach.</s><s>For details of the transfection reactions, see Methods section (summary table: mean ± standard deviation; n = 3).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,98.64,46.50,456.00,171.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">SCientifiC RepoRts | (2017) 7:17771 | DOI:10.1038/s41598-017-17651-0</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>All members of our laboratory are acknowledged for stimulating discussion.</s><s>We are grateful to Andreas Kurtz for his support, Marten Jäger for his advice on the NGS data and Elisa Degenkolbe for her technical assistance in the detection of BMP-2.</s><s>We thank the BCRT Flow Cytometry Lab and the BCRT Next Generation Sequencing Lab for assistance.</s><s>This work was financially supported by the Helmholtz Association through programme oriented funding (POF) as well as its Impuls-und Vernetzungsfond (SO-036), and the Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF), Germany (KMU Innovativ grants 031A191G und 031A522B).</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Data availability.</s><s>The datasets generated during and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author Contributions</head><p><s>Q.V.P. preformed most experiments and prepared the figures.</s><s>Q.V.P. and M.G. analysed the data.</s><s>J.C. provided technical support and performed the experiments for supplemental Figure S4.</s><s>P. S. provided support for the experiments related to BMP-2 expression.</s><s>Q.V.P. and M.G. wrote the paper.</s><s>Q.V.P, M.G., P.S. and J.C. discussed the data and agreed on the manuscript.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional Information</head><p><s>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-017-17651-0.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Competing Interests:</head><p><s>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</s></p><p><s>Publisher's note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Altering the genome by homologous recombination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Capecchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">244</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1288" to="1292" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Site-specific recombinases: molecular machines for the Genetic Revolution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Olorunniji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rosser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1042/BJ20151112</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1042/BJ20151112" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">473</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="673" to="684" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptional behavior of LCR enhancer elements integrated at the same chromosomal locus by recombinase-mediated cassette exchange</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bouhassira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Westerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Leboulch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3332" to="3344" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantification of factors influencing fluorescent protein expression using RMCE to generate an allelic series in the ROSA26 locus in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1242/dmm.006569</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1242/dmm.006569" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dis Model Mech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="537" to="547" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Performance of genomic bordering elements at predefined genomic loci</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Goetze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1128/MCB.25.6.2260-2272.2005</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1128/MCB.25.6.2260-2272.2005" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2260" to="2272" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The use of recombinase mediated cassette exchange in retroviral vector producer cell lines: predictability and efficiency by transgene exchange</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Coroadinha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2006.01.037</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbiotec.2006.01.037" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="468" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recombinant protein expression by targeting pre-selected chromosomal loci</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nehlsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/1472-6750-9-100</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1186/1472-6750-9-100" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accurate comparison of antibody expression levels by reproducible transgene targeting in engineered recombination-competent CHO cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mayrhofer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00253-014-6011-1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00253-014-6011-1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9723" to="9733" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flipase-mediated cassette exchange in Sf9 insect cells for stable gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fernandes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/bit.24542</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/bit.24542" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechnology and bioengineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2836" to="2844" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Site-specific DNA recombination in mammalian cells by the Cre recombinase of bacteriophage P1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Henderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5166" to="5170" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recombinase-mediated gene activation and site-specific integration in mammalian cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>O'gorman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Fox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">251</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1351" to="1355" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use of mutated FLP recognition target (FRT) sites for the exchange of expression cassettes at defined chromosomal loci</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Schlake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bode</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12746" to="12751" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome Editing Techniques and Their Therapeutic Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Calos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/cpt.542</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/cpt.542" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Pharmacol Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="42" to="51" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proven and novel strategies for efficient editing of the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mussolino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mlambo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Cathomen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.coph.2015.08.008</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coph.2015.08.008" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The art of CHO cell engineering: A comprehensive retrospect and future perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Handrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Otte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.biotechadv.2015.10.015</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biotechadv.2015.10.015" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechnol Adv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1878" to="1896" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanism of eukaryotic homologous recombination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>San Filippo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev.biochem.77.061306.125255</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.biochem.77.061306.125255" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu Rev Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="257" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A cell sorting protocol for selecting high-producing sub-populations of Sf9 and High Five cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vidigal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2013.10.020</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbiotec.2013.10.020" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">168</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="436" to="439" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homogeneity and persistence of transgene expression by omitting antibiotic selection in cell line isolation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kaufman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/nar/gkn508</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkn508" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e111</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Novel tag-and-exchange (RMCE) strategies generate master cell clones with predictable and stable transgene expression properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Qiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Oumard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wegloehner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bode</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jmb.2009.05.012</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2009.05.012" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of molecular biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">390</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="579" to="594" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Promoter crosstalk effects on gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hampf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gossen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jmb.2006.10.009</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2006.10.009" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of molecular biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">365</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="911" to="920" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of glucocorticoid receptor translocation and intranuclear organization in living cells with a green fluorescent protein chimera</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Htun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barsony</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Renyi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gould</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hager</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4845" to="4850" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generation of destabilized green fluorescent protein as a transcription reporter</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">273</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34970" to="34975" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new positive/negative selectable marker, puDeltatk, for use in embryonic stem cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genesis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Engineering chromosomal rearrangements in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/35093564</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/35093564" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="780" to="790" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plasmid vectors for the selection of promoters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Brosius</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="160" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detailed design and comparative analysis of protocols for optimized production of highperformance HIV-1-derived lentiviral particles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mitta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rimann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fussenegger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ymben.2005.06.006</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ymben.2005.06.006" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metabolic engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="426" to="436" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effectiveness and safety of recombinant human bone morphogenetic protein-2 for adults with lumbar spine pseudarthrosis following spinal fusion surgery: A systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Bodalia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Balaji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kaila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1302/2046-3758.54.2000418</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1302/2046-3758.54.2000418" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bone Joint Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="152" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of bone morphogenetic proteins in the treatment of clinical oral and maxillofacial osseous defects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Boyne</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Bone Joint Surg Am</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="S146" to="150" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl 1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recombinant human BMP-2 for the treatment of open tibial fractures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3928/01477447-20120525-23</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3928/01477447-20120525-23" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Orthopedics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="e847" to="854" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stability of protein production from recombinant mammalian cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bentley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dickson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/bit.10517</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/bit.10517" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechnology and bioengineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="631" to="639" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stability of producer hybridoma cell lines after cell sorting: a case study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kromenaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Srienc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/bp00027a010</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1021/bp00027a010" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechnol Prog</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="307" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The vagaries of variegating transgenes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Whitelaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/bies.950181111</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/bies.950181111" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BioEssays: news and reviews in molecular, cellular and developmental biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="919" to="923" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epigenetic effects on transgene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Whitelaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1385/1-59259-220-1:351</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">158</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="368" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inducible expression of coding and inhibitory RNAs from retargetable genomic loci</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Weidenfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/nar/gkp108</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkp108" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e50</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A study on the temperature dependency and time course of the cold capture antibody secretion assay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pichler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2009.03.001</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbiotec.2009.03.001" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="80" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Magnetic sorting of membrane associated IgG for phenotypebased selection of stable antibody producing cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Poitevin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pontini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kosco-Vilbois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Elson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jim.2017.02.004</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jim.2017.02.004" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Immunol Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">444</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metabolic burden in recombinant CHO cells: effect ofdhfr gene amplification andlacZ expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Todd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kompala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/BF00767763</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00767763" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cytotechnology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effects of G418 on the growth and metabolism of recombinant mammalian cell lines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Yallop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Svendsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1023/A:1017550902771</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1017550902771" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cytotechnology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptional interference and termination between duplicated alpha-globin gene constructs suggests a novel mechanism for gene regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Proudfoot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/322562a0</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/322562a0" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="562" to="565" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A) signals and transcriptional pause sites combine to prevent interference between RNA polymerase II promoters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Eggermont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Proudfoot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Poly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2539" to="2548" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A highly efficient ligand-regulated Cre recombinase mouse line shows that LoxP recombination is position dependent</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vooijs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jonkers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Berns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/embo-reports/kve064</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/embo-reports/kve064" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="292" to="297" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-frequency off-target mutagenesis induced by CRISPR-Cas nucleases in human cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nbt.2623</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/nbt.2623" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="822" to="826" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Enhanced homology-directed human genome engineering by controlled timing of CRISPR/Cas9 delivery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Staahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Alla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Doudna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7554/eLife.04766</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.04766" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e04766</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recombinase mediated cassette exchange into genomic targets using an adenovirus vector</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sorrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-A</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kolb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/nar/gkq192</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkq192" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">e123</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient conditional and promoter-specific in vivo expression of cDNAs of choice by taking advantage of recombinase-mediated cassette exchange using FlEx gene traps</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schebelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/nar/gkq044</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkq044" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e106</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Insertion of sequences at the original provirus integration site of mouse ROSA26 locus using the CRISPR/Cas9 system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Quadros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Harms</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ohtsuka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Gurumurthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.fob.2015.03.003</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.fob.2015.03.003" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FEBS Open Bio</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="191" to="197" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">One-step generation of mice carrying mutations in multiple genes by CRISPR/Cas-mediated genome engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cell.2013.04.025</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2013.04.025" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="910" to="918" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">One-step generation of mice carrying reporter and conditional alleles by CRISPR/Cas-mediated genome engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cell.2013.08.022</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2013.08.022" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">154</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1370" to="1379" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiplex genome engineering using CRISPR/Cas systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/science.1231143</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1231143" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">339</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="819" to="823" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiplexed pancreatic genome engineering and cancer induction by transfection-based CRISPR/Cas9 delivery in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Maresch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/ncomms10770</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms10770" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10770</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolution of variants of yeast site-specific recombinase Flp that utilize native genomic sequences as recombination target sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bolusani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/nar/gkl548</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkl548" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5259" to="5269" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Directed evolution of a recombinase that excises the provirus of most HIV-1 primary isolates with high specificity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Karpinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nbt.3467</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/nbt.3467" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="409" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chimeric TALE recombinases with programmable DNA sequence specificity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mercer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Fuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Barbas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Iii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/nar/gks875</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gks875" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11163" to="11172" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">III Murine hematopoietic cells with pre-B or pre-B/myeloid characteristics are generated by in vitro transformation with retroviruses containing fes, ras, abl, and src oncogenes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Holmes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Pierce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Davidson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Morse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Exp Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">164</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="457" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modes of TAL effector-mediated repression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Werner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gossen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/nar/gku1124</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gku1124" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13061" to="13073" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Production and titration of lentiviral vectors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Salmon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Trono</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/0471142905.hg1210s54</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1002/0471142905.hg1210s54" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Protoc Hum Genet Chapter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Unit12</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increasing the efficiency of homology-directed repair for CRISPR-Cas9-induced precise gene editing in mammalian cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Chu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nbt.3198</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1038/nbt.3198" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="543" to="548" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preparation of colloidal gold for staining proteins electrotransferred onto nitrocellulose membranes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yamaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Asakawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">172</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="104" to="107" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bone morphogenetic protein-2 converts the differentiation pathway of C2C12 myoblasts into the osteoblast lineage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Katagiri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1755" to="1766" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Activating and deactivating mutations in the receptor interaction site of GDF5 cause symphalangism or brachydactyly type A2</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Seemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1172/JCI25118</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1172/JCI25118" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2373" to="2381" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
