<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Advantages of RNA-seq Compared to RNA Microarrays for Transcriptome Profiling of Anterior Cruciate Ligament Tears</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2019-01-01">2019 January 01.</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Muhammad</forename><forename type="middle">Farooq</forename><surname>Rai</surname></persName>
							<email>rai.m@wustl.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Orthopaedic Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Musculoskeletal Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Washington University School of Medicine at Barnes-Jewish Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>660 S. Euclid Ave</addrLine>
									<postCode>63110</postCode>
									<settlement>St. Louis</settlement>
									<region>MO</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cell Biology and Physiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Washington University School of Medicine at Barnes-Jewish Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>660 S. Euclid Ave</addrLine>
									<postCode>63110</postCode>
									<settlement>St. Louis</settlement>
									<region>MO</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Eric</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Tycksen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Genome Technology Access Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Washington University School of Medicine at Barnes-Jewish Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>660 S. Euclid Ave</addrLine>
									<postCode>63110</postCode>
									<settlement>St. Louis</settlement>
									<region>MO</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Ph.D</roleName><forename type="first">Linda</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sandell</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Orthopaedic Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Musculoskeletal Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Washington University School of Medicine at Barnes-Jewish Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>660 S. Euclid Ave</addrLine>
									<postCode>63110</postCode>
									<settlement>St. Louis</settlement>
									<region>MO</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cell Biology and Physiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Washington University School of Medicine at Barnes-Jewish Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>660 S. Euclid Ave</addrLine>
									<postCode>63110</postCode>
									<settlement>St. Louis</settlement>
									<region>MO</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biomedical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Washington University School of Medicine at Barnes-Jewish Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>660 S. Euclid Ave</addrLine>
									<postCode>63110</postCode>
									<settlement>St. Louis</settlement>
									<region>MO</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Brophy</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Orthopaedic Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Musculoskeletal Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Washington University School of Medicine at Barnes-Jewish Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>660 S. Euclid Ave</addrLine>
									<postCode>63110</postCode>
									<settlement>St. Louis</settlement>
									<region>MO</region>
									<country key="US">United States</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Orthopaedic</forename><forename type="middle">R H</forename><surname>Research</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Brophy</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Tycksen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Rai</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Orthopaedic Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Washington University School of Medicine at Barnes-Jewish Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>660 South Euclid Avenue</addrLine>
									<postCode>8233, 63110</postCode>
									<settlement>St. Louis</settlement>
									<region>MS, MO</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Advantages of RNA-seq Compared to RNA Microarrays for Transcriptome Profiling of Anterior Cruciate Ligament Tears</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2019-01-01">2019 January 01.</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BEFB81C42CBFC2C6F6385C319C2FDD73</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1002/jor.23661</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>anterior cruciate ligament</term>
					<term>time-from-injury</term>
					<term>isoforms</term>
					<term>periostin</term>
					<term>transcripts</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Microarrays and RNA-seq are at the forefront of high throughput transcriptome analyses.</s><s>Since these methodologies are based on different principles there are concerns about the concordance of data between the two techniques.</s><s>The concordance of RNA-seq and microarrays for genome-wide analysis of differential gene expression has not been rigorously assessed in clinically derived ligament tissues.</s><s>To demonstrate the concordance between RNA-seq and microarrays and to assess potential benefits of RNA-seq over microarrays, we assessed differences in transcript expression in anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) tissues based on time-from-injury.</s><s>ACL remnants were collected from patients with an ACL tear at the time of ACL reconstruction.</s><s>RNA prepared from torn ACL remnants was subjected to Agilent microarrays (N = 24) and RNA-seq (N = 8).</s><s>The correlation of biological replicates in RNA-seq and microarrays data was similar (0.98 vs. 0.97), demonstrating that each platform has high internal reproducibility.</s><s>Correlations between the RNA-seq data and the individual microarrays were low, but correlations between the RNA-seq values and the *</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p><s>Microarrays and RNA-seq technologies have revolutionized gene discovery studies.</s><s>The ability to simultaneously examine thousands of gene transcripts using a genome-wide transcriptome profiling approach puts these technologies in the forefront of high throughput screening.</s><s>These technologies have a broad spectrum of applications including but not limited to identification of differentially expressed gene transcripts between healthy and diseased cells (and tissues), providing new insights into developmental processes, pharmacogenomics, and the examination of gene regulation <ref type="bibr">1; 2</ref> .</s><s>Because of their popularity in the scientific community, cost-effectiveness, and ease of analysis, microarrays remain the most extensively used approach in transcriptome profiling.</s><s>Nevertheless, hybridization issues with degraded clinically derived RNA, low abundance transcripts, and the availability of probes for known genes on the chip are the drawbacks of microarrays technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> .</s><s>Like microarrays, RNA-seq also has some potential pitfalls with the use of degraded RNA samples, however, unlike microarrays, there are several protocols available that can circumvent some, if not all, of the problems associated with RNA-seq such as to remove bases adapters and overrepresented or low-quality sequences <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> .</s></p><p><s>RNA-seq utilizes high throughput sequencing technology to directly sequence gene transcripts and is emerging as an alternative for whole-genome transcriptome profiling <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> .</s><s>RNA-seq has considerable advantages for examining transcriptome profile structure such as the detection of novel transcripts and splice junctions, although it does pose novel algorithmic and logistical challenges for data analysis and storage <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> .</s><s>It does not depend on genome annotation for prior probe selection and avoids the related biases introduced during hybridization of microarrays <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> .</s><s>Despite the fact that many computational methods have been developed for alignment of reads, quantification of genes or gene transcripts and identification of differentially expressed genes, there is great variability in the maturity of the available computational tools <ref type="bibr">8; 9</ref> .</s></p><p><s>Using the microarrays approach, we have recently identified a number of gene transcripts that showed repressed expression with time-from-injury in human anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) tears using the 24-sample microarrays data set <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> .</s><s>We observed that the largest differences in expression of gene transcripts exist between acute (&lt;3 month from injury) and chronic (&gt;12 months from injury) groups with little differences between acute and intermediate (3-12 months from injury) and chronic and intermediate groups.</s><s>The differentially expressed gene transcripts were enriched for numerous biological processes that were consistent with the initial repair activity in the injured ligament to repair.</s><s>To the best of our knowledge, no study has compared RNA-seq and microarrays transcriptome profiles in any area of musculoskeletal research.</s><s>Studies performed on other tissues have focused on the concordance between RNA-seq and microarrays <ref type="bibr">8; 11; 12</ref> .</s><s>Our study focused on both the consistencies, as well as differences, between these technologies and further investigated the reasons for any observed discrepancies.</s><s>The purpose of the present study was to evaluate the relative concordance between the two assays and to determine the benefits of RNA-seq over the microarrays for evaluating injured ligament tissues.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study design</head><p><s>Informed written consent was obtained from study patients approved by the Institutional Review Board of Washington University.</s><s>Patients with clinically diagnosed ACL tear were recruited (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>Patients of any age, body mass index, and sex were included and patients with other concomitant intra-articular or associated extra-articular injuries and those undergoing revision ACL reconstruction were excluded.</s><s>Previously we reported gene expression differences as a function of time-from-injury using RNA from 24 ACL tissues via microarrays.</s><s>Here, we selected a subset of RNA samples (N = 8) from the 24-sample cohort and performed Illumina RNA-seq.</s><s>As we already know that most important differences in gene expression exist between acute and chronic ACL tears 10 , we randomly selected samples from acute (N=5) and chronic (N=3) groups only for RNA-seq analysis.</s><s>We compared the 8-sample RNA-seq data with the microarrays data using 24-sample cohort (14 acute, 4 chronic, while keeping the 6 intermediate samples in the model) as well as with microarrays data from the same 8 samples on which RNA-seq was performed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tissue collection, processing and RNA isolation</head><p><s>Fragments of torn ACL were collected at the time of ACL reconstruction surgery <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> .</s><s>Tissues immersed in TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen) were homogenized using Polytron System (Kinematica AG).</s><s>RNA was prepared using TRIzol-chloroform method followed by purification using Minispin columns (Qiagen) <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> .</s><s>Quality and quantity of RNA samples was ascertained with the use of Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies).</s><s>Mean RNA integrity number (RIN) was 4.7 (range 3.0 to 6.9).</s><s>RNA was aliquoted after preparation and RIN did not change with time.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Microarrays hybridization</head><p><s>A total of 30-ng of RNA was amplified by WTA2 kit (Sigma-Aldrich) and 2.5-µg of complementary DNA was labeled with Kreatech ULS labeling kit (Kreatech Diagnostics).</s><s>Labeled samples were purified with QIAquick polymerase-chain-reaction (PCR) purification columns (Qiagen) and quantitated on a Nanodrop spectrophotometer (NanoDrop Technologies).</s><s>The labeled DNA was hybridized using Agilent Human 8×60K microarrays chips (Agilent Technologies) at 65°C for 20h followed by routine washing.</s><s>The microarrays were scanned on an Agilent SureScan scanner to detect Cy5 fluorescence.</s><s>Gridding and analysis of images were performed using Agilent Feature Extraction software v10.7.3.1.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Microarrays data analysis</head><p><s>Data were imported into the R/Bioconductor package Limma.</s><s>The raw probe fluorescence signals were background subtracted, expressed in log 2 format for normal distribution, and then quantile normalized to adjust gene expression signals for differences in hybridization efficiency.</s><s>Genes with Limma quantile normalized expression levels &lt;10% over the 95 th percentile of negative background control probes in more than half the samples were prefiltered to increase the signal to noise ratio among lower expressing genes and to reduce the number of genes tested and corrected for by the Benjamini-Hochberg method of adjusting pvalues i.e. false-discovery rate (FDR).</s><s>The Limma probe-level data were then averaged by probe identification and all probes were annotated with the R/Bioconductor package biomaRt <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> to Ensembl Release 76 (GRch38.76).</s><s>The quality and performance of the samples were then assessed with a spearman correlation matrix (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>) of all probe-averaged quantile normalized logged intensities that passed the pre-filter as well as multidimensional scaling plots (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>) to assess the variance between and within conditions.</s><s>Significance testing was performed with Limma's generalized-linear model using moderated t-statistics and robustly trended estimates of residual standard errors to control for outlier sample variances due to varying degrees of hybridization and sample performance with factors controlling for other confounders (age, sex, body-mass-index, and variation in RNA integrity number).</s><s>The residual standard errors were then plotted to confirm the trended fit conformed to the observed mean-variance relationship (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>).</s><s>To create a comprehensive list of differentially expressed genes, we applied a ≥1.5 fold-change as the minimum threshold with secondary levels of FDR adjusted p-values ≤0.05 based on previous experience <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RNA-seq library preparation</head><p><s>RNA quality was assessed prior to RNA-seq analysis with an Agilent Bioanalyzer.</s><s>Library preparation was performed with 10-ng of total RNA.</s><s>All samples were DNase-I treated to remove residual DNA and ds-cDNA was prepared using the SeqPlex RNA kit (Sigma-Aldrich) per manufacturer's protocol.</s><s>The cDNA was then blunt ended, an A base added to the 3' ends, and then Illumina sequencing adapters were ligated to the ends.</s><s>Ligated fragments were then amplified for 12 cycles using primers incorporating unique index tags.</s><s>Fragments from all samples were then pooled and sequenced on an Illumina HiSeq-2500 across two lanes of sequencing in two different flow cells using single reads extending 50 bases, targeting 30M read per sample.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RNA-seq data analysis</head><p><s>RNA-seq reads were aligned to Homo sapiens Ensembl GRCh38.76 with STAR v2.0.4b <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> .</s></p><p><s>Approximately, 28-43 million reads were obtained per sample.</s><s>Low quality reads (&lt;10%) were eliminated, resulting in 24-41 million mapped reads.</s><s>In total, 11-25 million uniquely mapped read pairs per sample were obtained and aligned to the human reference genome as shown in (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>).</s><s>Gene counts were derived from the number of uniquely aligned unambiguous read by Subread:featureCount version 1.4.5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref> .</s><s>Transcript counts were produced by Sailfish version 0.6.3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref></s><s>.</s><s>Sequencing performance was assessed for total number of aligned reads, total number of uniquely aligned reads, genes and transcripts detected, ribosomal fraction, known junction saturation, and read distribution over known gene models with RSeQC version 2.3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> .</s><s>In order to determine that the total number of aligned reads properly represented all known exon-exon junctions, junction saturation curves (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4A</ref>) and 3'/5' end bias plots (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B</ref>) were created with RSeQC to verify that those reads aligned uniformly across known transcripts.</s></p><p><s>All gene-level and transcript counts were then imported into the R/Bioconductor package EdgeR <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> and TMM (trimmed mean of M-values) normalized to adjust for differences in library size.</s><s>Genes or transcripts not expressed in any sample were excluded from further analysis.</s><s>Performance of the samples were assessed with a spearman correlation matrix (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5A</ref>) and multidimensional scaling plots (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5B</ref>) of the first 2 eigenvectors to confirm that time-from-injury was the largest source of variation and that within-group variance was less than those between groups.</s><s>A plot of the tagwise and fitted trended dispersions estimates generated by EdgeR showed that the mean-variance relationship among biological replicates met the assumptions of the negative binomial model (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5C</ref>).</s><s>Generalized linear models with robust dispersion estimates were created to test for gene/transcript level differential expression between acute and chronic time-from-injury with additional blocking factors controlling for differences due to age, gender, body-mass-index, and sample quality based on variation in RNA integrity values.</s><s>The fit of the trended and tagwise dispersion estimates were then plotted to confirm proper fit of the observed mean to variance relationship where the tagwise dispersions are equivalent to the biological coefficients of variation of each gene (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5C</ref>).</s><s>Differentially expressed genes and transcripts were then filtered for FDR adjusted p-values ≤0.05.</s><s>The EdgeR analysis revealed that 49% of all differentially expressed genes with unadjusted p-value ≤0.01 could be derived from the time-from-injury component of the fitted additive generalized linear model alone for RNA-seq (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6A</ref>) and 52% for microarrays (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6B</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gene isoforms</head><p><s>We selected POSTN as an example for isoform analysis for a the following specific reasons:</s></p><p><s>(i) we have previously reported that its expression was highly down-regulated in chronic tears compared to acute tears <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> , which is consistent with RNA-seq data from the current study, (ii) this gene plays an important role in tissue repair and degeneration <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref> , and (iii) there are six known transcript variants for this gene <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref> .</s><s>The process of accurately quantifying and validating isoforms (splice variants) of known genes is still an ongoing endeavor, but recent tools utilizing advanced expectation-maximization algorithms such as Sailfish, Salmon, RSEM, and Kallisto has made that process more efficient and accurate versus older methods such as Bayesian methods such as Cufflinks <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28</ref> .</s><s>The examination of gene alternative splice isoforms has always been difficult at best or impossible with microarrays technology.</s><s>Affymetrix now offers several new array types that attempt to query the expression of isoforms at the exon level, but de-convoluting the expression of genes with many isoforms has proven difficult due to the many to one relationship of the expressed exons to known or novel isoforms.</s><s>Because RNA-seq reads can span known exons in the form of reads aligned across exon-exon or exon-retained intron junctions, it is now possible to de-convolute isoform expression patterns using advanced statistical modeling on the placement and numbers of unique and unambiguously aligned reads within exons with the number of reads aligned across known exon-exon or exon-retained intron junctions that define known expressed isoforms.</s><s>Here, we used Sailfish 20 to estimate the expression of isoforms using an expectation-maximization model on k-mers matched to a k-mer index derived from FASTA file comprised of all known isoforms of all known genes found in the Ensembl release 76 reference transcriptome.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gene ontology</head><p><s>To highlight the biological interpretation of the large set of transcripts, grouping of genes/ transcripts based on functional similarity was achieved using GeneGo MetaCore tools as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> .</s><s>The altered biological processes (gene ontology distribution) were ranked based upon enrichment score and p-values.</s><s>Gene ontology was performed for the differentially expressed genes between acute and chronic ACL remnants from 8-sample microarrays and RNA-seq analyses.</s><s>In addition, we conducted gene ontology and network analysis on genes common to microarrays and RNA-seq to see if these genes are interlinked or they function in relation to each other using GeneGo MetaCore Direct Interaction path.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Microfluidic quantitative PCR</head><p><s>The expression of 12 transcripts differentially expressed by microarrays and RNA-seq was validated via microfluidic-based PCR 96.96 Dynamic Arrays (Fluidigm Corp.) as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> .</s><s>Analysis of data was performed using 2 −ΔCt method with peptidylprolyl isomerase A (PPIA, cyclophilin A) as the housekeeping gene.</s><s>PPIA was selected as housekeeping gene based on our previous work as it showed relatively stable expression across all the samples <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> .</s><s>We applied non-parametric two-tailed Mann-Whitney test (GraphPad) to observe the differences in transcript expression between any of the two timefrom-injury categories.</s><s>Data are presented as mean ± standard error of the mean.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data deposition</head><p><s>The raw data is available on National Center of Biotechnology Information Gene Expression Ontology website (http:www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/geo) with accession numbers GSE61385 (microarray) and GSE65469 (RNA-seq).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gene transcripts differentially expressed by time-from-injury</head><p><s>We detected 2816 gene transcripts significantly differentially expressed (at any fold-change) between acute and chronic tears in 24-sample microarrays (Supplementary Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>), 2447 in 8-sample microarrays (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">2</ref>) and 6549 in RNA-seq samples (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">3</ref>).</s><s>The number of genes differentially expressed between acute and chronic ACL tissues for each cohort is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref> for any fold-change and in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref> at ≥1.5 log 2 fold-change and P≤0.05.</s><s>We noted that 424 gene transcripts were common to all three analyses at any fold-change (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">4</ref>) and 42 gene transcripts were common to all three analyses at ≥1.5 log 2 fold-change (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).</s><s>Using a stringent criterion of FDR of &lt;0.05, no significant gene transcripts were found for 24-sample microarray, only 61 in 8-sample microarrays (Supplementary Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>) and 2112 in RNA-seq (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Concordance between microarrays and RNA-seq</head><p><s>We investigated the concordance between 8-sample microarrays and RNA-seq based on the expression profile of gene transcripts differentially expressed between acute and chronic tears.</s><s>We observed that RNA-seq data had a tighter distribution of fold-changes around zero and a characteristic fantail indicative of lower signal to noise ratios at the lowest levels of detectable gene expression (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">7A</ref>).</s><s>Despite the higher ratio of attributable gene expression to the time-from-injury condition, the Limma microarrays data demonstrated lower signal to noise throughout the spectrum of gene expression as can be seen by the more diffuse cloud of signals in the MA plot (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">7B</ref>).</s><s>A violin/box plot of the distribution of the observed log2 fold-changes across the two Lima microarrays analyses and single EdgeR RNA-seq dataset show that RNA-seq dataset has a much larger tighter and more elongated range of observed log 2 fold-changes that indicates the RNA-seq data also exhibits signs of less log 2 fold-change compression (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">7C</ref>).</s><s>Further examination of the rank ordered observed p-values across all three datasets illustrate that the RNA-seq data not only exhibits less signs of log fold-change compression, but higher degrees of statistical sensitivity as well (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">7D</ref>).</s></p><p><s>The correlation between log 2 fold-changes between microarrays and RNA-seq datasets were computed by plotting an XY plot after filtering the gene-lists of both datasets for just those that were expressed greater than 8 log counts-per-million across all samples in the RNA-seq dataset.</s><s>The results were then plotted with the RNA-seq data on the y-axis and the microarrays data on the x-axis and a least-sum-squares linear regression model and LOESS model was then fitted to the data.</s><s>The measured Spearman and Pearson correlation coefficients across these high expressing genes were respectively 0.64 and 0.54, indicating that the cross-platform concordance was relatively moderate across the two similar RNA-seq and microarrays datasets, particularly when focused on highly expressed genes (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</s><s>The correlation coefficients and XY plots become incomprehensible when low expressing genes are included (data not shown).</s></p><p><s>An added advantage of RNA-seq is the ability to query the distribution of aligned reads across gene bodies.</s><s>In this case, we have found that many of the differences between the two platforms can be attributed to the less than ideal RNA quality that is typical for operating room derived specimens, especially those coming from damaged tissues.</s><s>RSeQC end bias analysis clearly shows that the reads sequenced and successfully aligned across all known genes by STAR have clear signs of RNA degradation indicated by drops in coverage across the 5 prime end and middle of a hypothetical normalized 100 base pair gene body (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B</ref>).</s><s>This signature of degradation limits the depth of sequencing across the 5 prime end of known genes, but does not render them undetectable as long as there is some part of the degraded transcript that can be sequenced, but hybridization of these RNA fragments to probes targeting these regions in the reference genome are very negatively impacted due to a loss of hybridization efficiency.</s><s>The high correlations between the two platforms for high expressing genes suggests that although the integrity of the samples were compromised, reasonable comparisons of relative expression can still be gained when limited to high expressing genes that may have less degradation or more tolerant of degradation due to sheer numbers of transcripts.</s><s>Consequently, in future studies to identify biomarkers transferrable between two gene-expression measurement platforms, an emphasis should be placed on the above-median expressed genes when sample RNA integrity is less than optimal.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gene isoforms</head><p><s>The complexity inherent in quantifying isoforms is readily apparent in the visualization of the aligned reads across POSTN with sashimi plots created by the Integrated Genomic Viewer (IGV).</s><s>The plot clearly shows the convolution of reads aligned across exon-exon junctions of a single gene with multiple known isoforms (10 known isoforms; 6 of which are protein-coding and 4 are processed transcripts) and necessitates the use of advanced statistical modeling for the estimation of isoform level expression (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A</ref>).</s><s>Here we used Sailfish to quantify the expression of known Ensembl GRCh38 isoforms and measure their differential expression using the same statistical model and methods outlined for our gene level analysis with EdgeR.</s><s>A closer examination of the EdgeR analysis of the Sailfish estimated counts per isoform revealed that POSTN-001 (−9.40 log 2 fold-change) and POSTN-004 (−8.17 log 2 fold-change) comprised the most differentially regulated isoforms driving the repression of the POSTN gene in chronic tears.</s><s>A closer examination of the mean log 2 fold-change observed by EdgeR across all the annotated isoforms of POSTN yield a value of −3.95 which closely follows the gene-level observed fold-change from EdgeR of −3.22 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3B</ref>).</s><s>The difference most likely comes from the uncertainty in accurately estimating the isoform expression of a complex transcript with any given statistical model rather than the absolute integer count value of reads aligned across all exons of a gene as was done with the gene-level analysis.</s></p><p><s>In order to pseudo-validate our isoform findings, we followed the logic that genes are the summation of their isoforms and that the observed gene-level log 2 fold-change is approximately the mean of a given gene's isoforms and used a method similar to the Bioconductor package tximport to sum the Sailfish estimated counts to the gene-level as illustrated by Soneson et.</s><s>al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> The summed estimated counts for isoforms were then expressed as counts-per-million (CPM) in order to adjust for differences in library size across samples and then compared to the counts-per-million of the genes used in our prior analyses in the form of a spearman correlation matrix (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C</ref>).</s><s>The spearman correlation matrix supports our prior expectation that the summation of expressed isoforms to the level of their parent genes in the data follows a positive trend with high correlation (87%).</s><s>The relative accuracy of isoform expression was further bioinformatically interrogated by averaging the observed isoform-level EdgeR log 2 fold-changes for all isoforms of a given gene to their gene-level and then measuring the correlation of these changes to those of the same genes from a nearly identical EdgeR analysis of the genes previously described.</s><s>An XY plot shows that the observed mean isoform and gene changes follow a linear trend with a Pearson correlation across all genes of 68% and 89% for all genes previously identified as having a Benjamini-Hochberg FDR adjusted p-values less than or equal to 0.05 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>).</s><s>This supports the assumption that the Sailfish estimated counts for isoforms are reasonably accurate and differential expression analysis of these counts is statistically sound, especially when focused on isoforms of genes previously identified as statistically significant.</s><s>Where larger deviations between gene and isoform differential expression are observed, we have found that they are primarily limited to low expressing genes or genes with many isoforms where only one or two isoforms are driving the expression, such as is the case with POSTN.</s><s>This may explain the differences we have observed in observed gene-level expression between the microarrays and RNA-seq datasets where the probes of the microarrays appear to favorably hybridize to the higher expressing isoforms of POSTN.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gene transcripts common to microarrays and RNA-seq and their biological significance</head><p><s>Further interrogation of the differentially expressed transcript in microarrays and the RNAseq cohorts showed that 424 gene transcripts were found to recur across the datasets and majority of these were down-regulated in chronic tears.</s><s>At a fold-change cutoff of ≥1.5 log 2 fold 42 genes were common to the three platforms.</s><s>Only two gene transcripts (G0S2 and PLIN4) were up-regulated while other 40 gene transcripts were down-regulated in chronic versus acute tears and were common across three analyses (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>).</s><s>Examples include COL1A1, COL1A2, COL3A1, COL5A2, COL6A1, COL6A3, COL12A1, TGFBI, POSTN, MMP9, VEGFA, PLUA, FSCN1, MAFB, HMOX1, AEBP1, and EMILIN1.</s><s>Gene ontology of these 40 transcripts was represented by several important biological processes relevant to ACL healing (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>) such as extracellular matrix organization, blood vessel development, multicellular organismal metabolic process, regulation of cell-substrate adhesion, collagen metabolic process, cell motility, wound healing, blood vessel morphogenesis, cellular component organization or biogenesis, epithelial to mesenchymal transition, and response to hypoxia.</s><s>Furthermore, network analysis showed that out of 40 transcripts down-regulated and common to microarrays and RNA-seq analyses, 18 were interlinked in a module clearly indicating that they correlate to a function, signifying their role in the same biological process (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>).</s><s>Using lists of all gene transcripts differentially expressed between acute and chronic remnants identified by 8-sample microarrays and RNA-seq, we noted that only a small number of biological processes were common between the two platforms: only 7/50 processes were common between the two platforms for the gene transcripts elevated in chronic remnants (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">5</ref>) compared to 19/50 for the gene transcripts repressed in chronic remnants (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">6</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Validation of microarrays and RNA-Seq data</head><p><s>With the use of Fluidigm PCR, we validated expression of 14 gene transcripts based on biological interest or magnitude of their expression between acute and chronic ACL tears for 7 down-regulated in acute (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6A-G</ref>) and 7 up-regulated in acute (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6H-N</ref>).</s><s>Expression pattern of all transcripts was highly concordant with microarrays and RNA-seq data.</s><s>Therefore, it can be concluded that PCR data for the 14 gene tested showed 100% concordance (in expression pattern) with RNA-seq and microarrays data.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>This study comparing microarrays and RNA-seq to evaluate gene expression in ACL tears confirms that several transcripts representing important, distinct biological processes vary with time-from-injury.</s><s>Overall, microarrays and RNA-seq show a significant difference between acute and chronic tears.</s></p><p><s>A number of studies have compared RNA-Seq and hybridization-based arrays in other tissues and have reported that RNA-seq has a broader dynamic range and detected low abundance transcripts and biologically critical isoforms, which were not possible with microarrays 8; 30-34 .</s><s>Several investigators have proposed empirical protocols and statistical frameworks for the analysis of gene expression using RNA-seq, with a majority agreeing that RNA-seq data is negative-binomially distributed in nature and that count-based methods of differential expression analysis (EdgeR, DESeq2, or optionally Limma Voom) of the same gene across two or more conditions containing an appropriate number of biological replicates is the ideal method that yields the fewest false positives, highest true positives, and proper modeling of all known sources of biological or technical variation <ref type="bibr">32; 35-38</ref> .</s><s>The choice of tools or methods is largely determined by familiarity with the tools themselves, the ability to optimize the tools for their experimental conditions, and ease of use.</s><s>Our decision to use STAR, subread:FeatureCounts, Sailfish, and EdgeR are largely guided by these same principles and analysis with similar tools such as Salmon with tximport for isoform and gene expression measurements, and DESeq2 or Limma Voom for differential expression analysis would yield very similar findings (data not shown, but available on request).</s><s>Furthermore, numerous other studies have reviewed in detail the challenges and benefits associated with its technology and application <ref type="bibr">7; 39-42</ref> and have advocated the use of RNA-seq in transcriptome profiling of RNA samples.</s></p><p><s>Advantages of RNA-seq over microarrays include a higher number of differentially expressed gene transcripts than microarrays as it is based on sequencing rather than hybridization, which is independent of both probe availability and expression intensity <ref type="bibr">7; 43</ref> but is dependent on sequencing depth.</s><s>The precision of expression measurements, especially for transcripts present in low abundance, is limited by the background levels of hybridization as well as hybridization properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44</ref> .</s><s>Thus, although comparing hybridization results across arrays can detect gene expression differences among samples <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45</ref> , hybridization outcomes from a single sample may not provide a true assessment of the relative expression of different transcripts.</s><s>Furthermore, arrays are generally limited to probing transcripts with relevant probes on the array and therefore accurate measurements of expression levels and the reliable detection of genes with low abundance are challenging to accomplish.</s><s>This could be due to a number of reasons such as sub-optimal choice of probes, imperfect probe design, and incorrect probe annotations.</s><s>However, a well-designed data analysis methodologies can resolve some, if not all, of these issues <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46</ref> .</s></p><p><s>While the focus of this study was to assess how RNA-seq might be used to characterize gene expression differences between samples, sequence data may help answer other questions that are difficult to address using arrays.</s><s>In particular, array technologies can measure expression only of genes that have corresponding probes on the array, and, in most cases, probes are designed only to cover a very small portion of a gene.</s><s>Consequently, it is not possible to detect novel transcribed regions or the presence of alternative splice forms of a gene.</s><s>Both of these problems can potentially be overcome using the RNA-sequencing data.</s><s>Since microarrays only yield gene level differences without any knowledge of the transcript variants (isoforms), RNA-seq could identify specific isoforms that each gene has with P values and fold-change, thereby providing new information on which specific isoforms are actually responsible for the gene expression differences.</s><s>For instance, we knew that POSTN gene is significantly suppressed in chronic tears, but did not know which particular isoforms of POSTN drove the expression.</s><s>RNA-seq informed us that isoforms 1, 3, 4 and 202 have −9.40,</s><s>−4.08, −8.17 and −4.88-fold expression and other isoforms such as 201 remained unchanged or showed subtle differences in expression between acute and chronic tears (−0.19 fold).</s><s>Estimating isoform-specific gene expression (especially where one isoform has greater influence on phenotype than others) may be important for deeper understanding of complex biological processes and for disease susceptibility genes mapping.</s><s>Nevertheless, identification of splice variants using RNA-seq methodology assumes that an adequate number of reads span exon-exon junctions <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43</ref> .</s><s>This may not hold true when a sample is sequenced in only a single lane, and additional data are perhaps needed to circumvent this issue.</s><s>Furthermore, sample quality and proper library preparation are as important as sequencing depth when it comes to sequencing bias.</s></p><p><s>It is also worth mentioning that gene transcripts differentially expressed between acute and chronic remnants using the 24-sample cohort did not pass the most stringent criterion of 5% FDR and thus we had to limit the data to less stringent criterion of 5% P value.</s><s>While reporting only P value-based significance level is not ideal, it is not entirely incorrect.</s><s>In contrast, the 8-sample cohort yielded some (61 gene transcripts) and RNA-seq yielded numerous (2112 gene transcripts) that passed the 5% P values as well as 5% FDR thresholds.</s><s>This observation represents a clear advantage of RNA-seq over the microarrays and it gives more reliable gene list, although additional validation by PCR, in situ hybridization or protein expression by immunostaining is still necessary.</s></p><p><s>This study compared the RNA-seq and microarrays using human ACL tear tissues measuring gene expression as a function of injury chronicity.</s><s>We clearly observed several advantages associated with the use of RNA-seq over the microarrays in conjunction with current study.</s><s>RNA-seq gave almost 40 times more gene transcripts than the microarrays for the same set of samples indicating that the former is more comprehensive.</s><s>RNA-seq is more robust in identifying gene transcripts than microarrays, which are limited by the number of hybridized probes, background noise, and incorrect annotations.</s><s>In addition, RNA-seq provided information about transcript variants and isoforms.</s><s>RNA-seq is more sensitive than microarrays, as it can detect gene transcripts with very low expression, and is more accurate than microarrays across the spectrum of the expression.</s></p><p><s>We made two additional interesting observations when we compared microarrays with RNA-seq.</s><s>First, RNA-seq data had a tighter distribution of fold-changes around zero and a characteristic fantail indicative of lower signal to noise ratios at the lowest levels of detectable gene expression.</s><s>Second, RNA-seq data exhibited less signs of log fold-change compression and but higher degrees of statistical sensitivity.</s><s>This supports the observed higher sensitivity and dynamic range of RNA-seq over conventional microarrays gene expression approaches as evidenced by the large differences in significant gene expression between the two platforms allowing for increasing levels of statistical stringency.</s><s>The differences between the two microarrays datasets are a result of the exclusion of the intermediate condition and the absence of related factors for age, sex, body-mass-index, and RNA integrity number.</s><s>When coefficients of a statistical model are changed, so do the resulting proportion of variances to the remaining factors thereby inducing differences of statistical results even in the case where many of the samples within the statistical models are identical.</s><s>Had these ACL tissues come from genetically identical mice, it most likely would not have been necessary to include additional factors in the statistical modeling and the differences between acute and chronic across the two microarrays analyses would be negligible.</s></p><p><s>Our data showed relatively moderate cross-platform concordance across the two similar RNA-seq and microarrays datasets.</s><s>This suggests that the above-median expressed genes may have a good transferability between the two platforms and that the differences in the observed log 2 fold-changes and statistical significance may be a result of the limitations of hybridization based technologies and degraded tissue specimens as evidenced by nearly no correlation across low to medium expressors and only moderate correlation across high expressing genes.</s></p><p><s>We identified a discrete set of biological processes based on differentially expressed gene transcripts by 8-sample microarrays and RNA-seq.</s><s>Although there was a larger overlap in the biological processes from gene transcripts repressed in chronic remnants between the two platforms, there is no reason to give preference to the biological processes from one platform over the other.</s><s>However, here discuss some the biological processes that were enriched for gene transcripts common to all platforms.</s></p><p><s>A number of important gene transcripts were common across all analysis, with and most (40 out of 42) were repressed in chronic tears than acute tears, which is consistent with our prior study <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> .</s><s>Similarly, the biological processes represented by these repressed genes demonstrated that pathways associated with tissue repair and matrix synthesis were inhibited in chronic tears, again as previously reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> .</s><s>Finally, the gene transcripts repressed in chronic tears were not independent but rather work in concert as evidenced by the biological processes and network analysis.</s></p><p><s>This study has some limitations.</s><s>While our analysis covered mRNA expression, we did not examine other species of RNA (e.g.</s><s>micro-RNAs and long non-coding RNAs).</s><s>Our analysis of isoform detection was limited primarily to the POSTN gene.</s><s>In addition, the data on transcript isoforms is largely computational and were not validated by PCR.</s><s>Further studies will test the expression of specific isoforms by PCR and western blot in cells and tissues.</s><s>In this study, we did not use single-end 150 bp or paired-end sequencing to evaluate the differences in sequencing types.</s><s>However, available literature suggests that there is a saturation point where increased depth of sequencing does not increase the knowledge gained from gene or isoform level differential expression analysis.</s><s>Junction saturation plots of all known exon-exon junctions are very good at showing at what point a particular set of samples would benefit from further sequencing.</s><s>The characteristic signature in this case would be a plateau of saturation.</s><s>In the case of paired-end sequencing, the extra information to be gained over single-end sequencing would largely benefit the estimation of isoform level expression since longer split reads would span more exon-exon junctions that could be used to determine what isoforms of a given gene are expressed over other isoforms <ref type="bibr">9; 47</ref> .</s><s>If one of the primary goals of a study is to evaluate splice variants, chimeric fusion genes, or expressed single nucleotide polymorphisms (allele specific expression), then both higher depths of sequencing and paired-end sequencing would be the best choice.</s><s>None of these three factors were primary goals in this study and were therefore not evaluated.</s></p><p><s>In conclusion, RNA-seq appears to be an extremely promising tool for the assessment of mRNA expression as well as identification of differentially expressed gene transcripts, comparable, and to some extent superior, to existing microarrays platforms in the analysis of ligamentous tissues.</s><s>As the costs of sequencing are falling rapidly, RNA-seq is becoming widely embraced in the research community for accurate gene profiling.</s><s>Future research into musculoskeletal biology should strongly consider the use of RNA-seq where appropriate and feasible.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary Material</head><p><s>Refer to Web version on PubMed Central for supplementary material.</s><s>XY plot of log 2 fold-changes between N = 8 microarrays and RNA-seq datasets.</s><s>The genelists of both datasets were filtered for just those that were expressed greater than 8 log counts-per-million across all samples in the RNA-seq dataset.</s><s>The results were then plotted with the RNA-seq data on the y-axis and the microarrays data on the x-axis and a linear and LOESS model was then fitted to the data.</s><s>Spearman and Pearson correlation coefficients were then measured, respectively.</s><s>for isoforms were compared to the counts-per-million of the genes used in our prior analyses in the form of a spearman correlation matrix.</s><s>This matrix supports our prior expectation that the summation of expressed isoforms to the level of their parent genes in the data follows a positive trend with high correlation (87%).</s><s>(D) The relative accuracy of isoform expression was further interrogated by averaging the observed isoform-level EdgeR log 2 fold-changes for all isoforms of a given gene to their gene-level and then measuring the correlation of these changes to those of the same genes from a nearly identical EdgeR analysis of the genes previously described.</s><s>An XY plot shows that the observed mean isoform and gene changes follow a linear trend with a Pearson correlation across all genes of 68% and 89% for all genes previously identified as having a Benjamini-Hochberg FDR adjusted P values ≤0.05.</s><s>This supports the assumption that the Sailfish estimated counts for isoforms are reasonably accurate and differential expression analysis of these counts is statistically sound, especially when focused on isoforms of genes previously identified as statistically significant.</s><s>Validation of transcripts by microfluidic quantitative PCR.</s><s>We validated the expression of 14 gene transcripts via microfluidic-based quantitative PCR based either on their biological significance or magnitude of their expression between acute and chronic groups.</s><s>The expression pattern of 7 down-regulated in acute group (A-G) and 7 up-regulated in acute group (H-N) was highly concordant with microarrays and RNA-seq data sets.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Venn diagrams representing the number of differentially expressed gene transcripts for each comparison as well as their overlaps between the three comparisons are shown for any foldchange (A) or at a fold-change set at log 2 fold of ≥ 1.5 (B at a P ≤ 0.05).</s><s>The numbers of differentially expressed gene transcripts shown in parenthesis for each comparison and the numbers shown in overlapping areas represent the number of gene transcripts common to any two or three comparisons.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="17,138.12,62.00,395.76,489.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="18,92.28,62.00,487.44,489.36" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. (A) Display of aligned reads across POSTN with sashimi plots created by the Integrated Genomic Viewer (IGV) demonstrating the convolution of reads aligned across exon-exon junctions that make the use of statistical modeling necessary for the estimation of isoform level expression.</s><s>(B) Barplot of the estimated log2 fold-changes observed by EdgeR on the estimated counts of reads per known isoform of POSTN.</s><s>(C) The summed estimated counts</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="19,91.20,62.00,489.60,336.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. Barplot representing the mean log 2 fold-change of 40 recurring genes across the N = 24 microarrays dataset, N = 8 microarrays dataset, and the N = 8 RNA-seq dataset.</s><s>Individual points indicate the mean log 2 fold-change for each dataset.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="20,84.18,62.00,503.63,329.04" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5.</s><s>The molecular networks using 40 genes down-regulated in chronic remnants and common across microarrays and RNA-seq analyses were generated by GeneGo MetaCore are shown.</s><s>Pathway analysis showed that these genes represent extracellular matrix organization and demonstrate significant interactions with each other pathways.</s><s>Green arrows indicate activation, red arrows indicate inhibition, and gray arrows indicate unspecified interaction.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="21,91.20,62.00,489.60,393.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Characteristics of study patients according to type of analysis</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Assay</cell><cell>Category</cell><cell>Acute</cell><cell>Intermediate</cell><cell>Chronic</cell></row><row><cell>Microarray</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Average TFI (months)</cell><cell>1.53</cell><cell>3.92</cell><cell>40.53</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean age (Range) in years</cell><cell>31.6 (13-63)</cell><cell>37.8 (14.49)</cell><cell>45.0 (20-63)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean BMI</cell><cell>26.3</cell><cell>24.6</cell><cell>28.2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Sex</cell><cell cols="3">7 female, 7 male 2 female, 4 male 2 female, 2 male</cell></row><row><cell>RNA-seq</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Average TFI (Range) months</cell><cell>1.41</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>50</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean age (Range) years</cell><cell>31.6 (16-50)</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>45.7 (20-63)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mean BMI</cell><cell>25.5</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>29.9</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Sex</cell><cell>2 female, 3 male</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>1 female, 2 male</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">TFI = time-from-injury; BMI = body mass index</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>J Orthop Res.</s><s>Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 01.</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">J Orthop Res. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 01.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p><s>We thank Washington University Genome Technology Access Center for help with transcriptome and quantitative PCR assays.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p><s>These studies were supported by these grants from the National Institutes of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS), National Institutes of Health (NIH): R01AR063757 (PI: L. J. Sandell), P30-AR057235 (Musculoskeletal Research Center, PI: L. J. Sandell), 1K99AR064837 (PI: M. F. Rai).</s><s>The content of this publication is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the NIH or the NIAMS.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 2</head><p><s>Gene transcripts common to microarray and RNA-seq analyses</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Techniques for clustering gene expression data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kerr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ruskin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Crane</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computers in biology and medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="283" to="293" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 18061589</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative trait transcripts for nicotine resistance in Drosophila melanogaster</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Passador-Gurgel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hsieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="264" to="268" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 17237783</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Advantages and limitations of microarray technology in human cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Russo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zegar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Giordano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncogene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6497" to="6507" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 14528274</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequencing degraded RNA addressed by 3&apos; tag counting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sigurgeirsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Emanuelsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lundeberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e91851</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 24632678</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA-seq: impact of RNA degradation on transcript quantification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gallego</forename><surname>Romero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Pai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24885439</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of RNA integrity on uniquely mapped reads in RNA-Seq</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Souaiaia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Herstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Res Notes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">753</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 25339126</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA-Seq: a revolutionary tool for transcriptomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gerstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Snyder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature reviews Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of RNA-Seq and microarray in transcriptome profiling of activated T cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Fung-Leung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bittner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24454679</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computational methods for transcriptome annotation and quantification using RNA-seq</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Garber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Grabherr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Guttman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="469" to="477" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 21623353</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changes in Transcriptome-Wide Gene Expression of Anterior Cruciate Ligament Tears Based on Time From Injury</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Brophy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Tycksen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sandell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Sports Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2064" to="2075" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 27159315</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The concordance between RNA-seq and microarray data depends on chemical treatment and transcript abundance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bushel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="926" to="932" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 25150839</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Concordance between RNA-sequencing data and DNA microarray data in transcriptome analysis of proliferative and quiescent fibroblasts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Trost</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Moir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gillespie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">R Soc Open Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">150402</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 26473061</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship of age and body mass index to the expression of obesity and osteoarthritis-related genes in human meniscus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Rai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sandell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cheverud</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Obes (Lond)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1238" to="1246" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 23318714</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BioMart and Bioconductor: a powerful link between biological databases and microarray data analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Durinck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Moreau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kasprzyk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3439" to="3440" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 16082012</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcriptome analysis of injured human meniscus reveals a distinct phenotype of meniscus degeneration with aging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Rai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Patra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sandell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2090" to="2101" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 23658108</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship of gene expression in the injured human meniscus to body mass index: a biologic connection between obesity and osteoarthritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Rai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Patra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sandell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2152" to="2164" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 24692131</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA Microarray Analysis of Macroscopically Normal Articular Cartilage from Knees Undergoing Partial Medial Meniscectomy: Potential Prediction of the Risk for Developing Osteoarthritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Rai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sandell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e0155373</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 27171008</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">STAR: ultrafast universal RNA-seq aligner</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dobin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Schlesinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 23104886</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">featureCounts: an efficient general purpose program for assigning sequence reads to genomic features</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Smyth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24227677</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sailfish enables alignment-free isoform quantification from RNA-seq reads using lightweight algorithms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Patro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mount</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kingsford</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="464" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 24752080</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RSeQC: quality control of RNA-seq experiments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2184" to="2185" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 22743226</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robustly detecting differential expression in RNA sequencing data using observation weights</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lindsay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e91</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 24753412</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of periostin in tissue remodeling across health and disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Conway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Izuhara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kudo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Mol Life Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1279" to="1288" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 24146092</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Elevated expression of periostin in human osteoarthritic cartilage and its potential role in matrix degradation via matrix metalloproteinase-13</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Attur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Shimada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FASEB J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4107" to="4121" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 26092928</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expression and pathological effects of periostin in human osteoarthritis cartilage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chijimatsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kunugiza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Taniyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Musculoskelet Disord</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">215</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 26289167</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microarray analysis reveals age-related differences in gene expression during the development of osteoarthritis in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Loeser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Olex</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mcnulty</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="705" to="717" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 21972019</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Periostin expression and epithelial-mesenchymal transition in cancer: a review and an update</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Morra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Moch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Virchows Arch</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">459</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="465" to="475" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 21997759</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative assessment of methods for the computational inference of transcript isoform abundance from RNA-seq data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kanitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gypas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gruber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">150</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 26201343</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Differential analyses for RNA-seq: transcript-level estimates improve gene-level inferences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Soneson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Love</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">F1000Res. 2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1521</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 26925227</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating accuracy of RNA-Seq and microarrays with proteomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">161</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 19371429</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating gene expression in C57BL/6J and DBA/2J mouse striatum using RNA-Seq and microarrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bottomly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Walter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hunter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">17820</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 21455293</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA-seq: an assessment of technical reproducibility and comparison with gene expression arrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Marioni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Mason</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mane</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1509" to="1517" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 18550803</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effector CD4+ T cell expression signatures and immunemediated disease associated genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ferguson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e38510</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 22715389</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RNA-Seq vs dual-and single-channel microarray data: sensitivity analysis for differential expression and clustering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sirbu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kerr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Crane</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e50986</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 23251411</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey of best practices for RNA-seq data analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Conesa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Madrigal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tarazona</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 26813401</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential expression analysis of multifactor RNA-Seq experiments with respect to biological variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mccarthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Smyth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4288" to="4297" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 22287627</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Precision weights unlock linear model analysis tools for RNA-seq read counts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Law</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">24485249</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comprehensive assessment of RNA-seq accuracy, reproducibility and information content by the Sequencing Quality Control Consortium</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sm-I</forename><surname>Consortium</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="903" to="914" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 25150838</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring differential gene expression by short read sequencing: quantitative comparison to 2-channel gene expression microarrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bloom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kruglyak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">221</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 19435513</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An experimental evaluation of castellated laryngofissure and bilateral arytenoid lateralisation for the relief of laryngeal paralysis in dogs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Burbidge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Goulden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Australian veterinary journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="268" to="272" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 1953550</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of massively parallel nucleotide sequencing with oligonucleotide microarrays for global transcription profiling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bradford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yates</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">282</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 20444259</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microarrays, deep sequencing and the true measure of the transcriptome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Malone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Oliver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">34</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 21627854</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomewide analysis of mRNA processing in yeast using splicing-specific microarrays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Sugnet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ares</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">296</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="907" to="910" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 11988574</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">affy--analysis of Affymetrix GeneChip data at the probe level</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gautier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cope</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bolstad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="315" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 14960456</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microarray data analysis: from disarray to consolidation and consensus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Allison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Page</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature reviews Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reliability and reproducibility issues in DNA microarray measurements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Draghici</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Khatri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Eklund</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="109" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 16380191</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis and design of RNA sequencing experiments for identifying isoform regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Airoldi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1009" to="1015" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 21057496</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
