<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Le Coutre</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Medizinische Klinik m.S. Hämatologie und Onkologie</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow Klinikum</addrLine>
									<settlement>Charité</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Cancer Theme</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Haematology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">SA Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">South Australian Health and Medical Research Institute (SAHMRI)</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Adelaide</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Adelaide</settlement>
									<region>South Australia</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">F-X</forename><surname>Mahon</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratoire d&apos;Hématologie et Service des Maladies du Sang</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Bordeaux</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Bordeaux et Institut Bergonié</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bordeaux</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">D-W</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Hematology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Seoul St Mary&apos;s Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">The Catholic University of Korea</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">South Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Steegmann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Hematology and IIS-IP</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hospital Universitario de la Princesa</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Madrid</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Division of Hematology/Oncology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of California at San Francisco School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>San Francisco</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gooden</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="institution">Bristol-Myers Squibb</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Princeton</settlement>
									<region>NJ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cortes</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="institution">Bristol-Myers Squibb</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Princeton</settlement>
									<region>NJ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Cancer Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Leukemia</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">The University of Texas</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">MD Anderson Cancer Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Houston</settlement>
									<region>TX</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">313D84E7FD8B45501CE66278E9D15C76</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1038/leu.2015.352</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>HOXB6 overexpression in murine bone marrow immortalizes a myelomonocytic precursor in vitro and causes hematopoietic stem cell expansion and acute myeloid leukemia in vivo.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>OPEN</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Low incidence of peripheral arterial disease in patients receiving dasatinib in clinical trials</head><p><s>Leukemia (2016) 30, 1593-1596; doi:10.1038/leu.2015.352</s></p><p><s>2]<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[6]</ref> The selection of BCR-ABL TKI treatment for an individual patient is influenced by factors including any previous treatment, likelihood of benefit, risk of toxicities and the potential for end-organ damage resulting from use, particularly as a long-term therapy is expected in chronic myeloid leukemia in chronic phase (CML-CP).</s><s>Despite considerable overlap of safety profiles, there are distinct drug-specific adverse events associated with each TKI. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> Peripheral arterial disease (PAD) is often associated with claudication, and may result in critical limb ischemia, and increased risks of loss of limb or death. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">7</ref></s><s>We evaluated safety databases of dasatinib clinical trials in patients with Philadelphia chromosome-positive (Ph+) leukemias to identify PAD or PADrelated events.</s><s>We also conducted a standardized incidence ratio (SIR) analysis to evaluate the rate of PAD or PAD-related events in the trials relative to the rate in external reference populations derived from administrative data sets, representing a general adult population in the United States and a CML population that did not receive dasatinib.</s><s>This retrospective analysis used pooled safety data from 2712 adults with CML or Ph+ acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL) treated with dasatinib in 11 clinical trials, including two first-line trials (n = 324) and nine trials in imatinibresistant or -intolerant patients (n = 2388; Supplementary Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S1</ref>).</s><s>The median duration of dasatinib treatment was 19 months (range: 0.03-93 months).</s><s>The trial enrollment criteria permitted inclusion of patients with myocardial infarction 46 months prior, congestive heart failure 43 months prior and previously uncontrolled angina controlled ⩾ 3 months.</s></p><p><s>Bristol-Myers Squibb safety databases for the included trials were examined to identify PAD or PAD-related events, using the following Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities preferred terms: arterial stenosis, arterial thrombosis, arteriosclerosis, arterial stenosis limb, intermittent claudication, femoral artery occlusion, necrosis ischemic and PAD.</s></p><p><s>For the SIR analysis (SIR = observed number of events/expected number of events; detailed description in Supplementary Materials), two external populations were extracted from Truven Health Analytics Marketscan Commercial Claims and Medicare Supplementary database (Ann Arbor, MI, USA) between 2008 and 2013.</s><s>MarketScan consists of data from commercial health plans, Medicaid, Medicare, and self-insurance for Americans.</s><s>Each reference population included individuals enrolled in the databases for ⩾ 60 days before the index date.</s><s>Adult patients were included in the general reference population (n = 90 000 000), and the CML reference population had ⩾ 2 diagnostic codes for CML and were not using dasatinib (n = 15 000).</s><s>To obtain the expected number of cases, the age and gender-specific person-time of dasatinib-treated patients in the trials were multiplied by the age and gender-specific rates of events in the external populations.</s></p><p><s>PAD or PAD-related events were detected in 11 patients during dasatinib treatment among 2712 individuals with a cumulative dasatinib exposure of 6421 patient-years, which corresponds to a cumulative incidence of 0.4% and an incidence rate (per 100 patient-years) of 0.2%.</s><s>Of the 11 patients, all were previously treated with a TKI; 8 were resistant and 3 were intolerant to prior imatinib therapy (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1)</ref>  The chronic phase disease of this patient had clonal evolution.</s></p><p><s>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s><s>For these patients, median age at baseline was 68 years (range: 44-80 years) and median duration of dasatinib before diagnosis of PAD or PAD-related event was 777 days (range: 3-2227 days).</s><s>Median duration of prior imatinib therapy amongst these patients was 29 months (n = 9; range: 2-74 months).</s></p><p><s>Of the 11 patients, 8 had CML-CP, 2 had CML in accelerated phase (CML-AP) and one had CML in blast phase (CML-BP) of lymphoid phenotype.</s><s>Ten of the 11 patients were on BID (twice daily) dosing regimens.</s><s>Of the eight patients with CML-CP, only one started at a dose of 100 mg QD (once daily), the current recommended dose of dasatinib for CML-CP. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> Dosing regimens for the other seven patients with CML-CP ranged from 25 to 70 mg BID.</s><s>The current recommended dose for CML-AP or CML-BP is 140 mg QD; 2 however, the patients with CML-AP (n = 2) and CML-BP (n = 1) received a 70 mg BID starting dose of dasatinib.</s><s>All 11 patients had pre-existing comorbidities/conditions that potentially increased the risk of developing PAD (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>), including one patient who had prior arterial bypass surgery, one with a history of angioplasty and stent, and one who had pre-existing PAD.</s><s>Furthermore, six patients had hypertension, four had pre-existing ischemic heart disease, four were former or current smokers, two had pre-existing noncardiac atherosclerosis, two had hypercholesterolemia, two had diabetes mellitus and one had deep vein thrombosis (DVT).</s><s>Of nine patients with PAD or a PAD-related event with available data, all were receiving other medications at baseline.</s><s>The PAD or PAD-related events in the 11 cases included intermittent claudication (four patients), femoral artery occlusion (two patients), PAD (two patients), peripheral ischemia (two patients), peripheral artery thrombosis (one patients) and peripheral vascular disorder (one patient), with one patient experiencing two of these events (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>All events identified were Common Terminology Criteria grade ⩽ 3. Of seven patients with available molecular response data, best responses at any time included 27% (n = 3) with a major molecular response, 18% (n = 2) achieving complete molecular response (CMR 4.5 ) and 36% (n = 4) achieving a complete cytogenetic response.</s><s>Dasatinib treatment was interrupted in five patients due to PAD or a PAD-related event, and no patients discontinued dasatinib because of PAD or PAD-related events (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>SIR analysis showed that the observed number of PAD or PADrelated events (n = 11) in the pooled population did not exceed the expected number of events (n = 20) in the general population (SIR (95% confidence interval; CI), 0.56 (0.31-1.01)).</s><s>Similarly, the observed number of PAD or PAD-related events (n = 11) in the pooled population did not exceed the expected number (n = 43) based on rates in the reference CML population (SIR (95% CI), 0.26 (0.14-0.46);</s><s>Supplementary Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">S2</ref>).</s></p><p><s>The current analysis investigated the incidence of PAD or PADrelated events in patients treated with dasatinib to test the hypothesis that PAD might be a class effect among second-and third-generation BCR-ABL TKIs.</s><s>Previous reports have described an association of PAD with either ponatinib or nilotinib treatment. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">5</ref></s><s>he cumulative incidence and incidence rate (per 100 patientyears) reported here are higher than those previously published in a retrospective analysis by Giles and colleagues for imatinib (0.2% and 0.1%, respectively); however, they are lower than cited for nilotinib (1.3% and 0.5%, respectively) and interferon-α plus cytarabine (0.6% and 0.6%, respectively; Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>). <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">8</ref></s><s>No PAD or PAD-related events were identified in newly diagnosed CML patients treated with dasatinib in the DASISION trial, which has the longest median exposure time to dasatinib of any study.</s></p><p><s>Generally, risk factors for cardiovascular disease are also risk factors for PAD or PAD-related events. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">9</ref></s><s>The prevalence of PAD increases with age and concomitant cardiovascular disease risk factors. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">10</ref></s><s>Some clinical trials report a lower incidence of PAD in CML and Ph+ ALL compared with published rates for the general population; however, this may be affected by the study entry criteria that exclude patients with significant cardiovascular disease. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">11</ref></s><s>The included dasatinib clinical trials (with the exception of CA180-002) allowed the participation of patients with diabetes and patients with a history of cardiac comorbidities.</s><s>Ten of the 11 patients with PAD or PAD-related events had at least one potential risk factor for PAD (the remaining patient had DVT).</s></p><p><s>The extended survival of CML patients in the TKI era makes it important to understand the implications of long-term treatment and understand better the potentially irreversible and severe toxicities of some TKIs.</s><s>The results presented here do not show an association between dasatinib treatment and development of symptomatic PAD in patients with CML or Ph+ ALL, and are consistent with the hypothesis that PAD observed in CML patients is not a class effect of second-and thirdgeneration BCR-ABL TKIs.</s><s>Similar analyses evaluating cardiac and cerebrovascular adverse events in CML patients treated with BCR-ABL TKIs are warranted, based on the findings by Chai-Adisaksopha et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">12</ref> Second-generation TKIs, including dasatinib, have established higher rates of molecular remission in CML than reported with imatinib, with the hope for cure or at least treatment-free remissions.</s><s>When selecting treatment for Ph+ leukemia, physicians should carefully assess overall cardiovascular health, as well as pre-existing comorbidities and risk factors present at baseline.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>. No cases of PAD or PAD-related events were identified among the 258 patients treated with first-line dasatinib in DASatinib versus Imatinib Study In treatment-Naive CML patients (DASISION) (median duration of 60 months (range: 0.03-73 months)).</s><s>Characteristics, comorbidities and risk factors of the 11 patients with PAD or a PAD-related event are shown in Accepted article preview online 21 December 2015; advance online publication, 12 January 2016</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Characteristics, outcomes, risk factors and management of PAD and PAD-related adverse events</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Outcomes (best response Adverse event</cell><cell>at any time) management</cell><cell cols="2">MMR CMR 4.5 CCyR Dasatinib dose</cell><cell>modification</cell><cell>NR NR No Interrupted</cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes Yes Yes None</cell><cell></cell><cell>No No No Interrupted</cell><cell></cell><cell>No No No None</cell><cell>No No No None</cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes No Yes Interrupted</cell><cell></cell><cell>NR NR Yes None</cell><cell></cell><cell>NR NR No None</cell><cell></cell><cell>NR NR No None</cell><cell></cell><cell>Interrupted</cell><cell>No No No None</cell><cell>Yes Yes Yes Interrupted</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>First</cell><cell></cell><cell>occurrence?</cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell>No</cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell>Yes</cell></row><row><cell>Adverse event characteristics</cell><cell></cell><cell>CTC Dasatinib Time on dasatinib</cell><cell cols="2">grade a starting dose before onset, days</cell><cell>1 25 mg BID, 5 d 2227</cell><cell>per wk</cell><cell>2, 2 70 mg BID NR, 42</cell><cell></cell><cell>2 70 mg BID 3</cell><cell></cell><cell>1, 3 70 mg BID 343, 657</cell><cell>2 70 mg BID 868</cell><cell></cell><cell>3, 3 50 mg BID 777, 870</cell><cell></cell><cell>2 70 mg BID 151</cell><cell></cell><cell>3 70 mg BID 367</cell><cell></cell><cell>1 50 mg BID 1177</cell><cell></cell><cell>3 1323</cell><cell>3, 3, 3 100 mg QD 1229, 1361, 1447</cell><cell>3 50 mg BID 1692</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Preferred term</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Femoral artery</cell><cell>occlusion</cell><cell>Intermittent</cell><cell>claudication</cell><cell>Femoral artery</cell><cell>occlusion</cell><cell>PAD</cell><cell>Intermittent</cell><cell>claudication</cell><cell>Peripheral artery</cell><cell>thrombosis</cell><cell>Intermittent</cell><cell>claudication</cell><cell>PAD</cell><cell></cell><cell>Intermittent</cell><cell>claudication</cell><cell>Peripheral</cell><cell>vascular disorder</cell><cell>Peripheral</cell><cell>ischemia</cell><cell>Peripheral</cell><cell>ischemia</cell></row><row><cell>Pre-existing comorbidities and risk factors present at baseline</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Pre-existing heart disease, previous smoker</cell><cell></cell><cell>Previous smoker</cell><cell></cell><cell>Pre-existing noncardiac atherosclerosis, hypertension,</cell><cell>hypercholesterolemia</cell><cell>Diabetes mellitus</cell><cell>Pre-existing ischemic heart disease, hypertension,</cell><cell>diabetes mellitus</cell><cell>Hypertension</cell><cell></cell><cell>Deep vein thrombosis</cell><cell></cell><cell>Pre-existing ischemic heart disease, pre-existing</cell><cell>noncardiac atherosclerosis, hypertension</cell><cell>Arterial bypass surgery, pre-existing ischemic heart</cell><cell>disease</cell><cell></cell><cell>PAD on a pre-existing lesion, hypertension, previous</cell><cell>smoker</cell><cell>History of angioplasty and stent, hypertension,</cell><cell>hypercholesterolemia, smoker</cell></row><row><cell>Age/CML</cell><cell>phase</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>73/CP</cell><cell></cell><cell>68/AP</cell><cell></cell><cell>80/AP b</cell><cell></cell><cell>63/CP</cell><cell>74/CP</cell><cell></cell><cell>71/CP</cell><cell></cell><cell>54/LBP</cell><cell></cell><cell>67/CP c</cell><cell></cell><cell>75/CP</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>65/CP</cell><cell>44/CP</cell></row></table><note><p><s>Abbreviations: AP, accelerated phase; BID, twice daily; CCyR, complete cytogenetic response; CML, chronic myeloid leukemia; CMR, complete molecular response; CP, chronic phase; CTC, Common Terminology Criteria; d, day; LBP, lymphoid blast phase; MMR, major molecular response; NR, not reported; PAD, peripheral arterial disease; QD, once daily; wk, week.</s><s>a National Cancer Institute CTCAE v.3.0.</s><s>b This patient was the sole patient for whom the PAD-related adverse event was not a first occurrence.</s><s>c</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Incidence of PAD and PAD-related events in patients receiving treatment for Ph+ leukemia in clinical trials Abbreviations: Ara-C, cytarabine; BID, twice daily; CML, chronic myeloid leukemia; CP, chronic phase; ENESTnd, Evaluating Nilotinib Efficacy and Safety in clinical Trials-newly diagnosed patients; IFN, interferon; IRIS, International Randomized Study of Interferon and ST1571; PAD, peripheral arterial disease; Ph+, Philadelphia chromosome-positive; QD, once daily; TOPS, Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor Optimization and Selectivity Study.</s><s>a Includes newly diagnosed CML-CP (n = 324) and imatinib-resistant or -intolerant CML (any phase) and Ph+ ALL (n = 2388).</s><s>b In Giles et al, 7 PAD included atherosclerotic and thrombotic events, excluding functional (vasoreactive), embolic or aneurysmal disorders, in the arteries of lower and upper extremities.</s><s>Terms indicative of PAD included: arterial disorder, peripheral ischemia, arterial insufficiency, arteriosclerosis obliterans, peripheral vascular disorder, arterial occlusive disease, femoral arterial stenosis, arterial stenosis, femoral artery occlusion, peripheral artery angioplasty, arterial stenosis limb, intermittent claudication, peripheral revascularization, arterial thrombosis limb and PAD. 8 c Patients treated with IFN+Ara-C had shorter median duration of therapy (8 months) compared with nilotinib (36 months) and imatinib (45 months) cohorts, because of early crossover to imatinib.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Dasatinib</cell><cell>Imatinib</cell><cell>Nilotinib</cell><cell>No BCR-ABL inhibitor</cell></row><row><cell>Dose</cell><cell cols="2">15-240 mg per day 400 mg QD or BID</cell><cell>300 or 400 mg BID</cell><cell>IFN 5 × 10 6 U/m 2 per day; Ara-C</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>20 mg/m 2 per day for 10 days per month</cell></row><row><cell>Trial</cell><cell cols="2">11 dasatinib trials TOPS, IRIS, ENESTnd</cell><cell>ENESTnd</cell><cell>IRIS</cell></row><row><cell>Study population</cell><cell>Ph+ leukemia a</cell><cell cols="3">Newly diagnosed CML-CP Newly diagnosed CML-CP Newly diagnosed CML-CP</cell></row><row><cell>Patients treated (n)</cell><cell>2712</cell><cell>1301</cell><cell>556</cell><cell>533</cell></row><row><cell>PAD cases b (n)</cell><cell>1 1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Cumulative incidence (%) 0.4</cell><cell>0.2</cell><cell>1.3</cell><cell>0.6</cell></row><row><cell>Exposure, patient-years</cell><cell>6421</cell><cell>4523</cell><cell>1464</cell><cell>534 c</cell></row><row><cell>Incidence rate (per 100</cell><cell>0.2</cell><cell>0.1</cell><cell>0.5</cell><cell>0.6</cell></row><row><cell>patient-years), %</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Data source</cell><cell>Current analysis</cell><cell></cell><cell>Adapted from Giles et al. 7,8</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">© 2016 Macmillan Publishers LimitedLeukemia (2016) 1580 -1627</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Leukemia (2016) 1580 -1627 © 2016 Macmillan Publishers Limited</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head><p><s>We acknowledge Jeanette A Preston, formerly of BMS, for review of the manuscript.</s><s>This analysis was supported by BMS.</s><s>Professional medical writing support was provided by Ami P Modi, PhD and Beverly E Barton, PhD of StemScientific, an Ashfield Company, part of UDG Healthcare plc.</s><s>We did not receive financial compensation for the manuscript.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</head><p><s>All authors provided feedback and guidance on the analysis and interpretation of the results, critically reviewed the manuscript and approved the final draft for submission.</s><s>The authors take full responsibility for the content of this publication and confirm that it reflects their viewpoint and medical expertise.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</head><p><s>PDL has received honoraria from BMS, Novartis and Pfizer, and has received research funding from Novartis.</s><s>TPH has received honoraria and research funding from BMS and Novartis, and has acted in an advisory role for both companies.</s><s>F-XM has served as a consultant for and has received research funding from BMS and Novartis; he has served on advisory boards for BMS, Novartis, Pfizer and Ariad.</s><s>D-WK has served as a consultant for and has received honoraria and research funding from Novartis, BMS, Pfizer and Ilyang.</s><s>JLS has served as a consultant for and received honoraria from BMS, Novartis and Pfizer.</s><s>NPS has received research funding from BMS, Ariad and Pfizer, and serves as a DSMB member for Teva.</s><s>KG and NW are employees of BMS.</s><s>JEC has served as a consultant for Ariad, BMS, Novartis and Pfizer, and has received research funding from Ariad, BMS, Novartis, Pfizer and Teva.</s></p><p><s>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on the Leukemia website (http://www.nature.com/leu)</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SOX11 defines two different subtypes of mantle cell lymphoma through transcriptional regulation of BCL6</head><p><s>Leukemia (2016) 30, 1596-1599; doi:10.1038/leu.2015.355</s><s>4]<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[5]</ref> Intriguingly, the presence of Accepted article preview online 29 December 2015; advance online publication, 22 January 2016</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vitro activity of Bcr-Abl inhibitors AMN107 and BMS-354825 against clinically relevant imatinib-resistant Abl kinase domain mutants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>O'hare</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Walters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Stoffregen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Manley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mestan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4500" to="4505" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sprycel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>dasatinib) [prescribing information</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gleevec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>imatinib) [prescribing information</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">NJ: Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">East</forename><surname>Hanover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Iclusig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>prescribing information</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cambridge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>Ariad Pharmaceuticals, Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Tasigna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>prescribing information</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Switzerland</forename><surname>Stein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Novartis Pharma Stein AG</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bosulif</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>Pfizer Labs</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>prescribing information</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rates of peripheral arterial occlusive disease in patients with chronic myeloid leukemia in the chronic phase treated with imatinib, nilotinib, or non-tyrosine kinase therapy: a retrospective cohort analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Giles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mauro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ortmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mcneill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Woodman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Leukemia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1310" to="1315" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inter-Society Consensus for the Management of Peripheral Arterial Disease (TASC II)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Norgren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hiatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dormandy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Nehler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fgr</forename><surname>Fowkes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Vasc Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="S5" to="S67" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of global estimates of prevalence and risk factors for peripheral artery disease in 2000 and 2010: a systematic review and analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Fowkes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rudan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Rudan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Aboyans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Denenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mcdermott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">382</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1329" to="1340" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nilotinib versus imatinib for newly diagnosed chronic myeloid leukemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Saglio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Issaragrisil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Le Coutre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Etienne</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lobo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">362</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2251" to="2259" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Risk factors and cardiovascular diseases associated with asymptomatic peripheral arterial occlusive disease. The Limburg PAOD Study. Peripheral arterial occlusive disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hooi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Stoffers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kester</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rinkens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kaiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Van Ree</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scand J Prim Health Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="182" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chai-Adisaksopha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Lam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hillis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3109/10428194.2015.1091929</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Leuk Lymphoma</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-10-20">2015. 20 October 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Major arterial events in chronic myeloid leukemia patients treated with tyrosine kinase inhibitors: a metaanalysis. To view a copy of this license, visit http://</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
