<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="de">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Aus der Klinik für Anästhesiologie mit Schwerpunkt operative Intensivmedizin der Medizinischen Fakultät Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin DISSERTATION Leukocyte opioid receptors mediate analgesia via Ca 2+ -regulated release of opioid peptides zur Erlangung des akademischen Grades Doctor of Philosophy (PhD)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Medizinischen</forename><surname>Fakultät</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin von Melih Özgür Celik aus Istanbul</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Türkei</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Datum der Promotion</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Aus der Klinik für Anästhesiologie mit Schwerpunkt operative Intensivmedizin der Medizinischen Fakultät Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin DISSERTATION Leukocyte opioid receptors mediate analgesia via Ca 2+ -regulated release of opioid peptides zur Erlangung des akademischen Grades Doctor of Philosophy (PhD)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D0FE5C94E17E2EF222814A531074A6D6</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="de">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Zusammenfassung</head><p><s>Opioide sind der Goldstandard zur Behandlung von mittelstarken bis starken Schmerzen.</s><s>Gemäß</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Abstract</head><p><s>Opioid are the gold standard for treatment of moderate to severe pain.</s><s>Traditionally, opioids produce analgesia by regulating both pre-and post-synaptic neurons via blocking Ca 2+ influx, consequently inhibiting the release of excitatory neurotransmitters (e.g., glutamate) and by hyperpolarizing the synaptic membrane via decreasing intercellular K + concentrations.</s><s>Even though the number of prescriptions for opioids has greatly increased in the last decade, there are major problems with opioids due to their central side affects, such as respiratory depression and addiction, which might be avoided by peripheral administration of the opioids.</s><s>Circulating leukocytes also produce opioid peptides and opioid receptors during injury and they accumulate at the inflammation site.</s><s>Here we show that the activation of opioid receptors on leukocytes leads to the secretion of leukocyte derived endogenous opioid peptides Met-enkephalin, βendorphin and dynorphin A, which bind to the local opioid receptors on peripheral sensory neurons to cause analgesia.</s><s>As a model of neuropathy, chronic constriction injury of the sciatic nerve was performed on mice, which caused mechanical hypersensitivity.</s><s>Pain was attenuated by the application of exogenous agonists of the δ-, µ-, and κ-opioid receptors at the injury site, which was infiltrated by opioid peptide containing leukocytes.</s><s>The analgesic effect was abolished by systemic leukocyte depletion and pharmacological inactivation of opioid peptides.</s></p><p><s>In addition, agonist induced pain relief was attenuated on opioid peptide knock-out mice.</s></p><p><s>Adoptive transfer of leukocytes from wild-type into leukocyte depleted mice reconstituted agonist induced analgesia in vivo.</s><s>Analgesia could not be reconstituted when leukocytes were transferred from opioid receptor knock-out mice.</s><s>Ex vivo, opioid receptor agonists significantly elevated the secretion of opioid peptides from leukocytes isolated from damaged nerves.</s><s>This secretion was dependent on intracellular Ca 2+ and blocking Gαi/o and Gβγ subunits, PLC and IP 3 receptor decreased the opioid peptide secretion back to the basal levels while PKC inhibition only had a partial effect.</s><s>Similarly, leukocyte depletion resulted in the decrease of exogenous opioid analgesia in vivo.</s><s>The analgesic effects could be re-established by transfer of leukocytes ex vivo pretreated with extracellular Ca 2+ chelator, but was unaltered when leukocytes were pretreated with blockers of Gαi/o, Gβγ proteins or intracellular Ca 2+ chelator.</s><s>These findings demonstrate that both in vivo analgesia and ex vivo opioid peptide release were mediated by opioid receptors on leukocytes coupled to the Gαi/o-Gβγ protein-PLC-IP 3 receptors pathway and dependent on intracellular Ca 2+ which can be identified as an unconventional mechanism of pathological pain control.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Affidavit</head><p><s>I, Melih Özgür Celik, certify under penalty of perjury by my own signature that I have submitted the dissertation on the topic "Leukocyte opioid receptors mediate analgesia via Ca 2+ -regulated release of opioid peptides".</s><s>I prepared this dissertation independently and without assistance from third parties, I used no other aids than the listed sources and resources.</s></p><p><s>All points based literally or in spirit on publications or presentations of other authors are, as such, in proper citations (see "uniform requirements for manuscripts (URM)" the ICMJE www.icmje.org)</s><s>indicated.</s><s>The section on methodology (in particular practical work, laboratory requirements, statistical processing) and results (in particular images, graphics and tables) corresponds to the URM (s.o) and are answered by me.</s><s>My contribution in the selected publication for this dissertation corresponds to those that are specified in the following joint declaration with the responsible person and supervisor.</s></p><p><s>The importance of this affidavit and the criminal consequences of a false affidavit (section 156,161 of the Criminal Code) are known to me and I understand the rights and responsibilities stated therein.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Detailed Declaration of Contribution</head><p><s>Melih Özgür Celik had the following share in the following publication:</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>der klassischen Sichtweise bewirken sie eine Analgesie über die Regulation prä-und postsynaptischer Neuronen durch die Blockade des Ca 2+ -Einstroms, und somit die Freisetzung exzitatorischer Neurotransmitter (z.B.</s><s>Glutamat), sowie durch Hyperpolarisierung der synaptischen Membran über die Herabsetzung der intrazellulären K + -Konzentration.</s><s>Die Anzahl der Verschreibungen von Opioiden ist innerhalb des letzten Jahrzehnts stark angestiegen, obwohl die Anwendung von Opioiden schwerwiegende, über das zentrale Nervensystem vermittelte Nebenwirkungen wie Atemdepression und Abhängigkeit zeigt.</s><s>Diese Nebenwirkungen können möglicherweise durch die periphere Verabreichung von Opioiden umgangen werden.</s><s>Immunzellen, welche sich an Verletzungen und Entzündungsherden anreichern, exprimieren Opioidrezeptoren und Opioidpeptide.</s><s>In dieser Studie zeigen wir, dass die Aktivierung von Opioidrezeptoren auf Immunzellen diese zur Sekretion der endogenen Opioidpeptide Met-Enkephalin, β-Endorphin und Dynorphin A veranlasst, welche wiederum lokal Opioidrezeptoren auf peripheren sensorischen Neuronen binden und darüber eine Analgesie bewirken.</s><s>Als Modell für neuropathischen Schmerz wurde eine chronische Kontstriktionsläsion des Ischiasnerves an Mäusen durchgeführt, welche zu mechanischer Hypersensitivität in der Pfote führte.</s><s>Die lokale Verabreichung exogener Agonisten der δ-, µ-und κ-Opioidrezeptoren nahe der Verletzung und in der Gegenwart Opioidpeptid-exprimierender Immunzellen führte zu einer Schmerzminderung.</s><s>Eine systemische Entfernung von Immunzellen sowie eine pharmakologische Inaktivierung von Opioidpeptiden führten zur Aufhebung dieses analgetischen Effekts.</s><s>In Opioidpeptid-Knockout Mäusen war zudem die Schmerzlinderung durch lokal applizierte Opioidrezeptor-Agonisten verringert.</s><s>In Immunzell-depletierten Mäusen führte ein Transfer von Immunzellen aus Wildtyp, nicht aber aus Opioidrezeptor-Knockout Mäusen zur Wiederherstellung der Opioid-induzierten Analgesie in vivo.</s><s>Ex vivo bewirkten Agonisten der Opioidrezeptoren eine verstärkte Sekretion von Opioidpeptiden durch zuvor aus geschädigten Nerven isolierte Immunzellen.</s><s>Die Peptidsekretion war abhängig von intrazellulärem Ca 2+ .</s><s>Eine Blockade der Gai/o und Gbg Untereinheiten heterotrimerer G-Proteine, der PLC und des IP 3 -Rezeptors führten zu einer auf basale Werte reduzierten Peptidsekretion, während eine Inhibition der PKC einen nur teilweise mindernden Effekt auf die Sekretion zeigte.</s><s>Analog dazu konnte der analgetische Effekt lokal applizierter Opioide in Immunzell-depletierten Mäusen durch den Transfer von Immunzellen wiederhergestellt werden, wenn die Immunzellen ex vivo mit einem Chelator für extrazelluläres Ca 2+ behandelt wurden, nicht aber nach Behandlung der Immunzellen mit Inhibitoren der Gαi/o-und Gβγ Proteine oder einem Chelator für intrazelluläres Ca 2+ .</s><s>Diese Ergebnisse zeigen, dass Opioidrezeptoren auf Immunzellen über den Signalweg Gαi/o-Gβγ Protein-PLC-IP 3 Rezeptor, abhängig von intrazellulärem Ca 2+ , ex vivo die Sekretion von Opioidpeptiden und in vivo Analgesie vermitteln.</s><s>Dieser Signalweg stellt einen unkonventionellen Mechanismus zur Kontrolle pathologischer Schmerzen dar.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Abbreviated Journal Title(linked to journal information) ISSN</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>Firstly, I would like to thank Professor Halina Machelska for the opportunity to work in her lab.</s><s>I am also grateful for the supervision and support which I received from her.</s><s>I would also express my sincere thanks to Dr. Dominika Labuz and Philip Stötzner for their support, technical assistance and being available when I needed.</s><s>Special thanks to Dr. Melanie Busch-Dienstfertig and Barbara Trampenau for their technical assistance.</s><s>I would also like to thank all my current colleagues Giovanna Del Vecchio, Johanna Meyer, Maria Pannell, Julia Temp and Simone Scheffel and my former colleagues which is not listed here.</s><s>Special thanks to Onur Güralp, Can Gülenay and Asli Baysal for their invaluable friendship.</s><s>Finally, yet importantly, I give all my love and thanks to my family Perisan Celik, Adil Celik, Tijen Celik,   Sinan Celik, Ozan Celik, Anna Baum, Gitta Baum, Gisbert Waschk, Peyima Kaya, Cetin Hakan   Kaya, Özcan Kaya and Ülker Barlak.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Curriculum vitae</head><p><s>Mein Lebenslauf wird aus datenschutzrechtlichen Gründen in der elektronischen Version meiner Arbeit nicht veröffentlicht.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Curriculum vitae</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mein Lebenslauf wird aus datenschutzrechtlichen Gründen in der elektronischen</head><p><s>Version meiner Arbeit nicht veröffentlicht.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leukocyte opioid receptors mediate analgesia via Ca2+-regulated release of opioid peptides</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>Celik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Labuz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Henning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Busch-Dienstfertig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gaveriaux</forename><surname>Ruff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kieffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zimmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Machelska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Behav Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.bbi.2016.04.018</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bbi.2016.04.018" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Complete list of publications</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leukocyte opioid receptors mediate analgesia via Ca2+-regulated release of opioid peptides</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>Celik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Labuz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Henning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Busch-Dienstfertig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gaveriaux</forename><surname>Ruff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kieffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zimmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Machelska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Behav Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="242" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Impact factor: 5.81</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinct roles of exogenous opioid neuropathy-triggered heat pain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Labuz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>Celik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zimmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Machelska</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">32799</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Impact factor: 5.47</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Recent advances in understanding neuropathic pain: glia, sex differences, and epigenetics. F1000Res</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Machelska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>Celik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>in press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adoptive transfer of M2 macrophages reduces neuropathic pain via opioid peptides</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pannell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Labuz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>Celik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Keye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Batra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Siegmund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Machelska</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neuropimflammation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">262</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Impact factor: 5.49</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Helicobacter pylori in lacrimal secretions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Batioglu-Karaaltin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Saatci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Akpinar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>Celik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Develioglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Yigit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Külekci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Akarsubasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ear Nose Throat J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="E8" to="E11" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Impact factor: 1.000</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Opioids and TRPV1 in the peripheral control of neuropathic pain-Defining a target site in the injured nerve</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Labuz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Spahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>Celik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Machelska</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuropharmacology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="330" to="340" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Impact factor: 5.106</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Which uterine sparing technique should be used for uterine atony during cesarean section? The Bakri balloon or the B-Lynch suture?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Guralp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tuten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Unal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>Celik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dogan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch Gynecol Obstet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="1007" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leukocyte opioid receptors mediate analgesia via release of opioid peptides</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>Çelik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Machelska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">BMBF meeting</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin/Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Poster</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Leukocyte opioid receptors and neuroimmune interactions in the control of neuropathic pain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>-Çelik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dominika</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Machelska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<pubPlace>Florence/Italy</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Poster, 2013 EFIC Congress</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Leukocyte opioid receptors and neuroimmune interactions in the control of neuropathic pain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>-Çelik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dominika</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Machelska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2013</date>
			<pubPlace>Berlin Brain Days; Berlin/Germany</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neuroimmune interactions after nerve injury and opioid-mediated pain control. [Oral presentation and Poster</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>-Çelik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dominika</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Machelska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">GEBIN meeting</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Regensburg/Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Leukocyte opioid receptors in the control of neuropathic pain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>Çelik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Machelska</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain, Behavior and Immunity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012. 2013. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>s2-s9] and Poster</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterization of airborne bacteria in Istanbul urban areas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>-Kumru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Baysal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Uzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>Çelik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Akman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Akarsubasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Symposium on Microbial Ecology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Screening of ammonia-oxidizing archaea abundance in domestic and industrial wastewater plants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>-Çelik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kurt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kumru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Akarsubasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Poster, 2010 ISME symposia (Seattle/USA)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Use of cultivation independent methodology to assess bacterial communities in chronic tonsillitis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>-Durrer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>Çelik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kumru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Akarsubasi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Poster, 2010 ISME symposia (Seattle/USA)</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
