<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Reciprocal regulation of carbon monoxide metabolism and the circadian clock</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Roman</forename><surname>Klemz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Chronobiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Silke</forename><surname>Reischl</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Chronobiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Wallach</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Chronobiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nicole</forename><surname>Witte</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Cardiovascular Research CCR</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Karsten</forename><surname>Jürchott</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Chronobiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sabrina</forename><surname>Klemz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Chronobiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Veronika</forename><surname>Lang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Chronobiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stephan</forename><surname>Lorenzen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Bernhard-Nocht-Institut</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hamburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Miriam</forename><surname>Knauer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Cardiovascular Research CCR</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Steffi</forename><surname>Heidenreich</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Cardiovascular Research CCR</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Min</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cell and Developmental Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jürgen</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ripperger</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Fribourg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Fribourg</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Schupp</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Cardiovascular Research CCR</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ralf</forename><surname>Stanewsky</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cell and Developmental Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Achim</forename><surname>Kramer</surname></persName>
							<email>achim.kramer@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Chronobiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Westfälische Wilhelms-Universität Münster</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Münster</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Reciprocal regulation of carbon monoxide metabolism and the circadian clock</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5DEBFF9B1EEDC46255858651E2C1904E</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Circadian clocks are cell-autonomous oscillators regulating daily rhythms in a wide range of physiological, metabolic and behavioral processes.</s><s>Feedback of metabolic signals, such as redox state, NAD + /NADH and AMP/ADP ratios, or heme, modulate circadian rhythms and thereby optimize energy utilization across the 24-h cycle.</s><s>We show that rhythmic heme degradation, which generates the signaling molecule carbon monoxide (CO), is required for normal circadian rhythms as well as circadian metabolic outputs.</s><s>CO suppresses circadian transcription by attenuating CLOCK-BMAL1 binding to target promoters.</s><s>Pharmacological inhibition or genetic depletion of CO-producing heme oxygenases abrogates normal daily cycles in mammalian cells and Drosophila.</s><s>In mouse hepatocytes, suppression of CO production leads to a global upregulation of CLOCK-BMAL1dependent circadian gene expression and dysregulated glucose metabolism.</s><s>Together, our findings show that CO metabolism is an important link between the basic circadian-clock machinery, metabolism and behavior.</s></p><p><s>1 http://doc.rero.ch</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>In animals, fundamental clock mechanisms are highly conserved and are based on autoregulatory feedback loops that generate molecular oscillations in the transcript levels of approximately 5-10% of genes in essentially all tissues.</s><s>In mammals, the transcription-factor heterodimer CLOCK-BMAL1 (or NPAS2-BMAL1) activates the transcription of Per1, Per2 and Per3 (denoted Period) and Cry1 and Cry2 (denoted Cryptochrome) genes from E-box enhancer elements, whose protein products form complexes inhibiting CLOCK-BMAL1 transactivational activity after a delay of several hours.</s><s>In additional feedback loops, CLOCK-BMAL1 also supports the rhythmic expression of Rev-Erb and Rev-Erb (official symbols Nr1d1 and Nr1d2, respectively), which modulate the expression of Bmal1 (official symbol Arntl), and D-site-binding protein (Dbp), which modulates the expression of Per2 (ref.</s><s>1).</s></p><p><s>Although circadian-clock regulation of many metabolic processes is well established, there is increasing evidence that metabolic signals feed back to the circadian oscillator and consequently adjust metabolic pathways within individual cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> .</s><s>Heme, an iron-containing porphyrin that serves as a prosthetic group in several hemoproteins, has also been described to be a ligand of REV-ERB .</s><s>Heme binding to REV-ERB supports co-repressor recruitment and transcriptional repression <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> , thereby coordinating circadian and metabolic pathways.</s><s>In addition, heme binding to NPAS2 in vitro mediates the CO-sensitive DNA binding of NPAS2-BMAL1 (ref.</s><s>6).</s></p><p><s>Heme synthesis is governed by the rate-limiting enzyme aminolevulinate synthase 1 (Alas1), which is negatively regulated by glucose and heme concentrations <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> .</s><s>In addition, Alas1 transcription is circadian, through transcriptional regulation by NPAS2-BMAL1 (ref.</s><s>8).</s><s>Heme catabolism is mediated by heme oxygenases 1 and 2 (Ho-1 and Ho-2; official symbols Hmox1 and Hmox2, respectively), which generate biliverdin (and subsequently bilirubin), iron and carbon monoxide at the expense of nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate (NADPH) <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> .</s><s>Although heme can regulate the transcription of Period genes <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> , and circadian heme proteins may sense the redox state and potentially diatomic gases such as oxygen, nitric oxide and CO, the relevance of heme catabolism to circadian transcription and dynamics is unknown.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Inhibition of heme degradation alters circadian dynamics</head><p><s>To test whether cellular heme levels are critical for circadian dynamics, we treated human U2-OS reporter cells expressing firefly luciferase from a Bmal1 promoter fragment with various concentrations of either hemin (iron protoporphyrin) or cobalt protoporphyrin, a specific inhibitor of the heme-degrading heme oxygenases <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> .</s><s>Both compounds probably lead to increased intracellular heme levels either by providing additional heme or by inhibiting heme degradation.</s><s>Whereas hemin treatment had no effect on the circadian period, the inhibition of heme degradation by cobalt protoporphyrin resulted in an inhibitor-dose-dependent lengthening of the circadian period of up to 1.5 h (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>Thus, in this assay, heme-degradation products rather than the heme level itself were critical for circadian dynamics.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Heme degradation is regulated by the circadian clock</head><p><s>The intricate connection between the circadian and metabolic systems manifests itself in that metabolic feedbacks into the circadian oscillator often have a circadian component.</s><s>To test whether heme degradation is regulated by the circadian clock, we analyzed transcript and activity levels of Ho-1, the major heme-degrading enzyme in peripheral tissues <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> .</s><s>In regular 6-h intervals over the course of two consecutive days, we harvested livers from mice kept in constant darkness and determined Ho-1 transcript levels by quantitative RT-PCR.</s><s>Ho-1 expression showed a circadian rhythm with a peak at circadian time (CT) 12-15 and an approximately three-fold peak-to-trough ratio (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a</ref>), results consistent with findings in peritoneal macrophages (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>) and with the diurnal variation observed by Xu and colleagues in liver tissue <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> .</s></p><p><s>Transcription of Ho-1 is induced by heme via stress-response enhancer elements (StREs) in its promoter <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> .</s><s>To test whether rhythmic Ho-1 expression is regulated by potentially rhythmic heme levels, we applied constant high concentrations of heme or cobalt protoporphyrin to synchronized primary hepatocytes.</s><s>Whereas we observed the expected increase in Ho-1 transcription (and HO-1 activity, in the case of heme treatment), circadian oscillations persisted (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2b</ref>) but were absent in hepatocytes from Bmal1 −/− mice (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>).</s><s>This finding indicates that rhythmic Ho-1 regulation is different from rhythmic StRE activation and depends on the canonical circadian oscillator.</s><s>Importantly, the activity of heme oxygenase was also rhythmic in the liver in both basal and heme-induced conditions (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2c</ref>), thus indicating that heme is rhythmically degraded.</s><s>Interestingly, expression of Alas1, which encodes the rate-limiting enzyme in the heme biosynthesis pathway, is also rhythmic with a similar phase <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> to that of Ho-1, thus suggesting a potential mechanism for intracellular heme homeostasis.</s></p><p><s>To investigate whether Ho-1 is a direct output gene of the circadian clock, we searched for clock-controlled enhancer elements within the Ho-1 promoter and identified a highly conserved E box close to the transcription start site (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>).</s><s>A 1,000-bp fragment of the Ho-1 promoter was activated by CLOCK-BMAL1 in HEK293 cells and repressed by CRY1, but this regulation was abolished by E-box mutation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2d</ref>).</s><s>In addition, chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) experiments on liver nuclei revealed that the Ho-1 E box was occupied by endogenous BMAL1 in a manner dependent on the time of day (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2e</ref>).</s><s>Moreover, transcript levels of Ho-1 were deceased in the hepatocytes of Bmal1 −/− mice (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1d</ref>).</s><s>Together, these results support the role of Ho-1 as a direct target gene of CLOCK-BMAL1 in vivo.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The heme-degradation product CO modulates circadian transcription</head><p><s>Rhythmic heme degradation mediated by HO-1 leads to rhythmic accumulation of heme-degradation products, i.e., biliverdin, iron and CO.</s><s>In vitro, CO inhibits binding of NPAS2-BMAL1 to DNA <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> .</s><s>If such an inhibitory effect also occurs in vivo, transcription of NPAS2-BMAL1target genes should increase when endogenous CO levels are decreased.</s><s>Because heme oxygenase activity is the primary source of endogenous CO, and Ho-1 is the dominant paralog in the periphery <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> , we measured circadian transcript levels of CLOCK(NPAS2)-BMAL1-target genes in primary fibroblasts from Ho-1-knockout mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> .</s><s>Indeed, transcript levels of clock genes containing functional promoter E boxes, such as Dbp, Rev-Erb and Per2, were substantially upregulated, whereas transcription of Bmal1 was downregulated during periods in which levels of the repressor REV-ERB was high (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a</ref>).</s><s>The extent of this upregulation (for example, for Dpb transcript levels) was somewhat variable, ranging from 1.5-fold up to six-fold (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</s><s>It is likely that the effect of Ho-1 depletion on E-box-controlled mRNA levels was transcriptional rather than post-transcriptional, because precursor (pre)-mRNA levels of Dbp and Rev-Erb were similarly upregulated in Ho-1-knockout cells (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a</ref>).</s><s>Thus, decreasing CO levels by downregulating heme oxygenase activity has a major effect on circadian transcription.</s></p><p><s>If the upregulation of E-box-containing circadian transcripts in Ho-1-knockout animals were due a decrease in endogenous CO levels, exogenous application of CO should, at least in part, reverse this transcriptional effect.</s><s>Continuous application of 6% gaseous CO (compared with 6% nitrogen as a control for any hypoxia-induced effects) to primary fibroblasts from wild-type mice led to a slight decrease in expression of the E-box-controlled transcripts Dbp and Rev-Erb , but not Bmal1 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3b</ref>).</s><s>Similarly, acute CO application through use of CO-releasing molecules (CORMs) had only subtle effects on Dbp transcription in wild-type fibroblasts (discussion of the CO concentration in Supplementary Note 1).</s><s>In contrast, acute or continuous CO treatment of Ho-1 −/− primary fibroblasts substantially, yet not always completely, rescued high Dbp transcript levels in Ho-1-knockout fibroblasts (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3c</ref> and Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</s><s>Importantly, this CO-mediated rescue was also present at the pre-mRNA level, a result consistent with the hypothesis that CO modulates transcription (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3b</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CO suppresses transactivation and target-gene binding of CLOCK-BMAL1</head><p><s>To test whether CO-mediated transcriptional inhibition of genes containing functional E boxes correlates with CO inhibition of CLOCK(NPAS2)-BMAL1, we measured the transactivation activity of CLOCK-BMAL1 from an E-box-driven luciferase reporter in HEK293 cells treated with either CORMs or inactive controls (iCORMs).</s><s>We found a CO-dose-dependent decrease in CLOCK-BMAL1-mediated transcription (Fig. <ref type="figure">4a</ref>), thus indicating that CO directly regulates circadian transcriptional activity.</s><s>This inhibitory effect is probably due to CO interfering with CLOCK(NPAS2)-BMAL1 binding to DNA, because ChIP experiments revealed that CO treatment decreased BMAL1 binding to the Rev-Erb promoter in synchronized U2-OS cells at times when BMAL1 is transcriptionally active (Fig. <ref type="figure">4b</ref>), although overall BMAL1 levels remained unchanged (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3c</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Heme oxygenase-derived CO is essential for normal circadian dynamics in mammalian cells</head><p><s>The lengthening of the circadian period after pharmacological inhibition of heme oxygenases (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>) suggested that heme oxygenase activity is an integral part of circadian-rhythm generation.</s><s>To genetically test this phenomenon, we lentivirally transduced Ho-1 −/− primary fibroblasts with a Bmal1-luciferase reporter construct and measured circadian-rhythm dynamics, but we were unable to detect a change in circadian period when this heme oxygenase was individually depleted (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">4a</ref>).</s><s>We therefore further decreased heme oxygenase activity (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">4b</ref>), and thus probably endogenous CO levels, by RNA interference (RNAi)mediated knockdown of the second active heme oxygenase paralog, Ho-2 (ref.</s><s>15), in Ho-1 −/− primary fibroblasts (genotype denoted Ho-1 −/− ; Ho-2 KD ).</s><s>Circadian rhythms in these Ho-1 −/− ; Ho-2 KD fibroblasts showed a substantial lengthening of the period by up to 2 h (Fig. <ref type="figure">5a</ref> and Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">5a</ref>), probably as a result of effects on circadian transcription, given that upregulation of the transcript ; n = 6 independent precipitations from liver samples from three mice per ZT and genotype).</s><s>One-way ANOVA with a Bonferroni post test comparing all the different conditions indicated that the wild-type ZT6 data for the presence of BMAL1 at Rev-Erb or Ho-1 were highly significantly different from all other data for the same gene, and there were no such significant changes observed for the negative control, Bmal1.</s><s>levels of the E-box-controlled genes Dbp and Rev-Erb was enhanced in the Ho-1 −/− ; Ho-2 KD fibroblasts (Fig. <ref type="figure">5b</ref>).</s></p><p><s>If depletion of endogenous CO in Ho-1 −/− ; Ho-2 KD cells also contributes to the altered circadian dynamics, application of exogenous CO should be able to, at least in part, revert the period lengthening in Ho-1 −/− ; Ho-2 KD cells.</s><s>Indeed, continuous application of 6% CO, but not N 2, led to a reshortening of the circadian period in Ho-1 −/− ; Ho-2 KD fibroblasts (Fig. <ref type="figure">5c</ref> and Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">5b</ref>) but had no effect on the circadian period in wild-type cells (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">5c</ref>), thus indicating that endogenous CO levels are essential for normal circadian-rhythm generation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Heme oxygenase depletion globally alters clock-controlled transcription in hepatocytes</head><p><s>The strong effect of heme oxygenase depletion on circadian transcription and dynamics suggests a substantial effect on clock-controlled transcriptional output.</s><s>To investigate this possibility globally, we performed microarray-based genome-wide transcriptional profiling of primary hepatocytes from wild-type or Ho-1 −/− mice with or without additional knockdown of Ho-2.</s><s>As expected from results in primary fibroblasts (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a</ref>), circadian transcript levels of the clock-controlled genes Dbp and Rev-Erb were upregulated in Ho-1 −/− hepatocytes, even more so in Ho-2 KD hepatocytes and to the greatest extent in Ho-1 −/− ; Ho-2 KD cells (Fig. <ref type="figure">6a</ref>).</s><s>We identified 2,335 genes that were differentially expressed among these genotypes and grouped them into six clusters according to their gene-expression patterns (Fig. <ref type="figure">6b</ref> and Supplementary Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</s></p><p><s>If heme oxygenase depletion acts globally on circadian transcriptional output, genes that are rhythmically expressed in the liver should be highly represented among differentially expressed genes <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> .</s><s>This was indeed the case in cluster 1 (P &lt; 10 −14 ) and to a lesser extent in cluster 2 (P &lt; 10 −4 ) (Fig. <ref type="figure">6b</ref>).</s><s>Cluster 1 contained 473 genes whose transcript profiles were most similar to that of the E-box-containing clockcontrolled gene Dbp (comparison with Fig. <ref type="figure">6a</ref>).</s><s>In addition, cluster 1 was highly enriched in genes reported to bind endogenous BMAL1 in ChIP experiments on liver chromatin (P &lt; 10 −22 (ref.</s><s>17)), and genes with promoter E-box motifs (both E1 and E2 E boxes) were overrepresented only in cluster 1 (Fig. <ref type="figure">6c</ref>).</s><s>Although clusters 1 and 2 were  <ref type="figure">5b</ref>).</s><s>also enriched in target genes of REV-ERB and REV-ERB (ref.</s><s>18), we believe that it is unlikely that the upregulation of these targets in Ho-1-and Ho-2-depleted hepatocytes was due to CO directly regulating the activity of REV-ERB and REV-ERB (discussion in Supplementary Note 2).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Heme oxygenase depletion alters glucose homeostasis</head><p><s>Gene ontology analysis revealed significant enrichment of genes involved in metabolic processes in cluster 1, whereas in the Ho-1dominated cluster 4, the significant GO terms reflect known roles of Ho-1 in cytoprotection and immune response <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> (Fig. <ref type="figure">6b</ref>).</s><s>Genes  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</s><s>CO has a negative influence on CLOCK(NPAS2)-BMAL1-mediated transcriptional activity (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>), thereby also inhibiting genes important for glucose production (Fig. <ref type="figure">7a</ref>).</s><s>High glucose levels, however, lead to the induction of Ho-1 (ref.</s><s>46) and thereby support endogenous CO production.</s></p><p><s>important in glucose and lipid metabolism, such as Pck1, G6pc, Lpl or Cyp7a1, were strongly upregulated in Ho-1 −/− ; Ho-2 KD hepatocytes and to a lesser extent in Ho-1 −/− and Ho-2 KD hepatocytes, as verified by quantitative RT-PCR (Fig. <ref type="figure">7a</ref>).</s><s>Again, heme oxygenase probably affects transcriptional rather than post-transcriptional processes, because the pre-mRNA levels of Pck1, G6pc, Lpl and Cyp7a1 were similarly upregulated in heme oxygenase-depleted hepatocytes (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>).</s><s>Because Pck1 and G6pc are important players in gluconeogenesis, we investigated the effect of acute small interfering RNA (siRNA)-mediated Ho-2 depletion on glucagon-stimulated glucose production in primary hepatocytes.</s><s>Consistently with the upregulation of these enzymes in Ho-2-depleted cells, we found a significant increase in glucagon-stimulated glucose production, thus suggesting that heme oxygenase activity is required for normal glucose homeostasis (Fig. <ref type="figure">7b</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Heme oxygenase is essential for normal daily activity patterns in Drosophila</head><p><s>Because the expression of Alas1 and heme oxygenase has also been reported to be circadian in Drosophila melanogaster heads <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> , we investigated whether heme oxygenase (dHo (official symbol Ho), which is the only isoform of heme oxygenase in Drosophila and is essential for normal fly development <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> ) is also required for normal rhythms in this species.</s><s>To this end, we examined behavioral rhythms in flies in which dHo expression was knocked down in various cell types by two independent UAS-dHo-RNAi lines by using the binary Gal4-UAS system <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> .</s><s>Under standard 12 h-12 h light-dark (LD) cycles, wild-type flies exhibit crepuscular behavior, with pronounced morning (M) and evening (E) activity peaks <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref> (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">8a</ref>).</s><s>When released into constant dark conditions (DD), wild-type flies maintain their E peak, whereas the M peak weakens or disappears (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">8a</ref>).</s><s>Knockdown of dHo in all neurons (by using the pan-neuronal Gal4 driver elav-gal4) resulted in a substantially advanced M peak, whereas the E peak was unaffected (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">7a</ref>).</s><s>Next, we downregulated dHo with the timeless (tim)-gal4 driver, which is active in all clock neurons and peripheral clock cells throughout the body <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref> .</s><s>Also, using Pdf-gal, we directed dHo knockdown to the subset of the clock neurons important for regulating M activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[26]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref> .</s><s>In both cases, we observed a phase advance of the M peak, which, interestingly, was also maintained in the subsequent DD period, thus indicating that dHo knockdown in clock neurons somehow enhances M activity (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">8a</ref> and Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">7a</ref>).</s><s>Clock cell-specific dHo knockdown had no effect on E activity or circadian period in DD, and dHo RNAi directed toward glia cells (by using the pan-glial driver repo-gal4) did not alter LD activity (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">8a</ref>, Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">7a</ref>, Supplementary Table <ref type="table">2</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>and ref. 28).</head><p><s>To test whether heme oxygenase depletion increases transcription from E-box-containing promoters, as observed in mammalian cells, we performed a real-time in vivo luciferase reporter assay for Period transcription in live flies <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s><s>Flies in which dHo was downregulated in all clock cells (tim-gal4) showed normal expression levels and temporal regulation of Period-promoter-driven luciferase expression under LD and DD conditions (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">7b</ref>).</s><s>Similarly, clock cell-specific dHO RNAi had no effect on the expression of a Periodluciferase transgene reporter in central and peripheral clock cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30</ref> (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">7b</ref>).</s><s>On the basis of the behavioral phenotype of dHo RNAi flies, we used a reporter that directs PERIOD expression in only a subset of the behavior-controlling clock neurons and that is not active in peripheral clock cells (8.0-luc <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30</ref> ).</s><s>Strikingly, and consistently with the observed strengthening of behavioral rhythms, dHo knockdown resulted in a substantial increase in Period expression from the luciferase reporter during the normal peak expression times in LD and DD conditions, thus generating an increase in the overall amplitude of Period oscillations in LD (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">8b</ref> and Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">7b</ref>).</s><s>Because the 8.0-luc construct lacks the Period promoter sequences (including the E boxes), the observed increase in PERIOD expression was probably post-transcriptionally regulated.</s><s>Together, these results indicate that in Drosophila, as in mammals, the circadian system requires heme oxygenase for temporal coordination of behavioral activity and circadian accumulation of clock proteins, but in the Drosophila system, in contrast to the mammalian system, this coordination is not accomplished via increased transcription.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>Here, we show that endogenous CO production by heme oxygenase activity is required not only for circadian oscillator function but also for balanced clock-gene and clock-target-gene expression, thereby modulating glucose homeostasis in hepatocytes.</s><s>Mechanistically, we favor the hypothesis that, in mammals, heme oxygenase-derived CO attenuates CLOCK(NPAS2)-BMAL1 DNA binding, probably via coordination by a heme molecule bound to NPAS2 (ref.</s><s>6) and probably also to CLOCK <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31</ref> , and thereby modulates expression of CLOCK(NPAS2)-BMAL1-target genes.</s><s>Although this scenario is not the only possible interpretation of our results (as described below), our preferred model is consistent with both past and present observations.</s><s>(i) In vitro, micromolar concentrations of CO have been shown to impair DNA binding and BMAL-heterodimer formation of heme-bound NPAS2 but not apo-NPAS2 (ref.</s><s>6), and in the brain, these concentrations of CO are generated by heme oxygenases <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32</ref> (detailed discussion of CO concentration in Supplementary Note 1).</s><s>(ii) Mutation of heme-coordinating residues within NPAS2 also impairs heterodimer formation with BMAL1, thus decreasing both specific DNA binding to canonical E boxes and NPAS2-BMAL1 transactivation activity, probably via conformational changes within the PAS-A domain of NPAS2 (ref.</s><s>33).</s><s>(iii) Although much less is known about whether CLOCK is also able to bind heme and whether CO can modulate CLOCK activity, recent biophysical data have confirmed that the PAS-A domain of CLOCK binds heme in vitro with spectroscopic properties that are consistent with a sensor of diatomic gases 31 .</s><s>(iv) We show here that depleting endogenous CO via heme oxygenase knockout leads to strong transcriptional upregulation of target genes of CLOCK(NPAS2)-BMAL1 in human and mouse hepatocytes.</s><s>This observed modulation of circadian transcription is probably a direct effect of CO, because application of exogenous CO, but not N 2 , suppresses CLOCK-BMAL1 transcriptional activation through E-box elements, attenuates transcription of endogenous CLOCK(NPAS2)-BMAL1 targets, partially rescues transcriptional upregulation in heme oxygenase knockouts and suppresses BMAL1 binding to target promoters.</s></p><p><s>Together, these observations provide compelling evidence of a role of endogenous CO in modulating the transcriptional stimulatory activity of CLOCK(NPAS2)-BMAL1.</s><s>However, additional potential mechanisms underlying the influence of heme oxygenases on circadian transcription and dynamics are not eliminated, because heme degradation also produces biliverdin and iron in addition to CO.</s><s>Moreover, heme degradation consumes NADPH, whose intracellular concentration modulates circadian dynamics and expression of CLOCK-BMAL1target genes <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34</ref> .</s><s>However, relevant to the present findings, we consider it unlikely that an increase in NADPH levels-as predicted to occur after heme oxygenase depletion-would generate long circadian periods and upregulation of CLOCK-BMAL1 targets, because such effects have previously been associated with decreased levels of NADPH <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34</ref> .</s></p><p><s>It is also possible that CO indirectly influences circadian gene expression.</s><s>The extent of CO's effect on CLOCK(NPAS2)-BMAL1 transcriptional activity is difficult to estimate.</s><s>Although CO was originally considered to be a metabolic waste product, today most of the described anti-inflammatory, antiapoptotic, antiproliferative and cytoprotective roles of heme oxygenases are ascribed to CO <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35</ref> .</s><s>Owing to the affinity of CO for metal ions, the few known CO sensors are heme-containing proteins including hemoglobin, myoglobin, soluble guanylyl cyclase (sGC), cytochrome c oxidase and the transcription factors Bach-1, Bach-2 and NPAS2.</s><s>For example, heme oxygenasederived CO can, like nitric oxide, activate sGC, thereby leading to increased levels of cGMP.</s><s>Such a mechanism has been proposed to play a role in resetting the cholinergic clock in the suprachiasmatic nucleus <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36</ref> , where heme oxygenase activity is circadian <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37</ref> .</s><s>Moreover, increased cGMP levels can enhance AMP kinase (AMPK) activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38</ref> , which in turn may act on the clock by promoting CRY-protein degradation <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39</ref> .</s><s>Activation of AMPK in the liver also represses expression of gluconeogenesis enzymes such as Pck1 and G6pc 40 , results opposite from those observed in heme oxygenase-depleted hepatocytes.</s><s>If the increases in Pck1 and G6pc transcript levels in HO-depleted hepatocytes were due to decreased AMPK activity (perhaps mediated by increased oxidative stress <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41</ref> ), transcript levels of genes involved in other anabolic pathways would also be expected to be elevated <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42</ref> .</s><s>However, this was not the case: the expression of key genes involved in lipogenesis, such as sterol regulatory element-binding protein-1, carbohydrate response element-binding protein, acetyl CoA carboxylase, fatty acid synthase, stearoyl-CoA desaturase, and glycerol-3-phosphate acyltransferase, was essentially unaltered.</s><s>Thus, modulation of AMPK activity is unlikely to be the cause of altered clock function and increased gluconeogenesis in heme oxygenase-depleted cells.</s></p><p><s>Our results further establish that heme oxygenase also functions in the Drosophila circadian clock.</s><s>Downregulation of dHo leads to an advanced morning peak and to increased PERIOD levels and higher-amplitude oscillations in clock neurons, presumably via post-transcriptional regulation.</s><s>The enhanced molecular oscillations may explain the robustness of the morning activity peak and the persistence of bimodal behavior under constant conditions.</s><s>Typically, the morning activity peak weakens or disappears under constant conditions, whereas the evening peak is sustained, thus leading to unimodal behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43</ref> .</s><s>The enhanced molecular oscillations are reminiscent of the effects of the Pdf 01 mutation on the same 8.0-luc reporter used in the present study <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44</ref> .</s><s>This reporter construct is expressed in a small subset of dorsal clock neurons, and enhanced 8.0-luc oscillations in Pdf 01 mutants are correlated with expression in additional dorsal clock neurons belonging to the evening oscillator, which show robust and synchronized PER oscillations in the absence of PDF <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44</ref> .</s><s>Because we observed advanced morning activity after downregulation of dHo in only the PDF cells, it is possible that heme oxygenase may affect PDF or the communication between the PDF cells and the dorsal clock neurons expressing 8.0-luc.</s></p><p><s>Interestingly, heme oxygenase activity has previously been linked to glucose homeostasis <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> , and Ho-2 −/− mice develop symptoms of type 2 diabetes, including hyperglycemia <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45</ref> .</s><s>However, hepatocyte Ho-1 −/− mice are insulin hypersensitive <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46</ref> , and high glucose levels lead to Ho-1 induction <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47</ref> as well as to increased CO exhalation <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> .</s><s>Considering these results together with our present observation that heme oxygenasedepleted hepatocytes show increased gluconeogenesis, we suggest a feedback model that links CO production to the expression of genes important in glucose homeostasis (Fig. <ref type="figure">7c</ref>).</s><s>In our model, rhythmic heme oxygenase activity causes rhythmic CO production that in turn generates time-of-day-dependent repression of CLOCK(NPAS2)-BMAL1 transcriptional activation activity.</s><s>CLOCK(NPAS2)-BMAL1target genes supporting glucose production are thus inhibited by CO, whereas high glucose levels lead to counter-regulation via heme oxygenase induction.</s><s>Changes in redox state and heme levels not included in this feedback model are likely to have modulatory effects.</s><s>It will be interesting to investigate whether CO, as a gaseous molecule, also contributes to intercellular circadian synchronization, thereby temporally coordinating metabolic signals within the organism.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head><p><s>Methods, including statements of data availability and any associated accession codes and references, are available in the online version of the paper.</s></p><p><s>Note: Any Supplementary Information and Source Data files are available in the online version of the paper.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ONLINE METHODS</head><p><s>Mice.</s><s>We used 6-to 8-week-old male C57Bl/6 mice for harvesting organs and fibroblast preparations.</s><s>The animals were purchased from the Bundesinstitut für Risikobewertung (Berlin, Germany).</s><s>Ho-1 −/− mice (kind gift from A. Zenclussen) were raised with a normal diet and housed under and 12-h light-12-h dark conditions in the Animal Facility of Charité-Universitätsmedizin, Berlin, Germany.</s><s>All mouse experiments were carried out in accordance with the German and European legal and ethical regulations and were approved by the Senatsverwaltung für Gesundheit und Soziales, Berlin, Germany.</s></p><p><s>Flies.</s><s>As controls, wild-type ATDD <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49</ref> and Df1 w (y w) flies were used.</s><s>UAS-dHo-RNAi line 21-1 (third-chromosome insertion), as previously described, decreases endogenous dHo expression by &gt;50% (ref.</s><s>21).</s><s>We obtained similar results with UAS-dHo-RNAi line 21-8, bearing an independent X-chromosomal insertion of the same construct (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">7a</ref>).</s><s>To exclude any off-target effects, two insertion lines from the NIG-Fly RNAi collection (http://www.shigen.nig.</s><s>ac.jp/fly/nigfly/) (UAS-dHo-RNAi lines R1 and R3 inserted on chromosomes 3 and 2, respectively), bearing a dHo-RNAi construct targeting a different region of dHo RNA were tested (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">7a</ref>).</s><s>As unrelated UAS controls, we used UAS-GFP:T2 (ref.</s><s>24) and an insertion of an empty pUASTattB vector into the attP landing site at 51C 50 .</s><s>Pdf-gal4, tim-Gal4:62, 67, 27, repo-gal4 and elav-gal4 have been described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[51]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[52]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[53]</ref> .</s><s>To record period-luciferase rhythms 8.0-luc:9, XLG-luc:1 (ref.</s><s>30) and plo:3b-1I (ref.</s><s>29) were crossed into the respective mutant and control backgrounds.</s></p><p><s>Activity monitoring of flies.</s><s>Locomotor activity of individual male flies aged 3 to 4 d was recorded automatically with a Drosophila Activity Monitoring (DAM) system (Trikinetics) as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54</ref> .</s><s>Flies were kept in glass tubes supplemented with 5% sucrose and 2% agar and kept under 12-h-12-h LD cycles at 25 °C for 5-8 d before being released into free-running conditions (DD and 25 °C).</s><s>Calculation of the free-running period and plotting of daily average histograms and actograms was performed with the fly toolbox and MATLab software <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55</ref> .</s><s>Autocorrelation was applied to determine the rhythmicity and free-running period in Supplementary Table <ref type="table">1</ref>, as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54</ref> .</s><s>Flies with RS (rhythmicity statistics) &gt;1.5 were considered to be rhythmic.</s><s>Only rhythmic flies were included in the period calculation.</s></p><p><s>Isolation and culture of primary hepatocytes.</s><s>Isolation of hepatocytes was performed essentially as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56</ref> .</s><s>In brief, livers of anesthetized 6-to 12-week-old male WT C57BL/6J or Ho-1 −/− mice were perfused with digestion buffer containing 5,000 U collagenase (Worthington Biochemical).</s><s>After filtration and separation with a Percoll gradient (Biochrome), cells were seeded in gelatin (0.2% in PBS) or collagen-coated 12-well plates in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM) containing 10% FBS (Invitrogen) and 1% penicillin/ streptomycin (Gibco).</s></p><p><s>Isolation and culture of primary fibroblasts.</s><s>6-to 12-week-old male mice were sacrificed, and ear, lung or tail tissues were cut into very small pieces and incubated overnight in cell culture medium (DMEM supplemented with 20% FBS, penicillin/streptomycin and HEPES and amphotericin B (final concentration 2.5 g/ml)) mixed with Liberase (Roche).</s><s>The next day, cells were pelleted by centrifugation, seeded into a new dish and grown in medium containing 20% FBS and amphotericin B for 4 d.</s><s>Then culture conditions were changed to normal cell culture medium containing 10% FBS and no amphotericin B. Cells were either frozen in liquid nitrogen or used directly in experiments.</s></p><p><s>Synchronization of circadian rhythms.</s><s>Circadian rhythms were synchronized by treatment with 1 M dexamethasone for 30-60 min.</s></p><p><s>RNA interference.</s><s>Experiments with shRNA.</s><s>Hairpin shRNAs in the pLKO.1 lentiviral vector designed by The RNAi Consortium (TRC) for mouse Ho-2 were purchased from Thermo Scientific, OpenBiosystems.</s><s>The following clone IDs were used: TRCN0000076353 (mature antisense, ATGTGAAGTAAAGTGCAGTGG), TRCN0000076356 (mature antisense, ATAGCTCCTTCTTAATGTTTC) and TRCN0000076357 (mature antisense, TGTAACGAGTATAAGCATGGG).</s><s>As a nonsilencing control, a pLKO.1 vector containing scrambled shRNA (plasmid 1864, Addgene, hairpin sequence CCTAAGGTTAAGTCGCCCTCGCTC GAGCGAGGGCGACTTAACCTTAGG) was used.</s><s>For lentivirus production, HEK293T cells (Thermo Scientific HCL4517, regularly tested for mycoplasma) were seeded in T25 flasks and transfected with 2.5 mg psPAX, 1.5 mg pMD2G and 3.5 mg of the respective lentiviral expression plasmid (RNAi constructs) with a CalPhos Mammalian Transfection Kit (BD Biosciences) according to the manufacturer's protocol.</s><s>Virus-containing supernatants were filtered, and cells were transduced with 1 ml of virus filtrate plus 8 ng/ml protamine sulfate (Sigma).</s><s>After 24 h, medium was exchanged to puromycin-containing (10 g/ml) medium for selection.</s></p><p><s>Experiments with siRNA.</s><s>After the attachment of hepatocytes to the cell culture plate, the medium was replaced with 500 l of DMEM only, and cells were transfected with 1 nM of siRNA (Eurogentec) and 4 l of Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen) per well overnight.</s><s>The next morning, the medium was replaced by DMEM containing 10% FBS and 1% penicillin/streptomycin. Protoporphyrin preparation.</s><s>For hemin (Fe 3+ -protoporphyrin IX) and cobaltprotoporphyrin IX (Sigma-Aldrich), stock solutions of 1 mg/ml were prepared: 10 mg porphyrin was dissolved in 800 l NaOH (0.2 M) and incubated for 30 min in darkness (RT).</s><s>8 ml PBS was added and the pH was adjusted to 7.4 with 150-200 l of 1 M HCl.</s></p><p><s>Transfection and luciferase reporter assays.</s><s>Transient transfections were carried out with Lipofectamine 2000 (Life Technologies) according to the manufacturer's protocol.</s><s>HEK293 cells (human, ATCC CRL-1573, regularly tested for mycoplasma) were seeded in 24-well plates in antibiotic-free medium.</s><s>Transfection was performed after cells had reached 80-90% confluence.</s><s>The total amount of transfected DNA in each sample was 1.2 g, composed of a firefly luciferase reporter construct (50 ng pGL3/mouse Ho-1_E-box_WT or 50 ng pGL3/mouse Ho-1_E-box_mut) and mouse Clock (300 ng), mouse Bmal1 (300 ng) and mouse Cry1 (30 ng), as indicated.</s><s>For normalization, 2 ng of a Renilla luciferase vector pRL-SV40 was cotransfected.</s><s>The total amount of DNA per well was adjusted to 1.2 g by addition of empty pDEST26 vector.</s><s>Cells were harvested 48 h after transfection in 200 l passive lysis buffer (PLB) and frozen at −80 °C for 1 h.</s><s>Cell lysates were homogenized by vortexing, and luciferase activity was measured with a Dual-Luciferase Reporter Assay System (Promega) according to the manufacturer's protocol, by using a 96-well-plate-reading luminometer (Orion II, Berthold Detection System). 5 l of each cell extract was measured in duplicate by the addition of 25 l LARII to measure firefly luciferase activity and then 25 l Stop &amp; Glo reagent to detect the Renilla luciferase activity.</s><s>For data analysis, firefly luciferase activity was normalized to the corresponding Renilla luciferase activity.</s></p><p><s>Cloning and mutagenesis.</s><s>The −1,000-bp region of the mouse Ho-1 promoter was cloned into the luciferase reporter vector pGL3prom (Promega) by use of the KpnI and NheI restriction sites.</s><s>The resulting luciferase reporter vector containing an E box (pGL3/mouse Ho-1_E-box_WT) was verified by DNA sequencing.</s><s>Mutagenesis of the E box to an inactive form (CACGTG to TTTAGT; described in ref. 57) was performed by site-directed mutagenesis (QuikChange Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit; Stratagene).</s></p><p><s>Live-cell and fly bioluminescence recording.</s><s>U2-OS cells (human, ATCC HTB-96, regularly tested for mycoplasma) stably expressing firefly luciferase from a 0.9-kb Bmal1 promoter fragment <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">58</ref> were seeded into a white 96-well plate (20 × 10 4 cell/well).</s><s>After 24 h, cells were synchronized with a single pulse of dexamethasone (1 M) for 30 min.</s><s>After being washed with PBS, cells were cultured in 150 l phenol red-free DMEM containing 10% FBS, antibiotics (100 U/ml penicillin and 100 g/ml streptomycin), and 250 M d-luciferin (Biothema).</s><s>Bioluminescence recordings were performed at 35-37 °C in a 96-well-plate-reading luminometer (TopCount, PerkinElmer).</s><s>Primary fibroblasts were lentivirally transduced with reporter vector expressing firefly luciferase from a 0.9-kb Bmal1 promoter fragment <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">58</ref> .</s><s>Bioluminescence rhythms were analyzed in light-tight boxes with a single photomultiplier tube (Hamamatsu Photonics).</s><s>Raw data were detrended through division by the 24-h running average.</s><s>Periods were estimated by fitting the cosine wave function with ChronoStar software, as described in ref. 58.</s></p><p><s>Luciferase expression of individual flies carrying the various period-luciferase transgenes were measured as described in ref. 30.</s><s>Briefly, 2-to 3-d-old males were ether-anesthetized and loaded in a 96-well plate in which every other well</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1 Inhibition of heme degradation alters circadian dynamics in human cells.</s><s>(a) Circadian oscillation dynamics of dexamethasonesynchronized human osteosarcoma cells (U2-OS) bearing a Bmal1 promoter-luciferase reporter construct treated with the indicated concentrations of hemin or the heme oxygenase inhibitor cobalt protoporphyrin (CoPPIX).</s><s>Shown are detrended average time series of six parallel treatments.</s><s>(b) Circadian periods of time series shown in a (mean s.d.; n = 6 independent cell cultures).</s><s>Two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni post test revealed a significant difference between hemin and CoPPIX effects (P &lt; 0.0001) and concentration (P &lt; 0.0001).</s><s>Three independent experiments yielded similar results.</s><s>**P &lt; 0.01; ***P &lt; 0.001.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,136.31,107.47,59.18,51.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2Heme degradation is regulated by the circadian clock.</s><s>(a) Heme oxygenase 1 (Ho-1) transcript levels (normalized to Hprt and relative to mean levels) from mouse liver over 2 d in constant darkness (mean s.e.m.; n = 4 livers).</s><s>(b) HO activity rhythms in untreated and hemin (30 M)-stimulated primary hepatocytes.</s><s>Shown are mean levels (large symbols) of two independent hepatocyte samples (small symbols).</s><s>(c) Ho-1 transcript rhythms (relative to Hprt) in primary hepatocytes treated with hemin or cobalt protoporphyrin (30 M each).</s><s>Data are normalized to mean levels of untreated control cells.</s><s>Shown are mean levels (large symbols) of two independent hepatocyte samples (small symbols).</s><s>(d) CLOCK-BMAL1 (C-B)-mediated transactivation and repression by CRY1 in HEK293 cells from a Ho-1 promoter luciferase reporter with (mut) or without (WT) a mutated E box (mean s.e.m.; n = 4 independent cell cultures).</s><s>(e) ChIP analysis of BMAL1 at the Ho-1, Rev-Erb and Bmal1 genes at zeitgeber time (ZT) ZT6 and ZT18 from wild-type or Bmal1 −/− (Bmal1 KO) liver chromatin (mean s.d.; n = 6 independent precipitations from liver samples from three mice per ZT and genotype).</s><s>One-way ANOVA with a Bonferroni post test comparing all the different conditions indicated that the wild-type ZT6 data for the presence of BMAL1 at Rev-Erb or Ho-1 were highly significantly different from all other data for the same gene, and there were no such significant changes observed for the negative control, Bmal1.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3The heme-degradation product CO modulates circadian transcription.</s><s>(a) Transcript rhythms of Bmal1, Per2, Rev-Erb and Dbp in dexamethasone-synchronized primary fibroblasts from Ho-1 −/− mice (Ho1 KO) or wild-type littermates (Ho1 WT).</s><s>Data are normalized to Hprt expression and are presented relative to mean expression in wild-type cells.</s><s>Shown are mean levels (large symbols) of two independent fibroblast samples from one mouse per genotype (small symbols).</s><s>The amplitudes of sine fits (peak-to-trough ratios) for Ho1 WT versus Ho1 KO are 3.1 versus 2.9 for Dbp; 4.6 versus 6.1 for Rev-Erb ; 1.5 versus 3.2 for Per2; and 1.6 versus 3.4 for Bmal1.</s><s>(b) Transcript rhythms of Dbp, Rev-Erb and Bmal1 in dexamethasonesynchronized primary fibroblasts from wild-type mice continuously treated with 6% CO or N 2 .</s><s>Normalization and presentation are as in a. (c) Transcript levels of Dbp in embryonic fibroblasts from Ho-1 −/− mice (or wild-type littermates 24 h after dexamethasone synchronization, which were treated for 1 h with 100 M CO-releasing molecules (CORMs) or inactive control molecules (iCORMs) before harvesting.</s><s>Data are normalized to Gapdh expression and are presented relative to mean expression in wild-type cells treated with iCORMs.</s><s>Data are shown as mean s.d. of three independent samples from one mouse per genotype.</s><s>Two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni post test revealed a significant difference between genotypes (P &lt; 0.0001) and drugs (P &lt; 0.0001).</s><s>***P &lt; 0.001; N.S., not significant.</s><s>Similar experiments with samples from different mice are shown in Supplementary Figure2.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 Figure 5</head><label>45</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4 Carbon monoxide suppresses transactivation and target-gene binding of CLOCK-BMAL1.</s><s>(a) CLOCK-BMAL1-mediated transactivation from an E-box-containing artificial promoter in HEK293 cells treated with CO-releasing molecules (CORMs) or inactive control molecules (iCORMs).</s><s>Data are shown as mean s.d.; n = 3 independently transfected cell cultures.</s><s>Two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni post test revealed a significant difference between iCORM and CORM treatments (P &lt; 0.0001).</s><s>***P &lt; 0.001; **P &lt; 0.01.</s><s>(b) ChIP analysis of BMAL1 bound to the Rev-Erb gene in synchronized U2-OS cells treated with 100 M CORMs or control iCORMs (mean s.e.m. of four pairwise comparisons).</s><s>Two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni post test revealed a significant difference between genotype (P &lt; 0.0001) and time (P &lt; 0.0001).</s><s>***P &lt; 0.001; *P &lt; 0.05.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 6 Figure 7</head><label>67</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6 Heme oxygenase depletion globally alters clock-controlled transcription in hepatocytes.</s><s>(a) Circadian transcription of Dbp and Rev-Erb in synchronized primary hepatocytes of Ho-1 −/− or wild-type littermate mice with or without additional Ho-2 depletion by RNAi.</s><s>Data are normalized to Gapdh expression and are presented relative to mean expression in wild-type cells transduced with the nonsilencing (NS) control.</s><s>Shown are mean levels (large symbols) of two independent samples from two mice (small symbols).</s><s>(b) Left, Heat diagram sorted in six clusters, showing changes in gene expression detected in a microarray experiment with hepatocytes, as described in a, 24 h after synchronization, the time of maximal CLOCK-BMAL1 binding to DNA (n = 2 mice per genotype).</s><s>Increases (red) or decreases (blue) in transcript levels are shown.</s><s>Middle, P values indicate significance for overrepresentation (Fisher's test) of genes with a circadian transcript in liver<ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> or with BMAL1 binding in their promoters<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> .</s><s>Right, Most significant nonredundant gene ontology terms for genes enriched in the clusters.</s><s>(c) Bioinformatics analysis of cluster 1 genes for overrepresentation of E-box motifs in regions from −1,000 bp to +1,000 bp with respect to the transcription start site.</s><s>Shown are P-value distributions of TRAP scores (Online Methods) for depicted E-box motifs compared with background gene sets.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,256.67,131.95,87.02,183.74" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 8 Heme oxygenase (dHo) is essential for normal daily activity patterns in Drosophila.</s><s>(a) Average locomotor activity of Drosophila males in 12 h light-12 h dark conditions for 5-8 d, followed by 7 d in constant darkness (DD).</s><s>Exact genotypes from left to right: UAS-dHo-RNAi:21-1/+ (n = 15 flies); timeless-gal4:62/UAS-dHo-RNAi:21-1 (n = 16 flies); Pdf-gal4/UAS-dHo-RNAi:21-1 (n = 16 flies).</s><s>Top, double-plotted actograms showing average activity during the entire experiment.</s><s>Gray and white areas indicate dark and light periods, respectively.</s><s>The morning peak in flies with decreased dHo expression persists in DD but disappears rapidly in the controls.</s><s>Bottom, histograms showing average activity within in 30 min (bars); dark bars, 'lights off'; white bars, 'lights on', dots, s.e.m.</s><s>The phaseadvanced morning activity peak in flies with decreased dHo expression in clock cells.</s><s>The same advance was observed in transgenic flies bearing a different dHo-RNAi construct (additional data and additional control genotypes in Supplementary Fig. 7a).</s><s>(b) Real-time luciferase recordings of flies expressing a PERIOD-LUCIFERASE fusion protein in dorsal clock neurons encoded by the promoterless 8.0-luc transgene 30 .</s><s>Male flies were recorded in LD and DD, as indicated by the bars below the plots (white and black bars indicate lights on and lights off, respectively).</s><s>Exact genotypes: gray circles, 8.0-luc/+;tim-gal4:67/UAS-dHo-RNAi:21-1 (n = 14 flies); black circles, 8.0-luc/UAS-GFP;tim-gal4:67/+ (n = 10 flies); open circles, 8.0-luc/UAS-attP-51C;tim-gal4:67/+ (n = 10 flies).</s><s>The peak levels were higher in LD and DD, and the amplitude of PER-LUC oscillations increased in dHo-RNAi flies.</s><s>Similar results were obtained in two independent experiments and with the dHo-RNAi:21-8 line (Supplementary Fig. 7b).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">http://doc.rero.ch</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>We thank A. Grudziecki, B. Koller and U. Ungethüm for excellent technical support.</s><s>We also thank M. Rauer and H. Herzel for bioinformatics help as well as A. Zenclusen (Otto von Guericke University Magdeburg), M. Brunner (Ruprecht-Karls-University Heidelberg), S. Taketani (Insect Biomedical Research Center, Kyoto Institute of Technology) and the NIG-Fly Stock Center (Genetic Strain Research Center, National Institute of Genetics Mishima) for materials.</s><s>This work was supported by the BBSRC (grant BB/J018589/1 to R.S.) and the German Research foundation (Emmy Noether grant SCHU 2546/1-1 to M.S. and SFB 618/A4 and SFB 740/D2 to A.K.).</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS R.K., S.R., T.W., N.W., S.K., V.L., M.K., S.H., M.X. and J.A.R. performed experiments; K.J. performed bioinformatics analyses; S.L. provided the ChronoStar software; R.K., S.R., T.W., K.J., S.K., V.L., J.A.R., M.S., R.S. and A.K. designed experiments and analyzed data; R.S. and A.K. wrote the paper; and A.K. oversaw the project.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>COMPETING FINANCIAL INTERESTS</head><p><s>The authors declare no competing financial interests.</s></p><p><s>Reprints and permissions information is available online at http://www.nature.com/</s><s>reprints/index.html.</s><s>contained 100 l of 5% sucrose, 1% agar and 15 mM luciferin (Biosynth).</s><s>Flies were measured in a TopCount instrument (PerkinElmer) for 3 d in 12-h-12-h LD (25 °C) followed by DD for additional 3 d.</s><s>Raw data were plotted with BRASS software (version 2.1.3)</s><s>(ref.</s><s>59).</s></p><p><s>Western blotting.</s><s>U2-OS cells were seeded in 10 cm 2 dishes.</s><s>On the next day, the cells were synchronized by addition of 1 M dexamethasone for 20 min.</s><s>23 h after synchronization, the cells were treated with either CORMs (dissolved in DMSO) or iCORMs (dissolved in ethanol) (100 M final concentration, solvent was adjusted in all dishes) for 1 h.</s><s>For harvesting, cells were washed with PBS, lysed in RIPA buffer (1× PBS, 1% IGEPAL CA-630, 0.5% Na-deoxycholate and 0.1% SDS) containing protease-inhibitor cocktail (Sigma-Aldrich).</s><s>Lysates were homogenized by passage 5-10 times through a 21-gauge syringe needle and then centrifuged.</s><s>The protein concentrations of the supernatants were determined with BCA assays.</s><s>25 g of total protein was denatured in NuPAGE LDS loading buffer (Life Technologies) by boiling for 5 min at 95 °C, separated by SDS-PAGE with NuPAGE 4-12% Bis-Tris gels (Life Technologies) according to the manufacturer's protocol, transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane and incubated with an anti-BMAL1 primary antibody (gift from M. Brunner; validated in ref. 17) and anti--actin (A3853, Sigma-Aldrich).</s><s>The next day, membranes were probed with HRP-conjugated secondary antibodies (sc-2317, Santa Cruz Biotechnologies), and a chemiluminescence assay was performed using Super Signal West Pico substrate (Pierce) followed by protein detection with a ChemoCam Imager (INTAS).</s></p><p><s>Determination of HO activity.</s><s>HO activity was determined as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">60</ref> .</s><s>Briefly, lysates of cultured cells were prepared by mixture with lysis buffer (100 mM Tris/HCl, 150 mM NaCl and 1% Triton X-100, pH 7.4) and analyzed for the amount of total protein with Coomassie blue.</s><s>The reactions were performed with 10 l (20-100 g total protein) of the crude lysates in 100 mM Tris-HCl with 15 M hemin, 0.8 mM NADPH, 1 mM MgCl 2 , 0.8 mM glucose-6-phosphate, 300 M BSA and 1 U glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase and 3 l of a bacterial lysate of biliverdinreductase (BVR)-overexpressing cells.</s><s>The reaction samples were mixed, and 100 l of the mixture was transferred into a black 96-well fluorescence microtiter plate (Nunc) in triplicates.</s><s>Fluorescence emission was detected at a wavelength of 528 nm ( 2 nm) in a fluorescence reader (Infinte M200, Tecan) at 37 °C with excitation at 441 nm, with a gain value of 140.</s><s>Fluorescence was monitored every 3 min over 1.5 h and was detected five times per well and time point.</s><s>The arithmetic mean was used to calculate the slope of the linear increase in fluorescence.</s><s>HO activities were determined on the basis of an empirical value of 0.14 pmol bilirubin production per unit of fluorescence.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP).</head><p><s>ChIP from liver tissue from male wild-type (C57Bl/6) or Bmal1 −/− mice (Fig. <ref type="figure">2f</ref>) was performed as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">61</ref> .</s><s>Primers for the E-box-containing region in the mouse Ho-1 promoter were: 5 -TGCAACAGCAGCGAGAAC-3 (forward), 5 -GAAACTC TGGAGGCGACTG-3 (reverse) and 5 -FAM-CCACCACGTGACCCGCGTAC-TAMRA-3 (probe).</s><s>As a positive control for BMAL1 binding, we used the upstream region of Rev-Erb with 5 -TCACATGGTACCTGCTCCAG-3 (forward), 5 -CTTTTGCCCGAGCCTTTC-3 (reverse) and 5 -FAM-ACAGAG GGCTCTGCGCAGGC-TAMRA-3 (probe); as a negative control, we used the promoter region of Bmal1 with 5 -AGCGAGCCACGGTGAGTGT-3 (forward), 5 -CCGGGAACTCGCGACCC-3 (reverse) and 5 -FAM-AGCC GTCTCGGGGCGTCCCG-TAMRA-3 (probe).</s><s>For carbon monoxide treatment (Fig. <ref type="figure">4b</ref>), U2-OS cells were grown in 15-cm dishes to 95% confluence.</s><s>Cells were synchronized with 1 M dexamethasone for 1 h and treated with either 100 M CORMs or iCORMs for 1 h before cross-linking at the described time points.</s><s>Cross-linking, chromatin preparation and chromatin immunoprecipitation were performed as described in ref. 61, with modifications.</s><s>Cells were sonicated on ice for 15 s five times at a 50% setting, then centrifuged for 10 min (16,000g).</s><s>Supernatants were diluted in buffer (1.1% Triton X-100, 2 mM EDTA, 150 mM NaCl and 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.1) and incubated with anti-BMAL1 antibody <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> (a kind gift from M. Brunner), for 1 h under rotation (RT); agarose-A bead slurry in the same buffer was then added, and samples were incubated for 1 h under rotation (RT).</s><s>Precipitates were washed sequentially in TSE I (0.1% SDS, 1% Triton X-100, 2 mM EDTA, 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.1, and 150 mM NaCl), TSE II (0.1% SDS, 1% Triton X-100, 2 mM EDTA, 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.1, and 500 mM NaCl), TSE III (0.25 M LiCl, 1% NP-40, 1% deoxycholate, 1 mM EDTA and 10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.1) and TSE IV (10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.1, 150 mM NaCl and 1 mM EDTA).</s><s>Cross-linking was reversed at 65 °C in TSE V (20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 2 mM EDTA and 1% SDS) overnight.</s><s>DNA fragments were purified with a QIAquick Spin Kit (Qiagen) and eluted in 60 l TE buffer.</s><s>Q-PCR was performed with SYBR Green (Fermentas) on a CFX384 Real-Time PCR Detection System (Bio-Rad).</s><s>For detection of BMAL1 binding to an E box in the promoter region of the human Rev-erb gene, the primers (1 M) 5 -CCTTCTCTGGACTTTGCCCT-3 (forward) and 5 -AAACCTTGCAAACGTGAGGG-3 (reverse) were used.</s></p><p><s>Real-time quantitative PCR.</s><s>Total RNA was prepared with a PureLink RNA Mini Kit (Life Technologies) with an additional DNase treatment step (PureLink DNase (Life Technologies)) and then reverse transcribed to cDNA with RevertAid H Minus Reverse Transcriptase and 500 M random pentadecamers (MWG).</s><s>Quantitative PCR was performed with a CFX96 detection system (Bio-Rad) with Maxima SYBR Green master mix (Fermentas) and QuantiTect Primer Assays (Qiagen) and the following primers for mouse Gapdh, 5 -ACGGGAAGCTCACTGGCATGGCCTT-3 (forward), 5 -CATGAG GTCCACCACCCTGTTGCTG-3 (reverse).</s><s>The primers for analysis of pre-mRNA were as follows: Dbp, 5 -GCTCTGAGAACGCAGACCTC-3 (forward), 5 -AGGTCATTAGCACCTCCACG-3 (reverse); Rev-Erb , 5 -CCCTCCCCTTGTGTTCTCTT-3 (forward), 5 -CTGCCATTGGAGCT GTCACT-3 (reverse); Bmal1, 5 -TGTCGCACATCTGTATTGACG-3 (forward), 5 -CTTCCATGAGGGTCATCTTTGT-3 (reverse); Pck1, 5 -TTCTC TGGCCTGCAACTTTC-3 (forward), 5 -TTGTCTTCACTGAGGTGCCA-3 (reverse); G6pc, 5 -GGCTGATGCCTTGACAGTCT-3 (forward), 5 -AG TATACACCTGCTGCGCCC-3 (reverse); Lpl, 5 -TCATTTCACATAGATG CTTGCC-3 (forward), 5 -GGGCACCCAACTCTCATACA-3 (reverse); Cyp7a1, 5 -CCCCCATATGTCTCCTTCCA-3 (forward), 5 -TAAATGGCAT TCCCTCCAGA-3 (reverse).</s><s>The transcript levels for each gene were normalized to those of Gapdh or Hprt and evaluated according to the 2 − Ct method <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">62</ref> .</s></p><p><s>Carbon monoxide gas treatment.</s><s>Cells were cultured in sodium bicarbonateand phenol red-free DMEM (Sigma-Aldrich) containing 10% FCS, 100 U/ml penicillin, 100 g/ml streptomycin and 25 mM HEPES.</s><s>For bioluminescence recordings (Fig. <ref type="figure">5c</ref>), reporter cells were seeded in 35-mm dishes and incubated with 250 M d-luciferin in light-and gas-tight aluminum boxes, including single photomultiplier tubes (Hamamatsu Photonics).</s><s>For gene-expression studies (Fig. <ref type="figure">3b</ref> and Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>) cells were seeded in 24-well plates and incubated in gas mixtures of 6% carbon monoxide (99.97%;</s><s>Linde AG) with 94% air or 6% nitrogen (99.99%;</s><s>Linde AG) with 94% air generated with DIGAMIX gas-mixing pumps (H.</s><s>Wösthoff).</s><s>These pumps have the highest accuracy for preparing high-quality calibration gas mixtures from pure gases.</s><s>The gas mixtures were humidified to 100% and passed with a flow of 20-30 ml/min through gastight tubes, and aluminum or Plexiglas boxes incubated at 37 °C.</s><s>According to Henry's law, 6% CO results in an ~50 M CO concentration in aqueous solution at 37 °C (ref.</s><s>63).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Carbon monoxide-releasing molecules (CORMs). CORMs (tricarbonyldichl ororuthenium(ii) dimer; [Ru(CO) 3 Cl 2 ]</head><p><s>2 ) or iCORMs (ruthenium(iii) chloride; RuCl 3 ) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich and dissolved in a mixture of DMSO and ethanol. 1 mol CORMs dissociates into 4 mol CO.</s><s>We used 400 M CO in these experiments, a concentration eight times higher than 6% CO (50 M); however, in contrast to that from constant gas treatment, CO from CORMs volatizes very rapidly, and only an undefined concentration reaches the cells.</s></p><p><s>Glucose production assay.</s><s>48 h after cell attachment, hepatocytes were synchronized with 1 M dexamethasone (Dex) for 1 h, washed twice with PBS and incubated overnight with phenol red-free DMEM containing 5 mM glucose, 0.5% FBS and 100 nM glucagon.</s><s>The next morning, cells were washed twice.</s><s>Then the medium was replaced with phenol red-free and glucose-free medium supplemented with 2 mM pyruvate, 20 mM lactate and 100 nM glucagon for 5 h.</s><s>The glucose concentration in the medium was determined with an Amplex Red Glucose Assay Kit (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer's instructions.</s><s>Total protein content was determined with the bicinchoninic acid (BCA) method (Thermo Scientific) for normalization.</s></p><p><s>Microarray experiments.</s><s>Primary hepatocytes from Ho-1 −/− 14-to 16-week-old male mice or their wild-type littermates with or without additional Ho-2 depletion were synchronized with dexamethasone.</s><s>24 h after synchronization, total RNA was isolated with a PureLink RNA Mini Kit (Life Technologies) with an additional DNase treatment step (PureLink DNase (Life Technologies)).</s><s>The integrity and amount of total RNA were analyzed with an Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer.</s><s>Synthesis of cDNA, amplification, labeling and hybridization were performed by the Labor für Funktionelle Genomforschung (LFGC) with GeneChip Mouse Gene 1.0 ST arrays (Affymetrix).</s></p><p><s>Bioinformatics analysis.</s><s>All steps of the bioinformatics analysis were performed in R 2.15.0 (http://www.R-project.org/).</s><s>Raw data from Affymetrix arrays were preprocessed and RMA normalized with the 'affy' package <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">64</ref> .</s><s>Differentially expressed probe sets were identified with an empirical Bayes approach implemented in the 'limma' package <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">65</ref> .</s><s>A minimum expression value of 6 on at least two arrays was set as a threshold.</s><s>The false discovery rate was set to 0.05, and a minimum fold change of 1.5 was assumed between two experimental groups.</s><s>Selected probe sets were clustered into six groups by application of a k-means algorithm to the scaled data.</s><s>To ensure a robust reproducible solution, 100 random start sets for the cluster centers were used.</s><s>Subsequently, probe sets were mapped to the associated genes.</s><s>Identification of GO terms with an over-representation of associated genes in the clusters was performed with a classical Fisher test implemented in the package 'topGO' (version 2.10.0;</s><s>http://www.bioconductor.</s><s>org/packages/release/bioc/html/topGO.html).</s><s>Because of the high redundancy of the GO hierarchy, no adjustment for multiple testing was done.</s><s>Overlaps with data sets from Hughes et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> and Rey et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> were analyzed with the Fisher test with a multiple-testing Bonferroni correction of the P values.</s><s>Circadian transcripts from Hughes et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> were identified after fitting of the array data to a cosine-model with a Bonferroni-corrected P value &lt;0.05, a minimal magnitude of six and a minimal amplitude of 0.5.</s><s>E-box motifs from Rey et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> were used to calculate the TRAP scores <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">66</ref> genome wide for all promoter regions from −1,000 to 1,000 bp relative to the potential transcription start site <ref type="bibr" target="#b66">67</ref> .</s><s>The maximum number of background sets was randomly sampled without replacement in the same sizes as the foreground sets (genes in clusters), and the scores were tested for higher values in the foreground sets with single-sided Wilcoxon rank-sum tests.</s><s>All P values were log 10 -transformed for plotting, and the geometric mean was calculated.</s></p><p><s>Statistics, sample size and conditions.</s><s>Statistical test are described in the respective figure legends or in the section above.</s><s>Sample sizes were not predetermined by statistical methods, and experiments were not randomized or conducted blind to conditions.</s><s>Data availability.</s><s>The microarray data of this study have been deposited in the NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database and are accessible through GEO series accession number GSE55448.</s><s>Source data for all other experiments are available on request.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular components of the mammalian circadian clock</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Buhr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Takahashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Handb. Exp. Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">217</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crosstalk between components of circadian and metabolic cycles in mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Asher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Schibler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Metab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="137" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nuclear receptor Rev-erbalpha: a heme receptor that coordinates circadian rhythm and metabolism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lazar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucl. Recept. Signal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e001</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rev-erbalpha, a heme sensor that coordinates metabolic and circadian pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">318</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1786" to="1789" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of heme as the ligand for the orphan nuclear receptors REV-ERB and REV-ERB</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Raghuram</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1207" to="1213" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NPAS2: a gas-responsive transcription factor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dioum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">298</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2385" to="2387" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ALAS1 gene expression is down-regulated by Akt-mediated phosphorylation and nuclear exclusion of FOXO1 by vanadate in diabetic mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Oliveri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Davio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Batlle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gerez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">442</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="310" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reciprocal regulation of haem biosynthesis and the circadian clock in mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kaasik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">430</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="467" to="471" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pharmacological and clinical aspects of heme oxygenase</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Abraham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kappas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacol. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="127" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Properties of human kidney heme oxygenase: inhibition by synthetic heme analogues and metalloporphyrins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Martasek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="480" to="487" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dual control mechanism for heme oxygenase: tin(IV)-protoporphyrin potently inhibits enzyme activity while markedly increasing content of enzyme protein in liver</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sardana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kappas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2464" to="2468" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diurnal variation of hepatic antioxidant gene expression in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e44237</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heme oxygenase-1/carbon monoxide: from basic science to therapeutic applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ryter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Alam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiol. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="583" to="650" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hypoxia induces severe right ventricular dilatation and infarction in heme oxygenase-1 null mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Yet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clin. Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="R23" to="R29" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emerging roles of cadmium and heme oxygenase in type-2 diabetes and cancer susceptibility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Satarug</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tohoku J. Exp. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">228</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="288" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Harmonics of circadian gene transcription in mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1000442</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide and phase-specific DNA-binding rhythms of BMAL1 control circadian output functions in mouse liver</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1000595</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulation of circadian behaviour and metabolism by REV-ERBand REV-ERB</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">485</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="127" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide expression analysis in Drosophila reveals genes controlling circadian behavior</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Ceriani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9305" to="9319" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome-wide transcriptional orchestration of circadian rhythms in Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ueda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">277</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14048" to="14052" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relevant expression of Drosophila heme oxygenase is necessary for the normal development of insect tissues</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">377</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1156" to="1161" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Targeted gene expression as a means of altering cell fates and generating dominant phenotypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Brand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Perrimon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="415" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Behavior of period-altered circadian rhythm mutants of Drosophila in light:dark cycles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hamblen-Coyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wheeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rutila</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rosbash</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Insect Behav</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="446" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neuroanatomy of cells expressing clock genes in Drosophila: transgenic manipulation of the period and timeless genes to mark the perikarya of circadian pacemaker neurons and their projections</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kaneko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comp. Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">422</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="66" to="94" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morning and evening peaks of activity rely on different clock neurons of the Drosophila brain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Grima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Chélot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Xia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rouyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">431</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="869" to="873" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isolation and chronobiological analysis of a neuropeptide pigment-dispersing factor gene in Drosophila melanogaster</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Rhythms</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coupled oscillators control morning and evening locomotor behaviour of Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stoleru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Agosto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rosbash</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">431</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="862" to="868" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genes for iron metabolism influence circadian rhythms in Drosophila melanogaster</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mandilaras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Missirlis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metallomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="928" to="936" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple circadianregulated elements contribute to cycling period gene expression in Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Stanewsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Jamison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Plautz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5006" to="5018" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A selfsustaining, light-entrainable circadian oscillator in the Drosophila brain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Veleri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Brandes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Helfrich-Förster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Stanewsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1758" to="1767" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hemebased sensing by the mammalian circadian protein CLOCK</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lukat-Rodgers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Correia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Botuyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rodgers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inorg. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6349" to="6365" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Carbon monoxide: an endogenous modulator of the nitric oxide-cyclic GMP signaling system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ingi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Ronnett</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="835" to="842" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of mutations in the heme domain on the transcriptional activity and DNA-binding activity of NPAS2</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ishida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ueha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sagami</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">368</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="292" to="297" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The pentose phosphate pathway regulates the circadian clock</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Metab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="462" to="473" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CO as a cellular signaling molecule</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ryter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Pharmacol. Toxicol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="449" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Carbon monoxide and nitric oxide: interacting messengers in muscarinic signaling to the brain&apos;s circadian clock</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Artinian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Gillette</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp. Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">171</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circadian heme oxygenase activity in the hamster suprachiasmatic nuclei</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Rubio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Agostino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ferreyra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Golombek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurosci. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">353</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nitric oxide increases GLUT4 expression and regulates AMPK signaling in skeletal muscle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Physiol. Endocrinol. Metab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">293</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="E1062" to="E1068" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AMPK regulates the circadian clock by cryptochrome phosphorylation and degradation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lamia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">326</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="440" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification and characterization of a small molecule AMPK activator that treats key components of type 2 diabetes and the metabolic syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cool</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Metab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="416" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A redox-dependent mechanism for regulation of AMPK activation by Thioredoxin1 during energy starvation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Metab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="245" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AMPK: lessons from transgenic and knockout animals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Viollet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Biosci. (Landmark Ed.)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two clocks in the brain: an update of the morning and evening oscillator model in Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yoshii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rieger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Helfrich-Förster</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog. Brain. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">199</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The neuropeptide pigment-dispersing factor adjusts period and phase of Drosophila&apos;s clock</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yoshii</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2597" to="2610" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epoxyeicosatrienoic acid agonist rescues the metabolic syndrome phenotype of HO-2-null mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sodhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Pharmacol. Exp. Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">331</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="906" to="916" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heme oxygenase-1 drives metaflammation and insulin resistance in mouse and man</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jais</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">158</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pro-oxidant role of heme oxygenase in mediating glucose-induced endothelial cell damage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Barbin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chakrabarti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Free Radic. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1301" to="1310" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exhaled carbon monoxide levels elevated in diabetes and correlated with glucose concentration in blood: a new test for monitoring the disease?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Paredi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Biernacki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Invernizzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kharitonov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1007" to="1011" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A molecular basis for natural selection at the timeless locus in Drosophila melanogaster</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sandrelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">316</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1898" to="1900" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An optimized transgenesis system for Drosophila using germ-line-specific phiC31 integrases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bischof</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Maeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hediger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Karch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Basler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3312" to="3317" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A pdf neuropeptide gene mutation and ablation of PDF neurons each cause severe abnormalities of behavioral circadian rhythms in Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Renn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rosbash</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Taghert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">99</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="791" to="802" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Peripheral glia direct axon guidance across the CNS/PNS transition zone</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sepp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schulte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Auld</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">238</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diet and energy-sensing inputs affect TorC1-mediated axon misrouting but not TorC2-directed synapse growth in a Drosophila model of tuberous sclerosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dimitroff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e30722</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">QUASIMODO, a novel GPI-anchored zona pellucida protein involved in light input to the Drosophila circadian clock</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Peschel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zavodska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sehadova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Stanewsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="719" to="729" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Signal analysis of behavioral and molecular cycles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Funes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dowse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Liver-specific overexpression of pancreatic-derived factor (PANDER) induces fasting hyperglycemia in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Endocrinology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">151</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5174" to="5184" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of the CLOCK protein in the mammalian circadian mechanism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Gekakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">280</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1564" to="1569" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A large-scale functional RNAi screen reveals a role for CK2 in the mammalian circadian clock</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Maier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="708" to="718" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extension of a genetic network model by iterative experimentation and mathematical analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C W</forename><surname>Locke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">13</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005. 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Amplifying the fluorescence of bilirubin enables the real-time detection of heme oxygenase activity. Free Radic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Klemz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Mashreghi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Spies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Volk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kotsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="311" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rhythmic CLOCK-BMAL1 binding to multiple E-box motifs drives circadian Dbp transcription and chromatin transitions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ripperger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Schibler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="374" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of relative gene expression data using realtime quantitative PCR and the 2 − CT method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Livak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Schmittgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="402" to="408" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">CRC Handbook of Chemistry and Physics: a Ready-Reference Book of Chemical and Physical Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Lide</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">affy: analysis of Affymetrix GeneChip data at the probe level</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gautier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cope</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bolstad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Irizarry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="315" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Smyth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gentleman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Carey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Irizarry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dudoit</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics and Computational Biology Solutions Using R and Bioconductor</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">397</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">420</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting transcription factor affinities to DNA from a biophysical model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Roider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kanhere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Manke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vingron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="134" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Flicek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="D84" to="D90" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
