<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Risk of Rotavirus Nosocomial Spread After Inpatient Pentavalent Rotavirus Vaccination</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Annika</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hofstetter</surname></persName>
							<email>annika.hofstetter@seattlechildrens.org</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatrics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Washington</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle, Washington</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>RN</roleName><forename type="first">Kirsten</forename><surname>Lacombe</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Seattle Children&apos;s Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>Washington</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD, MPH</roleName><forename type="first">Eileen</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatrics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Washington</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle, Washington</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Seattle Children&apos;s Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>Washington</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MPH</roleName><forename type="first">Charla</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Seattle Children&apos;s Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>Washington</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MPH</roleName><forename type="first">Bonnie</forename><surname>Strelitz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Seattle Children&apos;s Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>Washington</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename><surname>Jacobson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatrics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Washington</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle, Washington</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Seattle Children&apos;s Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>Washington</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MPH</roleName><forename type="first">Daksha</forename><surname>Ranade</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Seattle Children&apos;s Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>Washington</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MEd</roleName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Leanne</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Seattle Children&apos;s Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>Washington</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">National Center for Immunization and Respiratory Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<country key="GE">Georgia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MSc</roleName><forename type="first">Slavica</forename><surname>Mijatovic-Rustempasic</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">National Center for Immunization and Respiratory Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<country key="GE">Georgia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>BS</roleName><forename type="first">Diana</forename><surname>Evans</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">National Center for Immunization and Respiratory Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<country key="GE">Georgia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MPH</roleName><forename type="first">Mary</forename><surname>Wikswo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">National Center for Immunization and Respiratory Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<country key="GE">Georgia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bowen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">National Center for Immunization and Respiratory Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<country key="GE">Georgia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MBBS, MPH</roleName><forename type="first">Umesh</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Parashar</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">National Center for Immunization and Respiratory Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<country key="GE">Georgia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD, MSPH</roleName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Payne</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">National Center for Immunization and Respiratory Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Atlanta</settlement>
									<country key="GE">Georgia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Janet</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Englund</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatrics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Washington</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle, Washington</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Seattle Children&apos;s Research Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>Washington</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatrics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Washington</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1900 Ninth Ave, M/S JMB-9</addrLine>
									<postCode>98101</postCode>
									<settlement>Seattle</settlement>
									<region>WA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Risk of Rotavirus Nosocomial Spread After Inpatient Pentavalent Rotavirus Vaccination</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">Numbers: Print, 0031-4005; online, 1098-4275</idno>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">82BED103992895600CA71A6D515F4B92</idno>
					<note type="submission">Accepted for publication Sep 20, 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:20+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BACKGROUND:</head><p><s>Infants born prematurely or with underlying conditions are at increased risk of severe rotavirus disease and associated complications.</s><s>Given the theoretical risk of nosocomial transmission of vaccine-type rotavirus, rotavirus vaccination is recommended for infants at or after discharge from neonatal care settings.</s><s>Because the first dose should be administered by 104 days of age, some infants may be age-ineligible for vaccination if delayed until discharge.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS:</head><p><s>This prospective cohort included infants admitted to an urban academic medical center between birth and 104 days who received care in intensive care settings.</s><s>Pentavalent human-bovine reassortant rotavirus vaccine (RV5) was used, per routine clinical care.</s><s>Stool specimens were collected weekly (February 2013-April 2014) and analyzed for rotavirus strains using real-time reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction.</s><s>Demographic and vaccine data were collected.</s><s>RV5 safety was not assessed.</s></p><p><s>RESULTS: Of 385 study infants, 127 were age-eligible for routine vaccinations during hospitalization.</s><s>At discharge, 32.7% were up-to-date for rotavirus vaccination, compared with 82.7% for other vaccinations.</s><s>Of rotavirus-unvaccinated infants, 42.6% were discharged at age &gt;104 days and thus vaccination-ineligible.</s><s>Of 1192 stool specimens collected, rotavirus was detected in 13 (1.1%): 1 wild-type strain from an unvaccinated infant; 12 vaccine-type strains from 9 RV5-vaccinated infants.</s><s>No vaccine-type rotavirus cases were observed among unvaccinated infants (incidence rate: 0.0 [95% confidence interval: 0.0-1.5]</s><s>cases per 1000 patient days at risk).</s></p><p><s>CONCLUSIONS: These data suggest that delaying rotavirus vaccination until discharge from the hospital could lead to missed vaccination opportunities and may be unnecessary in institutions using RV5 with comparable infection control standards.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>What's KnoWn on this subject: Rotavirus vaccination is considered generally safe for infants born prematurely or with underlying conditions.</s><s>It is recommended at or after discharge from neonatal care units, given the potential spread of vaccine-type rotavirus, despite the lack of data demonstrating hospital transmission.</s></p><p><s>What this study adds: Many hospitalized infants did not receive rotavirus vaccination before discharge and were no longer ageeligible for vaccination after discharge from the hospital.</s><s>Although vaccine-type rotavirus shedding occurred in patients who received the pentavalent rotavirus vaccine, no vaccine-type rotavirus was detected in any unvaccinated infant.</s></p><p><s>to cite: Hofstetter AM, Lacombe K, Klein  Infants born prematurely, with low birth weight, or with other high-risk medical conditions are at increased risk of severe rotavirus disease that may necessitate hospitalization. <ref type="bibr">1 -3</ref> Data reveal that rotavirus vaccine is well tolerated in these infants. <ref type="bibr">4 -8</ref></s><s>hus, the US Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices (ACIP) recommends rotavirus vaccination of clinically stable preterm infants without contraindications who fulfill chronological age requirements (ie, 42-104 days of age for dose 1).</s><s>0]<ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[11]</ref> The authors of a previous study found that 63% of very low birth weight infants failed to receive rotavirus vaccine at the time of NICU discharge, often because they exceeded the upper age limit for vaccine receipt. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">12</ref></s><s>ta describing vaccine-type rotavirus shedding and transmission in the NICU are scarce.</s><s>In a recent study, researchers were unable to detect any rotavirus infections among unvaccinated infants who neighbored vaccinated infants in the NICU; &lt;1% had nonspecific gastrointestinal symptoms or fever that were attributed to concomitant medical conditions. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref></s><s>Because of the serious consequences of rotavirus infection in high-risk infants, 1 -3 understanding shedding and the nosocomial spread of vaccine-type rotavirus in a large sample of hospitalized infants is important.</s><s>Greater knowledge of other gastrointestinal pathogens shed in this population, which may cause symptoms similar to those associated with rotavirus, may also be valuable in the diagnosis and management of these high-risk patients.</s></p><p><s>This study evaluated infection, vaccination, and the potential nosocomial spread of wild-type and vaccine-type rotavirus strains among hospitalized infants in a regional tertiary care children's hospital.</s><s>Pentavalent human-bovine reassortant rotavirus vaccine (RV5) was administered under a standard hospital-wide protocol during this period.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods study design, setting, and Population</head><p><s>We conducted prospective surveillance, funded by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), between February 2013 and April 2014 at an urban academic pediatric hospital.</s><s>This hospital is the main regional referral center for pediatric care, including care of infants born prematurely and/ or with major congenital anomalies at other institutions.</s><s>All infants in the cardiac or pediatric ICU, half of those in the NICU, and threequarters of those in non-ICU settings have single-room assignments; the remaining infants have doubleroom assignments.</s><s>All are screened for vaccination status as part of routine clinical care.</s><s>During the study period, the hospital policy was to administer RV5 (RotaTeq; Merck, Kenilworth Station, NJ), irrespective of hospital setting (ICU or non-ICU), to infants without a history of intussusception, without moderate-to-severe acute illnesses, on no more than a maintenance dose of steroids, and not otherwise immunocompromised.</s><s>An additional institution-specific criterion of ≥37 weeks postmenstrual age was used to indicate clinical stability for simplified vaccine decisionmaking.</s><s>Minimum and maximum ages for vaccine administration and dosing intervals followed ACIP recommendations.</s><s>During the study period, population-based surveillance for rotavirus disease was also conducted in this hospital. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">14</ref> </s><s>ants were eligible for inclusion if they were admitted to the study hospital between 0 and 104 postnatal days of life and had received care in an ICU setting, including the NICU, cardiac ICU, or pediatric ICU.</s><s>Infants who were wards of the state, were transferred from another institution at or after 60 postnatal days of life, or required extracorporeal membrane oxygenation at the time of eligibility assessment were excluded.</s><s>A waiver of consent was obtained.</s><s>The study was approved by the Seattle Children's Hospital and CDC institutional review boards.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Procedures</head><p><s>Research staff reviewed ICU census lists twice weekly to identify potentially eligible subjects.</s><s>Those who fulfilled eligibility criteria and had a stool specimen available for collection were enrolled.</s><s>Participants were observed throughout their hospitalization, including after transfer to a non-ICU setting, or until 245 days of age for those with prolonged hospitalization.</s><s>Demographic (age, sex, race, ethnicity, insurance status), visit (admission and discharge dates), and vaccine (types, administration dates) information were obtained from the electronic health records by using a standardized abstraction form.</s><s>Clinical data were not abstracted; thus, RV5 safety was not assessed.</s><s>Nonclinical surveillance stool specimens were collected during a fixed 24-hour period each week.</s><s>Specimens were sent to the CDC for rotavirus laboratory confirmation and genotypic analyses by using qualitative real-time reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and RT-PCR assays, as described previously. <ref type="bibr">15 -17</ref></s><s>our samples yielded an invalid qualitative real-time RT-PCR result (internal process control was not detected).</s><s>These samples were subsequently tested and determined to be negative for rotavirus by using an enzyme immunoassay (Premier Rotaclone Rotavirus Detection Kit; Meridian Diagnostics, Cincinnati, OH).</s><s>A subset of systematically sampled stool specimens (median: 9 specimens per observation month) was also analyzed for other gastrointestinal pathogens (Campylobacter, Clostridium difficile toxin A/B, Escherichia coli O157, enterotoxigenic E coli, Shiga-like toxin-producing E coli, Salmonella, Shigella, Vibrio cholerae, Yersinia enterocolitica, adenovirus 40/41, norovirus GI/GII, Cryptosporidium, Entamoeba histolytica, and Giardia) by using the xTAG Gastrointestinal Pathogen Panel (Luminex, Austin, TX).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures</head><p><s>The primary outcome was a stool specimen positive for rotavirus.</s><s>Secondary outcomes included rotavirus genotype, potential exposure to vaccine-type rotavirus, the presence of other gastrointestinal pathogens, and up-to-date vaccination status at the time of hospital discharge.</s><s>Potential exposure was defined as a temporal overlap between hospitalization of an unvaccinated infant and the 14-day postvaccination interval of a vaccinated infant who shed vaccinetype rotavirus (interval onset: day of RV5 administration [day 0] 6 ; interval offset: postvaccination day 14 or discharge date, whichever occurred first).</s><s>One vaccinated infant was discharged to an outside facility on postvaccination day 5 and readmitted on postvaccination day 6; the entire 14-day interval was included.</s><s>Geotemporal proximity was defined as concurrent hospitalization in the same hospital area (eg, closely located rooms with similar nursing assignments) within the 14-day postvaccination interval.</s><s>Up-to-date vaccination at hospital discharge was defined as receipt of 1, 2, or 3 doses of recommended vaccines (diphtheria-tetanus-acellular pertussis [DTaP] vaccine, Haemophilus influenzae type b [Hib] vaccine, inactivated poliovirus vaccine [IPV], pneumococcal conjugate vaccine, hepatitis B vaccine, and RV5) among those hospitalized beyond 3, 5, or 7 months of age (ie, 1-month grace period), respectively. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">18</ref></s><s>To minimize missing vaccine information, up-to-date vaccination was calculated only among infants admitted at &lt;2 days of age for hepatitis B vaccine and at &lt;42 days of age for all other vaccines.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>analyses</head><p><s>The associations between demographic or visit characteristics and up-to-date vaccination status were assessed by using χ 2 and Fisher's exact tests.</s><s>Patient days of potential exposure to vaccine-type rotavirus were calculated among unvaccinated infants with ≥1 stool specimen collected during a potential exposure interval, excluding the first 2 days after hospital admission (to limit detection of communityacquired rotavirus infection) and any days preceding the first specimen collection.</s><s>A sensitivity analysis included only days of specimen collection.</s><s>Geotemporal proximity was assessed among infants with stool specimens positive for rotavirus.</s><s>To generate a 95% confidence interval for the incidence rate of vaccine-type rotavirus detections among unvaccinated infants, we assumed that observed cases followed a Poisson distribution.</s><s>Analyses were performed by using SAS version 9.4 (SAS Institute, Inc, Cary, NC).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Screening was performed for 838 hospitalizations of 775 unique infants.</s><s>Of these, 248 hospitalizations (29.6%) were ineligible because the infant was a ward of the state (n = 8), was admitted at an age &gt;104 days (n = 191), was transferred at an age ≥60 days (n = 47), or required extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (n = 9) (&gt;1 reason, n = 7).</s><s>For another 200 hospitalizations (23.9%), the infant did not produce a stool specimen within the observation period.</s><s>The remaining 390 hospitalizations (46.5%) of 385 unique infants (49.7%) were included (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1, Fig 1)</ref>.</s><s>Infants were primarily male, non-Hispanic, white, and publicly insured.</s><s>Most (93.1%) were hospitalized ≥7 days (median hospitalization: 27 days).</s><s>The infants were typically enrolled on day 8 of hospitalization, at 16 days of age, and were observed for 14 days (median values).</s><s>No infant was hospitalized for rotavirus gastroenteritis.</s><s>There were 16 deaths during the study period (all RV5unvaccinated patients; none had stool specimens positive for rotavirus).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Vaccination coverage</head><p><s>Of the 385 study infants, 127 (33.0%) were age-eligible for routine vaccinations during their hospitalization.</s><s>At hospital discharge, the proportion of infants who were up-to-date was high for DTaP vaccine (86.5%, n = 45/52), Hib vaccine (86.5%, n = 45/52), IPV vaccine (84.6%, n = 44/52), pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (84.6%, n = 44/52), and hepatitis B vaccine (82.1%, n = 23/28), but not for rotavirus vaccine (32.7%, n = 17/52).</s><s>In total, 47 RV5 doses were administered (19</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rotavirus shedding and nosocomial spread</head><p><s>Two-thirds (67.2%) of infants eligible for stool specimen collection in a given week had a specimen collected, resulting in 1192 stool specimens (Figs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1 and 2</ref>).</s><s>Overall, 57% had &gt;1 specimen collected (mean: 3.1; range: 1-24).</s><s>Unvaccinated infants provided 976 specimens.</s><s>Vaccinated infants provided 216 specimens, 75 of which were collected postvaccination (52 within 28 days after vaccination; Fig <ref type="figure">3</ref>).</s><s>Fourteen vaccinated infants had &gt;1 postvaccination specimen (8 had between 2-4 consecutive postvaccination specimens); the mean number of postvaccination specimens (total and consecutive) did not differ between those who did and did not shed vaccine-type virus.</s></p><p><s>Of the 1192 specimens, 13 (1.1%) were positive for rotavirus and 1179 (98.9%) were negative for rotavirus.</s><s>Of the specimens positive for rotavirus, 1 specimen was genotyped as wild-type and 12 specimens were vaccine-type.</s><s>The single wild-type genotype, G3P [8], was observed in an unvaccinated infant (64 days of age) in April 2014, a time when rotavirus infection with a similar strain was observed in surrounding clinical settings through active surveillance (data not shown).</s><s>The 12 vaccine-type specimens from 9 RV5-vaccinated infants included G4P [5], G6P [8], and 10 unspecified strains (no reassortants identified).</s><s>They typically occurred after dose 1 and within 7 days after vaccination (Fig <ref type="figure">3</ref>).</s><s>One infant had 4 specimens positive for rotavirus: day 12 after dose 1, day 2 after dose 2, and days 6 and 27 after dose 3; specimens negative for the virus were collected on day 19 after dose 1; days 9 and 30 after dose 2; and days 13, 48, 55, and 62 after dose 3. The 24 RV5-vaccinated infants without detectable vaccine-type rotavirus shedding had 43 specimens collected postvaccination and were observed for a median of 12 days after the last dose (range: 1-117 days).</s></p><p><s>We observed no vaccinetype rotavirus strains in any unvaccinated study infant.</s><s>Of the 357 hospitalizations of unvaccinated infants, 301 overlapped temporally with a 14-day postvaccination  interval of an RV5-vaccinated infant, 202 occurred during a potential exposure interval, and 155 had specimens collected from an unvaccinated infant during a potential exposure interval (45.2% with &gt;1 specimen; range: 1-7 specimens; 275 total specimens).</s></p><p><s>The latter resulted in 1952 patient days of potential exposure.</s><s>Given that no vaccine-type rotavirus cases were observed among these unvaccinated infants, the incidence rate (95% confidence interval) was 0.0 (0.0-1.5) cases per 1000 patient days at risk (0.0 [0-10.9]</s><s>when using only days of specimen collection).</s></p><p><s>There was no geotemporal proximity between the unvaccinated infant who shed wild-type virus and the RV5vaccinated infants who shed vaccinetype rotavirus strains.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>other Gastrointestinal Pathogens</head><p><s>In total, 299 (25.1%) stool specimens were tested for other gastrointestinal pathogens.</s><s>One specimen (0.3%) had a positive result (C difficile, toxin B positive).</s><s>No other results were positive.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>discussion</head><p><s>In this prospective weekly surveillance of high-risk, medically complex infants during hospitalization, no transmission of vaccine-type rotavirus from an RV5vaccinated to unvaccinated infant was detected, including in those with geotemporal overlap.</s><s>Vaccine-type rotavirus strains were detected only among infants who had received RV5 vaccination.</s></p><p><s>As in earlier studies examining rotavirus vaccination in preterm and other high-risk infants, 5 -8 our data suggest that delaying rotavirus vaccination until hospital discharge may be unnecessary in institutions with comparable infection control standards.</s><s>Our observed incidence rate empirically supports this assessment, although it does not preclude the possibility of transmission.</s></p><p><s>Fewer than half of infants receiving routine childhood immunizations also received rotavirus vaccine before discharge, illustrating the extent of missed opportunities for rotavirus vaccination among infants at high risk for severe rotavirus infection.</s><s>Only one-third of vaccineeligible infants received rotavirus vaccine before discharge.</s><s>This finding is striking, given that the study took place in a hospital with a permissive policy toward rotavirus vaccination and in which vaccination PEDIATRICS Volume 141, number 1, January 2018 5</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3</head><p><s>Shedding after RV5 vaccination of study infants in the hospital setting.</s></p><p><s>is strongly supported, which is demonstrated by the high proportion of infants who were up-to-date for other routine vaccines at discharge.</s><s>Another institution reported up-todate levels for DTaP (58%), Hib (58%), IPV (58%), and hepatitis B (62%) vaccines at NICU discharge <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">19</ref> that were lower than observed here, even without the 1-month grace period (data not shown).</s><s>It is noteworthy that nearly half of infants unvaccinated against rotavirus in our study were no longer eligible for vaccination after hospital discharge.</s><s>These data are similar to those reported in a 2013 cohort, in which only 37% of very low birth weight infants were vaccinated against rotavirus before NICU discharge and in which 36% of unvaccinated infants were age-ineligible at discharge. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">12</ref></s><s>ata describing rotavirus vaccination rates in high-risk infants after hospital discharge are limited, although these rates likely fall below Healthy People 2020 target levels (80%) <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">20</ref> given the lower vaccination rates for rotavirus than for other routine vaccines in general. <ref type="bibr">21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">22</ref> </s><s>e RV5-vaccinated infants in our study had ≥1 stool specimen positive for vaccine-type rotavirus strains after rotavirus vaccination.</s><s>Some shedding of vaccine-type virus after RV5 vaccination is expected. <ref type="bibr">23 -26</ref></s><s>In a previous study of 15 preterm infants with 6 stool specimens collected during the 2 weeks after vaccination, 87% of infants shed a vaccine-type strain, and 77% of specimens were positive for a vaccine-type strain. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s>n another study of infants with intestinal failure who had stool specimens collected at 1, 2, and 4 weeks postvaccination, 47% shed rotavirus. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref></s><s>In the current study, most vaccine-type rotavirus shedding occurred within 1 week after vaccination, which is consistent with data in the general infant population, in whom peak shedding occurs at 4 to 7 days after dose 1 and at 1 to 3 days after doses 2 and 3. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">26</ref> Although vaccine-type rotavirus shedding did occur, no vaccinetype strains were detected in stool specimens collected during the 155 hospitalizations of unvaccinated infants with potential exposure.</s><s>This could be due, in part, to the small number of RV5-vaccinated infants with shedding during hospitalization.</s><s>It could also reflect reduced exposure due to hospital infection control measures.</s><s>The findings are consistent with those of studies in which only 10 of 801 "neighboring" unvaccinated infants in the NICU had gastrointestinal symptoms or fever postvaccination <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> and no household contacts (n = 53) of infants vaccinated at NICU discharge developed symptoms suggestive of rotavirus infection. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s>ring this 14-month study, 1 wild-type rotavirus specimen was detected, which was collected from an unvaccinated infant.</s><s>This finding is consistent with the findings of another study in which nosocomial cases of rotavirus gastroenteritis in the NICU were rare (ie, 4.9 per 10 000 patient days in the prevaccination period at 1 hospital). <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>imilarly, 1 of 299 specimens tested for other common gastrointestinal pathogens was positive.</s><s>This reveals surprisingly low rates of colonization with other viral pathogens and C difficile in this hospital.</s><s>Limited data describing gastrointestinal shedding, regardless of symptoms, among hospitalized infants are available.</s></p><p><s>One study from Australia found that 6% of stool specimens from preterm infants were colonized with viruses. <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">27</ref></s><s>Our data, obtained by using sensitive molecular techniques with prospective surveillance, indicate that common gastrointestinal pathogens in infants may not be frequent in ICUs today.</s></p><p><s>This study has several limitations.</s><s>First, approval from institutional review boards to passively enroll infants in this study facilitated stool specimen collection but limited our ability to acquire and review additional data (ie, assigned medical providers; clinical status of RV5vaccinated infants or infants with rotavirus-positive specimens).</s><s>Second, we likely underestimated the shedding rate in this study because specimens were collected on a weekly basis during hospitalization, and shedding can be intermittent. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> </s><s>wever, the authors of other studies have shown shedding of &gt;1 week's duration. <ref type="bibr">24 -26</ref></s><s>The use of sensitive molecular laboratory methods potentially increased viral detection overall, and shedding in sequential stool specimens from RV5-vaccinated patients was detected.</s><s>Only 1 study infant had intermittent RV5 shedding documented.</s><s>Third, this study was not designed to include all hospitalized infants, and we therefore could not determine actual exposure in all unvaccinated infants and may have also underestimated RV5 transmission.</s><s>Our ability to detect transmission in this study depended on the observation of vaccine-type rotavirus strains in unvaccinated patients within the time period when vaccine-type rotavirus strains were most likely to be shed. <ref type="bibr">24 -26</ref></s><s>It is worth noting that polymerase chain reaction detection of vaccine-type rotavirus among RV5-vaccinated infants does not necessarily mean that there is enough viable virus to transmit to unvaccinated infants, as suggested by comparatively lower rates of culture positivity. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">25</ref> </s><s>urth, this study included a diverse population of high-risk hospitalized infants in ICU and non-ICU settings, all with single and double-room assignments, at 1 academic medical center.</s><s>This could impact generalizability to other populations and settings.</s><s>Because all vaccinated infants received RV5, the findings also should not be generalized to the monovalent human rotavirus vaccine.</s><s>Evidence suggests that the monovalent human rotavirus vaccine has a comparable shedding rate, but a significantly higher viral load, than RV5. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">26</ref></s><s>Lastly, vaccines administered before or after hospitalization and reasons for missed vaccination opportunities were not captured.</s></p><p><s>The timing of rotavirus vaccination is somewhat controversial worldwide.</s></p><p><s>Recognizing the programmatic challenges and potential risk/benefit ratio in certain developing countries, the World Health Organization expanded the acceptable maximum age of rotavirus vaccination to 24 months. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28</ref></s><s>Although this recommendation has been poorly adopted worldwide, many preterm and high-risk infants may be potentially eligible for rotavirus vaccination after hospital discharge.</s><s>Given available data, 5, 7 however, RV5 vaccination during hospitalization could still be considered for optimal protection of these vulnerable infants.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>conclusions</head><p><s>Since the introduction of rotavirus vaccines, the disease burden and cost of rotavirus gastroenteritis has decreased substantially. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29</ref></s><s>Our study found that two-thirds of eligible highrisk infants failed to receive rotavirus vaccine during their hospitalization, and nearly half (43%) were no longer age-eligible for vaccination after hospital discharge.</s><s>No vaccinetype rotavirus transmission to unvaccinated study infants in this hospital environment was observed, despite documented shedding of vaccine-type rotavirus strains in RV5vaccinated infants.</s><s>Delaying rotavirus vaccination until the time of hospital discharge may be unnecessary in institutions where RV5 is used and with comparable infection control standards.</s><s>Such delays may leave medically-vulnerable infants unprotected and susceptible to severe rotavirus infection and associated complications.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>acKnoWledGMents</head><p><s>We thank the nurses and medical staff at Seattle Children's Hospital who facilitated stool specimen collection, as well as our research staff who participated in the conduct of this study, especially Diane Kinnunen, Catherine Bull, and Kristin Follmer.</s><s>In addition, we thank Anne Cent and staff in the University of Washington Clinical Virology Laboratory.</s><s>All individuals listed here have provided written permission to be acknowledged.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FiGuRe 1 flow</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FiGuRe 1 flow diagram of stool specimen collection and results, by vaccination status.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,46.80,380.51,320.40,218.28" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FiGuRe 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FiGuRe 2 Number of stool specimens collected among study infants eligible for stool specimen collection in the hospital each week (february 2013-April 2014).</s><s>The week number corresponds to the CDC Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report week.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,98.91,404.19,180.62,157.34" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Study Population (N = 385)</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Characteristics</cell></row></table><note><p><s>a five infants were hospitalized twice.</s><s>Age at enrollment, duration of observation, and duration of hospitalization were calculated for each hospitalization.</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Downloaded from http://publications.aap.org/pediatrics/article-pdf/141/1/e20171110/1065701/peds_20171110.pdf by guest</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>FundinG: Supported by the New Vaccine Surveillance Network of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (U01IP000457).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Potential conFlict oF inteRest:</head><p><s>Dr Hofstetter previously received research support from Pfizer Independent Grants for Learning and Change.</s><s>Dr Englund receives research support from Pfizer, Gilead, and GlaxoSmithKline.</s><s>Dr Englund was a consultant for Pfizer and Gilead and served on a data safety monitoring board for GlaxoSmithKline; the other authors have indicated they have no potential conflicts of interest to disclose.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A case-control study to determine risk factors for hospitalization for rotavirus gastroenteritis in U.S. children</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Dennehy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cortese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bégué</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatr Infect Dis J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1123" to="1131" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perinatal risk factors for infant hospitalization with viral gastroenteritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Newman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Grupp-Phelan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Shay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target=".pediatrics.org/cgi/content/full/103/1/e3" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Available at: www</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chronic rotavirus infection in immunodeficiency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Saulsbury Ft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Winkelstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Yolken</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pediatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">REST Study Team. Safety and efficacy of the pentavalent human-bovine (WC3) reassortant rotavirus vaccine in healthy premature infants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Goveia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rodriguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dallas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatr Infect Dis J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1099" to="1104" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Safety of rotavirus vaccine in the NICU</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Monk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Motsney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target=".org/cgi/content/full/133/6/e1555" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">133</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Available at: www. pediatrics</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rotavirus shedding in premature infants following first immunization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mcneal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Haase</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Dekker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vaccine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8141" to="8146" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of pentavalent rotavirus vaccination in neonatal intensive care units</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Thrall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Doll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vaccine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5095" to="5102" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The safety and immunogenicity of rotavirus vaccination in infants with intestinal failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Javid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Sanchez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jacob</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mcneal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Horslen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Englund</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="65" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cortese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Parashar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Prevention of rotavirus gastroenteritis among infants and children: recommendations of the Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices (ACIP)</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1074</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published correction appears in</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MMWR Recomm Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Addition of severe combined immunodeficiency as a contraindication for administration of rotavirus vaccine</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="687" to="688" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Addition of history of intussusception as a contraindication for rotavirus vaccination</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1427</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rotavirus vaccination of very low birth weight infants at discharge from the NICU</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Stumpf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sánchez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target=".pediatrics.org/cgi/content/full/132/3/e662" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Available at: www</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rotavirus strain trends during the postlicensure vaccine era: United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bowen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mijatovic-Rustempasic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Esona</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">214</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="732" to="738" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008-2013. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effectiveness of pentavalent and monovalent rotavirus vaccines in concurrent use among US children &lt;5 years of age</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Payne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Boom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Staat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009-2011. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real-time RT-PCR assays to differentiate wild-type group A rotavirus strains from Rotarix(®) and RotaTeq(®) vaccine strains in stool samples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gautam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Esona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mijatovic-Rustempasic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ian</forename><surname>Tam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gentsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bowen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum Vaccin Immunother</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="767" to="777" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiplexed one-step RT-PCR VP7 and VP4 genotyping assays for rotaviruses using updated primers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Esona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gautam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Tam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mijatovic-Rustempasic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bowen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Virol Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">223</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sensitive and specific quantitative detection of rotavirus A by one-step real-time reverse transcription-PCR assay without antecedent double-stranded-RNA denaturation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mijatovic-Rustempasic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Tam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kerin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3047" to="3054" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Timeliness of childhood immunizations: a statespecific analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Luman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Barker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mccauley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Drews-Botsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1367" to="1374" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Underimmunization at discharge from the neonatal intensive care unit</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Navar-Boggan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Halsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Escobar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Golden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Perinatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="367" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Rotavirus vaccination coverage among infants aged 5 months -immunization information system sentinel sites</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="521" to="524" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-06">September 5, 2017 21. June 2006-June 2009. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>US Department of Health and Human Services</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Available at: www. healthypeople. gov/ 2020/ topics-objectives/ topic/ immunization-and-infectious-diseases/ objectives</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">National, state, and selected local area vaccination coverage among children aged 19-35 months -United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Elam-Evans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yankey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Singleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kolasa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="889" to="896" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rotavirus Efficacy and Safety Trial (REST) Study Team. Safety and efficacy of a pentavalent humanbovine (WC3) reassortant rotavirus vaccine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Vesikari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Matson</forename><surname>Do</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dennehy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">354</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The integrated phase III safety profile of the pentavalent human-bovine (WC3) reassortant rotavirus vaccine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Dennehy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Goveia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dallas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Heaton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="S36" to="S42" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of fecal shedding of rotavirus vaccine in infants following their first dose of pentavalent rotavirus vaccine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jakob</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Esona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vaccine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4151" to="4155" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of virus shedding after lived attenuated and pentavalent reassortant rotavirus vaccine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hsieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wu Ft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hsiung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vaccine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1199" to="1204" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prevalence of viruses in stool of premature neonates at a neonatal intensive care unit</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Naing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Rayner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Killikulangara</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Paediatr Child Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="E221" to="E226" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">World Health organization. Rotavirus vaccines. WHo position paper</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Wkly Epidemiol Rec</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-01">January 2013. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">National estimates of reductions in acute gastroenteritis-related hospitalizations and associated costs in US children following implementation of rotavirus vaccines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Leshem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Tate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Curns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lopman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Parashar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>published online ahead of print August 10, 2017</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/jpids/pix057</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
