<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Successful intraprocedural anticoagulation with bivalirudin during pulmonary vein isolation in a patient with known heparin-induced thrombocytopenia type II</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-11-19">19 November 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Barbara</forename><surname>Bellmann</surname></persName>
							<email>barbara.bellmann@charite.de</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Patrick</forename><surname>Nagel</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Bogdan</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Muntean</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Benjamin Franklin, Hindenburgdamm 30</addrLine>
									<postCode>12203</postCode>
									<settlement>Charité Berlin, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medicine-Cardiology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Hindenburgdamm 30</addrLine>
									<postCode>12203</postCode>
									<settlement>Charité Berlin Campus Ben-jamin Franklin, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Successful intraprocedural anticoagulation with bivalirudin during pulmonary vein isolation in a patient with known heparin-induced thrombocytopenia type II</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-11-19">19 November 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">0FC911A4613242A4B8E4A898E12B69A8</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.joa.2015.10.004</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 7 September 2015 Received in revised form 8 October 2015 Accepted 9 October 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Pulmonary vein isolation Atrial fibrillation Heparin induced thrombocytopenia type II Bivalirudin Activated clotting time</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>We report the case of a 56-year-old female who presented with symptomatic paroxysmal atrial fibrillation.</s><s>Anamnestic heparin-induced thrombocytopenia (HIT) type II was suspected, and a rapid diagnostic test showed antibodies against platelet factor 4. The heparin-induced platelet activation-assay was negative.</s><s>Radiofrequency pulmonary vein isolation with intraprocedural anticoagulation using bivalirudin was ultimately performed.</s><s>Dosing was controlled by monitoring the activated clotting time.</s><s>Postprocedural blood tests were normal.</s><s>There were no thromboembolic or bleeding events.</s><s>Bivalirudin is a therapeutic option for anticoagulation during pulmonary vein isolation procedures in patients with a history of HIT type II.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Case report</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1.">History</head><p><s>We report the case of a 56-year-old female who presented with symptomatic paroxysmal atrial fibrillation.</s><s>Anamnestic heparininduced thrombocytopenia (HIT) type II was suspected, and a HIT diagnostic test was performed.</s><s>The initial diagnosis of HIT II was made in 2006.</s><s>A rapid test showed antibodies against platelet factor 4. The heparin-induced platelet activation assay was negative.</s><s>The patient was on oral Apixaban (5 mg 1-0-1) for anticoagulation, and also metoprolol (95 mg 1-0-1).</s><s>Relevant history included single-vessel coronary disease with moderately reduced systolic pump function, and a stroke without residual symptoms.</s><s>After extensive consideration, radiofrequency pulmonary vein isolation with intraprocedural anticoagulation using bivalirudin was ultimately performed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2.">Treatment and course</head><p><s>Laboratory parameters normalized after the patient was hospitalized (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</s><s>Oral anticoagulation with Apixaban was stopped the day before the planned procedure.</s><s>At the beginning of pulmonary vein isolation after transseptal puncture, bivalirudin was administered as a 0.75 mg/kg intravenous bolus, followed by a 1.75 mg/kg/h infusion.</s><s>The activated clotting time was subsequently closely monitored.</s><s>The values tended to be high, but the infusion rate was maintained (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).</s><s>The planned radiofrequency pulmonary vein isolation was performed successfully without complications after 3-dimensional mapping of the pulmonary veins and left atrium.</s><s>There was no post-interventional pericardial effusion.</s><s>Bivalirudin was stopped immediately after the final radiofrequency application.</s><s>No bleeding or clotting events were noted.</s><s>The laboratory values remained stable before and after ablation (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</s><s>After ablation, a direct and uncomplicated conversion to oral anticoagulation with Apixaban (5 mg 1-0-1) was performed.</s><s>The patient was discharged home on the third postoperative day. of thrombin, and is potent and highly specific.</s><s>Bivalirudin has a rapid onset of action with a plasma half-life of 25 min.</s><s>It inhibits circulating and clot-bound thrombin, while also inhibiting thrombin-mediated platelet activation and aggregation.</s><s>It does not bind to plasma proteins (other than thrombin) or to red blood cells.</s><s>Therefore, it has a predictable antithrombotic response.</s><s>It does not need a binding cofactor such as antithrombin.</s><s>Bivalirudin does not activate platelets.</s><s>Current studies recommend using bivalirudin as a preferred alternative to unfractionated heparin in patients with HIT for cardiac and vascular surgery as well as for percutaneous coronary intervention <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>Anticoagulation for radiofrequency pulmonary vein isolation may be another potential use for bivalirudin in the setting of HIT.</s><s>Ablation of pulmonary veins is an established therapeutic option for patients with symptomatic drug-refractory paroxysmal atrial fibrillation.</s><s>Radiofrequency is currently the most widely used source of energy for pulmonary vein ablation.</s><s>Our usual activated clotting time (ACT) values in radiofrequency procedures are above 350 s.</s><s>The initial ACT value in this procedure was 4500 s; we thought this was due to the initial bolus.</s><s>Although the ACT value throughout the procedure was higher than the usual 350 s, we maintained the infusion rate to avoid fluctuations below 350 s.</s><s>Despite lacking experience in the use of bivalirudin for radiofrequency pulmonary vein isolation, we tried not to undershoot our ACT target.</s><s>We felt supported in this intraprocedural anticoagulation management by the fact that there were no bleeding or thrombotic complications.</s><s>Anticoagulation is required during this procedure, since stroke risk is a feared complication of radiofrequency pulmonary vein isolation <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s>There are a few reports in the literature about the use of bivalirudin during electrophysiology procedures <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>; As in our case, bivalirudin was administered as a 0.75 mg/kg intravenous bolus, followed by a 1.75 mg/kg/h infusion.</s><s>ACT was monitored closely during pulmonary vein isolation.</s><s>There were no bleeding complications, although the ACT was intermittently increased (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).</s><s>To avoid fluctuations in a non-therapeutic range, the infusion rate was not lowered.</s><s>The ACT is the most commonly used functional test to measure heparin anticoagulation.</s><s>This test is based on the ability of whole blood to form a visible fibrin monomer within a glass tube.</s><s>However, this procedure has known limitations.</s><s>It is imprecise, and the sensitivity is in the lower range; thus, this method of measurement is of limited clinical use, in particular for the monitoring of hirudin and other direct thrombin inhibitors.</s><s>Most recently, the direct prothrombin pathway has predominated for monitoring of direct thrombin inhibitors, as with determination of the ecarin clotting time.</s><s>However, this is not always immediately and directly available.</s><s>Moreover, Weeks et al. reported that hyper-ACT responses to bivalirudin therapy in percutaneous coronary intervention were not associated with elevated bleeding risk <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>There were no thromboembolic events and the laboratory values remained stable before and after ablation (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</s><s>After ablation, a prompt and uncomplicated conversion to oral anticoagulation with Apixaban (5 mg 1-0-1) was performed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4.">Summary</head><p><s>This case shows that the treatment of patients with rhythmological concerns who have actual or suspected HIT II can be very complex.</s><s>Bivalirudin is a therapeutic option for anticoagulation during pulmonary vein isolation procedures in patients with a history of HIT.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p><s>1.</s><s>All authors contributed to the work and have reviewed and agree with the content of the article.</s><s>2. None of the article contents are under consideration for publication in any other journal or have been published in any journal.</s><s>3.</s><s>No portion of the text has been copied.</s><s>4. I am aware that it is the authors' responsibility to obtain permission for any figures or tables reproduced from any prior publications, and to cover fully any costs involved.</s><s>5.</s><s>All authors declare no conflict of interest related to this study.</s></p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bivalirudin provides rapid, effective, and reliable anticoagulation during off-pump coronary revascularization: results of the &quot;EVOLUTION OFF&quot; trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Koster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Spiess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jurmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anesth Analg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="540" to="544" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of cryoballoon and radiofrequency ablation of pulmonary veins in 40 patients with paroxysmal atrial fibrillation: a case-control study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Linhart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bellmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mittmann-Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1343" to="1348" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bivalirudin use during radiofrequency catheter ablation procedures in two patients with a history of heparin-induced thrombocytopenia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Baetz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gerstenfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kolansky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacotherapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">952</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of bivalirudin hyperand hypo-ACT responses in the setting of percutaneous coronary intervention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Weeks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Alkhateeb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Michaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Invasive Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="250" to="253" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
