<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Identification of Tp0751 (Pallilysin) as a Treponema pallidum Vascular Adhesin by Heterologous Expression in the Lyme disease Spirochete</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wei-Chien</forename><forename type="middle">Andrew</forename><surname>Kao</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Dentistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Matrix Dynamics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Helena</forename><surname>Pětrošová</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Dentistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Matrix Dynamics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Rhodaba</forename><surname>Ebady</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Dentistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Matrix Dynamics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Karen</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Lithgow</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Microbiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Victoria</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Victoria</settlement>
									<region>BC</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Pablo</forename><surname>Rojas</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité University Medicine Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yang</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Dentistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Matrix Dynamics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yae-Eun</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Dentistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Matrix Dynamics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yae-Ram</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tanya</forename><surname>Odisho</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Dentistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Matrix Dynamics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nupur</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Dentistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Matrix Dynamics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Annette</forename><surname>Moter</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Dentistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Matrix Dynamics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">German Heart Center Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Biofilmcenter, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Caroline</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cameron</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Microbiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Victoria</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Victoria</settlement>
									<region>BC</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Tara</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moriarty</surname></persName>
							<email>tara.moriarty@utoronto.ca</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Dentistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Matrix Dynamics Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathobiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Canada. Wei-Chien Andrew</addrLine>
									<settlement>Toronto, Kao, Helena</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Identification of Tp0751 (Pallilysin) as a Treponema pallidum Vascular Adhesin by Heterologous Expression in the Lyme disease Spirochete</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3C979610FDB4DC78FB807E4EDAEA52E1</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1038/s41598-017-01589-4</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 21 December 2016 Accepted: 29 March 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:16+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Treponema pallidum subsp.</s><s>pallidum, the causative agent of syphilis, is a highly invasive spirochete pathogen that uses the vasculature to disseminate throughout the body.</s><s>Identification of bacterial factors promoting dissemination is crucial for syphilis vaccine development.</s><s>An important step in dissemination is bacterial adhesion to blood vessel surfaces, a process mediated by bacterial proteins that can withstand forces imposed on adhesive bonds by blood flow (vascular adhesins).</s><s>The study of T. pallidum vascular adhesins is hindered by the uncultivable nature of this pathogen.</s><s>We overcame these limitations by expressing T. pallidum adhesin Tp0751 (pallilysin) in an adhesion-attenuated strain of the cultivable spirochete Borrelia burgdorferi.</s><s>Under fluid shear stress representative of conditions in postcapillary venules, Tp0751 restored bacterial-vascular interactions to levels similar to those observed for infectious B. burgdorferi and a gain-of-function strain expressing B. burgdorferi vascular adhesin BBK32.</s><s>The strength and stability of Tp0751-and BBK32-dependent endothelial interactions under physiological shear stress were similar, although the mechanisms stabilizing these interactions were distinct.</s><s>Tp0751 expression also permitted bacteria to interact with postcapillary venules in live mice as effectively as BBK32-expressing strains.</s><s>These results demonstrate that Tp0751 can function as a vascular adhesin.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Treponema pallidum subsp.</s><s>pallidum is a bacterium from the spirochete family and the causative agent of syphilis.</s><s>Syphilis is a sexually transmitted disease, which is often considered a disease of the past.</s><s>However, it still represents a global health problem with 36 million cases and 11 million new infections annually <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> .</s><s>Moreover, syphilis incidence has increased dramatically over the past two decades in Canada 2 , the United States 3 , China <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> , and in a number of European countries <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> .</s><s>Given its high prevalence, syphilis has a substantial impact on global health.</s><s>Syphilis infection in pregnancy has up to 80% morbidity and can result in stillbirth, neonatal death, and complications associated with congenital syphilis in newborns <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> .</s><s>Active syphilis infection also significantly increases infectivity of HIV-positive patients and risk of HIV acquisition <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> , and modeling studies suggest that controlling syphilis will contribute to HIV prevention <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> .</s><s>Since elimination of syphilis has not been achieved by antibiotic treatment, novel preventative approaches are needed to fight this disease.</s></p><p><s>To date, the molecular mechanisms of T. pallidum pathogenesis are still poorly understood.</s><s>This is mainly because the organism is an obligate human pathogen that cannot be cultured continuously in vitro <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> .</s><s>The inability to culture T. pallidum has limited the use of many experimental approaches, including genetic manipulation to study the molecular pathogenesis of this bacterium.</s><s>To overcome this issue, a heterologous gain-of-function system for expressing candidate T. pallidum virulence genes in related culturable organisms is needed.</s><s>The T. pallidum protein Tp0751 has been successfully expressed in the culturable non-adherent spirochete Treponema phagedenis, where it restores the capacity for host cell adhesion under static conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> .</s><s>Recently, expression of a candidate T. pallidum protein (Tp0435) in the Lyme disease spirochete Borrelia burgdorferi has been used to establish its role in immune evasion and host cell adhesion <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> .</s></p><p><s>T. pallidum disseminates widely via the bloodstream to invade multiple tissues and organs and the interaction of T. pallidum with the vasculature is therefore a critical step of the infection process <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> .</s><s>Dissemination allows the pathogen to spread from the initial site of infection to secondary target tissues including, but not limited to, the oral cavity <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> , kidney <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> , stomach <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> , spleen <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> , liver <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> , and central nervous system <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref> .</s><s>T. pallidum disseminates not only widely, but rapidly; T. pallidum can penetrate endothelial intracellular junctions <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref> , and in a rabbit model enters the circulatory system within minutes of initial infection <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref> .</s><s>It also is one of the few pathogens able to cross both the blood-brain and placental barriers <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref> .</s><s>Identification of the mechanisms underlying the extraordinary invasiveness of this pathogen is a key to understanding and preventing disease progression.</s></p><p><s>In order to invade tissue barriers such as the endothelial lining of blood vessels, bacteria must first attach to host ligands associated with endothelial surfaces via bacterial adhesion proteins (adhesins) <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26</ref> .</s><s>These interactions permit bacteria circulating at the speed of blood flow to slow down and transmigrate through the endothelial lining of blood vessels (extravasation).</s><s>Interaction of circulating bacteria with endothelia and its associated extracellular matrix (ECM) is challenging under vascular shear stress conditions.</s><s>The first step of this process, in which surface molecules on blood-borne bacteria interact with molecules on endothelial surfaces, is especially critical, since binding interactions must be sufficiently strong and stable to withstand the fluid shear stress (force) generated by blood flow over vessel walls.</s><s>Circulating host cells such as leukocytes, for example, must slow and roll along endothelial surfaces before they can extravasate.</s><s>Even in the vessels where shear stress is typically lowest (postcapillary venules: PCVs), leukocytes require specialized adhesion molecules with catch bond properties (bonds which strengthen as force increases) and/or elastic, bungee cord-like tethers, which anchor leukocytes to endothelial surfaces to stabilize interactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref> .</s><s>In the absence of such stabilizing mechanisms, leukocyte-endothelial interactions are very vulnerable to small changes in force, and leukocytes dissociate from endothelia at exponentially faster rates with small, linear increases in shear stress <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28</ref> .</s></p><p><s>Disseminating bacteria also require specialized adhesins and interaction mechanisms that can withstand the forces generated by blood flow, since such mechanisms are necessary for bacteria to slow down and extravasate through the endothelial lining of blood vessels.</s><s>B. burgdorferi-endothelial interactions mediated by the adhesin BBK32 become more stable with increasing force under PCV shear stress conditions and thus exhibit catch bond properties, and both BBK32-dependent and BBK32-independent B. burgdorferi-endothelial interactions are stabilized by tethers <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s><s>BBK32-mediated catch bonds also depend on plasma fibronectin (pFn) <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30</ref> .</s><s>In addition to BBK32, a number of other vascular adhesins have recently been identified in B. burgdorferi (BB0347, and decorin-binding proteins DbpA and DbpB) <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[31]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[32]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[33]</ref> and in Staphylococcus aureus (von Willebrand factor-binding protein, vWbp, and fibronectin-binding protein A, FnBPA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35</ref> .</s><s>All of these adhesins, including BBK32, share the property of binding to glycosylated structures and/or extracellular matrix components of blood and endothelial cells, including von Willebrand factor and fibronectin (Fn) <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[36]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[37]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[39]</ref> .</s><s>Additional bacterial adhesins and virulence factors such as the B. burgdorferi adhesin P66 <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40</ref> are also likely to be important for transmigration of bacteria through endothelial layers after or during shear stress-resistant adhesion.</s><s>Adhesion of T. pallidum to endothelial surfaces under physiological shear stress conditions has not been studied, and adhesins that are strong and stable enough to permit vascular interactions during dissemination of this pathogen have not yet been identified.</s><s>Identification of adhesins that promote cardiovascular dissemination of T. pallidum will be important for vaccine development to prevent the establishment of disseminated infection.</s></p><p><s>Several T. pallidum proteins have been identified as candidate adhesins, as determined by binding of recombinant proteins to ECM components in vitro <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref> .</s><s>One of these proteins, Tp0751 (pallilysin), has been localized to the T. pallidum surface <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45</ref> and has been found to bind the host ECM components laminin <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42</ref> , fibrinogen <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46</ref> , fibronectin (Fn) <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47</ref> , and collagen <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47</ref> , which are important constituents of blood and endothelia.</s><s>It has been predicted that Tp0751 promotes dissemination by attaching to host ECM components and by facilitating T. pallidum localization to cell junctions <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> .</s><s>The Tp0751 crystal structure revealed that interactions of Tp0751 with ECM components are facilitated by its unique lipocalin domain <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49</ref> .</s><s>A lipocalin domain that shares similar unique attributes to Tp0751 has been identified in the Neisseria meningitidis adhesin fHbp, which is a key component of the Meningococcal B vaccines <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50</ref> .</s><s>Similar to the fHbp protein, Tp0751 represents a promising vaccine candidate, as vaccination with Tp0751 inhibits dissemination of T. pallidum within the rabbit host <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">51</ref> .</s></p><p><s>Due to the propensity for Tp0751 to bind to host cell components found in blood and the vasculature and the ability of Tp0751 immunization to inhibit treponemal dissemination, in the present study we investigated whether Tp0751 can mediate vascular adhesion under the force conditions found in the vasculature.</s><s>We heterologously expressed Tp0751 on the surface of a non-infectious adhesion-attenuated strain of B. burgdorferi, which was previously used as a gain-of-function model system to identify BBK32 as a vascular adhesin <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49</ref> .</s><s>We then evaluated whether B. burgdorferi expressing Tp0751 could interact with human endothelia under both static and physiological shear stress conditions, characterized the biophysical properties of these interactions (strength and stability), and determined if Tp0751 could function as a vascular adhesin in the PCVs of live mice.</s><s>The methods we have used to characterize the role of Tp0751 in vascular adhesion provide a powerful new repertoire of approaches for studying T. pallidum pathogenesis, and will permit identification of other vascular adhesins and the underlying mechanisms of dissemination in this important, under-studied human pathogen.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Adhesion of Tp0751-expressing B. burgdorferi to human endothelia under static conditions.</s><s>It has been hypothesized that Tp0751 contributes to vascular dissemination of T. pallidum due to the capacity of this adhesin to attach to ECM components located in close proximity to the vasculature <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[46]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[47]</ref> .</s><s>To test this hypothesis, we cloned the full length Tp0751 gene fused to a C-terminal 3XFLAG tag into a non-infectious BBK32deficient adhesion-attenuated green fluorescent protein (GFP)-expressing strain of B. burgdorferi, resulting in Tp0751 localization to the bacterial surface (strain Bb-Tp0751) <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49</ref> .</s><s>Since virulent T. pallidum readily attaches to primary human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVEC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52</ref> , we then measured the ability of Bb-Tp0751 to adhere to monolayers of HUVEC in 12-hour co-incubations in the absence of fluid shear stress (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>Under these static conditions, bacteria expressing Tp0751 adhered to endothelia significantly more efficiently than the adhesion-attenuated parent strain (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>; "control").</s><s>Tp0751-dependent endothelial adhesion was inhibited by pre-incubation of bacteria with plasma fibronectin (pFn; the main source of fibronectin in blood) before addition to endothelia, but not by pre-incubation of endothelia with pFn before addition of bacteria (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>).</s><s>This result suggests that either Fn already present on endothelia was sufficient to mediate interactions, or that interactions may be occurring directly with endothelial surfaces.</s><s>Tp0751 might therefore mediate attachment to endothelia in a specific fashion that may be partially dependent upon the presence of pFn.</s></p><p><s>Interaction of Tp0751-expressing B. burgdorferi with human endothelia under postcapillary venule shear stress conditions.</s><s>In the circulatory system, fluid shear stress created by blood flow over vessel walls has a profound impact on the interactions of circulating cells with vascular surfaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53</ref> .</s><s>We therefore investigated whether Tp0751 could support B. burgdorferi interactions with HUVEC monolayers in flow chambers at the typical shear stress encountered in PCVs (1 dyn/cm 2 ), which is the site of most B. burgdorferi-vascular interactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54</ref> .</s><s>Interactions were measured by manually counting numbers of bacteria that paused on endothelial  <ref type="table">S1</ref>).</s><s>Positive control strains: Parent expressing B. burgdorferi vascular adhesin BBK32 (Bb-BBK32); BBK32-expressing B31-derived infectious strain (Infectious; GCB726: Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>).</s><s>surfaces but moved faster than 100 µm/s (tethered; tethered interactions), and numbers of bacteria which paused and moved more slowly than 100 µm/s (dragged; untethered interactions) along endothelial surfaces (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54</ref> .</s><s>Interactions were counted for the negative control parent and Bb-Tp0751, as well as parent-derived bacteria expressing C-terminally FLAG-tagged BBK32 (positive control: Bb-BBK32).</s><s>We have previously shown that gain of function expression of untagged BBK32 in this parent strain restores PCV interactions to the level observed for infectious B. burgdorferi <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55</ref> .</s><s>It was therefore not surprising that expression of FLAG-tagged BBK32 restored total interaction numbers to the same level observed for infectious bacteria (p &gt; 0.05; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>).</s><s>The FLAG tag itself did not promote bacterial-endothelial interactions, as addition of the FLAG tag did not affect endothelial interaction numbers or velocities at 1 dyn/cm 2 for a parent strain expressing RevB (p &gt; 0.05; Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1</ref>), a B. burgdorferi adhesin which does not restore vascular interactions to the adhesion-attenuated parent <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55</ref> .</s><s>Collectively, interaction numbers were similar for Bb-Tp0751 and Bb-BBK32 (p &gt; 0.05; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>), and were greater than for the parent strain (p &lt; 0.05; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>), suggesting that Tp0751 acts as an endothelial adhesin under physiological shear stress.</s></p><p><s>Tp0751 stabilizes and slows B. burgdorferi-endothelial interactions under shear stress.</s><s>Recently, we developed particle-tracking methods for measuring physical properties of B. burgdorferi-endothelial interactions under flow, including interaction dissociation rates, velocities, and adhesion complex bond strengths <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s><s>These methods permit us to determine if specific adhesins stabilize and strengthen interactions by slowing bond dissociation (stabilization) and/or increasing the force that load-bearing adhesion complexes can sustain (strengthening).</s><s>Using these approaches, we recently reported that BBK32-dependent adhesion complexes have catch bond properties-i.e.</s><s>become longer-lived with increasing force, and that force-dependent catch bond strengthening begins between 0.5 and 1 dyn/cm 2 , and that BBK32-mediated catch bonds are dependent on pFn <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30</ref> .</s><s>To determine if Tp0751 stabilizes and strengthens endothelial interactions under physiological shear stress, we performed flow chamber experiments at 0.5 and 1 dyn/cm 2 , and measured load-bearing bond dissociation rates, velocities and bond forces for interactions captured by particle-tracking (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>).</s><s>Sample time lapse projections of trajectories obtained by particle tracking are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2a</ref>.</s></p><p><s>We first determined bond dissociation rates of B. burgdorferi-endothelial interactions for all tracks obtained from 0.5-1 dyn/cm 2 , estimated from the negative slopes of log-transformed frequency distributions of the lifetimes of individual interactions (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2b,c</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56</ref> .</s><s>These distributions were linear for all strains (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2b</ref>), indicating that each bacterial-endothelial interaction exhibited single molecule dissociation kinetics-i.e. was formed by a single load-bearing adhesion complex-or was possibly formed by multiple adhesion complexes which dissociated in a synchronous concerted fashion <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56</ref> .</s><s>The dissociation rates for Bb-BBK32 and Bb-Tp0751 interactions were slower than dissociation rates for the adhesion-attenuated parent (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2c</ref>), indicating that both BBK32 and Tp0751 stabilized interactions.</s><s>Analysis of strain velocities demonstrated that Bb-BBK32 and Bb-Tp0751 also moved more slowly over endothelial surfaces than the parent strain (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2d</ref>), indicating that expression of these adhesins slowed interactions.</s><s>Bb-Tp0751 dissociated more slowly but moved faster than Bb-BBK32, implying that Tp0751 and BBK32 likely stabilized bacterial-endothelial interactions by different mechanisms.</s><s>We can conclude from these studies that Tp0751 stabilized and slowed B. burgdorferi-endothelial interactions under physiological shear stress conditions, but by different mechanisms than BBK32.</s></p><p><s>Tp0751-dependent stabilization of tethered and untethered endothelial interactions under shear stress.</s><s>The first steps of B. burgdorferi interactions with PCVs are tethering, where bacteria pause briefly on endothelial surfaces but travel at &gt;100 µm/s (tethered interactions), and dragging, which occurs when bacteria move at &lt;100 µm/s over endothelial surfaces (untethered interactions) <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54</ref> .</s><s>Tethering B. burgdorferi displace further than their cell length under flow, and are anchored to endothelia by tethers analogous to bungee cords which stabilize interactions; dragging interactions are untethered, and bacteria displace less than their cell length during each adhesion event <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s><s>Tethering and dragging interactions are mechanistically distinct <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55</ref> .</s><s>Since tethering exerts a strong stabilizing force on interactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30</ref> , understanding how individual adhesins stabilize interactions also requires examination of adhesin's effects on untethered interactions, where interpretation of an adhesin's interaction-stabilizing properties is not confounded by the effects of tethering.</s><s>BBK32 stabilizes both tethering and dragging interactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55</ref> .</s><s>Therefore, we investigated whether Tp0751 also contributed to both of these interaction types (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Bb-BBK32 spent a smaller proportion of the total interaction time tethering compared to the parent strain (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3a</ref>), although the lengths of tethers supporting parent and Bb-BBK32 interactions were similar (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3b</ref>).</s><s>This result implied that the Bb-BBK32 strain was likely less reliant on tethering for stabilization of interactions than the parent strain.</s><s>By contrast, parent and Bb-Tp0751 strains spent a similar proportion of the total interaction time tethering (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3a</ref>), and tether lengths were longer for Bb-Tp0751 than for both the parent strain and Bb-BBK32 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3b</ref>).</s><s>This result suggested that Bb-Tp0751 was as reliant on tethering for interaction stabilization as the parent strain, but that the tethers associated with Tp0751 adhesion complexes were possibly longer-lived compared to the parent strain and Bb-BBK32.</s></p><p><s>To test these hypotheses, we examined adhesion complex dissociation rates for untethered (dragging) and tethered interactions in Bb-Tp0751 and Bb-BBK32 strains (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3c,d</ref>).</s><s>Untethered Bb-BBK32 interactions dissociated more slowly than untethered parental interactions (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3c</ref>), demonstrating that BBK32 expression increased the stability (lifetime) of untethered interactions.</s><s>However, untethered Bb-Tp0751 and parental strain interactions dissociated at similar rates, which were comparable to the non-specific dissociation rates of negative control beads (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3c</ref>).</s><s>Thus, BBK32 stabilized untethered interactions, but Tp0751 did not.</s><s>In contrast, although both BBK32 and Tp0751 expression increased the stability of tethered interactions compared to the parental strain, tethered Bb-Tp0751 interactions dissociated more slowly than tethered Bb-BBK32 interactions (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3d</ref>).</s><s>Thus, Tp0751 promoted endothelial interactions at physiological shear stress specifically by stabilizing tethering.</s></p><p><s>Finally, we examined how Tp0751 expression affected the velocities of untethered and tethered interactions (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3e,f</ref>).</s><s>As expected, based on the rapid dissociation rates of untethered Tp0751-dependent interactions (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3c</ref>), Bb-Tp0751 bacteria moved as rapidly as the parent strain over endothelial surfaces, whereas Bb-BBK32 bacteria moved more slowly than the parent strain (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3e</ref>).</s><s>The velocities of tethered Bb-Tp0751 and Bb-BBK32 interactions were slower than the velocity of tethered parental interactions but were similar to each other (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3f</ref>).</s><s>This result implied that tethers extended at a similar speed in both strains, suggesting that tethers were likely longer in Tp0751-expressing bacteria (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3b</ref>) because they were longer-lived and thus extended further (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3d</ref>).</s><s>Collectively, these results showed that Tp0751 promoted bacterial association with endothelia under physiological shear stress specifically by stabilizing tethered but not untethered interactions.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tp0751 strengthens B. burgdorferi-endothelial interactions under shear stress.</head><p><s>We recently found that under physiological shear stress conditions, BBK32 expression increases the strength of B. burgdorferi-endothelial interactions, which can be determined by estimating the force imposed on load-bearing adhesion complexes (bond force) during interactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s><s>We also found that BBK32-dependent interactions become longer-lived as bond force increases and thus exhibit catch bond properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s><s>BBK32-dependent catch bond properties are most evident for untethered B. burgdorferi interactions, where the force sustained by load-bearing bonds is typically greater than for tethered interactions, and is greater than the force threshold at which BBK32-dependent catch bond properties are activated (0.2 pN) <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s></p><p><s>To determine if Tp0751 strengthened B. burgdorferi-endothelial interactions under shear stress, we estimated the forces sustained by load-bearing adhesion complexes during interactions (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4</ref>).</s><s>Tp0751 expression increased the force sustained by these complexes compared to the parent strain for all interactions (untethered  <ref type="figure">-d</ref>), bond dissociation rates and interaction velocities were calculated from interactions obtained at both 0.5 and 1 dyn/cm 2 .</s><s>N = 4 and N = 8 independent flow chamber experiments for each strain at 0.5 and 1 dyn/ cm 2 , respectively.</s><s>Eight replicate experiments were conducted at 1 dyn/cm 2 to obtain sufficient interaction numbers for tracking.</s><s>Strains: Negative control strain: BBK32-deficient non-infectious adhesion-attenuated B31-A-derived strain (Parent; GCB706: Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>).</s><s>Positive control strains: Parent expressing B. burgdorferi vascular adhesin BBK32 (Bb-BBK32); BBK32-expressing B31-derived infectious strain (Infectious; GCB726: Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>).</s><s>and tethered combined) (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4a</ref>), as well as untethered (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4b</ref>) and tethered (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4c</ref>) interactions.</s><s>Average Bb-Tp0751 and Bb-BBK32 bond forces for all interactions were similar (p &gt; 0.05; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4a</ref>), as were bond forces for  <ref type="figure">c,d</ref>).</s><s>Interaction properties were calculated from interactions obtained at both 0.5 and 1 dyn/cm 2 .</s><s>N = 4 and N = 8 independent flow chamber experiments for each strain at 0.5 and 1 dyn/cm 2 , respectively.</s><s>Strains: Negative control strain: BBK32deficient non-infectious adhesion-attenuated B31-A-derived strain (Parent; GCB706: Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>).</s><s>Positive control strains: Parent expressing B. burgdorferi vascular adhesin BBK32 (Bb-BBK32); BBK32expressing B31-derived infectious strain (Infectious; GCB726: Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>).</s><s>For untethered interactions, interactions were grouped by F b into a smaller number of bins than for all interactions combined (e), to provide sufficient interaction numbers in each bin for accurate calculation of bond dissociation rates at each bond force (f).</s><s>For the parent strain and Bb-Tp0751, fewer than 25 interactions were obtained in all but the lowest force bin.</s><s>For these strains, the data from the higher force bins were therefore pooled with values from the lowest force bin to obtain sufficient interaction numbers for dissociation rate calculations.</s><s>This resulted in a single data point reflecting the values obtained for all untethered interactions for parent and Bb-Tp0751 strains.</s><s>(f) Effect of increasing bond force on mean ± SEM bond dissociation rates.</s><s>Dotted line indicates the dissociation rate for negative control beads.</s><s>Strains: Negative control strain: BBK32deficient non-infectious adhesion-attenuated B31-A-derived strain (Parent; GCB706: Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>).</s><s>Positive control strains: Parent expressing B. burgdorferi vascular adhesin BBK32 (Bb-BBK32); BBK32-expressing B31-derived infectious strain (Infectious; GCB726: Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>).</s><s>Bb-Tp0751: Parent expressing Tp0751.</s><s>Numbers of interactions analyzed/strain: ≥288 (a,d); ≥39 (b,e,f); ≥249 (c).</s><s>Statistics: one-way Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA with Dunn's post-tests.</s><s>*Indicates p &lt; 0.05 vs parent.</s><s>+ Indicates p &lt; 0.05 vs BBK32.</s><s>tethered interactions (p &gt; 0.05; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4c</ref>).</s><s>However, although untethered Bb-Tp0751 interactions sustained greater force than the parent, they were substantially weaker than untethered Bb-BBK32 interactions (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4b</ref>).</s><s>Since untethered Bb-Tp0751 interactions were as unstable as untethered parent strain interactions and negative control beads (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3c</ref>), these data implied that Tp0751 expression primarily strengthened tethered interactions.</s></p><p><s>To estimate the range of forces sustained by Tp0751-dependent adhesion complexes, we binned interactions by bond force, and examined the proportion of total interactions for each strain within each force bin (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4d,e</ref>).</s><s>For all interaction types combined (untethered and tethered), the proportion of total parent strain interactions declined rapidly at bond forces &gt;0.1 pN.</s><s>In contrast, the percentage of total Bb-Tp0751 and Bb-BBK32 interactions remained stable from &gt;0.1 pN up to ~4 and ~8 pN for Tp0751-and BBK32-expressing bacteria, respectively (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4d</ref>).</s><s>Therefore, expression of Tp0751 and BBK32 increased the upper range of force which could be sustained by load-bearing adhesion complexes by ~40-fold and ~80-fold, respectively.</s></p><p><s>Untethered BBK32-dependent interactions exhibit catch bond properties above 0.2 pN; in other words, they become longer-lived as bond force increases <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s><s>To determine if Tp0751 expression conferred catch bond properties, we examined the proportion of total interactions that were untethered as bond force increased, as well as bond dissociation rates (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4e,f</ref>).</s><s>To obtain sufficient interaction numbers for accurate calculation of dissociation rates, bins containing fewer than 25 interactions were pooled with lower force bins.</s><s>For the parent strain and Bb-Tp0751, all untethered interactions were pooled into a single bin because so few untethered interactions occurred at forces &gt;0.05 pN.</s><s>The maximum average bond forces that untethered interactions of the parent, Bb-Tp0751 and Bb-BBK32 strains could sustain were approximately 0.05, 0.35 and 15 pN, respectively (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4e</ref>).</s><s>Therefore, the force range that untethered Tp0751-dependent interactions could sustain was ~7 times greater than the force range for the parent strain, but ~43 times smaller than the force range for the BBK32 strain.</s><s>Bond dissociation rates for untethered Bb-BBK32 interactions slowed as the force increased above ~0.08 pN, which is consistent with BBK32 conferring catch bond properties to these interactions (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4f</ref>).</s><s>However, untethered Bb-Tp0751 interactions did not become longer-lived as bond force increased (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">4f</ref>), indicating that Tp0751 expression did not strengthen interactions by a catch bond mechanism.</s><s>Collectively, these results indicated that Tp0751 significantly strengthened B. burgdorferi-endothelial interactions, but over a shorter force range than the B. burgdorferi catch bond adhesin BBK32.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tp0751 promotes interactions with postcapillary venules in vivo. Finally, to determine whether</head><p><s>Tp0751-dependent adhesion complexes were sufficiently strong to permit vascular adhesion in vivo, we performed intravital microscopy in dermal PCVs of live mice intravenously inoculated with Tp0751-expressing and control B. burgdorferi strains (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>), as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55</ref> .</s><s>Since parent and gain-of-function strains can be cleared more quickly from the circulation than infectious bacteria <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55</ref> , microscopy was performed only for the first 20 min after inoculation to reduce differences among experimental groups due to clearance.</s><s>As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5a</ref>, Tp0751 expression restored vascular interactions to the adhesion-attenuated parent as effectively as BBK32 expression, and both Bb-Tp0751 and Bb-BBK32 interacted with PCVs as efficiently as the infectious control strain (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5a</ref>).</s><s>To ensure that Tp0751's ability to promote interactions was not due to protection of bacteria from clearance compared to the parent strain, we measured copy number of B. burgdorferi flaB DNA in blood collected from mice immediately after intravital microscopy (IVM) (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5b</ref>), and normalized interaction numbers to bacterial copy number (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5c</ref>).</s><s>B. burgdorferi copy number in blood was not greater in any strain compared to the adhesion-attenuated parent strain on the time scale of these experiments (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5b</ref>).</s><s>Copy number-adjusted interaction numbers for all strains were ~6-, 8-and 10-fold greater than parent strain numbers for Bb-Tp0751, Bb-BBK32 and infectious bacteria, respectively (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5c</ref>).</s><s>These results demonstrated that Tp0751 can function as a vascular adhesin in vivo.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Like many other invasive pathogens, systemic dissemination via the bloodstream is critical to T. pallidum pathogenesis.</s><s>The highly invasive nature of T. pallidum is shown by the widespread rash characteristic of secondary syphilis, the ability of the bacterium to cross the placental and blood-brain barriers, and the symptomatic involvement of multiple organs and tissues during the course of infection <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57</ref> .</s><s>A critical step in bacterial dissemination via the bloodstream is attachment to the endothelial lining of blood vessels and associated ECM components.</s><s>Therefore, identifying host-interacting vascular adhesins of T. pallidum is crucial for advancing our understanding of the pathogenic mechanisms of this organism.</s><s>The fact that T. pallidum is an obligate human pathogen that cannot be cultured continuously in vitro <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> has hindered progress on understanding the molecular interactions involved in the host vasculature-pathogen interface for this organism.</s><s>Thus, heterologous expression in a related spirochete represents an attractive approach for studying the contributions of T. pallidum adhesins to these interactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> .</s></p><p><s>A gain-of-function approach such as heterologous expression is a powerful genetic tool that has been successfully used to identify and analyze adhesion-associated phenotypes conferred by pathogenic spirochetes <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">[58]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">[59]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[60]</ref> .</s><s>This approach overcomes a major limitation associated with loss-of-function methodologies, where the redundancy of multiple adhesins can mask the binding defect of a single adhesin-deficient mutant.</s><s>By combining a heterologous gain-of-function approach with flow-chamber, tracking and biophysical analysis methods, which we have recently developed for studying B. burgdorferi-endothelial interaction mechanisms, it is now feasible to identify and mechanistically characterize the vascular adhesins supporting T. pallidum dissemination.</s><s>The ability to study this process in flow chambers, which reproduce the interaction phenotypes observed in the complex environment of PCVs in live mice (Figs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">1 and 5</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> , also means that interaction mechanisms can be systematically dissected by addition, removal and blocking of host components targeted by bacteria expressing known and predicted vascular adhesins.</s><s>The ability to study bacterial-endothelial interactions in live mice using intravital microscopy also provides a powerful method for testing and validating hypotheses generated in flow chamber studies.</s><s>Together, these methods have the potential to rapidly advance our understanding of the mechanisms of T. pallidum dissemination.</s></p><p><s>The results of this study indicate that, like the B. burgdorferi adhesin BBK32 <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">59,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">61</ref> , Tp0751 can function as a vascular adhesin under static and flow chamber conditions and in PCVs in mice, although the mechanisms of BBK32-and Tp0751-dependent interactions differ (Figs 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5).</s><s>Tp0751 and BBK32 are multi-functional adhesins that bind to several host ECM components including Fn <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">61</ref> .</s><s>Fn plays an important role in B. burgdorferi tethering and dragging on vascular surfaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31</ref> , with tethering interactions being facilitated by BBK32 Fn-binding sequences <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55</ref> .</s><s>Our results suggest that Fn may also be important for Tp0751-dependent endothelial interactions (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Pre-incubation of Tp0751-expressing bacteria (but not endothelia) with pFn inhibited adhesion under static conditions (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>Therefore, it is possible that differences in Tp0751-and BBK32-dependent interaction properties under shear stress arise because Tp0751 may target insoluble Fn deposited on endothelial surfaces, whereas BBK32-dependent interactions occur via another mechanism.</s><s>BBK32 binds to Fn by a tandem β-zipper mechanism involving extensive regions of both proteins <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">62,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b62">63</ref> and induces Fn polymerization <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">64</ref> .</s><s>By contrast, our recent structural studies reveal that Tp0751 interacts with Fn via positively charged residues on only one face of the protein's lipocalin fold <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49</ref> .</s><s>Thus, even if Fn is a common component of Tp0751-and BBK32-dependent endothelial interaction mechanisms, it is likely that the affinity of these proteins for Fn and the conformation and physical properties of Fn in adhesion complexes is distinct.</s><s>Such differences in Fn conformation and/or the mechanisms by which Fn is anchored to surfaces and endothelia might account for the smaller range of force that can be sustained by untethered Tp0751 adhesion complexes (Figs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">3 and 4</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Structural and peptide mapping studies also reveal that although Tp0751 forms multiple charge-based contacts with Fn and other ECM proteins, Tp0751 adhesion to endothelia may involve distinct residues on the same surface of the lipocalin fold as the ECM-coordinating residues <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49</ref> .</s><s>These observations predict that the initial tethering association of Tp0751-expressing bacteria with endothelial surfaces may be mediated by charge-based interactions with ECM components such as Fn, but that subsequent dragging adhesion to endothelial cells likely involves a distinct adhesion target.</s><s>Since untethered dragging interactions were less stable, less abundant and weaker for Tp0751-expressing bacteria than for BBK32-expressing counterparts (Figs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">3 and 4</ref>), the endothelial targets for dragging interactions may differ for bacteria expressing these adhesins.</s><s>Binding of ECM components such as Fn to the Tp0751 lipocalin fold may also mask endothelial adhesion sites mediating dragging, suggesting that Tp0751 conformational change or detachment from the ECM could be required to expose endothelial interaction sites, and/or that dragging interactions might be dependent on a second T. pallidum adhesin which is not present in B. burgdorferi.</s></p><p><s>Despite the work that is still required to fully understand the mechanism of Tp0751-dependent endothelial interactions under physiological shear stress, it is nevertheless clear that Tp0751 can function as a vascular adhesin in flow chambers and in dermal PCVs of mice, where shear stress typically ranges from 0.75-1 dyn/cm <ref type="bibr">2 54</ref> .</s><s>Our results predict that Tp0751 may be sufficient for bacterial-endothelial interactions in vascular beds of tissues such as the skin where PCV shear stress is typically quite low, but that additional, stronger adhesion mechanisms are likely required for vascular interactions in organs like the brain, where shear stress is typically considerably higher than in the skin.</s><s>Thus, it is likely that T. pallidum encodes additional adhesins that collectively permit pathogen interactions with the vasculature of other dissemination sites in the body.</s></p><p><s>The model systems and biophysical analysis methodologies described herein have successfully identified Tp0751 as a T. pallidum vascular adhesin.</s><s>Development of these experimental tools represents a powerful advance that will enable the identification of additional spirochete vascular adhesins and will increase understanding of the molecular mechanisms facilitating vascular attachment of spirochete pathogens, particularly for intractable pathogens such as T. pallidum.</s><s>Mice, endothelial cells, B. burgdorferi.</s><s>Four to five-week-old male C57BL/6 mice (Charles River Laboratories, Montréal, Canada) were housed at 4 mice/cage, with environmental enrichment and ad libitum access to standard chow and water.</s><s>As described <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> , experiments were conducted with primary human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVEC) (Lonza, Allendale, NJ, USA) at passage 2-6.</s><s>All bacterial strains are listed in the Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>.</s><s>GFP-expressing B. burgdorferi strains were cultivated in selective medium supplemented with 100 μg/ml gentamicin and/or 200 μg/ml kanamycin (Bioshop Canada, Burlington, Canada) as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54</ref> .</s><s>All experiments were performed with at least 3 independent cultures/strain.</s><s>For intravital microscopy experiments, 1% C57BL/6 mouse blood obtained by cardiac puncture was added to cultures 48 hours before imaging <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54</ref> .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials and Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethics</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Static adhesion assays.</head><p><s>As described <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">65</ref> , HUVEC were grown to confluence in 4-well chamber slides (Nalgene Nunc International, Rochester, NY, USA) coated with 500 μg/mL phenol red-free matrigel (Corning, Tewksbury, MA, USA).</s><s>GFP-expressing B. burgdorferi (1.4 × 10 7 ) were resuspended in a 3:1 mixture of BSK-II:EGM-2 and added to duplicate wells containing HUVEC.</s><s>For competitive inhibition experiments, bacteria or HUVEC were pre-incubated with 8 μg of plasma fibronectin (pFn) (Sigma, Oakville, Canada) for 1 hour.</s><s>Chamber slides were incubated for 12 h, washed with HEPES-buffered saline, and fixed in buffered 10% formalin (Fisher Scientific, Ottawa, Canada).</s><s>B. burgdorferi adhered to HUVEC were counted in 10 fields of view/biological replicate using a Nikon 80i fluorescence microscope (Meridian Instrument Company, Kent, WA, USA).</s></p><p><s>Flow chamber assays.</s><s>Flow chamber assays were performed as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s><s>Briefly, HUVEC were cultivated to 2 days post-confluence in Ibidi µ-Slide VI 0.4 flow chambers (Ibidi GmbH, Planegg, Germany), endothelia were labeled with CellMask Deep Red plasma membrane dye (Life Technologies, Burlington, Canada), and washed B. burgdorferi diluted to 1 × 10 8 cells/ml in 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum (FBS: Sigma) and Hank's Balanced Salt Solution (HBSS: Life Technologies) were perfused through flow chambers mounted in a stage-top live cell imaging incubator (Live Cell Instrument, Seoul, Korea) at 0.5 and 1 dyn/cm 2 (0.284 and 0.568 ml/min, respectively).</s><s>As reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> , live cell imaging was performed at 14-15 frames/second (fps) using a custom-built spinning disk confocal microscope (Quorum Technologies, Guelph, Canada) equipped with a Zeiss 25×/0.8</s><s>NA LCI Plan-Apochromat water immersion lens (Carl Zeiss Canada Ltd., Toronto, Canada) and Volocity software v.6.3.0 (Improvision/Perkin-Elmer, Waltham, MA, USA).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Intravital microscopy (IVM).</head><p><s>IVM was performed in dorsal flank skin as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55</ref> , with the following exceptions.</s><s>Eight hundred µl of bacterial suspension (at 2 × 10 9 /ml in PBS) were mixed with 200 µl of 0.1% 2 MDa Texas Red Dextran (Life Technologies) and stored on ice.</s><s>After warming to room temperature, 250 µl of this mixture were injected via tail vein in mice anesthetized with 10 mg/kg xylazine (MTC Pharmaceuticals, Cambridge, Canada) and 200 mg/kg ketamine hydrochloride (Rogar/STB, Montréal, Canada).</s><s>Interactions were visualized in dermal postcapillary venules (PCVs) for 5-20 min after injection, using a custom-built high speed multi-wavelength resonant scanner Leica TCS SP8 confocal microscope (Leica, Mannheim, Germany) equipped with argon and DPSS 633 lasers operated at 100% power, a tandem scanner, HCX IRAPO L 25×/0.95 water objective, TD 488/561/633 excitation beam splitters and spectral HyD detectors in photon integration mode (100 gain, 0 offset).</s><s>Scanning was performed bidirectionally in resonant mode at 8000 Hz over a 1024 × 155 pixel area, at 0.227 µm/pixel and 30 fps with line averaging of 3. Pinhole size was 10.74 AU.</s><s>Emission wavelengths for green and red channels were 496-550 and 572-795 nm, respectively, and acquisition in red and green channels was simultaneous.</s><s>Time courses (2 min/PCV) were acquired using Leica Application Suite (LAS) software, and were analyzed post-acquisition after import into Volocity software.</s></p><p><s>After completion of imaging, blood was collected by cardiac puncture, and qPCR measurement of copies of B. burgdorferi flaB DNA/µl blood was performed as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55</ref> .</s><s>Mice were euthanized after cardiac puncture by cervical dislocation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis of live cell imaging experiments.</head><p><s>As described <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">54</ref> , B. burgdorferi-endothelial interactions were manually counted in 100 µm-long straight unbranched regions of PCVs (10-40 µm diameter) and a 30 × 100 µm region of interest (ROI) positioned at the center of flow chamber videos.</s><s>Interactions were counted as dragging if bacteria took &gt;1 s to pass through this ROI, and were counted as tethering if bacteria passed through the ROI in &lt;1 s but paused as they travelled.</s></p><p><s>Semi-automated centroid-based tracking of flow chamber videos was performed using a Volocity, custom tracking algorithm as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s><s>Interactions where bacterial area and velocity were &gt;50 µm 2 and 300 µm/s, respectively, were excluded from analyses.</s><s>For all analyses except interaction dissociation rates, each interaction was treated as an independent replicate for statistical analysis, since variation in the properties of individual interactions was greater than variation among individual biological replicates <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s></p><p><s>Interaction dissociation (K off ) rates were estimated from the negative slopes of linear regressions of log-transformed frequency distributions of the duration of individual interactions in populations <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56</ref> .</s><s>Curve fitting was performed by non-linear regression using the least squares method in GraphPad Prism v.6.02</s><s>(GraphPad, La Jolla, CA, USA), with runs post tests.</s><s>Statistical comparison of the slopes of linear regressions was performed by extra-sum-of-squares F-tests.</s><s>Dissociation rates for non-specific interactions (beads) are provided in dissociation rate graphs, as calculated previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s></p><p><s>As described <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> , tracked interactions were classified as tethered or untethered based on (a) the ratio of cumulative displacement to bacterial length measured at each time point of each interaction and (b) tethering duration, i.e. the percentage of the total duration of each interaction for which ratios of cumulative displacement to bacterial length at each time point were &gt;1.</s><s>Untethered interactions (dragging) were those where cumulative displacement was less than bacterial length (ratio &lt;1), and 0% of the total interaction duration was spent tethered.</s><s>Tethered interactions (tethering) were those where cumulative displacement was greater than bacterial length (ratio &gt;1), and &gt;0% of the total interaction time was spent tethered.</s><s>Tether length was calculated by dividing the average velocity of each interaction by the dissociation rate calculated for the population.</s><s>This method corrects for the effect of acquisition frame rate on tether length measurement <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s></p><p><s>As described <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> , the average force sustained by individual load-bearing adhesion bonds during each interaction (F b ) was calculated by averaging instantaneous F b values obtained at each time point within each interaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s><s>The formula used to estimate instantaneous F b was F b = F s /cosθ, where θ is the bond angle, F s is the force due to flow (31.97τ w r 2 ), τ w is wall shear stress and r is bacterial projection above the endothelial surface.</s><s>r was calculated from average cell volume values calculated for each bacterial strain as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s><s>This volume differed among strains because of strain-specific differences in average cell length.</s><s>For experiments reported in this study, average cell volumes for each strain were calculated from average cell lengths for each strain, which were measured under static, no-flow conditions as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s><s>Average cell lengths for GCB706, GCB726, TMB103 and TMB49 were16.</s><s>34, 16.59, 18.09 and 17.99 µm, respectively).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical analysis.</head><p><s>All statistical analysis was performed in GraphPad Prism.</s><s>Statistical tests used for all comparisons are described in figure legends and Materials and Methods.</s><s>Detailed description and justification for statistical methods used to analyze all reported biophysical values (K off , F b , velocity, tether length, % duration tethered) are provided in Ebady et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> .</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Interaction of Tp0751-expressing strains with human endothelia under static and shear stress conditions.</s><s>(a) Mean ± SEM numbers of parent and Tp0751-expressing B. burgdorferi (Bb-Tp0751) adhered to primary human umbilical vein endothelial cell (HUVEC) monolayers after 12 h of co-incubation under static (0 dyn/cm 2 ) conditions (HUVECs + Bb, control).</s><s>HUVECs+ (Bb + pFn): binding of bacteria pre-incubated with plasma fibronectin (pFn) to HUVECs.</s><s>(HUVECs + pFn) + Bb: binding of bacteria to HUVEC preincubated with pFn.</s><s>N = 3 independent bacterial and endothelial cultures/strain analyzed in 2 experiments.</s><s>(b) Mean ± SEM bacterial interactions per minute with HUVEC under typical postcapillary venule shear stress condition (1 dyn/cm 2 ).</s><s>Videos of representative flow chamber experiments are presented in Supplementary Videos S1-S3.</s><s>Numbers of bacteria that paused and moved more slowly over endothelia under flow were manually counted in time-lapses acquired at 15 frames per second (fps).</s><s>Strains: Negative control strain: BBK32-deficient non-infectious adhesion-attenuated B31-A-derived strain (Parent; GCB706: Supplementary TableS1).</s><s>Positive control strains: Parent expressing B. burgdorferi vascular adhesin BBK32 (Bb-BBK32); BBK32-expressing B31-derived infectious strain (Infectious; GCB726: Supplementary TableS1).Bb-Tp0751: Parent expressing Tp0751.</s><s>N = 8 independent cultures per strain analyzed in 3 experiments.</s><s>Statistics: one-way Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA with Dunn's post-test (a), one-way ANOVA with Holm-Sidak post-test (b).</s><s>*Indicates p &lt; 0.05 vs. parent within incubation condition (a) and vs. parent (b).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,155.64,46.50,201.60,263.16" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Interaction of Tp0751-expressing strains with human endothelia under static and shear stress conditions.</s><s>(a) Mean ± SEM numbers of parent and Tp0751-expressing B. burgdorferi (Bb-Tp0751) adhered to primary human umbilical vein endothelial cell (HUVEC) monolayers after 12 h of co-incubation under static (0 dyn/cm 2 ) conditions (HUVECs + Bb, control).</s><s>HUVECs+ (Bb + pFn): binding of bacteria pre-incubated with plasma fibronectin (pFn) to HUVECs.</s><s>(HUVECs + pFn) + Bb: binding of bacteria to HUVEC preincubated with pFn.</s><s>N = 3 independent bacterial and endothelial cultures/strain analyzed in 2 experiments.</s><s>(b) Mean ± SEM bacterial interactions per minute with HUVEC under typical postcapillary venule shear stress condition (1 dyn/cm 2 ).</s><s>Videos of representative flow chamber experiments are presented in Supplementary Videos S1-S3.</s><s>Numbers of bacteria that paused and moved more slowly over endothelia under flow were manually counted in time-lapses acquired at 15 frames per second (fps).</s><s>Strains: Negative control strain: BBK32-deficient non-infectious adhesion-attenuated B31-A-derived strain (Parent; GCB706: Supplementary TableS1).</s><s>Positive control strains: Parent expressing B. burgdorferi vascular adhesin BBK32 (Bb-BBK32); BBK32-expressing B31-derived infectious strain (Infectious; GCB726: Supplementary TableS1).Bb-Tp0751: Parent expressing Tp0751.</s><s>N = 8 independent cultures per strain analyzed in 3 experiments.</s><s>Statistics: one-way Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA with Dunn's post-test (a), one-way ANOVA with Holm-Sidak post-test (b).</s><s>*Indicates p &lt; 0.05 vs. parent within incubation condition (a) and vs. parent (b).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Bond dissociation rates and interaction velocities of Tp0751-expressing B. burgdorferi.</s><s>B. burgdorferi interactions with HUVEC in flow chambers at 0.5 and 1 dyn/cm 2 were captured by particle tracking of interaction trajectories (tracks) in time lapse sequences.</s><s>(a) Sample time lapse projections depicting interaction tracks of individual bacteria (1 color/bacterium) captured at 1 dyn/cm 2 over 2 min.</s><s>Scale bars: 38 µm.</s><s>(b)The linear regression of the log-transformed number of interactions versus the lifetime (seconds) of the spirochete for 4 representative tracks (1 track for each of the 4 strains).</s><s>The negative slope of each regression was an estimate of the dissociation rate (K off ) of the spirochete, as described in the Materials and Methods.</s><s>(c) Mean ± SEM dissociation rates (K off /off-rates) for individual load-bearing adhesion complexes mediating bacterial-endothelial interactions under flow.</s><s>(d) Velocities of interacting bacteria (mean ± 95% CI).</s><s>In (b-d), bond dissociation rates and interaction velocities were calculated from interactions obtained at both 0.5 and 1 dyn/cm 2 .</s><s>N = 4 and N = 8 independent flow chamber experiments for each strain at 0.5 and 1 dyn/ cm 2 , respectively.</s><s>Eight replicate experiments were conducted at 1 dyn/cm 2 to obtain sufficient interaction numbers for tracking.</s><s>Strains: Negative control strain: BBK32-deficient non-infectious adhesion-attenuated B31-A-derived strain (Parent; GCB706: Supplementary TableS1).</s><s>Positive control strains: Parent expressing B. burgdorferi vascular adhesin BBK32 (Bb-BBK32); BBK32-expressing B31-derived infectious strain (Infectious; GCB726: Supplementary TableS1).Bb-Tp0751: Parent expressing Tp0751.</s><s>Numbers of interactions analyzed/ strain: Parent (408), Infectious (647), Bb-BBK32 (578), and Bb-Tp0751 (288).</s><s>R 2 values for linear regressions in (b): &gt;0.9.</s><s>Statistics: one-way ANOVA with Holm-Sidak post-tests (c), one-way Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA with Dunn's post-tests (d).</s><s>*Indicates p &lt; 0.05 vs parent.</s><s>+ Indicates p &lt; 0.05 vs Bb-BBK32.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Bond dissociation rates and interaction velocities of Tp0751-expressing B. burgdorferi.</s><s>B. burgdorferi interactions with HUVEC in flow chambers at 0.5 and 1 dyn/cm 2 were captured by particle tracking of interaction trajectories (tracks) in time lapse sequences.</s><s>(a) Sample time lapse projections depicting interaction tracks of individual bacteria (1 color/bacterium) captured at 1 dyn/cm 2 over 2 min.</s><s>Scale bars: 38 µm.</s><s>(b)The linear regression of the log-transformed number of interactions versus the lifetime (seconds) of the spirochete for 4 representative tracks (1 track for each of the 4 strains).</s><s>The negative slope of each regression was an estimate of the dissociation rate (K off ) of the spirochete, as described in the Materials and Methods.</s><s>(c) Mean ± SEM dissociation rates (K off /off-rates) for individual load-bearing adhesion complexes mediating bacterial-endothelial interactions under flow.</s><s>(d) Velocities of interacting bacteria (mean ± 95% CI).</s><s>In (b-d), bond dissociation rates and interaction velocities were calculated from interactions obtained at both 0.5 and 1 dyn/cm 2 .</s><s>N = 4 and N = 8 independent flow chamber experiments for each strain at 0.5 and 1 dyn/ cm 2 , respectively.</s><s>Eight replicate experiments were conducted at 1 dyn/cm 2 to obtain sufficient interaction numbers for tracking.</s><s>Strains: Negative control strain: BBK32-deficient non-infectious adhesion-attenuated B31-A-derived strain (Parent; GCB706: Supplementary TableS1).</s><s>Positive control strains: Parent expressing B. burgdorferi vascular adhesin BBK32 (Bb-BBK32); BBK32-expressing B31-derived infectious strain (Infectious; GCB726: Supplementary TableS1).Bb-Tp0751: Parent expressing Tp0751.</s><s>Numbers of interactions analyzed/ strain: Parent (408), Infectious (647), Bb-BBK32 (578), and Bb-Tp0751 (288).</s><s>R 2 values for linear regressions in (b): &gt;0.9.</s><s>Statistics: one-way ANOVA with Holm-Sidak post-tests (c), one-way Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA with Dunn's post-tests (d).</s><s>*Indicates p &lt; 0.05 vs parent.</s><s>+ Indicates p &lt; 0.05 vs Bb-BBK32.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,155.64,46.50,396.00,241.92" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3.</s><s>Effect of Tp0751 on tethered and untethered interaction stability and velocity under shear stress.</s><s>B. burgdorferi interacts with endothelia under PCV shear stress conditions by two mechanisms: untethered (dragging) interactions, and tethered interactions.</s><s>Tethered interactions are stabilized by bungee cord-like tethers which anchor bacteria to endothelia, reduce force imposed on load-bearing adhesion complexes and increase adhesion bond stability (lifetime) 29 .</s><s>(a,b) Proportion of total bacterial-endothelial interaction times during which bacterial length extended beyond the normal length, indicative of tether formation stabilizing the interaction ((a) % duration), and the average tether length (b) for all interactions at 0.5-1 dyn/cm 2 .</s><s>(c,d) Interaction complex dissociation rates for untethered (c) and tethered (d) interactions.</s><s>Dotted lines indicate dissociation rates for non-specific interactions (non-adherent beads).</s><s>(e,f) Velocities of untethered (e) and tethered (f) interactions.</s><s>Summary values: mean ± 95% CI (a,b,e,f), mean ± SEM (c,d).</s><s>Interaction properties were calculated from interactions obtained at both 0.5 and 1 dyn/cm 2 .</s><s>N = 4 and N = 8 independent flow chamber experiments for each strain at 0.5 and 1 dyn/cm 2 , respectively.</s><s>Strains: Negative control strain: BBK32deficient non-infectious adhesion-attenuated B31-A-derived strain (Parent; GCB706: Supplementary TableS1).</s><s>Positive control strains: Parent expressing B. burgdorferi vascular adhesin BBK32 (Bb-BBK32); BBK32expressing B31-derived infectious strain (Infectious; GCB726: Supplementary TableS1).Bb-Tp0751: Parent expressing Tp0751.</s><s>Numbers of interactions analyzed/strain (a,b): ≥288; (c,e): parent (42), infectious (127), Bb-BBK32 (130) and Bb-Tp0751 (39); (d,f): parent (366), infectious (520), Bb-BBK32 (448), and Bb-Tp0751 (249).</s><s>Statistics: one-way Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA with Dunn's post-tests (a,b,e,f); one-way ANOVA with Holm-Sidak post-tests (c,d).</s><s>*Indicates p &lt; 0.05 vs parent.</s><s>+ Indicates p &lt; 0.05 vs Bb-BBK32.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,155.64,46.50,360.00,431.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3.</s><s>Effect of Tp0751 on tethered and untethered interaction stability and velocity under shear stress.</s><s>B. burgdorferi interacts with endothelia under PCV shear stress conditions by two mechanisms: untethered (dragging) interactions, and tethered interactions.</s><s>Tethered interactions are stabilized by bungee cord-like tethers which anchor bacteria to endothelia, reduce force imposed on load-bearing adhesion complexes and increase adhesion bond stability (lifetime) 29 .</s><s>(a,b) Proportion of total bacterial-endothelial interaction times during which bacterial length extended beyond the normal length, indicative of tether formation stabilizing the interaction ((a) % duration), and the average tether length (b) for all interactions at 0.5-1 dyn/cm 2 .</s><s>(c,d) Interaction complex dissociation rates for untethered (c) and tethered (d) interactions.</s><s>Dotted lines indicate dissociation rates for non-specific interactions (non-adherent beads).</s><s>(e,f) Velocities of untethered (e) and tethered (f) interactions.</s><s>Summary values: mean ± 95% CI (a,b,e,f), mean ± SEM (c,d).</s><s>Interaction properties were calculated from interactions obtained at both 0.5 and 1 dyn/cm 2 .</s><s>N = 4 and N = 8 independent flow chamber experiments for each strain at 0.5 and 1 dyn/cm 2 , respectively.</s><s>Strains: Negative control strain: BBK32deficient non-infectious adhesion-attenuated B31-A-derived strain (Parent; GCB706: Supplementary TableS1).</s><s>Positive control strains: Parent expressing B. burgdorferi vascular adhesin BBK32 (Bb-BBK32); BBK32expressing B31-derived infectious strain (Infectious; GCB726: Supplementary TableS1).Bb-Tp0751: Parent expressing Tp0751.</s><s>Numbers of interactions analyzed/strain (a,b): ≥288; (c,e): parent (42), infectious (127), Bb-BBK32 (130) and Bb-Tp0751 (39); (d,f): parent (366), infectious (520), Bb-BBK32 (448), and Bb-Tp0751 (249).</s><s>Statistics: one-way Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA with Dunn's post-tests (a,b,e,f); one-way ANOVA with Holm-Sidak post-tests (c,d).</s><s>*Indicates p &lt; 0.05 vs parent.</s><s>+ Indicates p &lt; 0.05 vs Bb-BBK32.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. Bond strengths of Tp0751-dependent interactions under shear stress.</s><s>Forces imposed on individual load-bearing adhesion bonds (F b ) for bacterial-endothelial interactions tracked at 0.5 and 1 dyn/cm 2 were estimated as described in the Materials and Methods.</s><s>(a-c) Bond forces for all (a), untethered (b) and tethered (c) interactions (mean ± 95% CI).</s><s>(d,e) Percentages of tracked interactions for each strain occurring at indicated F b values.</s><s>Percentages for both tethered and untethered interactions combined are shown in (d), and untethered interactions alone are shown in (e).</s><s>F b values for all interactions combined were binned by force range to obtain Mean ± SEM F b values plotted on x-axes.For untethered interactions, interactions were grouped by F b into a smaller number of bins than for all interactions combined (e), to provide sufficient interaction numbers in each bin for accurate calculation of bond dissociation rates at each bond force (f).</s><s>For the parent strain and Bb-Tp0751, fewer than 25 interactions were obtained in all but the lowest force bin.</s><s>For these strains, the data from the higher force bins were therefore pooled with values from the lowest force bin to obtain sufficient interaction numbers for dissociation rate calculations.</s><s>This resulted in a single data point reflecting the values obtained for all untethered interactions for parent and Bb-Tp0751 strains.</s><s>(f) Effect of increasing bond force on mean ± SEM bond dissociation rates.</s><s>Dotted line indicates the dissociation rate for negative control beads.</s><s>Strains: Negative control strain: BBK32deficient non-infectious adhesion-attenuated B31-A-derived strain (Parent; GCB706: Supplementary TableS1).</s><s>Positive control strains: Parent expressing B. burgdorferi vascular adhesin BBK32 (Bb-BBK32); BBK32-expressing B31-derived infectious strain (Infectious; GCB726: Supplementary TableS1).</s><s>Bb-Tp0751: Parent expressing Tp0751.</s><s>Numbers of interactions analyzed/strain: ≥288 (a,d); ≥39 (b,e,f); ≥249 (c).</s><s>Statistics: one-way Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA with Dunn's post-tests.</s><s>*Indicates p &lt; 0.05 vs parent.</s><s>+ Indicates p &lt; 0.05 vs BBK32.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,155.64,46.50,360.00,484.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. Interaction of Tp0751-expressing B. burgdorferi with postcapillary venules in vivo.</s><s>(a) Total bacterial interactions per minute with dermal PCVs of live mice, visualized by intravital microscopy (IVM).</s><s>Representative IVM videos are presented in Supplementary Videos S4-S6.</s><s>Numbers of bacteria that paused and moved more slowly over PCV surfaces under flow were manually counted in time-lapses acquired at 15 fps.</s><s>(b) B. burgdorferi flaB DNA copy numbers in blood of mice collected after IVM, as measured by quantitative real-time PCR.</s><s>(c) Copy number-adjusted interactions/min in PCVs.</s><s>Numbers of mice (venules) analyzed per strain: parent: 14 (30); infectious: 8 (22); Bb-BBK32: 8 (24); Bb-Tp0751: 9 (25).</s><s>Summary values represent means ± SEM for experiments performed with ≥4 independent bacterial cultures/strain.</s><s>Statistics: one-way Kruskal-Wallis ANOVA with Dunn's post-test.</s><s>*Indicates p &lt; 0.05 vs. parent.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,155.64,46.50,396.00,123.36" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>statement.</s><s>Animal experiments were carried out in accordance with the most recent Guide to the Care and Use of Experimental Animals (Canadian Council on Animal Care), and approved by the Animal Care Committee of the University of Toronto (protocol 20010430).</s><s>Work with B. burgdorferi was carried out in accordance with University of Toronto, University of Victoria biosafety permits 12a-M30-2 and 2109-107, respectively, and Public Health Agency of Canada and the Canadian Food Inspection Agency guidelines.</s></p></div></figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Scientific RepoRts | 7: 1538 | DOI:10.1038/s41598-017-01589-4</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>We thank N Zlotnikov for assistance with figure preparation and S Houston for critical manuscript review, A Bansal, A Javid and C Lo for technical assistance, and G Chaconas for bacterial strains.</s><s>We are also grateful for expert assistance from staff and use of facilities at the Sick Kids Imaging Facility, and University of Toronto Faculty of Medicine Department of Comparative Medicine.</s><s>This project was supported by the following operating and infrastructure funding: Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR) (</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Data availability statement.</s><s>Data underlying the findings reported in this manuscript are included in the summarized data presented in the paper and its Supporting Information files.</s><s>Spreadsheets of raw data can be converted and supplied upon requests directed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author Contributions</head><p><s>Conceptualization: W.C.K., H.P., R.E., K.V.L., C.E.C., T.J.M.; methodology: W.C.K., H.P., R.E., K.V.L., P.R., C.E.C., T.J.M.; software: R.E., T.J.M.; validation: W.C.K., H.P., R.E., K.V.L., P.R., C.E.C., T.J.M.; formal analysis: W.C.K., R.E., K.V.L., T.J.M.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional Information</head><p><s>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at doi:10.1038/s41598-017-01589-4</s></p><p><s>Competing Interests: The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</s></p><p><s>Publisher's note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">World Health Organization. Prevalence and incidence of selected sexually transmitted infections, Chlamydia trachomatis, Neisseria gonorrhoeae, syphilis and Trichomonas vaginalis: methods and results used by WHO to generate 2005 estimates</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Report on sexually transmitted infections in Canada</title>
		<idno>64-02-14-1200-STI-Report-2011_EN-FINAL.pdf (Accessed: 22nd</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.catie.ca/sites/default/files/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011-07">2011. July 2015. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Public Health Agency of Canada</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sexually transmitted diseases surveillance</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.cdc.gov/std/stats13/surv2013-print.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-07-22">2013. Accessed: 22nd July 2015. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">China&apos;s syphilis epidemic: epidemiology, proximate determinants of spread, and control responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Tucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/QCO.0b013e32834204bf</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Infect. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">European Surveillance of Antimicrobial Consumption (ESAC): outpatient macrolide, lincosamide and streptogramin (MLS) use in Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Adriaenssens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/jac/dkr456</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Antimicrob. Chemother</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997-2009. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An estimate of syphilis incidence in Eastern Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Herbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Middleton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7189/jogh.02.010402</idno>
		<idno>doi:10.7189/ jogh.02.010402</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Glob Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10402</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid increase in gonorrhoea and syphilis diagnoses in England in 2011</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Savage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Euro Surveill</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20224</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The need and plan for global elimination of congenital syphilis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Schmid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Stoner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hawkes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Broutet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/01.olq.0000261456.09797.1b</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sex Transm Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Penicillin treatment of syphilis: clearing away the shadow on the land</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Douglas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jama.2009.143</idno>
		<idno>doi:10.1001/ jama.2009.143</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JAMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">301</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="769" to="771" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Can population differences explain the contrasting results of the Mwanza, Rakai, and Masaka HIV/sexually transmitted disease intervention trials?: A modeling study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/01.qai.0000127062.94627.31</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Acquir. Immune Defic. Syndr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1500" to="1513" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biological basis for syphilis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lafond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lukehart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1128/CMR.19.1.29-49.2006</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Microbiol. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heterologous expression of the Treponema pallidum laminin-binding adhesin Tp0751 in the culturable spirochete Treponema phagedenis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1128/JB.01537-07</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Bacteriol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">190</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2565" to="2571" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Treponema pallidum lipoprotein TP0435 expressed in Borrelia burgdorferi produces multiple surface/periplasmic isoforms and mediates adherence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/srep25593</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25593</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Current status of syphilis vaccine development: need, challenges, prospects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lukehart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.vaccine.2013.09.053</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vaccine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1602" to="1609" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Primary and secondary syphilis, 20 years&apos; experience. 2. Clinical features</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mindel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tovey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Timmins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/sti.65.1.1</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genitourin Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="3" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nephrotic syndrome and granulomatous hepatitis in secondary syphilis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Bansal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Cohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lynfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/archderm.1978.01640200080025</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1228" to="1229" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Report of seven cases and review of the literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Greenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wilcox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/OLQ.0b013e3181c0d51</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clin. Gastroenterol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Gastric syphilis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical manifestations of secondary syphilis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Bhat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Chilikima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mooney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1365-4362.1987.tb00532.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="107" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Invasion of the central nervous system by Treponema pallidum: implications for diagnosis and treatment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lukehart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7326/0003-4819-109-11-855</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Intern. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="855" to="862" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interjunctional invasion of endothelial cell monolayers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Haake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lovett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0076-6879(94)36033-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Meth. Enzymol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">236</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="447" to="463" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vitro model of Treponema pallidum invasiveness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Riviere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cobb</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Infect Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2267" to="2271" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Treponema pallidum invades intercellular junctions of endothelial cell monolayers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.85.10.3608</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3608" to="3612" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interactions of Treponema pallidum with endothelial cell monolayers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fogelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lovett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/BF00145039</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The rate of multiplication of Treponema pallidum in normal and immune rabbits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cumberland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Syph Gonorrhea Vener Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="212" />
			<date type="published" when="1949">1949</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of Treponema pallidum in amniotic fluid and fetal blood from pregnancies complicated by congenital syphilis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wendel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="890" to="895" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Breaking the wall: targeting of the endothelium by pathogenic bacteria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Lemichez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lecuit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Nassif</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bourdoulous</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nrmicro2269</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biomechanics of leukocyte rolling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sundd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Pospieszalska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cheung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">.-L</forename><surname>Konstantopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3233/BIR-2011-0579</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biorheology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of PSGL-1 microbead and neutrophil rolling: microvillus elongation stabilizes P-selectin bond clusters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">Y H</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0006-3495(02)75534-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1835" to="1847" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biomechanics of Borrelia burgdorferi vascular interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ebady</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.celrep.2016.08.013</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2593" to="2604" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plasma fibronectin stabilizes Borrelia burgdorferi-endothelial interactions under vascular shear stress by a catch bond mechanism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Niddam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1365-4362.1987.tb00532.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="e3490" to="e3498" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular mechanisms involved in vascular interactions of the Lyme disease pathogen in a living host</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Norman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000169</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Pathog</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1000169</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A short-term Borrelia burgdorferi infection model identifies tissue tropisms and bloodstream survival conferred by adhesion proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Caine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Coburn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1128/IAI.00349-15</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Infect. Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3184" to="3194" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Flow-tolerant adhesion of a bacterial pathogen to human endothelial cells through interaction with biglycan</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Salo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/infdis/jiw003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">213</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1623" to="1631" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adhesion of Staphylococcus aureus to the vessel wall under flow is mediated by von Willebrand factor-binding protein</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Claes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1182/blood-2014-02-558890</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1669" to="1676" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of bacterial and human genetic variation on Staphylococcus aureus infections</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Messina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Thaden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sharma-Kuinkel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Fowler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.ppat.1005330</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Pathog</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1005330</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decorin-binding proteins A and B confer distinct mammalian cell type-specific attachment by Borrelia burgdorferi, the Lyme disease spirochete</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Parveen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Magoun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.1231043100</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7307" to="7312" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of a 47 kDa fibronectin-binding protein expressed by Borrelia burgdorferi isolate B31</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Probert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1998.01127.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1003" to="1015" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel von Willebrand factor binding protein expressed by Staphylococcus aureus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bjerketorp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1099/00221287-148-7-2037</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Microbiology (Reading, Engl.)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2037" to="2044" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two different genes encode fibronectin binding proteins in Staphylococcus aureus. The complete nucleotide sequence and characterization of the second gene</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Jönsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Signäs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lindberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1432-1033.1991.tb16468.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">202</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1041" to="1048" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intravital imaging of vascular transmigration by the Lyme spirochete: Requirement for the integrin binding residues of the B. burgdorferi P66 protein</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.ppat.1005333</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS Pathog</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1005333</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel Treponema pallidum antigen, TP0136, is an outer membrane protein that binds human fibronectin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Brinkman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1128/IAI.01424-07</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Infect. Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1848" to="1857" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of a Treponema pallidum laminin-binding protein</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1128/IAI.71.5.2525-2533.2003</idno>
		<idno>doi:10.1128/ IAI.71.5.2525-2533.2003</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Infect. Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2525" to="2533" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Treponema pallidum fibronectin-binding proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M Y</forename><surname>Kuroiwa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Schnapp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Brouwer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1128/JB.186.20.7019-7022.2004</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Bacteriol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">186</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7019" to="7022" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Treponema pallidum subsp. pallidum TP0136 protein is heterogeneous among isolates and binds cellular and plasma fibronectin via its NH 2 -terminal end</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Molini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lukehart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Giacani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pntd.0003662</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e0003662</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Activation and proteolytic activity of the Treponema pallidum metalloprotease, pallilysin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Houston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hof</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Honeyman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hassler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002822</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Pathog</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1002822</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bifunctional role of the Treponema pallidum extracellular matrix binding adhesin Tp0751</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Houston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1128/IAI.01083-10</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Infect. Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1386" to="1398" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conservation of the host-interacting proteins Tp0750 and pallilysin among treponemes and restriction of proteolytic capacity to Treponema pallidum</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Houston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1128/IAI.00643-15</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Infect. Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The multifunctional role of the pallilysin-associated Treponema pallidum protein, Tp0750, in promoting fibrinolysis and extracellular matrix component degradation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Houston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/mmi.12482</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="618" to="634" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The structure of Treponema pallidum Tp0751 (pallilysin) reveals a lipocalin-like fold that mediates adhesion to extracellular matrix components and interactions with host cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Parker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.ppat.1005919</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLOS Pathog</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1005919</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The factor H binding protein of Neisseria meningitidis interacts with xenosiderophores in vitro</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Veggi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1021/bi301161w</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9384" to="9393" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A defined syphilis vaccine candidate inhibits dissemination of Treponema pallidum subspecies pallidum</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Lithgow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/ncomms14273</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14273</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virulent Treponema pallidum activates human vascular endothelial cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Riley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Oppenheimer-Marks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Radolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Norgard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/infdis/165.3.484</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">165</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="484" to="493" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rolling cell adhesion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mcever</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev.cellbio.042308.113238</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="396" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real-time high resolution 3D imaging of the Lyme disease spirochete adhering to and escaping from the vasculature of a living host</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moriarty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000090</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Pathog</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1000090</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vascular binding of a pathogen under shear force through mechanistically distinct sequential interactions with host macromolecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moriarty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/mmi.12045</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1116" to="1131" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lifetime of the P-selectin-carbohydrate bond and its response to tensile force in hydrodynamic flow</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Alon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Springer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/374539a0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">374</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="542" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vaccine development for syphilis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Lithgow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cameron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/14760584.2016.1203262</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Expert Review of Vaccines</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heterologous expression of pathogen-specific genes ligA and ligB in the saprophyte Leptospira biflexa confers enhanced adhesion to cultured cells and fibronectin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Figueira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/1471-2180-11-129</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">129</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glycosaminoglycan binding by Borrelia burgdorferi adhesin BBK32 specifically and uniquely promotes joint colonization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-P</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/cmi.12407</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="860" to="875" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Host cell heparan sulfate glycosaminoglycans are ligands for OspF-related proteins of the Lyme disease spirochete</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-P</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bhowmick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Coburn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/cmi.12448</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell. Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fibronectin binding protein BBK32 of the Lyme disease spirochete promotes bacterial attachment to glycosaminoglycans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Leblanc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1128/IAI.74.1.435-441.2006</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Infect Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="435" to="441" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BBK32, a fibronectin binding MSCRAMM from Borrelia burgdorferi, contains a disordered region that undergoes a conformational change on ligand binding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1074/jbc.M401691200</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">279</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41706" to="41714" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Borrelia burgdorferi binds fibronectin through a tandem beta-zipper, a common mechanism of fibronectin binding in Staphylococci, Streptococci, and spirochetes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Raibaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1074/jbc.M501731200</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">280</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18803" to="18809" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel fibronectin binding motif in MSCRAMMs targets F3 modules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Prabhakaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Skare</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Potts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Höök</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0005412</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e5412</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interaction between Borrelia burgdorferi and endothelium in vitro</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Szczepanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Furie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Benach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fleit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1172/JCI114615</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1637" to="1647" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
