<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Production of gaseous and liquid chemicals by aqueous phase reforming of crude 1 glycerol: Influence of operating conditions on the process 2 3</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Remón</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad de Zaragoza. Mariano Esquillor s/n</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>E-50018</postCode>
									<settlement>Zaragoza</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Giménez</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad de Zaragoza. Mariano Esquillor s/n</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>E-50018</postCode>
									<settlement>Zaragoza</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Valiente</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad de Zaragoza. Mariano Esquillor s/n</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>E-50018</postCode>
									<settlement>Zaragoza</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>García</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad de Zaragoza. Mariano Esquillor s/n</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>E-50018</postCode>
									<settlement>Zaragoza</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Arauzo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Universidad de Zaragoza. Mariano Esquillor s/n</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>E-50018</postCode>
									<settlement>Zaragoza</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Production of gaseous and liquid chemicals by aqueous phase reforming of crude 1 glycerol: Influence of operating conditions on the process 2 3</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">22361C29F5539975F267A235DB8B398A</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:17+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>The present work studies the influence of the temperature (200-240 ºC), pressure 12 (38-50 bar), glycerol concentration (10-50 wt.%) and mass of catalyst/ glycerol mass 13 flow rate ratio (W/m glycerol = 10-40 g catalyst min/g glycerol) during the aqueous 14 phase reforming (APR) of a glycerol solution obtained from the production of 15 biodiesel.</s><s>The operating conditions exerted a statistically significant influence on the 16 reforming results.</s><s>Specifically, the global glycerol conversion and the carbon 17 converted into gas and liquid products varied as follows: 4-100%, 1-80% and 16-18 93%, respectively.</s><s>The gas phase was made up of H 2 (8-55 vol.%),</s><s>CO 2 (34-66 19 vol.%),</s><s>CO (0-4 vol.%) and CH 4 (6-45 vol.%).</s><s>The liquid phase consisted of a 20 mixture of alcohols (monohydric: methanol and ethanol; and polyhydric: 1,2-21 propanediol, 1,2-ethanediol, 2,3-butanediol), aldehydes (acetaldehyde), ketones (C3-22 ketones: acetone and 2-propanone-1-hydroxy; C4-ketones: 2-butanone-3-hydroxy 23 and 2-butanone-1-hydroxy; and cyclic ketones), carboxylic acids (acetic and 24 propionic acids) and esters (1,2,3-propanetriol-monoacetate), together with unreacted</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>2 glycerol and water.</s><s>The relative amount (free of water and un-reacted glycerol) of 1 these compounds in the liquid phase was as follows: monohydric alcohols: 4-47%, 2 polyhydric-alcohols: 14-68%, aldehydes: 0-5%, C3-ketones: 2-33%, C4-ketones: 0-3 10 %, ciclo-ketones: 0-6%, carboxylic acids: 2-43%, and esters: 0-46%.</s><s>This process 4 turned out to be highly customisable for the valorisation of crude glycerol for the 5 production of either gaseous or liquid products.</s><s>Gas production is favoured at a low 6 pressure (39 bar), high temperature (238 ºC), high W/m glycerol ratio (38 g catalyst 7 min/g glycerol) and employing a 15 wt.% glycerol solution.</s><s>A high pressure (45 bar), 8 medium temperature (216 ºC), medium W/m glycerol ratio (22 g catalyst min/g 9 glycerol) and the feeding of a 16 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solution favours the production of 10 Worldwide biodiesel production is increasing intensely as a result of widespread 2 environmental concerns and firmer regulations for fuels.</s><s>This biofuel is commonly 3 produced by the transesterification of triglycerides using an alcohol in the presence of a 4 catalyst.</s><s>Unfortunately, despite the environmental benefits of biodiesel, its production 5 originates glycerol as a by-product: 1 kg of crude glycerol is yielded with the 6 production of 10 kg of biodiesel.</s><s>This scenario could create a surplus of crude glycerol 7 unable to be absorbed by its current market, which may cause economic and 8 environmental problems, hampering the development of the biodiesel industry <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. 9 10 Given this background, two main options are usually considered to deal with this 11 biodiesel-derived glycerol.</s><s>The first consists of its purification for further use in other 12 industries such as the food, cosmetics and pharmaceutical sectors <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr">2]</ref>.</s><s>The second 13 option consists of upgrading the crude glycerol employing different valorisation routes.</s><s>14 These include gasification, steam reforming, aqueous phase reforming and supercritical 15 reforming, among others <ref type="bibr">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr">4]</ref>, allowing the production of different value-added 16 chemicals and/or energy, and thus improving biodiesel economy and sustainability <ref type="bibr">[5, 17 6]</ref>.</s><s>18</s></p><note type="other">19</note><p><s>The glycerol discharged from biodiesel production plants consists not only of glycerol 20 but also of many other chemicals <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, which can significantly reduce the yields and 21 efficiencies of the valorisation processes.</s><s>Therefore, an intermediate option that 22 includes a first purification of the crude glycerol up to an appropriate level for use in the 23 subsequent valorisation processes should be addressed.</s><s>This pre-treatment helps to 24 reduce troublesome impurities such as fatty acid methyl esters (FAMES) and soaps.</s><s>A 4 cost-effective purification method consists of the physical separation of the FAMES and 1 the elimination of the soaps by an initial acidification, normally with acetic, sulphuric or 2 phosphoric acid, and a subsequent liquid-liquid extraction with a polar solvent <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>This 3 pre-treatment using acetic acid provides a glycerol solution with 85-90% purity, which 4 still contains some of the acid used in the neutralization, part of the catalyst employed in 5 the biodiesel production (usually KOH or NaOH) as well as the alcohol used during the 6 transesterification reaction and/or in the purification step.</s><s>7 8 A promising strategy to obtain value-added chemicals from this biodiesel derived 9 glycerol is aqueous phase reforming (APR).</s><s>APR is a catalytic process carried out at 10 quite low temperatures and moderate pressures, allowing the production of different 11 chemicals (gases and liquids) from an organic feedstock.</s><s>During the APR of glycerol, 12 various liquid-gas-solid chemical reactions take place.</s><s>These include cracking and 13 reforming reactions to generate hydrogen, dehydrogenation of alcohols/hydrogenation 14 of carbonyls, deoxygenation and hydrogenolysis as well as cyclisation reactions.</s><s>The 15 gas phase consists of a gas with a high H 2 content, the liquid phase being a complex 16 mixture of different organic compounds in water.</s><s>These include alcohols, ketones, 17 acids, esters, paraffins, aldehydes and other oxygenated hydrocarbons with different 18 compositions depending on the operating conditions of the process and the nature of the 19 feed <ref type="bibr">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr">[9]</ref>.</s><s>The versatility of this valorisation process allows the customised conversion 20 of glycerol into chemicals of a different nature to suit the necessities of the market, thus 21 converting this process into a very promising tailor-made route for the treatment and 22 valorisation of the glycerol obtained from the biodiesel industry.</s><s>23 5 <ref type="bibr">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[11]</ref> and the vast majority of the publications in the literature are focused on 1 understanding the effect of the catalyst type and the operating conditions during the 2 APR of reagent-grade glycerol.</s><s>The catalysts used in the process are noble metals based 3 on Pt <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr">[16]</ref>, Ni <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr">12,</ref><ref type="bibr">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr">[20]</ref>, Pt-Ni, Cu, Co or Ru <ref type="bibr">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr">12,</ref><ref type="bibr">16,</ref><ref type="bibr">18,</ref><ref type="bibr">21]</ref> supported on 4 different oxides such as Al 2 O 3 , ZrO 2 , MgO, SiO 2, CeO 2 , or carbon <ref type="bibr">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr">22]</ref> and modified, 5 in some cases, with promoters such as La, Ce, Mg and Zr. 6 7</s></p><p><s>The influence of the operating variables on the process has been studied in some works.</s><s>8</s></p><p><s>Özgür et al. <ref type="bibr">[14]</ref> studied the effect of the temperature (160-280 ºC), flow rate (0.05-0.5 9 mL/min), pressure (0-75 atm) and glycerol concentration (5-85 wt.%).</s><s>The optimum 10 temperature for hydrogen production was 230 ºC and the maximum gas production rate 11 was found using feed flow rates of 0.1 mL/min.</s><s>In addition, they reported that the 12 hydrogen concentration in the gas increased with decreasing the glycerol concentration 13 of the feed.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Wawrzetz et al. [23]</ref> reported the effect of the glycerol concentration <ref type="bibr">(10-30 14</ref> wt.%) and pressure (26-45 bar) at 498 K. Reaction rates increased with the increase in 15 the glycerol concentration.</s><s>The pressure was found to have a significant effect on the 16 liquid product distribution without affecting the global conversion of the process.</s><s>17 18 Roy et al. <ref type="bibr">[21]</ref> investigated the effect of the initial pressure (0-41 bar of N 2 ) at 493 K 19 using a 9.2 wt.% glycerol solution in a batch reactor, initially fed with 3 g of glycerol 20 and 0.125 g of catalyst, for 6 h.</s><s>An increase in the initial pressure up to 14 bar of N 2 21 augmented the glycerol conversion from 43.2 to 50.2%, while a further increase up to 22 41 bar decreased the glycerol conversion.</s><s>The product distribution was not greatly 23 affected by the pressure.</s><s>An increase in temperature from 473 to 523 K at 14 bar of N 2 6 glycol and increased the concentration of ethanol in the liquid. 1 2 Manfro et al. <ref type="bibr">[19]</ref> used a batch reactor to study the effect of the glycerol concentration 3</s></p><p><s>(1-10 wt.%), temperature (523-543 K) and its corresponding pressure (37-52 atm).</s><s>The 4 highest glycerol conversion (30%) was achieved at 543 K using a 1 wt.% glycerol 5</s></p><p><s>solution.</s><s>An increase in the glycerol concentration decreased the glycerol conversion 6 and H 2 formation.</s><s>A rise in the temperature and pressure increased the glycerol 7 conversion and decreased the proportion of H 2 in the gas.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Luo et al. [24]</ref> reported the 8 effect of the temperature (180-220 ºC) and its corresponding pressure (1.14 -2.5 MPa), 9 glycerol concentration (5-10 wt.%) and liquid hourly space velocity (1.56-3.12</s><s>h -1 ) in a 10 flow reactor.</s><s>An increase in temperature (and its corresponding pressure) facilitated the 11 reforming process and increased the hydrogen yield.</s><s>The carbon conversion to gas and 12 the H 2 yield decreased with augmenting the glycerol concentration.</s><s>Decreasing the 13 hourly space velocity resulted in a higher hydrogen yield, hydrogen selectivity and 14 carbon conversion to gas.</s><s>15 16 Seretis and Tsiacaras <ref type="bibr">[25,</ref><ref type="bibr">26]</ref> studied the effect of the reaction time (30-240 min), 17 temperature (200-240 ºC), glycerol concentration (1-10 wt.%) and catalyst weight using 18 a Ni/SiO 2 -Al 2 O 3 catalyst (0.5-10 g) [25] and a Pt/Al 2 O 3 catalyst (0.5-2.5 g) <ref type="bibr">[26]</ref>.</s><s>The 19 glycerol conversion increased with increasing the reaction time and temperature.</s><s>The H 2 20 production was maximised with the use of short reaction times and low glycerol 21</s></p><p><s>concentrations.</s><s>An increase in the amount of catalyst increased the C-C cleavage, 22 favouring the formation of ethylene glycol, ethanol and methane.</s><s>When using the 7 and 36%, respectively, while for the Pt/Al 2 O 3 catalyst they were 41 and 39%, 1</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>respectively. 2 3</head><p><s>The large number of operating variables significantly influencing the process increases 4 its intrinsic complexity.</s><s>Some interactions between some of the operating variables can 5 occur so that the effects of some variables may depend on others, resulting in different 6 consequences for the process.</s><s>These interactions have never been considered in the 7 parametric studies reported in the literature, and they could be responsible for some of 8 the contradictory results reported.</s><s>In addition, the effect of the operating conditions on 9 the production and selectivity to the different liquid products is not yet well understood; 10 therefore, an in-depth study is needed for gaining a better understanding of this process <ref type="bibr">. 11 12</ref> Given this background, this work addresses the effect of the temperature (200-240 ºC), 13 pressure (38-50 bar), glycerol concentration (10-50 wt.%) and W/m glycerol ratio (10-40 g 14 catalyst min/g glycerol) on the aqueous phase reforming process of biodiesel-derived 15 glycerol using a Ni-based catalyst.</s><s>Optimal values for the production of gas and liquid 16 products were also sought for their selective production.</s><s>17</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Material and methods 19</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Crude glycerol 20</head><p><s>The crude glycerol used for this work was obtained from the transesterification of 21 sunflower oil with methanol, employing potassium hydroxide as a catalyst.</s><s>The 22 characterisation results of the crude glycerol, including the Total Organic Carbon 23 8 chemical composition was calculated by means of a Gas Chromatography-Mass 1 Spectrometry analysis, Karl Fischer titration and ash content.</s><s>The GC-MS analysis of 2 the glycerol also revealed the presence of a small proportion of some FAMES (linoleic, 3 palmitic, oleic and stearic).</s><s>The crude glycerol was neutralised with acetic acid using a final pH of 6. Acetic acid 11 was selected for the glycerol purification as its presence in the refined glycerol solution 12 can contribute to H 2 formation, without deactivating the catalysts used in APR as occurs 13 when using H 2 SO 4 due to the presence of S. In addition, the work of Manosak et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> 14 indicates that this acid is suitable for the purification of glycerol obtained from the 15 biodiesel industry.</s><s>16 9</s></p><p><s>The glycerol was then subjected to a vacuum distillation where acetic acid and methanol 1 were recovered for further use in the subsequent neutralisation and purification steps. 2</s></p><p><s>This strategy improves the economics of this purification-valorisation process.</s><s>As a 3 result of this two-step strategy, a rich glycerol solution was obtained and used for the 4 aqueous phase reforming experiments.</s><s>The characterisation results of the rich glycerol 5 phase (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>) reveal a significant increase in the glycerol purity (up to 85 wt.%) and a 6 decrease in the concentration of methanol.</s><s>Additionally, an increase in the viscosity and 7 a decrease in the LHV of the glycerol solution also occur as a result of the reduction in 8 the methanol and FAMES contents in the solution.</s><s>9 10 As listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, the glycerol used in this work also contains CH 3 COOH, CH 3 OH, 11</s></p><p><s>KOH and H 2 O as major impurities.</s><s>For better readability, the glycerol solutions are 12 only defined by indicating their glycerol concentrations throughout the text, although 13 they contain the corresponding amounts of impurities resulting from the dilution of the 14 glycerol solution in water.</s><s>15 16</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Experimental system 17</head><p><s>The experiments were carried out in a small bench scale continuous unit employing a 18 NiAlLa catalyst.</s><s>A reaction time of 3 hours was selected in order to be able to analyse 19 the evolution over time of the gas and liquid phases while also studying the stability of 20 pressure is reached with the aid of a micrometric valve which automatically adapts its 3 position with the help of a rotor.</s><s>A pressure gauge, located at the exit of the reactor, 4 measures the pressure of the reaction section.</s><s>A PDI control system is used to keep the 5 reactor pressure constant during the experiments.</s><s>The aqueous solutions of crude 6 glycerol are fed into the reactor by means of a high performance liquid chromatography 7</s></p><p><s>(HPLC) pump.</s><s>The reaction products (gas and liquids) and the unreacted glycerol leave 8 the reactor from its upper part, pass through the valve, where they are depressurised, 9 and arrive at the condensation system.</s><s>This system consists of four different condensers 10</s></p><p><s>where the liquid products are separated from the gas mixture at intervals of 1 h to 11 analyse the evolution over time of the liquid phase.</s><s>The gas mixture is made up of N 2 , 12 used as an internal standard, and the different gaseous products formed during the 13 aqueous phase reforming reaction.</s><s>A micro chromatograph equipped with thermal 14 conductivity detectors (TCD) was used for the online analysis of the gas phase.</s><s>At the 15 end of the experiment the liquid fractions were collected and analysed offline with a gas 16 chromatograph equipped with Flame Ionization (FID), and Mass Spectrometry (MS) 17 detectors.</s><s>A schematic diagram of the experimental system is shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">1</ref>.</s><s>18 19</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Operating conditions, response variables and statistical analyses 20</head><p><s>The effect of the temperature (200-240 ºC), pressure (38-50 bar), glycerol concentration 21 The experiments were designed using a 2 k factorial design, where k indicates the 6 number of factors studied (in this case 4 operating conditions) and 2 k represents the 7 number of runs (in this case 16).</s><s>In addition, 4 replicates at the centre point (centre of 8 the variation interval of each factor) were carried out in order to evaluate both the 9 experimental error and the curvature shown by the evolution of each variable, i.e. 10 whether or not this evolution is linear within the experimental range studied.</s><s>This 11 factorial design minimises the number of experiments needed to understand the effect 12 on the process of the operating variables and the interactions between them.</s><s>As the 13 response variables did not show a linear trend, this design was increased with 8 axial 14 runs following a Box-Wilson Central Composite Face Centred (CCF, α: ± 1) design, 15 enabling the operating variables and interactions responsible for the curvature to be 1 identified without modifying the range of study initially considered for the operating 2 variables.</s><s>The values for the operating conditions employed in the experiments 3 according to this experimental design are listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>.</s><s>The lower and upper limits 4 of all the operating variables were normalised from -1 to 1 (codec factors).</s><s>This 5 codification enables all factors to vary within the same interval and helps to identify 6 their influence in comparable terms.</s><s>7 8 The effect of the operating conditions on the process was analysed for the following 1 response variables: global glycerol conversion (X gly, %), carbon conversion to gas, 2 liquid and solid products (CC gas %, CC liq %, and CC sol %) as well as the 3 composition of the gas (N 2 and H 2 O free, vol.%) and liquid (relative chromatographic 4 area free of water and un-reacted glycerol, %).</s><s>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> summarises the response 5 variables and the analytical methods used for their calculation.</s><s>6 7  CC liq = Carbon conversion to liquid products (unreacted glycerol free).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>11</head><p><s>CC liq * = Carbon conversion to liquids including unreacted glycerol</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="12">13</head><p><s>Some of the used catalysts were characterised by X-Ray diffraction (XRD) and 14 Thermogravimetric (TG) analyses.</s><s>XRD patterns of the used catalysts were obtained 15 with a D-Max Rigaku diffractometer equipped with a CuK α1.2 at a tube voltage of 40 16 kV and current of 80 mA.</s><s>The measurements were carried out using continuous-scan 17 mode with steps of 0.03 • /s at Bragg's angles (2θ) ranging from 5 • to 85 • .</s><s>The phases 18 present in the samples were defined with reference to the JCPDS-International Centre 19 for Diffraction Data 2000 database.</s><s>TG analyses were conducted under a N 2 20 14 ºC at a heating rate of 10 ºC/min.</s><s>The weight loss was measured and the conversion (X), 1 defined as the variation of the mass with the respect to the initial sample mass, was 2 calculated.</s><s>3 4 First of all, the evolution over time of the response variables was studied.</s><s>For each 5 experiment, the results are divided into three intervals.</s><s>Each interval corresponds to the 6 average value of the studied response variables obtained during each one of the three 7 hours of experiment.</s><s>All these values (three per experiment) have been compared using 8 a one-way analysis of variance (one-way ANOVA) and Fisher´s least significant 9 difference (LSD) test, both with 95% confidence.</s><s>The results of the ANOVA analyses 10 are provided as p-values.</s><s>P-values lower than 0.05 indicate that at least two values are 11 significantly different.</s><s>Furthermore, the LSD test was used to compare pairs of data, i.e. 12 either between two intervals of the same experiment or between two intervals of two 13 different experiments.</s><s>The results of the LSD tests are presented graphically in the form 14 of LSD bars.</s><s>To ensure significant differences between any pairs of data, their LSD bars 15 must not overlap.</s><s>16 17 Secondly, the effect of the operating conditions was studied considering the results 18 corresponding to the first hour using a statistical analysis of variance (one-way 19 ANOVA) test with 95% confidence.</s><s>This strategy allows not having to include the 20 effect of the variations with time of the different response variables in the analysis.</s><s>In 21 addition, the cause-effect Pareto principle was used to calculate the relative importance 22 of the operating variables on each response variable.</s><s>23</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Possible reaction network during the aqueous phase reforming of glycerol 1</head><p><s>A plausible reaction pathway for the aqueous phase reforming of glycerol is shown in 2 the thermal decomposition and/or reforming reactions of the glycerol and all the liquid 8 intermediates (Eq.1) as well as by all the decarbonylation reactions that release CO.</s><s>In 9 addition, the water gas shift reaction (Eq.2) and methanation reactions (Eq.3-4) are also 10 possible, explaining the presence of CO 2 and CH 4 in the gas phase <ref type="bibr">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr">7,</ref><ref type="bibr">21,</ref><ref type="bibr">23,</ref><ref type="bibr">[34]</ref><ref type="bibr">[35]</ref><ref type="bibr">[36]</ref> The presence of 3-hydroxypropanal in the liquid product has not been detected in the 6 vast majority of works dealing with the aqueous phase reforming of glycerol.</s><s>This 7 indicates that dehydration forming 1-hydroxypropan-2-one is more likely to occur 8 and/or that 3-hydroxypropanal may be instantaneously converted into other products in 9 subsequent reactions.</s><s>These reactions produce 3-hydroxypropionic acid, acetaldehyde 10 and formaldehyde via the retro-aldol reaction <ref type="bibr">[35]</ref>, and/or propane-1,3-diol [34, 35] via 11 hydrogenation.</s><s>Propane-1,3-diol can be further dehydrated to produce propionaldehyde 12 <ref type="bibr">[35]</ref>.</s><s>13 14 2.4.3</s><s>Formation of products via 2,3-dihydroxypropanal: route C 15 2,3-dihydroxypropanal can be transformed into 2,3-dihydroxypropionic acid, 16 dehydrated to form 2-oxopropanal and/or decarbonylated to produce ethane-1,2-diol.</s><s>17</s></p><p><s>Subsequently, 2-oxopropanal can be further hydrogenated to form propane-1,2-diol. 18</s></p><p><s>Additionally, 2-hydroxyacetaldehyde can be obtained from the dehydrogenation of the 19</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Carbon distribution and global glycerol conversion 2</head><p><s>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">3</ref> displays the carbon conversion to gas and liquid (CC gas, CC liq) as well as 3 the global glycerol conversion (X gly) obtained in the experiments.</s><s>The statistical 4 analysis reveals significant differences between the results obtained in the experiments 5 for the CC gas, CC liq and X gly (p-values &lt; 0.001).</s><s>Specifically, they vary by 1-80%, 6</s></p><p><s>16-93% and 4-100%, respectively.</s><s>The effect of the operating variables on the CC sol 7</s></p><p><s>was not significant (p-value &gt; 0.05); in all the experiments the CC sol was lower than 8</s></p><p><s>1.5 %.</s><s>The evolution over time of these variables shows drops in the X gly together 9 with increases and decreases in both the CC gas and the CC liq.</s><s>These variations 10 indicate the existence of changes in the product distribution as the reaction advances 11 and/or that a catalyst deactivation may have taken place.</s><s>12 13 Significant drops in the CC gas occurred in experiments 6, 8, 12, 16, 22, 24, 26 and 28, 14 which were conducted at temperatures higher than 220 ºC and where initially relatively 15 high amounts of CC gas (&gt;20 %) were obtained.</s><s>In addition, the greatest drops for this 16 variable are observed for the experiments employing W/m glycerol ratios higher than 25 g 17 catalyst min/g glycerol.</s><s>This variation is particularly marked for experiments 12 and 16, 18</s></p><p><s>where the highest temperature (240 ºC), pressure (50 bar) and W/m glycerol ratio (40 g 19 catalyst min/g glycerol) were employed.</s><s>These two experiments display both the 20 highest initial CC gas (greater than 65%) and the biggest drop in this variable.</s><s>The X 21 gly remained constant over time while an increase in the CC liq is observed for both 22 experiments.</s><s>23  production of gases is highly favoured during the first reaction steps due to a substantial 7 extension of all the reactions involved in the process: cracking and reforming reactions 8 of glycerol, reactions to produce intermediate liquids as well as all the reforming 9 reactions of these intermediates towards gas production.</s><s>This is consistent with the 10 work of <ref type="bibr">Wawrzetz et al. [23]</ref>, which demonstrated that the formation of H 2 and CO 2 via 11 dehydrogenation followed by decarbonylation with the subsequent water gas shift is one 12 of the fastest reactions in this process.</s><s>The progressive deactivation of the catalyst over 13 time could lead to the reforming reactions occurring to a lesser extent, decreasing the 14 CC gas and augmenting the CC liq <ref type="bibr">[23]</ref>.</s><s>These trends also apply to experiments 6 and 8.  employed.</s><s>High W/m glycerol ratios and elevated temperatures might favour the initial 2 formation of gases and consequently the drop observed in the gas production over time 3 is sharper.</s><s>These phenomena were also observed by El <ref type="bibr">Doukkali et al. [37]</ref>, who 4 reported a decrease and an increase over time in the production of gas and liquid 5 products, respectively, due to the progressive deactivation of the catalyst when 6 employing a Ni/Al 2 O 3 catalyst for the APR of glycerol.</s><s>This deactivation was the 7 consequence of the transformation of the alumina of the support into boehmite <ref type="bibr">[37]</ref>.</s><s>8 9 Conversely, when lower W/m glycerol ratios are employed (25 g catalyst min/g glycerol), 10 the drop in the CC gas is less pronounced (experiments 24 and 26).</s><s>In these conditions, 11 the production of intermediate liquid products is more favoured than the formation of 12 gases, as the amount of catalyst in the bed is not high enough for their complete 13 transformation to gases.</s><s>Lower initial amounts of CC gas are obtained compared with 14 experiments using higher W/m glycerol ratios.</s><s>The CC liq remains steady over time and a 15 smaller decrease in the CC gas occurs.</s><s>16 17</s></p><p><s>The CC liq displays increases and decreases over time.</s><s>Increases occur in experiments 18 6, 12 and 16.</s><s>These trends have been explained above for the evolution of the CC gas 19 over time.</s><s>Decreases over time are observed for experiments 1, 2, 3, 21, 22, 24 and 27, 20 which were conducted with W/m glycerol ratios from 10 to 25 g catalyst min/g glycerol 21 and glycerol concentrations lower than 30 wt.%.</s><s>Additionally, the temperature exerts a 22 significant influence on the evolution of the CC liq with time.</s><s>The lower the 23 21 drops were observed for the experiments conducted at 200 ºC <ref type="bibr">(1, 3, 13 and 21</ref>).</s><s>An 1 increase in the W/m glycerol ratio exerts an effect on the kinetic of the process, increasing 2 the reaction rate of reactions leading to the formation of liquid products.</s><s>This 3 circumstance can partially compensate for the deactivation of the catalyst, as can be 4</s></p><p><s>observed comparing experiments 1 with 9 and 3 with 11. 5 6</s></p><p><s>The evolution of the X gly over time displays significant decreases for experiments 1-5, 7 9, 11, 13, 15, 21 and 27.</s><s>These drops can be accounted for by the use of either a low 8 temperature or a low W/m glycerol ratio.</s><s>Experiments 1-5 were conducted with the lowest 9 W/m glycerol ratio employed in this work (10 g catalyst min/g glycerol).</s><s>Here neither the 10 temperature nor the pressure exerts a significant influence on the X gly evolution with 11 time.</s><s>Conversely, for the same conditions of temperature and pressure but employing a 12 W/m glycerol ratio of 40 g catalyst min/g glycerol (runs 9-13), drops over time were only 13 appreciated at 200 ºC (runs 9, 1, 13 and 15).</s><s>These results seem to indicate that the 14 catalyst deactivation could be more favoured at a low temperature and/or that the 15 positive kinetic effect of the temperature is able to partially compensate for catalyst 16 deactivation.</s><s>17 18 Very interestingly, it is observed that an increase in the glycerol concentration 19 diminishes the deactivation of the catalyst, especially at low temperatures.</s><s>Comparing 20 the experiments conducted with low (1-4) and high (5-8) glycerol concentrations, a 21 higher decrease in the evolution of the X gly over time takes place for the former than 22 for the latter.</s><s>This result indicates that the greater the amount of water, the greater the 23 catalyst deactivation.</s><s>Under the operating conditions of the APR process, the alumina of the catalyst support can be transformed into boehmite by water.</s><s>This transformation is 1 enhanced employing high water concentrations, which might cause the catalyst 2 deactivation to be greater <ref type="bibr">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr">24,</ref><ref type="bibr">37]</ref>.</s><s>3 4 To corroborate this hypothesis, the spent catalysts for runs 3 and 4 (10 wt.% glycerol) 5 and 7 and 8 (50 wt.% glycerol) were characterised by XRD and TG analyses.</s><s>loss occurs for runs 3 and 4 (conducted using a 10 wt.% glycerol solution) than for 7 22 and 8 (conducted using a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solution).</s><s>The greatest differences in terms 23 of mass loss between the former and the latter occur between 166 and 362 ºC, which 24 indicates the greater presence of physisorbed water in the structure of the catalyst along 23 with a larger transformation of the alumina of the support into boehmite during the APR 1 reaction.</s><s>This accounts for the higher deactivation observed with the 10 wt.% than with 2 the 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solutions.</s><s><ref type="table">4</ref>. The CC gas is strongly affected by the temperature, the 1 W/m glycerol ratio and an interaction between these two variables.</s><s>An increase in these 2 two variables increases the CC gas.</s><s>The temperature, glycerol concentration, W/m glycerol 3 ratio and their interactions are the operating variables with the greatest effect on the CC 4 liq.</s><s>For this variable some quadratic terms of the temperature exert a high influence, 5 which indicates the existence of maxima and minima within the range of temperatures 6 considered in this work.</s><s>The glycerol conversion is greatly affected by the temperature, 7 the W/m glycerol ratio and the interaction between these two variables.</s><s>The CC sol was 8 lower than 1.5 % in all cases and the effect of the operating variables on the CC sol is 9 not significant with 95% confidence.</s><s><ref type="bibr">10 11</ref> Significant interactions between the operating variables also influence the CC gas, CC 12 liq and X gly, as can be appreciated from the models displayed in Table <ref type="table">4</ref>. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">5</ref> 13 illustrates the effect of these interactions according to the ANOVA analysis.</s><s>Figures 5 a 14</s></p><p><s>and b, e and f, and i and j show the effects on the CC gas, CC liq and X gly of the 15 reaction temperature, employing a pressure of 38 bar for W/m glycerol ratios of 10 and 40 16 g catalyst min/g glycerol, when feeding 10 and 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solutions, respectively.</s><s>17</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.1">Carbon conversion to gas: CC gas 1</head><p><s>The CC gas is mainly affected by the temperature and W/m glycerol ratio.</s><s>An increase in 2 these two variables augments the CC gas due to the positive kinetic effect that both 3 variables exert on the process <ref type="bibr">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr">19,</ref><ref type="bibr">21,</ref><ref type="bibr">23,</ref><ref type="bibr">24]</ref>.</s><s>At low temperatures, the production 4 of gas is not favoured, since reforming and cracking reactions are not predominant.</s><s>The 5 prevailing chemical reactions lead to the formation of intermediate liquid products, 6 since their formation is prevalent under low glycerol conversions <ref type="bibr">[23]</ref>.</s><s>Thus, between 7 200 and 220 ºC the CC gas is always lower than 30%, and the positive kinetic effect of 8 the temperature within this temperature range is relatively low.</s><s>Conversely, a further 9 increase in temperature up to 240 ºC increases the CC gas very sharply, especially when 10 using a W/m glycerol ratio of 40 g catalyst min/g glycerol, which permits the CC gas to 11 reach 80% in some cases.</s><s>Under this temperature range, reforming and cracking 12 reactions of both glycerol and its intermediate liquid products might be more favoured.</s><s>13 14</s></p><p><s>The effect of the temperature also depends on the W/m glycerol ratio.</s><s>This variable 15 positively influences the CC gas due to its positive kinetic effect on cracking and 16 reforming reactions.</s><s>The higher the W/m glycerol ratio, the greater is the increase in the 17 CC gas with temperature.</s><s>This effect is especially marked when the highest value for 18 this variable is employed (40 g catalyst min/g glycerol).</s></p><p><s>Table <ref type="table">4</ref>. Relative influence of the operating conditions on the CC gas, CC liq and X gly according to the ANOVA analysis for the first hour of 1 reaction.</s><s>that the effect of the pressure is only significant at high temperatures.</s><s>For a 10 wt.% 9 glycerol solution, an increase in pressure from 38 to 50 bar only increases the CC gas 10 for a W/m glycerol ratio of 40 g catalyst min/g glycerol when using temperatures higher 11 than 220 ºC.</s><s>Conversely, when 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol is used, the same increment in 12 pressure only exerts a significant influence on the CC gas at temperatures higher than 13 220 and employing a low spatial velocity (10 g catalyst min/g glycerol).</s><s>In both cases, 14 the effect of pressure is only significant when gas production is favoured.</s><s>The pressure 15 exerts a significant influence on the kinetics of the process, since an increase in the total 1 pressure of the system also increases the partial pressures of glycerol and its 2 intermediates.</s><s>This produces an increase in the reaction rates and consequently makes 3 the effect of the glycerol concentration significant.</s><s>4 5</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">2 3 4 R 2 Indep.. T P C W T•P T•C T•W P•C P•W C•W T 2 P 2 C 2 W 2 T•P• C T•P• W T•C• W P•C• W T 2 •P T 2 •C T 2 •W T•P 2</formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">= Indep. + Coefficient T•T + Coefficient P•P + Coefficient C•C + Coefficient W•W + Coefficient T•C•T•C + Coefficient T•W•T•W + Coefficient P•C•P•C + Coefficient P•W•P•W + Coefficient C•W•C•W + Coefficient T 2 •T 2 + Coefficient P 2 •P 2 + Coefficient C 2 •C 2 + Coefficient W 2 •W 2 + Coefficient T•P•C•T•P•C + Coefficient T•P•W•T•P•W + Coefficient T•C•W•T•C•W + Coefficient P•C•W•P•C•W + Coefficient T 2 •P T 2 •P + Coefficient T 2 •C T 2 •C + Coefficient T 2 •W T 2 •W + Coefficient T•P 2 •T•P 2 + Coefficient T•P•C•W•T•P•C•W.</formula><p><s>The increase in the glycerol partial pressure when the total pressure of the system is 6 increased is lower for a 10 wt.% glycerol solution than for 50 wt.%.</s><s>For a 10 wt.% 7 solution this effect is only observed employing high W/m glycerol ratios, while for a 50 8 wt.% solution the increase in the CC gas only occurs for low W/m glycerol ratios.</s><s>Under 9 high pressure, the increase in the glycerol partial pressure is higher and the positive 10 kinetic effect of the W/m glycerol ratio can mask the effect of the increase in the partial 11 pressure.</s><s>Consequently, this circumstance is only observed for low W/m glycerol ratios.</s><s>An 12 increase in the CC gas when increasing the total pressure of the system has also been 13 reported in other works concerning the aqueous phase reforming of glycerol [15, 21, 14</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>41]. 15 16</head><p><s>The effect of the glycerol concentration can be studied comparing Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_12">5 a and b</ref> and 17 5 c and d.</s><s>An increase in the glycerol concentration from 10 to 50 wt.%</s><s>significantly 18 influences the CC gas at 240 ºC when using a W/m glycerol ratio of 10 g catalyst min/g 19 glycerol.</s><s>The CC gas is little affected by the glycerol concentration and therefore this 20 effect is only observed under low spatial time.</s><s>At high spatial time the positive kinetic 21 effect of the catalyst is higher than that of the glycerol concentration.</s><s>Additionally, the 22 increase in the CC gas when the glycerol concentration increases is greater at 50 than at 23</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2">Carbon conversion to liquid products: CC liq 2</head><p><s>The temperature exerts two different effects on the CC liq depending on the glycerol 3 concentration.</s><s>For a 10 wt.% solution, in most cases the CC liq increases between 200 4 and 220 ºC and drops with a further increase in the temperature to between 220 and 240 5 ºC.</s><s>The temperature exerts a kinetic effect on the process, augmenting the reaction rates 6 of the reactions involved.</s><s>At low temperatures (200-220 ºC) the positive kinetic effect 7 helps to shift the reaction towards the formation of intermediate liquids, increasing the 8 CC liq.</s><s>Conversely, a further increase in temperature up to 240 ºC favours the 9 transformation of these liquid products into gases, decreasing the CC liq.</s><s>These results 10 are in accordance with the reaction pathway of the process [6, 7, 21, 23, 34-36] and with 11 the experimental observations reported in the work of <ref type="bibr">Wawrzetz et al. [23]</ref>, where the 12 proportions of gas and liquid products augmented and dropped, respectively, as the 13 glycerol conversion increased.</s><s>An increase in the W/m glycerol ratio from 10 to 40 g 14 catalyst min/g glycerol increases the CC liq between 200 and 210 ºC, where the 15 formation of liquid products is more favoured, while at temperatures higher than 210 ºC 16 it decreases the CC liq, as the catalyst favours the production of gas from glycerol and 17 its intermediate products.</s><s>18 19 For a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solution, the CC liq generally diminishes with temperatures 20 between 200 and 220 ºC and increases between 220 and 240 ºC.</s><s>When a concentrated 21 glycerol solution is employed, the partial pressure of the organics inside the reactor 22 increases, and gas formation is more favoured, especially when using a W/m glycerol ratio 23 of 40 g catalyst min/g glycerol.</s><s>Thus, under these conditions an increase in temperature 30 increase in temperature up to 240 ºC increases the CC liq.</s><s>This phenomenon will be 1 further described below when explaining the effect of the total pressure.</s><s>The effect of 2 the W/m glycerol ratio displays the same trends as described for a 10 wt.% glycerol 3 solution.</s><s>4 5 A comparison between Figures 5 e and f and 5 g and h illustrates the effect of the 6 glycerol concentration.</s><s>An increase in the glycerol concentration from 10 to 50 wt.%</s><s>7 increases the partial pressure of the organics inside the reactor, increasing the reaction 8 rate of the reactions involved in the process.</s><s>At low temperatures (200-210 ºC), where 9 liquid formation is favoured, an increase in the glycerol concentration increases the CC 10 liq, while at high temperatures (210-230 ºC), where the formation of gases becomes 11 predominant, the CC liq decreases.</s><s>A rise in the CC liq is observed between 230 and 12 240 ºC, especially for low W/m glycerol ratios.</s><s>This is a consequence of an increase in the 13 global glycerol conversion due to the increase in the partial pressure of the organics 14 inside the reactor and will be discussed when explaining the evolution of the X gly.</s><s>15 16</s></p><p><s>The influence of the pressure can be gathered comparing Figures 5 e and g and 5 f and 17 h.</s><s>The effect of the pressure on the CC liq is related to the glycerol concentration.</s><s>For a 18 10 wt.% solution, an increase in the pressure from 38 to 50 bar has different effects 19 depending on the temperature.</s><s>Between 210 and 230 ºC, where the formation of liquid 20 products is favoured, an increase in the CC liq occurs with an increase in the total 21 pressure.</s><s>Between 230 and 240 ºC the CC liq decreases due to gas formation.</s><s>These 22 results mean that at low temperature (200 ºC) liquid production is favoured under low 23 pressure (38 bar).</s><s>At medium temperature (220 ºC) liquid production is enhanced at 24 31 occurs within the whole range of pressure when the greatest amount of catalyst is used 1 (Wm glycerol = 40 g catalyst min/g glycerol).</s><s>Conversely, for a W/m glycerol ratio of 10 g 2 catalyst min/g glycerol, liquid production is favoured at low pressure (38 bar).</s><s>3 4 When a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solution is employed, the same increase in pressure decreases 5 the CC liq from 200 to 220 ºC and increases it from 220 to 240 ºC.</s><s>This increment is 6 related to an increase in glycerol conversion.</s><s>At 220 ºC the CC liq is greater at 50 than 7 at 38 bar for a W/m glycerol ratio of 40 g catalyst min/g glycerol.</s><s>The effect of the pressure 8 is not significant under the following conditions: at 240 ºC regardless of the W/m glycerol 9 ratio; and at 220 ºC when using a W/m glycerol ratio of 10 g catalyst min/g glycerol.</s><s>10 11</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.3">Global glycerol conversion: X gly 12</head><p><s>The global glycerol conversion is greatly affected by the reaction temperature especially 13 when using a W/m glycerol ratio of 10 g catalyst min/ g glycerol.</s><s>An increase in 14 temperature between 200 and 220 ºC leads to an increase in glycerol conversion.</s><s>The 15 endothermicity of the aqueous phase reforming and the fact that the reaction rates of all 16 the reactions involved in the process are intensified with temperature [14, 19, 21, 23, 17 24] accounts for this finding.</s><s>Within this temperature range, the lower the W/m glycerol 18 ratio, the higher is the increase in the conversion with temperature.</s><s>These results 19 indicate that the effect of the temperature is kinetically less important than the 20 W/m glycerol ratio and that the catalyst is active even at low temperatures.</s><s>A further 21 increase in temperature up to 240 ºC produces different tendencies depending on the 22 glycerol concentration.</s><s>For a 10 wt.% solution, an increase in the temperature has two 23 effects.</s><s>On the one hand, employing 10 g glycerol min/g catalyst, the X gly drops with the temperature.</s><s>This low spatial time is insufficient for achieving the production of the 1 H 2 needed for the extension of the hydrogenation reactions of the liquid intermediates. 2</s></p><p><s>This accounts for the drop in the CC liq and the small increase in the CC gas that takes 3 place under these conditions.</s><s>On the other hand, when a spatial time of 40 g glycerol 4 min/g catalyst is used, the X gly slightly increases with temperature.</s><s>These results are in 5 agreement with the high increase in the CC gas observed between 220 and 240 ºC.</s><s>6 7 Interestingly, the drop in the X gly disappears when a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solution is fed 8 in the reactor.</s><s>Between 220 and 240 ºC the X gly is very high and does not depend on 9 the temperature.</s><s>Additionally, the effect of the W/m glycerol ratio on the X gly becomes 10 insignificant, indicating that it is possible to achieve high conversions with the lowest 11 amount of catalyst employed.</s><s>This increase in the glycerol concentration increases the 12 partial pressure of all the organic species inside the reactor, raising the reaction rate of 13 the reactions involved in the process.</s><s>14 15</s></p><p><s>The effect of the total pressure depends on the temperature.</s><s>At low temperatures (200-16 220 ºC) where gas formation is not preferential, an increase in the total pressure of the 17 system results in a drop in the X gly.</s><s>This decrease is the consequence of the drop in the 18 CC liq with pressure under this temperature range.</s><s>Since the process is not shifted 19 towards gas production, the negative effect of the pressure on the CC liq is greater than 20 the positive effect on the CC gas, resulting in a drop in the global conversion (X gly).</s><s>21 This phenomenon is not observed between 220 and 240 ºC because the gas production 22 is preferential.</s><s>23</s></p><p><s>Other authors have also reported the different effects that pressure can have on the 1 global glycerol conversion.</s><s>This is explained by having used different temperatures, 2 glycerol concentrations, catalysts and/or spatial velocities.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Manfro et al. and Roy et al. 3 [19,</ref><ref type="bibr">21]</ref> reported an increase in glycerol conversion with pressure, while Wawrzetz et 4 al.</s><s><ref type="bibr">[23]</ref> found that the pressure had a significant effect on the liquid product distribution 5 without affecting the global glycerol conversion.</s><s>6 7</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Effect of the operating conditions on the volumetric composition of the gas 8</head><p><s>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">6</ref> shows the composition of the gas obtained for the different experiments 9 divided into three intervals of 60 minutes each.</s><s>The gas phase is made up of a mixture 10 of H 2 (8-55 vol.%),</s><s>CO 2 (33-73 vol.%),</s><s>CO (0-4 vol.%) and CH 4 (6-44 vol.%).</s><s>The 11 ANOVA analysis reveals significant differences between experiments and time 12 intervals (p-values &lt; 0.05).</s><s>As regards the evolution of the gas composition over time, 13 statistically significant increases and decreases are detected for the proportions of both 14 The specific effects of the operating conditions as well as their possible interactions on 1 the volumetric composition of the gas were studied considering the results obtained 2 during the first 60 minutes of reaction.</s><s>Table <ref type="table">5</ref> shows the results of the statistical 3 analyses performed.</s><s>This analysis shows that the glycerol concentration and the 4 pressure-temperature and glycerol concentration-temperature interactions are the 5 operating variables with the greatest influence on the proportion of H 2 in the gas.</s><s>The 6 temperature is the operating variable with the greatest influence on the proportion of 7 CO 2 .</s><s>The interactions of the glycerol concentration with the W/m glycerol ratio and the 8 temperature also exert a significant influence on this gas, although their relative 9 importance is lower.</s><s>The concentration of CO in the gas is mostly affected by the 10 W/m glycerol ratio and the following interactions: temperature-W/m glycerol ratio, W/m glycerol 11 ratio-glycerol concentration and temperature-pressure.</s><s>The W/m glycerol ratio, the glycerol 12 concentration and its interaction with temperature substantially influence the relative 13 amount of CH 4 in the gas.</s><s>14 15 Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">7</ref> illustrates the effect of these interactions according to the ANOVA analysis.</s><s>16</s></p><p><s>The effects of the reaction temperature, at 38 bar and 50 bar for W/m glycerol ratios of 10 17 and 40 g catalyst min/g glycerol, feeding a 10 wt.% glycerol concentration, are shown 18 in Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">7 a and b, e and f, i and j</ref>, and m and n.</s><s>Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">7 c and d, g and h, k and l</ref>, 19 and o and p display the effect of the temperature and the W/m glycerol ratio at 38 and 50 20 bar for a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solution.</s></p><p><s>Table <ref type="table">5</ref>.</s><s>Relative influence of the operating conditions on the composition of the gas and liquid phases according to the ANOVA analysis for the</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_2">1 first hour of reaction. 2 3 R 2 Indep.. T P C W T•P T•C T•W P•C P•W C•W T 2 P 2 C 2 W 2 T•P• C T•P• W T•C• W P•C• W T 2 •P T 2 •C T 2 •W T•P 2 T•P•C •W H2 (vol.</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">H 2 and CO 2 1</head><p><s>The reaction temperature exerts a significant influence on the concentrations of H 2 and CO 2 . 2</s></p><p><s>In general, an increase in the temperature from 200 to 240 ºC results in an increase in the H 2 3 concentration and a drop in the CO 2 concentration, as reported in other works <ref type="bibr">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr">15]</ref>.</s><s>The H 2 4 solubility in the liquid phase decreases with the temperature, diminishing the extent of the 5 hydrogenation reactions, thus augmenting the proportion of H 2 in the gas <ref type="bibr">[23]</ref>.</s><s>In addition, the 6 reforming reactions are endothermic, while the WGS reaction is exothermic, which also 7 results in an increase in H 2 and a decrease in CO 2 with the temperature.</s><s>8 9</s></p><p><s>The effect of the pressure on the proportion of these two gases depends on the glycerol 10 concentration and W/m glycerol ratio.</s><s>For a W/m glycerol ratio of 10 g catalyst min/g glycerol, an 11 increase in the total pressure of the system from 38 to 50 bar has two different effects 12 depending on the glycerol concentration.</s><s>On the one hand, when a 10 wt.% glycerol solution 13 is used, increases in the H 2 and decreases in the CO 2 concentrations take place between 200 14 and 230 ºC.</s><s>A diminution in the consumption of H 2 during the hydrogenation of the liquid 15 products might account for this increment.</s><s>Furthermore, the analysis of the liquid phase, 16 which will be discussed in detail in section 3.3, shows that this increase in pressure leads to a 17 drop in the proportion of poly-alcohols.</s><s>This depletion is the consequence of the decline in the 18 proportion of 1,2-propane-diol, which is obtained from the hydrogenation of acetol <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[42,</ref><ref type="bibr">43]</ref>.</s><s>19</s></p><p><s>This drop in the proportion of H 2 causes the relative amount of CO 2 in the gas to increase.</s><s>20 21 On the other hand, for a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solution, the same increase in pressure exerts the 22 opposite effect on the concentrations of H 2 and CO 2 .</s><s>Hydrogen solubility increases with 23 pressure, thus hydrogenation reactions in the liquid phase may be more favoured with the 1 increase in pressure for this glycerol concentration.</s><s>The higher the glycerol concentration, the 2 lower the amount of water and consequently the higher the partial pressure of H 2 .</s><s>The rise in 3 the proportion of CO 2 is basically a consequence of the decline in the proportion of H 2 in the 4</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_3">) c) d) e) f) g) h) i) j) k) l) m) n) o) p)</formula><p><s>Different effects for the total pressure have been reported in other works.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Luo et al. [24]</ref> found 1 an increase in the proportion of H 2 when increasing the pressure, while <ref type="bibr">Manfro et al. [19]</ref> and 2 Özgür and Uysal [14] reported a drop in the proportion of H 2 .</s><s>3 4 When a W/m glycerol ratio of 40 g catalyst min/g glycerol is used, an increase in pressure from 5 38 to 50 bar reduces the proportion of H 2 regardless of the glycerol concentration and 6 increases the proportion of CO 2 only for a 10 wt.% glycerol solution.</s><s>In the case of H 2 , this 7 decrease is greater when employing a 10 wt.% than a 50 wt.%</s><s>solution.</s><s>For a 10 wt.% 8 glycerol solution, the higher the pressure, the higher the solubility of H 2 in the liquid phase, 9 which might promote the hydrogenation reactions due to the high W/m glycerol ratio employed.</s><s>10 Under these conditions, an increase in the proportion of mono-alcohols in the liquid takes 11 place, ethanol being the alcohol responsible for this increment.</s><s>Ethanol is a hydrogenation 12 end product in glycerol aqueous phase reforming, which justifies that this trend is only 13 observed for a high W/m glycerol ratio.</s><s>Conversely, for a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solution little 14 variation in the proportions of H 2 and CO 2 are observed.</s><s>Under these conditions, a high 15 increase in the proportion of CH 4 takes place, indicating that CH 4 formation might be 16 favoured.</s><s>CH 4 is an end product in glycerol aqueous phase reforming.</s><s>It can be formed by an 17 initial hydrogenation of ethane-1,2-diol to produce ethanol, which undergoes posterior 18 dehydrogenation to produce CH 4 .</s><s>These reactions explain the increase in the proportion of 19 CH 4 and the steady evolution of H 2 .</s><s>20 21</s></p><p><s>The greatest effect of the W/m glycerol ratio on the concentrations of H 2 and CO 2 occurs when a 22 10 wt.% glycerol solution is fed.</s><s>This effect depends on the total pressure.</s><s>For 38 bar, an 23 increase in the W/m glycerol ratio from 10 to 40 g catalyst min/g glycerol increases the H 2 and 1 decreases the CO 2 .</s><s>This increase in the H 2 concentration was also reported in the work of Luo 2 et al. <ref type="bibr">[24]</ref>, conducted at relatively low pressure (25 bar).</s><s>Conversely, an increase in the 3 pressure up to 50 bar has the opposite effect, although little variation occurs for the proportion 4 of CO 2 in the gas.</s><s>An increase in the W/m glycerol favours reforming reactions, increasing the 5 H 2 production.</s><s>When a total pressure of 50 bar is used, the partial pressure of H 2 could be 6 high enough to carry out hydrogenation reactions in the liquid phase, reactions that are 7 promoted with the increase in the W/m glycerol ratio.</s><s>These phenomena lead to a decrease in the 8 proportion of H 2 .</s><s>Conversely, hydrogenation reactions might take place to lesser extent at 38 9 bar due to the lower H 2 partial pressure.</s><s>An increase in the W/m glycerol ratio increases the 10 concentration of H 2 in the gas.</s><s>11 12 A multivariate analysis by means of Spearman´s test was conducted to find evidence for the 13 relationship between the concentrations of H 2 and CO 2 in the gas.</s><s>The relationship between 14 the two gases was found to be statistically significant (p-value=0.0001)</s><s>and direct (R 2 =0.89).</s><s>15 16</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.2">CO and CH 4 17</head><p><s>During the aqueous phase reforming of glycerol, CO is mainly obtained from cracking and 18 decarbonylation reactions <ref type="bibr">[23]</ref>.</s><s>Under the temperatures studied in this work, the water gas 19 shift (WGS) reaction is shifted towards H 2 and CO 2 , which explains the low proportion of CO 20 in the gas.</s><s>The temperature has two different effects on the concentration of CO depending 21 on the W/m glycerol used.</s><s>For 10 g catalyst min/g glycerol, an increase in temperature increases 22 the proportion of CO, while for 40 g catalyst min/g glycerol the effect of the temperature is 1 lower and it is only significant for low glycerol concentrations (10 wt.%). 2 3</s></p><p><s>The pressure exerts a weak effect on the concentration of CO, being statistically significant 4 only for a high glycerol concentration (50 wt.%) when a W/m glycerol ratio of 10 g catalyst 5 min/g glycerol is used.</s><s>Under these conditions, an increase in pressure reduces the proportion 6 of CO in the gas.</s><s>An increase in the W/m glycerol ratio from 10 to 40 g catalyst min/g glycerol 7 causes the relative amount of CO in the gas to drop, especially at temperatures between 220 8 and 240 ºC where CO production can be intensified by decarbonylation and WGS reactions 9 occur to a lesser extent.</s><s><ref type="bibr">10 11</ref> In general, an increase in temperature provokes a decrease in the relative amount of CH 4 .</s><s>This 12 drop is the consequence of the exothermic character of the methanation reaction <ref type="bibr">[15]</ref>.</s><s>13</s></p><p><s>Conversely, when a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol concentration and a W/m glycerol ratio of 40 g catalyst 14 min/g glycerol are employed, the proportion of CH 4 with temperature increases sharply.</s><s>This 15 increase might be caused by acetaldehyde decarbonylation, as was previously explained for 16 the concentration of H 2 .</s><s>17 18 An increase in the total pressure between 38 and 50 bar increases the proportion of CH 4 in the 19 gas.</s><s>This increase can have a thermodynamic background as the pressure shifts CH 4 formation 20 through the methanation reaction.</s><s>As an exception, it is observed that this increase does not 21 occur between 200 and 230 ºC when a 10 wt.% glycerol solution and a W/m glycerol ratio of 10 22 g catalyst min/g glycerol were used, conditions at which a reduction in the concentration of 23 CH 4 occurs.</s><s>This decrease is the consequence of the high increase in the concentration of H 2 1 in the gas, as previously explained.</s><s>This rise in H 2 diminishes the formation of acetaldehyde, 2 which leads to a decrease in the proportion of CH 4 in the gas.</s><s>In the vast majority of cases, an 3 increase in the W/m glycerol ratio increases the concentration of CH 4 .</s><s>4 5</s></p><p><s>The effect of the glycerol concentration on the concentration of CH 4 depends on the 6 temperature and the W/m glycerol ratio.</s><s>Between 200 and 220 ºC at high pressure and employing 7 a low W/m glycerol ratio, an increase in the glycerol concentration increases the proportion of 8 CH 4 in the gas.</s><s>Under these conditions the methanation reaction is favoured.</s><s>Conversely, for 9 a high W/m glycerol ratio and pressure, the same increase in the glycerol concentration decreases 10 the proportion of CH 4 in the gas.</s><s>An increase in the W/m glycerol ratio increases the reaction 11 rates of the reactions in the liquid phase.</s><s>This shifts the process towards the production of 12 liquid end products, such as acetaldehyde, which can be converted into CH 4 by 13 decarbonylation <ref type="bibr">[23]</ref>.</s><s>14 15 as 2-propanone (acetone) and 2-propanone-1-hydroxy, C4-ketones (2-butanone-3-hydroxy 23 and 2-butanone-1-hydroxy) and cyclic ketones.</s><s>Acetaldehyde is the most abundant compound 1 for the aldehydes, while the carboxylic acids are mainly made up of acetic and propionic 2 acids.</s><s>The presence of these compounds in the condensates is consistent with the pathway 3 proposed in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref> and those proposed by several authors <ref type="bibr">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr">7,</ref><ref type="bibr">21,</ref><ref type="bibr">23,</ref><ref type="bibr">[34]</ref><ref type="bibr">[35]</ref><ref type="bibr">[36]</ref>. Glycerol 4 monoacetate is the most abundant ester compound, indicating that esterification reactions can 5 also take place under some operating conditions.</s><s>6 7</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Effect of the operating conditions on the composition of the liquid phase 16</head><p><s>The statistical analysis reveals significant differences (p-values&lt;0.005) in the relative 8 amounts of these compounds in the liquid phase.</s><s>The results of the Fisher´s LSD test are 9 plotted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_18">8</ref>.</s><s>The relative concentration for these compounds, expressed as relative 10 chromatographic area, varies as follows.</s><s>Monohydric alcohols: 4-47%, polyhydric-alcohols: 11 14-68%, carboxylic acids: 2-43%, aldehydes: 0-5%, C3-ketones: 2-33%, C4-ketones: 0-10 %, 12 cyclic-ketones: 0-6% and esters: 0-46%.</s><s>Increases and decreases in the proportions of these 13 families with time are detected.</s><s>The highest variations occur for aldehydes, polyhydric 14 alcohols, C3-ketones and esters.</s><s>These variations have been analysed with the multivariate 15 Spearman´s test to find significant relationships between the increases and decreases of the 16 families of compounds with time.</s><s>17  Aldehydes show increases with time for runs 8 and 16.</s><s>The increases take place along with 1 decreases with time in the CC gas and increases in the CC liq or X gly.</s><s>According to the 2 pathway shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>, aldehydes are end products of glycerol aqueous phase reforming; 3 therefore, their proportions increase as the X gly increases.</s><s>Conversely, the proportion of 4 aldehydes drops with time for runs 2, 4, 9, 12, 14, 23, 24, 26 and 28.</s><s>These decays occur 5 along with decreases in the relative amount of monohydric alcohols (runs 23, 24, 26 and 28) 6 together with increases in the proportion of esters (runs 2, 4, 9, 14 and 28) or polyhydric 7 alcohols (runs 23, 24, 26 and 28).</s><s>The multivariate analysis reveals significant relationships 8 for the proportions of aldehydes with the proportions of carboxylic acids (p-value = 0.002; R 2 9 = 0.33), monohydric alcohols (p-value = 0.0001; R 2 = 0.57) and esters (p-value = 0.0001; R 2 10 = 0.48).</s><s>In addition, the proportion of carboxylic acids depends on the proportion of 11 monohydric alcohols (p-value = 0.0001; R 2 = 0.55) and polyhydric alcohols (p-value = 12 0.0001; R 2 = 0.44).</s><s>These relationships confirm the pathway shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2</ref>. 13 14</s></p><p><s>The proportions of carboxylic acids in the condensate remain steady over time for the vast 15 majority of the experiments.</s><s>Runs 1, 17 and 23 display a mild increase with time, while drops 16 can be observed for runs 8 and 27.</s><s>The multivariate analysis reveals a significant relationship 17 between the relative amount of monohydric and polyhydric alcohols and carboxylic acids.</s><s>18</s></p><p><s>This relationship explains the experimental trend since 1,2-propane-diol and ethanol are 19 intermediate compounds for acetic acid production.</s><s>20</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>21</head><p><s>The relative amount of monohydric alcohols shows decreases for runs 9, 22, 23, 24, 26 and 22 28.</s><s>These drops occur at the same time as increases in the proportion of polyhydric alcohols 23 and decreases in the proportion of aldehydes (runs 9, 22, 23, 24, 26 and 28).</s><s>Polyhydric 24 alcohols display increases (runs 6, 8, 22, 23, 24, 26, 27 and 28) and decreases (runs 1, 2, 3, 9, 1 10, 11, 13, 15, 17, 21 and 25) with time.</s><s>In general, the increases occur together with 2 decreases in the proportion of monohydric alcohols.</s><s>Exceptionally, this decrease is not 3 observed for experiments 6 and 27.</s><s>These trends are in concordance with the multivariate 4 analysis (p-value = 0.05; R 2 = 0.20).</s><s>However, although the relationship is significant, it is 5 not strongly direct, which indicates that this drop is more related to the drop observed in the 6 proportion of aldehydes.</s><s>This result suggests that the limiting step for the production of 7 ethanol is the dehydration of ethane-1,2-diol to produce acetaldehyde.</s><s>In general, increases in 8 the proportion of esters occur together with decreases in the relative amount of polyhydric 9 alcohols (p-value = 0.0002; R 2 = 0.40).</s><s><ref type="bibr">10 11</ref> The variations over time for the relative amount of ketones and esters in the liquid are scarce.</s><s>12 C3-ketones exhibit decreases with time for runs 2, 3, 4, 6, 11, 16, 17, 22 and 25, while 13 increases were not detected.</s><s>The multivariate analysis indicates a relationship between the 14 proportion of C3-ketones and monohydric alcohols in the liquid (p-value = 0.0004; R 2 = 15 0.38).</s><s>This relationship is not strongly direct, which is consistent with the intermediate 16 condition that ketones have in the aqueous phase reforming process of glycerol, participating 17 in a great number of reactions.</s><s>The relative amount of C4-ketones and cyclic-ketones in the 18 liquid is low and steady, as they are not major products in the process.</s><s>Increases in the 19 relative amount of esters, coinciding with increases in the proportion of carboxylic acids, take 20 place in some experiments, as explained above.</s><s>21</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>22</head><p><s>The specific effects of the operating conditions as well as all the interactions between the 23 variables on the liquid composition have been studied considering the results obtained during 24 the first 60 minutes of reaction.</s><s>Table <ref type="table">5</ref> shows the significant terms in the codec model and 1 their relative influence in the process according to the ANOVA analysis.</s><s>The reaction 2 temperature is the operating variable with the greatest influence for the relative amount of 3 aldehydes in the liquid.</s><s>The glycerol concentration and the interaction temperature-W/m glycerol 4 ratio exert the greatest influence on the proportion of carboxylic acids.</s><s>Monohydric alcohols 5 are strongly influenced by the temperature, glycerol concentration and W/m glycerol ratio; while 6 the temperature and the interaction temperature-W/m glycerol ratio greatly influence the relative 7 amount of polyhydric alcohols.</s><s>The proportions of ketones and esters mainly depend on the 8 temperature and the glycerol concentration, respectively.</s><s>The temperature exerts a low 9 influence on the relative amount of C3-ketones, the glycerol concentration-W/m glycerol ratio 10 interaction being more influential for this family of ketones.</s><s>11</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>12</head><p><s>To gain a deeper understanding of the influence of the operating variables and the interactions 13 on the proportion of the most important liquid families, Figures 9 illustrates the effect of these 14 interactions according to the ANOVA analysis for the proportions of carboxylic acids, 15 monohydric and polyhydric alcohols, and aldehydes.</s><s>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_25">10</ref> displays these effects for the 16 proportions of C3, C4 and cyclic ketones, and esters.</s><s>Specifically, the effects of the reaction 17 temperature, employing a pressure of 38 bar for W/m glycerol ratios of 10 and 40 g catalyst 18 min/g glycerol, feeding glycerol concentrations of 10 and 50 wt.%,</s><s>are shown in Figures 9 19 and 10 a and b, e and f, i and j, and m and n.</s><s>Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_25">9 and 10 c and d, g and h, k and l, and o</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.1">Carboxylic acids 6</head><p><s>Acetic and propionic acids are the most abundant carboxylic acids in the liquid phase.</s><s>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">7</ref> 2 shows that acetic acid is produced through routes B and C, while propionic acid is formed 8 through route A. Propionic acid formation occurs to a lesser extent due to the higher 9 proportion of 1-hydroxypropan-2-one hydrogenated compounds than dehydrated compounds 10 in the liquid.</s><s>The temperature exhibits two different effects on the proportion of carboxylic acids 1 depending on the other operating conditions (pressure, W/m glycerol ratio and glycerol 2 concentration) due to the interaction of these variables with the temperature.</s><s>When a 10 wt.% 3 glycerol solution is fed to the reactor, two different trends are found depending on the 4 W/m glycerol ratio.</s><s>For 10 g catalyst min/ g glycerol, an increase in temperature between 200 5 and 240 ºC does not have a statistically significant influence on the relative amount of this 6 family of compounds.</s><s>Conversely, when a W/m glycerol ratio of 40 g catalyst min/g glycerol is 7 used, this same increment in temperature causes the proportion of carboxylic acids to 8 increase.</s><s>Under these conditions, an increase in the W/m glycerol ratio from 10 to 40 g catalyst 9 min/g glycerol decreases the proportion of carboxylic acids.</s><s>Acetic acid is present in the 10 crude glycerol solution as an impurity; therefore, an increase in the amount of catalyst favours 11 its decomposition.</s><s>However, as the temperature increases, the reaction rate of acetic acid 12 formation from glycerol could be higher than its rate of decomposition, leading to an increase 13 in the proportion of acetic acid and thus augmenting the relative amount of carboxylic acids in 14 the liquid.</s><s>This formation-transformation scenario might make the effect of the temperature 15 insignificant when employing a low W/m glycerol ratio (10 g catalyst min/g glycerol) due to the 16 compensatory effect of these two developments.</s><s>At a low temperature this W/m glycerol ratio is 17 not high enough for the decomposition of acetic acid to take place.</s><s>18 19</s></p><p><s>In general, similar interactions and trends as those described for a 10 wt.% glycerol solution 20 are apparent when feeding a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solution, although they are more appreciable at 21 38 than at 50 bar.</s><s>Increasing the concentration from 10 to 50 wt.%</s><s>causes the proportion of 22 carboxylic acids to decrease.</s><s>As the glycerol concentration increases, the partial pressure of 23 acetic acid also increases, enhancing its decomposition rate.</s><s>This effect is greater for the 24 lowest W/m glycerol ratio.</s><s>The greater kinetic effect of the W/m glycerol ratio masks the effect of 1 the concentration for high W/m glycerol ratios.</s><s>In addition, the effect of the W/m glycerol ratio 2 decreases when increasing the glycerol concentration.</s><s>It can be seen that for a 50 wt.% 3 solution the effect of the W/m glycerol ratio is only significant between 200-210 ºC at 38 bar, as 4 the transformation of acetic acid could be more favoured when feeding a more concentrated 5 glycerol solution.</s><s>6 7</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.2">Alcohols: monohydric and polyhydric alcohols 8</head><p><s>The compounds with the highest relative amounts in the liquid phase are alcohols, essentially 9 mono and polyhydric alcohols.</s><s>The proportion of monohydric alcohols varies between 0 and 10 45 %.</s><s>This basically corresponds to variations in ethanol, as the relative amount of methanol 11 in the liquid phase shifts from 2 to 6%.</s><s>The proportion of polyhydric alcohols increases from 12 10 to 80%.</s><s>A slightly negative proportion of monohydric alcohols is predicted under some 13 operating conditions due to the empirical character of the models.</s><s>14 15</s></p><p><s>The temperature has different influences on the proportion of monohydric and polyhydric 16 alcohols depending on the glycerol concentration, pressure and W/m glycerol ratio due to the 17 large number of interactions detected between these variables.</s><s>When a 10 wt.% glycerol 18 solution is used, an increase in temperature exerts two different effects on the proportion of 19 alcohols depending on the total pressure.</s><s>At 38 bar the proportion of monohydric alcohols 20 decreases between 200 and 220 ºC, and increases between 220 to 240 ºC, while polyhydric 21 alcohols exhibit the opposite trend (increases between 200 and 220 ºC and decreases between 22 220 and 240 ºC).</s><s>The decrease with temperature in the proportion of monohydric alcohols 23 between 200 and 220 ºC might be the consequence of fewer hydrogenation reactions of 1,2-1 ethane-diol due to the lower solubility of H 2 in the liquid phase when the temperature 2 increases.</s><s>This leads to an increase in the proportions of H 2 and polyhydric alcohols in the 3 gas and the liquid phases, respectively <ref type="bibr">[23]</ref>.</s><s>In addition, an increase in temperature shifts the 4 glycerol decomposition, which also causes an increase in the relative amount of polyhydric 5 alcohols in the liquid.</s><s>Between 220 and 240 ºC, the proportion of monohydric alcohols 6 increases while that of polyhydric alcohols drops <ref type="bibr">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr">35]</ref>.</s><s>The lesser extent of the 7 hydrogenation reactions of 1-hydroxy-2-propanone due to the lower solubility of H 2 in the 8 liquid phase, favouring route C over route A, might be responsible for this variation <ref type="bibr">[23]</ref>.</s><s>9 10 An increase in pressure up to 50 bar when feeding a 10 wt.% glycerol solution weakens the 11 effect of the temperature on the proportion of monohydric alcohols for a W/m glycerol ratio of 40 12 g catalyst min/ g glycerol.</s><s>The effect is insignificant for 10 g catalyst min/ g glycerol.</s><s>The 13 proportion of polyhydric alcohols decreases with pressure, while monohydric alcohols 14 slightly increase between 215 and 230 ºC.</s><s>The solubility of H 2 in the liquid increases with 15 pressure, favouring hydrogenation reactions.</s><s>This shifts the hydrogenation of 1,2-ethane-diol 16 to ethanol, increasing and decreasing the proportions of monohydric and polyhydric alcohols, 17 respectively.</s><s>In addition, the partial pressure of polyhydric alcohols also increases, which also 18 favours the advancement of the reactions in the liquid phase.</s><s>At high pressure, the proportion 19 of monohydric alcohols does not drop with temperature, as the positive effect of the pressure 20 can compensate for the negative effect of the temperature.</s><s>Furthermore, the increase in the 21 proportion of polyhydric alcohols between 200 and 220 is lower at 50 than at 38 bar, due to 22 their quicker transformation into other liquid intermediates.</s><s>23 When a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solution is used, an increase in temperature from 200 to 240 ºC at 1 38 bar increases and decreases the proportions of monohydric and polyhydric alcohols, 2 respectively.</s><s>This increase in the glycerol concentration increases the concentration of liquid 3 intermediates, intensifying their partial pressure inside the reactor and favouring the 4 displacement of the reactions in the liquid phase towards end products.</s><s>This causes the 5 maximum in the relative amount of polyhydric alcohols to be reached at lower temperatures 6 (220 and 200 ºC for 10 and 50 wt.%</s><s>solutions, respectively).</s><s>Therefore, under these 7 conditions, thanks to the high total pressure employed which helps to increase the partial 8 pressure of the organics in the reactor, an increase in temperature moves the process towards 9 end products, i.e. it reduces the proportion of polyhydric alcohols and increases the relative 10 amount of monohydric alcohols to their lowest and highest values, respectively.</s><s>11 12 An increase in pressure up to 50 bar for a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol concentration causes the 13 maximum in the proportion of monohydric alcohols and the minimum in polyhydric alcohols 14 to be reached at a lower temperatures (220 ºC) due to the positive effect the pressure exerts on 15 the process.</s><s>An increase in the total pressure increases the partial pressure of the organics 16 inside the reactor, favouring hydrogenation reactions.</s><s>Furthermore, a rise in the glycerol 17 concentration helps to intensify this effect.</s><s>As a consequence, an increase in temperature from 18 200 to 220 increases and decreases the proportions of monohydric and polyhydric alcohols, 19 respectively.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Wawrzetz et al. [23]</ref> found the highest proportion of polyhydric alcohols <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1,</ref><ref type="bibr">(2)</ref><ref type="bibr">(3)</ref><ref type="bibr">(4)</ref><ref type="bibr">(5)</ref><ref type="bibr">(6)</ref><ref type="bibr">(7)</ref><ref type="bibr">(8)</ref><ref type="bibr">(9)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(11)</ref><ref type="bibr">(12)</ref><ref type="bibr">(13)</ref><ref type="bibr">(14)</ref><ref type="bibr">(15)</ref><ref type="bibr">(16)</ref><ref type="bibr">(17)</ref><ref type="bibr">(18)</ref><ref type="bibr">(19)</ref><ref type="bibr">(20)</ref> propanediol and 1,2-ethanediol) in the liquid when the glycerol conversion was around 50%.</s><s>21</s></p><p><s>With the increase in the glycerol conversion the proportions of these liquids decreased while 22 the proportion of ethanol increased, which accounts for the experimental observations of this The effect of the W/m glycerol ratio exerts a weaker influence on the proportions of alcohols 1 than the other operating variables.</s><s>The greatest effect of this variable on the proportion of 2 monohydric alcohols occurs feeding a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solution at 38 bar.</s><s>Under these 3 conditions, an increase in the W/m glycerol ratio increases the proportion of monohydric 4 alcohols, helping to increase their maximum.</s><s>An increase in the W/m glycerol ratio slightly 5 increases the proportion of polyhydric alcohols for a 10 wt.% glycerol solution at 38 and 50 6 bar.</s><s>A higher amount of catalyst favours a greater spread of glycerol dehydration and 7 hydrogenation reactions.</s><s>However, the higher the pressure, the weaker is the effect of the 8 W/m glycerol ratio.</s><s>The positive kinetic effect of the pressure makes the effect of the catalyst 9 less important.</s><s>When feeding a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solution, this increase in the W/m glycerol ratio 10 also increases the proportion of polyhydric alcohols due to the decrease in the proportion of 11 the relative amount of aldehydes in the liquid.</s><s>Under these conditions, the methanation 12 reaction is favoured and an increase in the W/m glycerol ratio favours the transformation of 13 acetaldehyde into CH 4 .</s><s>14 15</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.3">Aldehydes 16</head><p><s>Acetaldehyde is the major compound of this family.</s><s>It is obtained in the final steps of route C, 17 which indicates that many reactions are involved during its production.</s><s>It can also be 18 produced in route B. 19 20</s></p><p><s>The relative amount of this compound in the liquid phase is low (0-3%), probably because it 21 is one of the end products of glycerol aqueous phase reforming and can be easily transformed 22 into gas in the final steps of the process.</s><s>An increase in temperature from 200 to 220 ºC 23 increases the proportion of this family regardless of the other operating conditions.</s><s>A 1 temperature increase within this range results in an increase in the CC liq due to the positive 2 kinetic effect of the temperature in the process, favouring the advancement of the reaction in 3 the liquid phase towards the formation of final products.</s><s>4 5 However, a further increase in temperature up to 240 ºC has different consequences 6 depending on the other operating variables.</s><s>On the one hand, for a low glycerol concentration 7 (10 wt.%), this increase in temperature slightly increases the proportion of aldehydes and the 8 effect of the W/m glycerol ratio is not significant.</s><s>On the other hand, when increasing the 9 glycerol concentration up to 50 wt.%, the same increase in the temperature exerts two 10 different effects on the proportion of aldehydes depending on the W/m glycerol ratio.</s><s>For 10 g 11 catalyst min/g glycerol, the temperature does not exert a significant influence and the 12 proportion of aldehydes remains constant, while for 40 g catalyst min/g glycerol there is a 13 drop in the proportion of aldehydes.</s><s>These differences in the evolution of the proportion of 14 aldehydes depending on the glycerol concentration could be the consequence of the different 15 partial pressure of aldehydes inside the reactor.</s><s>16 17 An increase in the glycerol concentration increases the partial pressure of aldehydes.</s><s>This 18 increase inside the reactor as the glycerol concentration increases from 10 to 50 wt.%</s><s>could 19 raise the decomposition velocity to give liquid (acetic acid and ethanol) and gaseous 20 (methane, ethane and ethylene) products.</s><s>Furthermore, an increase in the W/m glycerol ratio 21 might increase the decomposition reaction towards gases, decreasing the proportion of 22 aldehydes.</s><s>This accounts for the differences observed when using glycerol concentrations of 23 10 and 50 wt.%.</s><s>For a 10 wt.% glycerol solution, the increase in the proportion of aldehydes 1 with the temperature is small and the subsequent decay is not observed.</s><s>This is probably due 2 to the lower partial pressure of aldehydes that hinders their production and subsequent 3 transformation into end liquids and gases.</s><s>4 5</s></p><p><s>In general, high temperatures, glycerol concentrations and W/m glycerol ratios lead to a greater 6 gas production, thus decreasing the proportion of liquid intermediates.</s><s>These patterns are 7 consistent with the experimental observations of Wawrzet et al. <ref type="bibr">[23]</ref>, where the proportion of 8 aldehydes in the liquid initially increases with the increase in the glycerol conversion from 0 9 to 50 % and then decreases as the glycerol conversion reaches 100 %. <ref type="bibr">10 11</ref> The effect of the total pressure is only significant at a high glycerol concentration (50 wt.%) 12 and low W/m glycerol ratio (10 g catalyst min/g glycerol).</s><s>Under these concentrations, an 13 increase in pressure from 38 to 50 bar reduces the relative amount of aldehydes in the liquid 14 due to the increase in the partial pressure of acetaldehyde, which favours its transformation 15 into gases.</s><s>16 17</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.4">Ketones: C3-ketones, C4-ketones and cyclic ketones 18</head><p><s>The ketonic fraction in the liquid shifts from 0-30% and is made up of ketones of three and 19 four carbon atoms (C3-ketones and C4-ketones) together with cyclic ketones.</s><s>C3-ketones, 20 mainly obtained from dehydration reactions through route A, are the most abundant ketones 21 in the liquid phase.</s><s>The statistical analysis reveals that the operating variables exert different 22 effects on the proportions of C3-ketones in the liquid due to the numerous interactions 1 between the variables detected for the proportion of this family.</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_5">) c) d) e) f) g) h) i) j) k) l) m) n) o) p)</formula><p><s>intermediates, which increases the dehydration rate of glycerol and increases the proportion of 1 1-hydroxypropan-2-one.</s><s>In addition, the solubility of H 2 decreases with temperature, 2 hindering the hydrogenation of 1-hydroxypropan-2-one, thus increasing the proportion of H 2 3 in the gas as previously explained.</s><s>This circumstance increases the proportion of 1-4 hydroxypropan-2-one in the liquid, which leads to an increase in the proportion of C3-5 ketones.</s><s>6 7 Conversely, at 50 bar and feeding a 10 wt.% glycerol solution the temperature and W/m glycerol 8 ratio do not significantly influence the relative amount of C3-ketones.</s><s>An increase in the total 9 pressure raises the solubility of H 2 in the liquid, which can compensate for the decrease in the 10 solubility of this gas with temperature.</s><s>At low temperature, the reaction rate of glycerol 11 dehydration is slow and the temperature promotes its dehydration to 1-hydroxypropan-2-one, 12 increasing the proportion of C3-ketones.</s><s>However, the subsequent hydrogenation of 1-13 hydroxypropan-2-one at high pressure is also favoured, decreasing the proportion of C3-14 ketones.</s><s>These two consecutive reactions might be responsible for the insignificant effect of 15 the temperature.</s><s>16 17 When a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solution is used, two different trends on the proportion of the ketone 18 family with pressure can also be observed.</s><s>The effect of the temperature does not have a 19 significant effect at 38 bar regardless of the W/m glycerol ratio, while a sharp increase in the 20 proportion of C3-ketones takes place at 50 bar when a W/m glycerol ratio of 40 g catalyst min/g 21 glycerol is used.</s><s>This increase accounts for a sharp increase in the proportion of acetone in the 22 liquid.</s><s>Under these conditions, the high partial pressure of liquid products inside the reactor 23 together with the large amount of catalyst present in the bed can favour the dehydration of 1 1,2-propanediol to acetone, increasing the proportion of C3-ketones in the liquid <ref type="bibr">[23]</ref>.</s><s>The 2 chemical composition of the liquid phase accounts for these results as the proportion of 3 acetone increases from 1 to 27% and the relative amount of 1,2-propanediol in the liquid 4 drops from 55 to 32%. 5 6</s></p><p><s>The proportion of C4-ketones and cyclic-ketones in the liquid phase is relatively small.</s><s>2-7 butanone and cyclopentanone are the most abundant compounds of these two families.</s><s>These 8 types of ketones can be obtained by the reaction of an alcohol with a ketone <ref type="bibr">[44]</ref>.</s><s>Therefore, it 9 is suggested that their presence in the liquid might be the consequence of the reaction of 10 glycerol with acetone.</s><s>11 12</s></p><p><s>In general, the proportion of C4-ketones increases with temperature, suggesting that their 13 formation is favoured at high temperatures.</s><s>The higher the glycerol concentration, the greater 14 is the proportion of C4-ketones in the liquid.</s><s>An increase in the glycerol concentration not 15 only increases the glycerol available in the liquid, it also increases the proportion of acetone 16 to react with, such as the increases observed in the proportions of C3-ketones (mainly 17 acetone).</s><s>Therefore, the highest proportion of C4-ketones in the liquid is obtained when 18 feeding a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solution.</s><s>For this concentration, two different trends are found 19 depending on the total pressure of the system.</s><s>On the one hand, at 38 bar the effect of the 20 temperature is only significant for a W/m glycerol ratio of 10 g catalyst min/g glycerol.</s><s>Under 21 these conditions, reforming reactions take place to a lesser extent, allowing part of the 22 glycerol to react with the acetone formed in the process.</s><s>However, when increasing the 23 W/m glycerol ratio up to values of 40 g catalyst min/g glycerol, reforming reactions occur to a 1 greater degree, reducing the amount of glycerol available and thus decreasing the formation of 2 C4-ketones in the liquid.</s><s>On the other hand, at 50 bar, an increase in temperature from 200 to 3 240 ºC increases the proportion of C4-ketones regardless of the W/m glycerol ratio, since under 4 this pressure the formation of acetone is favoured, increasing the proportion of acetone in the 5 liquid to react with glycerol.</s><s>6 7</s></p><p><s>The presence of cyclic-ketones in the liquid phase is scarce (lower than 5%), being detected 8 only under few experimental conditions.</s><s>This compound is only observed at 38 bar when a 9 high temperature (240 ºC) and high glycerol concentration (50 wt.%) are used, regardless of 10 the W/m glycerol ratio.</s><s>11 12</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.5">Esters 13</head><p><s>The proportion of esters (basically glycerol monoacetate) in the liquid phase is quite small.</s><s>In 14 general, their formation consists of the reaction between an acid and an alcohol.</s><s>Therefore, 15 glycerol monoacetate can be formed by the reaction of glycerol with the acetic acid present as 16 an impurity and/or formed in the process.</s><s>In addition KOH, also present in the feed, can 17 catalyse this reaction.</s><s>The concentration of glycerol exerts a great impact on the proportion of 18 glycerol monoacetate.</s><s>An increase in the glycerol concentration increases the proportion of 19 esters.</s><s>20 21 When feeding a 50 wt.%</s><s>glycerol solution, where the presence of esters is significant, the 22 temperature and W/m glycerol ratio significantly influence the relative amount of esters in the liquid.</s><s>For a W/m glycerol ratio of 10 g catalyst min/g glycerol, an increase in temperature 1 reduces the proportion of esters in the liquid.</s><s>Conversely, for a W/m glycerol ratio of 40 g 2 catalyst min/g glycerol, the effect of the temperature depends on the total pressure of the 3 system.</s><s>At 38 bar an increase in temperature increases the proportion of esters, while at 50 bar 4 the proportion of esters decreases.</s><s>5 6</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Theoretical prediction of optimal operating conditions within the range of study 7</head><p><s>Optimal conditions for gas and liquid production were sought for this process making use of 8 the experimental models developed, bearing in mind the possibility of scaling-up this process.</s><s>9</s></p><p><s>Modelling and optimisation tools are gaining increasing attention from the research 10 community for their use in various processes related to biomass/bio-product 11 conversion/production <ref type="bibr">[45,</ref><ref type="bibr">46]</ref>.</s><s>The predicted R 2 of all the models is higher than 0.90, 12 allowing their use for prediction purposes.</s><s>Six different optimisations were carried out.</s><s>The 13 first comprised the maximisation of the X gly.</s><s>In the second and the third optimisations, apart 14 from the X gly, the CC gas and CC liq were also maximised.</s><s>The fourth maximised the 15 production of H 2 and the fifth and sixth maximised the proportion of monohydric and 16 polyhydric alcohols, respectively.</s><s>In addition, the evolution over time for the CC gas, CC liq 17 and X gly were minimised for all the optimisations.</s><s>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_8">6</ref> lists the criteria used in the 18 optimisations, together with the optimums for the operating variables and the values for the 19 response variables considered.</s><s>20 21</s></p><p><s>The highest glycerol conversion (Opt. 1) is obtained using intermediate values for the 22 temperature and W/m glycerol ratio, at high pressure and feeding a concentrated glycerol 23 solution.</s><s>Conversely, if the optimisation includes the maximisation of the CC gas (Opt.</s><s>2), 1 high values (close to the maximum values studied in this work) for the temperature and 2 W/m glycerol ratio are needed.</s><s>In addition, low pressure and glycerol concentrations are also 3 required.</s><s>The comparison between the values obtained in Opt. 1 and Opt. 2 reveals slight 4 decreases for the X gly and CC liq and a considerable increase (by a factor of three) in gas 5 production (CC gas).</s><s>The proportion of H 2 in the gas is enlarged, the proportion of polyhydric 6 alcohols drops and the relative amount of monohydric alcohols increases.</s><s>The composition of 7 the liquid phase shows a greater spread of the reactions leading to the formation of liquid 8 products, which is in agreement with the results previously discussed in the parametric study.</s><s>9 10 For the production of liquid products, the maximisation of the CC liq (Opt.</s><s>3) implies 20 medium values (within the interval studied in this work) for the temperature and the 21 W/m glycerol ratio together with the use of high pressure and a relatively diluted glycerol 22 solution.</s><s>Under these conditions the CC liq increases up to 86%.</s><s>The liquid phase is mainly 23 made up of alcohols (68 %), the vast majority being polyhydric alcohols (61%).</s><s>These results 1 suggest that for maximising the production of intermediate liquids, the reaction should be 2 stopped at the early reaction steps.</s><s>The advancement of the reaction with the formation of end 3 products facilitates their transformation into gases, decreasing the CC liq <ref type="bibr">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr">23]</ref>.</s><s>4</s></p><p><s>As regards the properties of the gas and liquid phases, the maximisation of the production of 5 H 2 (Opt.</s><s>4) is achieved employing a high temperature, a high W/m glycerol ratio, low pressure 6 and feeding a diluted glycerol solution.</s><s>The highest proportion of monohydric alcohols in the 7 liquid (Opt.</s><s>5) is achieved at low pressure and temperature, feeding a medium glycerol 8 solution, and using a high W/m glycerol ratio.</s><s>The maximisation of monohydric alcohols implies 9 the use of conditions for temperature and pressure where the formation of liquid products is 10 highly favoured combined with high W/m glycerol ratios to favour the extension of the reaction 11 in the liquid phase towards end products, minimising their subsequent transformation into 12 gases.</s><s>Optimum conditions for the production of polyhydric alcohols (Opt.</s><s>6) are medium 13 temperature, high pressure, low glycerol concentration and an intermediate value for the 14 W/m glycerol ratio.</s><s>These conditions are able to stop the advancement of the reactions in the 15 liquid phase, thus providing a high production of liquids together with an excellent selectivity 16 to polyhydric alcohols.</s><s>17</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusions 19</head><p><s>This work addresses the valorisation process of a crude glycerol solution obtained from 20 biodiesel production by aqueous phase reforming (APR).</s><s>The process has been 21</s></p><p><s>experimentally evaluated and optimised in a flow reactor using a Ni-based catalyst.</s><s>A design 22 of experiments with statistical analysis of the results has been used to analyse the effect on the 23 process of the temperature, pressure, glycerol concentration, W/m glycerol ratio and all the 1 interactions between these variables.</s><s>As a result, this work provides a good understanding of 2 the aqueous phase reforming of glycerol in general and the effect of the operating variables on 3 the process in particular.</s><s>In addition, appropriate operating conditions for the selective 4 production of liquids and gases are provided.</s><s>The most important conclusions obtained from 5 this work are summarised as follows.</s><s>6</s></p><p><s>1.</s><s>The operating variables exert a significant influence on the global results of the aqueous 7 phase reforming (glycerol conversion and carbon converted into liquid and gas products) as 8 well as on the composition of the gas and liquid phases.</s><s>9 2. Gas production is favoured at low pressure, high temperature and employing a concentrated 10 glycerol solution.</s><s>Under these conditions, reforming and cracking reactions of glycerol and its 11 intermediate liquids are enlarged.</s><s>Conversely, a high pressure and medium temperature and 12 W/m glycerol ratio favour the production of liquid products.</s><s>A high selectivity to liquids is 13 achieved maximising the proportion of polyhydric alcohols in the liquid, i.e. detaining the 14 process at early reaction steps.</s><s>15 3.</s><s>The gas phase is composed of H 2 , CO 2 , CO and CH 4 .</s><s>The proportion of H 2 in the gas does 16 not only depend on the extent of the chemical reactions involved in its production, such as 17 reforming and/or cracking reactions, but also of those where it is consumed, such as 18 hydrogenation.</s><s>The temperature is the variable with the greatest impact on the composition of 19 the gas.</s><s>An increase in temperature increases the proportion of H 2 and decreases the 20 proportion of CO 2 due to the decrease in solubility of H 2 with temperature as well as the 21 endothermic reactions of the process.</s><s>22 4.</s><s>The liquid phase is made up of a mixture of carboxylic acids (2-32%), aldehydes (0-3%), 23 monohydric alcohols (4-47%), polyhydric alcohols (14-68%), C3-ketones (2-33%), C4-1 ketones (0-10 %) ciclo-ketones (0-6%) and esters (0-46%). 2 5. Alcohols are the most abundant compounds in the liquid phase.</s><s>Monohydric alcohols are 3 formed under conditions of temperature and pressure (209 ºC and 39 bar) where the formation 4 of liquid products is highly favoured together with the use of high W/m glycerol ratios (40 g 5 catalyst min/g glycerol) to favour the extension of the reactions in the liquid phase towards 6 liquid end products.</s><s>The production of polyhydric alcohols is favoured at an intermediate 7 temperature (218 ºC), high pressure (49 bar), low glycerol concentration (16 wt.%) and a 8 medium W/m glycerol ratio (20 g catalyst min/g glycerol).</s><s>These conditions are able to stop the 9 advancement of the reactions in the liquid phase at the early steps.</s><s>10 11</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements 12</head><p><s>The authors wish to express their gratitude to the Aragon Government (GPT group), ESF and 13 Spanish MINECO (projects ENE2010-18985 and ENE2013-41523-R) for providing financial 14 support.</s><s>The authors would also like to acknowledge the use of the Servicio General de 15 Apoyo a la Investigación-SAI of the Universidad de Zaragoza.</s><s>In addition, Javier <ref type="bibr">Remón 16</ref> Núñez would like to express his gratitude to the Spanish MINECO for the FPI grant awarded 17</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>crude glycerol, aqueous phase reforming, value-added liquids, gas 13</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>18</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>the catalyst in the process [30--33].</s><s>The catalyst was prepared by coprecipitation, having 21 a 28% (relative atomic percentage) of Ni expressed as Ni/(Ni+Al+La), an atomic La/Al 22 ratio of 0.035 and a BET surface area of 187 m 2 /g.</s><s>The experimental ring used in the 23 experiments was a microactivity unit designed and built by PID (Process Integral Development Eng &amp; Tech, Spain).</s><s>It consists of a stainless steel tubular reactor with an 1 inner diameter of 9 mm, heated up by means of an electric furnace [33].</s><s>The system 2</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>( 10 -Figure 1 .</head><label>101</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Schematic diagram of the aqueous phase reforming experimental rig. 4 5</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. The reaction network includes the formation of gases and liquid products.3</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Possible reaction pathways during the aqueous phase reforming of glycerol.</s><s>5 6</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 3 .5</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. Conversion to gas (a), liquid (b) and global glycerol conversion (c) obtained 2 during the APR experiments.</s><s>Results are presented as the overall values obtained every 3 60 minutes and expressed as mean ± 0.5 Fisher LSD intervals with 95% confidence.</s><s>4 5</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>15</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figures 4 6 a</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>and b and Figures 4 c and d show the XRD patterns and TG results of the used 7 catalysts, respectively.</s><s>The XRD patterns have wide and asymmetric peaks, which 8 denote quite low crystallinity, and indicate the presence of Ni, NiAl 2 O 3 and boehmite 9 (AlO(OH)) in the four used catalysts.</s><s>This finding confirms that under the operating 10 conditions of APR, the alumina of the support can be transformed in boehmite.</s><s>In 11 addition, C and LaCO 3 OH are present in some of the samples.</s><s>The TG analysis displays 12 four decomposition steps (25-166 ºC; 166-247 ºC; 247-362 ºC and 362-600 ºC), which 13 correspond to the decomposition of boehmite into alumina.</s><s>At constant heating rates 14 this decomposition can be accurately modelled by a 4-reaction mechanism [38-40] 15 involving: (I) the loss of physisorbed water, (II) the loss of chemisorbed water, (III) the 16 conversion of boehmite into transition alumina, and (IV) the dehydration of transition 17 alumina (loss of residual hydroxyl groups).</s><s>The experimental temperature ranges for the 18 decomposition of the used catalysts are fairly similar to those reported for the 19 decomposition of pure boehmite; the small differences being the consequence of having 20 incorporated different metals on the structure [40].</s><s>Very interestingly, a greater mass 21</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>3 4 5 Figure 4 .8</head><label>54</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. XRD patterns (a and b) and TG analysis (c and d) for the used catalysts 6</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figures 5 c</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figures 5 c and d, g and h, and k and l display the effect of the temperature and the 18</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>6</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Numbers in brackets indicate the percentage Pareto influence of each factor on the response variable.</s><s>Pareto values represent the percentage of the orthogonal estimated total value.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>1 Figure 5 .4</head><label>15</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. Interaction plots for the initial CC gas (a), CC liq (b) and global glycerol 2 conversion (c).</s><s>Bars are LSD intervals with 95% confidence.</s><s>3 4</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>4 5Figure 6 . 10 A</head><label>4610</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6.</s><s>Relative amounts (vol.%) of H 2 (a), CO 2 (b) CO (c) and CH 4 (d) in the gas 6 obtained during the APR experiments.</s><s>Results are presented as the overall values 7 obtained every 60 minutes and expressed as mean ± 0.5 Fisher LSD intervals with 95% 8 confidence.</s><s>9 10</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 7. Interaction plots for initial relative amounts (vol.%) of H 2 (a), CO 2 (b) CO (c) and 8 CH 4 (d) in the gas.</s><s>Bars are LSD intervals with 95% confidence.</s><s>9</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Figure 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 8 summarises the relative amount of each of the different families of liquid compounds 17</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 8. Proportions (% chromatographic area) of carboxylic acids (a), monohydric alcohols 2 (b), polyhydric alcohols (c), aldehydes (d), C3-ketones (e), C4-ketones (f), cyclic ketones (g) 3 and esters (h) in the liquid obtained during the APR experiments.</s><s>Results are presented as the 4 overall values obtained every 60 minutes and expressed as mean ± 0.5 Fisher LSD intervals 5 with 95% confidence.</s><s>6 7</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>1 Figure 9 .</head><label>19</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 9. Interaction plots for the relative amounts in the liquid of carboxylic acids, 2 monohydric alcohols, polyhydric alcohols and aldehydes.</s><s>Bars are LSD intervals with 95% 3 confidence.</s><s>4 5</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head>11</head><label>11</label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_25"><head>Figure 10 .7</head><label>10</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 10.</s><s>Interaction plots for the relative amounts in the liquid of C3-ketones, C4-ketones, 5 cyclic ketones and esters.</s><s>Bars are LSD intervals with 95% confidence.</s><s>6 7</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_26"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>18</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="11,91.50,104.45,412.00,300.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>The properties of this crude glycerol are consistent with 4 Properties of the crude and purified glycerol solutions.</s><s>Results are presented as 7 mean ± standard deviation.</s><s>8</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>5</cell><cell cols="3">those reported in other works in the literature [27-29].</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Crude glycerol</cell><cell>Purified glycerol</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Composition</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Glycerol (wt.%)</cell><cell>63.17±2.26</cell><cell>85.25±0.79</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>CH3OH (wt.%)</cell><cell>34.37±2.13</cell><cell>6.03±0.17</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>CH3COOH (wt.%)</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3.94±0.86</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Ashes (wt.%)</cell><cell>2.06± 0.23</cell><cell>4.56± 0.37</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>H2O (wt.%)</cell><cell>1.63±0.02</cell><cell>1.38±0.002</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Ultimate Analysis</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>C (%)</cell><cell>40.48±0.29</cell><cell>36.33±0.65</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>H (%)</cell><cell>8.19±0.06</cell><cell>7.55±0.03</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>O (%) a</cell><cell>51.33±0.34</cell><cell>56.11±0.63</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>TOC (ppm)</cell><cell>404733±2850</cell><cell>363333±6536</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Physical properties</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>pH</cell><cell>13.1±0.3</cell><cell>6.0±0.3</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Density (g/mL)</cell><cell>1.060±0.001</cell><cell>1.043±0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Viscosity (mPa s)</cell><cell>49.93±1.48</cell><cell>247.41±3.93</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>LHV (MJ/kg)</cell><cell>21.89±0.05</cell><cell>16.96±0.03</cell></row></table><note><p><s>a Determined by difference 9 10</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Operating conditions employed in the experiments 9</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Run</cell><cell cols="2">Glycerol</cell><cell cols="2">Pressure</cell><cell cols="2">Temperature</cell><cell cols="2">Wcatalyst/mglycerol</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(wt.%)</cell><cell>(bar)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(ºC)</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(g cat min/g glycerol)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Actual</cell><cell>codec</cell><cell>actual</cell><cell>codec</cell><cell>actual</cell><cell>codec</cell><cell>Actual</cell><cell>codec</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell></cell><cell>-1</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>240</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell>-1</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell></cell><cell>-1</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>240</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell>-1</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell></cell><cell>-1</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>240</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell>-1</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell></cell><cell>-1</cell></row><row><cell>8</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>240</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell>-1</cell></row><row><cell>9</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>10</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>240</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>11</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>12</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>240</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>13</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>14</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>240</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>15</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>16</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>240</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>17* (17,18,19, 20)</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>44</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>220</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>21</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>44</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell></cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>22</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>44</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>240</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>23</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>220</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>24</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>220</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>25</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>44</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>220</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>26</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>44</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>220</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>27</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>44</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>220</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell>-1</cell></row><row><cell>28</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>44</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>220</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>10</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>11</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Response variables.</s><s>Definitions and analytical techniques used in their 8</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>9</cell><cell>determination.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Product</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Response variable</cell><cell>Analytical method</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Gas</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">CC  gas % =</cell><cell>C  in  the  gas  (g) C  fed  (g)</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>Micro Gas Chromatograph (Micro GC). N2 as internal standard</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Composition vol. % =</cell><cell>mol  of  each  gas total  mol  of  gas</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>Online analyses</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">CC  liq % =</cell><cell cols="2">C  in  the  liquid  products  (g) C  fed  (g)</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>Total Organic Carbon (TOC)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Liquid</cell><cell cols="4">Composition area  % =</cell><cell>area  of  each  compound total  area</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>GC-MS (Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectrometry)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>X  gly % =</cell><cell cols="3">glycerol  fed g − glycerol  in  the  liquid  (g) glycerol  fed  (g)</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>GC-FID (Gas Chromatography-Flame ionization detector)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Offline analyses</cell></row></table><note><p><s>SolidCC sol % = 100 − CC gas % − CC liq * (%)</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>. Results and discussion 1</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>CH 4</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>methane</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>CO</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>O</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>H 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>H 2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>OH acetic acid</cell><cell cols="2">O acetaldehyde</cell><cell>H 2</cell><cell>OH ethanol</cell><cell cols="2">H 2 O</cell><cell>ethene</cell><cell>ethane</cell></row><row><cell>CO</cell><cell></cell><cell>H 2</cell><cell>H 2 O</cell><cell>H 2</cell><cell>H 2 O</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>OH</cell><cell>O</cell><cell></cell><cell>HO</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>methanol</cell><cell>OH</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>OH</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2-hydroxyacetaldehyde</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">ethane-1,2-diol</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>CO</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>O</cell><cell>H 2 O</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>O</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">disproportionation</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2-oxopropanal</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>C</cell><cell>H 2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">H 2 O</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>O</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>OH propionic acid</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>B</cell><cell>H 2</cell><cell>retro-aldol</cell></row><row><cell>H 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>A</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(aq)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>H 2 O</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>O</cell><cell>H 2 O</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>acetaldehyde O</cell><cell>+</cell><cell>O formaldehyde</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>acrylaldehyde</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(aq)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>H 2 O</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>H 2</cell><cell></cell><cell>O</cell><cell>O</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>propionaldehyde</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>OH</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>H 2 O</cell><cell>H 2</cell><cell>acetic acid</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>HO</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>propan-1-ol</cell><cell>butane</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>H 2 O</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>O</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>OH</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>propane</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>propan-2-one</cell><cell>H 2</cell><cell></cell><cell>propan-2-ol</cell><cell>H 2</cell><cell>OH</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>ethanol</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>18</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Theoretical optimisation: Objectives, optimum values for the operating variables and 11 optimised values for some responses 12Var CC gas = 0.79 + 1.5 T + 6 P + 14.5 C + 7.5 W + 1.44 TP + 2.31 TC + 0.81 TW + 0.31 PC + 2.81 PW -1.06 CW -0.078 T 2 + 4.42 P 2 -13 6.08 C 2 + 5.92 W 2 + 0.19 TPC + 2.94 TPW -3.19 TCW + 1.81 PCW -4.69 T 2 P -10.06 T 2 C -8.81 T 2 W +4.81 TP 2 +1.69 TPCW (R 2 = 1)14Var CC liq = -1.91-10.61</s><s>T -9.83 W-3.19 TW + 8.31 CW + 26.3 T 2 -8.7 C 2 -5.06 TCW -8.69 PCW -7.31 T 2 P -9.69 T 2 C -3.56 TPCW (R 2 = Var X gly = 1.43 -16 T-9.44 W + 2.38 PW + 14 CW + 12.54 T 2 +5.54 W 2 + 4 TPC -4.38 TCW -3.12 T 2 P -10.75 T 2 C +5.87 TP 2 (R 2 =</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>T</cell><cell>P</cell><cell>[Gly]</cell><cell>W/mgly</cell><cell>X gly</cell><cell>CC gas</cell><cell>CC liq</cell><cell>H2</cell><cell>Mono-</cell><cell>Poly-</cell></row><row><cell>Opt</cell><cell>Variable/s maximised</cell><cell>(ºC)</cell><cell>(bar)</cell><cell>(wt.%)</cell><cell>gcat min/ggly</cell><cell>(%)</cell><cell>(%)</cell><cell>(%)</cell><cell>(vol.%)</cell><cell>Alcohols (%)</cell><cell>Alcohols (%)</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>X gly</cell><cell>222</cell><cell>42</cell><cell>49</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>42</cell><cell>34</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>46</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>X gly, CC gas</cell><cell>238</cell><cell>39</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>99</cell><cell>64</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>47</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>17</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>X gly, CC liq</cell><cell>216</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>96</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>86</cell><cell>39</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>61</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>X gly, CC gas, H2</cell><cell>236</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>54</cell><cell>43</cell><cell>51</cell><cell>28</cell><cell>24</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>X gly, CC liq, Mono-Alcohols</cell><cell>209</cell><cell>39</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>93</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>63</cell><cell>41</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>41</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>X gly, CC liq, Poly-Alcohols</cell><cell>218</cell><cell>49</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>91</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>82</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>66</cell></row><row><cell>15</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>16</cell><cell>0.97)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>17</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>18</cell><cell>0.95)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>19</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">raised the glycerol conversion from 20.6 to 82.6%, reduced the proportion of ethylene</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Ni/SiO 2 -Al 2 O 3 catalyst, the highest conversions to gaseous and liquid products were 74</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">(TOC), density, viscosity, pH and chemical composition, are listed in Table1. The</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">temperature, the greater is the drop over time for this variable. Therefore, the greatest</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="38">bar, since the increase in the glycerol partial pressure is also higher.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequential-refining of crude glycerol 2 derived from waste used-oil methyl ester plant via a combined process of chemical and 3 adsorption</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Manosak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Limpattayanate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hunsom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuel Processing Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Glycerol as a by-product of 5 biodiesel production in Brazil: Alternatives for the use of unrefined glycerol</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Leoneti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Aragão-Leoneti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V W B</forename><surname>De Oliveira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="145" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Renewable 6 Energy</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Hydrogen production from catalytic steam 8 reforming of biodiesel byproduct glycerol: Issues and challenges. Renewable and Sustainable 9 Energy Reviews</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="950" to="960" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Challenges and strategies for optimization of 11 glycerol steam reforming process</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Soria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Madeira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1187" to="1213" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biomass to chemicals: Catalytic 14 conversion of glycerol/water mixtures into acrolein, reaction network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Corma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sauvanaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Oconnor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Catalysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="171" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Catalytic valorization of glycerol to hydrogen and syngas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal 17 of Hydrogen Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2678" to="2700" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aqueous 19 phase reforming of glycerol for hydrogen production over Pt-Re supported on carbon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Xia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Karim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Heldebrant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Catalysis B: Environmental</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="206" to="213" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Production of 22 1,3-propanediol, 2,3-butanediol and ethanol by a newly isolated Klebsiella oxytoca strain 23 growing on biodiesel-derived glycerol based media</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Metsoviti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Paraskevaidi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Koutinas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A.-P</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Papanikolaou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Process Biochemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1872" to="1896" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biodiesel derived glycerol 26 hydrogenolysis to 1,2-propanediol on Cu/MgO catalysts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Yuan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioresource Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7088" to="7092" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Aqueous-phase reforming of 29 crude glycerol: effect of impurities on hydrogen production. Catalyst Science and 30 Technology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Boga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C A</forename><surname>Bruijnincx</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weckhuysen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influence of Pt particle size and support type on the aqueous-phase 32 reforming of glycerol</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lehnert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Claus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Catalysis Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2543" to="2546" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glycerol liquid phase conversion over monometallic and bimetallic catalysts: Effect of 35 metal, support type and reaction temperatures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Iriondo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Cambra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Barrio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Guemez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Arias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sanchez-Sanchez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">;</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Catalysis B: Environmental</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Production of 37 renewable hydrogen from aqueous-phase reforming of glycerol over Pt catalysts supported on 38 different oxides</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Menezes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Rodrigues</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zimmaro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E P</forename><surname>Borges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fraga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Renewable Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="595" to="599" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydrogen production by aqueous phase catalytic reforming of 40 glycerine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Ö</forename><surname>Özgür</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biomass and Bioenergy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="822" to="826" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aqueous-phase reforming of oxygenated 42 hydrocarbons over Sn-modified Ni catalysts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Shabaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dumesic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Catalysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">222</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="180" to="191" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Production of hydrogen by aqueous-phase 44 reforming of glycerol</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Tian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Hydrogen Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6657" to="6666" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydrogen production by 1 aqueous-phase reforming of glycerol over Ni-B catalysts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Azmat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Hydrogen 2 Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="234" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydrogen generation from liquid reforming of 4 glycerin over Ni-Co bimetallic catalyst</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ouyang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biomass and Bioenergy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="489" to="495" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydrogen production by 6 aqueous-phase reforming of glycerol over nickel catalysts supported on CeO 2</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Manfro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Da Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">F P</forename><surname>Ribeiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M V M</forename><surname>Souza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuel 7 Processing Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="330" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aqueous-phase reforming of methanol and ethylene glycol over alumina-9 supported platinum catalysts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shabaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Catalysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">215</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="344" to="352" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aqueous phase hydrogenolysis of glycerol to 11 1,2-propanediol without external hydrogen addition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Subramaniam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Chaudhari</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Catalysis Today</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">156</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">H2 production from aqueous-phase reforming of glycerol over Cu-Ni 13 bimetallic catalysts supported on carbon nanotubes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rahman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Hydrogen 14 Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14833" to="14844" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards 16 understanding the bifunctional hydrodeoxygenation and aqueous phase reforming of glycerol</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wawrzetz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hrabar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jentys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lemonidou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lercher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Catalysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="420" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glycerol aqueous phase reforming for 19 hydrogen generation over Pt catalyst -Effect of catalyst composition and reaction conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuel</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3483" to="3489" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">20. 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydrogenolysis of glycerol to propylene glycol by in situ 22 produced hydrogen from aqueous phase reforming of glycerol over SiO 2 -Al 2 O 3 supported 23 nickel catalyst</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Seretis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tsiakaras</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuel Processing Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="135" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aqueous phase reforming (APR) of glycerol over platinum 25 supported on Al 2 O 3 catalyst</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Seretis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tsiakaras</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Renewable Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1116" to="1126" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Steam 27 reforming of crude glycerol with in situ CO2 sorption</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rickett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Dupont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioresource Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2436" to="2442" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Production of high purity hydrogen by sorption enhanced 30 steam reforming of crude glycerol</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fermoso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Hydrogen Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="14047" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Valliyappan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ferdous</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Bakhshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Dalai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">33</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Syngas via Steam Gasification of Glycerol in a Fixed-Bed Reactor</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Topics in Catalysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydrogen production from pine and 36 poplar bio-oils by catalytic steam reforming. Influence of the bio-oil composition on the 37 process</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Remón</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Broust</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Volle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>García</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Arauzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Hydrogen Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5593" to="5608" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ni/Al-Mg-O solids modified 39 with Co or Cu for the catalytic steam reforming of bio-oil</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Remón</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Medrano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bimbela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>García</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Arauzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="433" to="444" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Applied Catalysis B: 40 Environmental</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of acetic acid, methanol and 42 potassium hydroxide on the catalytic steam reforming of glycerol: Thermodynamic and 43 experimental study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Remón</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Mercado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>García</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Arauzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuel Processing Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="325" to="336" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bioenergy II: 45 Hydrogen Production by Aqueous-Phase Reforming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Valiente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Medrano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oliva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Arauzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Chemical 46 Reactor Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influence of the nature of the support on the 1 catalytic properties of Pt-based catalysts for hydrogenolysis of glycerol</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Delgado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yap</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Vivier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Especel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Molecular 2 Catalysis A: Chemical</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">367</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hydrogenolysis of 4 glycerol to propanediols over a Pt/ASA catalyst: The role of acid and metal sites on product 5 selectivity and the reaction mechanism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Gandarias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Arias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Requies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Güemez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L G</forename><surname>Fierro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Catalysis B: Environmental</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="248" to="254" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation of Pt-8 Re surface properties with reaction pathways for the aqueous-phase reforming of glycerol</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Karim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Engelhard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Catalysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">287</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="43" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">El</forename><surname>Doukkali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Iriondo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Cambra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Gandarias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Jalowiecki-Duhamel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deactivation study of the Pt and/or Ni-based γ-Al 2 O 3 catalysts used in the 12 aqueous phase reforming of glycerol for H 2 production</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Dumeignil</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Catalysis A: General. 472</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="80" to="91" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reclamation of alumina as boehmite from an 15 alumina-supported spent catalyst</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Al-Sheeha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marafi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stanislaus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Mineral Processing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Boehmite-supported vanadium oxide catalysts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M D A</forename><surname>Cruz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Guillaume</forename><surname>Eon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Catalysis A: General</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="213" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surface analysis, TEM, dynamic and controlled rate 20 thermal analysis, and infrared emission spectroscopy of gallium doped boehmite nanofibres 21 and nanosheets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Frost</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Surface Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">255</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7925" to="7936" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect 23 of support and reaction conditions on aqueous phase reforming of polyol over supported Pt-24 Re bimetallic catalysts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-D</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T.-W</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-E</forename><surname>Jeong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-J</forename><surname>Chae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-Y</forename><surname>Jeong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Catalysis Today</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">185</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aqueous phase hydrogenolysis of glycerol to 26 bio-propylene glycol over Pt-Sn catalysts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Barbelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Santori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Nichio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioresource technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="500" to="503" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Low-pressure 28 hydrogenolysis of glycerol to propylene glycol</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dasari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P.-P</forename><surname>Kiatsimkul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Sutterlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Suppes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Catalysis A: General</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">281</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="231" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glycerol ketals: 31 Synthesis and profits in biodiesel blends</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Torres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Jiménez-Osés</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mayoral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pires</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>De Los</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Santos</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuel</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="614" to="616" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Xiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aramideh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-C</forename><surname>Kong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Modeling Effects of Operating Conditions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">33</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biomass Fast Pyrolysis in Bubbling Fluidized Bed Reactors. Energy &amp; Fuels</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5948" to="5956" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling the impact of bubbling 36 bed hydrodynamics on tar yield and its fluctuations during biomass fast pyrolysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Xiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ramirez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pannala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Daw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fuel</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">164</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
