<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Cystic fibrosis (CF) care through the patients&apos; eyes e A nationwide survey on experience and satisfaction with services using a disease-specific questionnaire *</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014-12-06">6 December 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Gratiana</forename><surname>Steinkamp</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Clinical Research</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Schwerin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Physicians Working Group</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Katja</forename><surname>Stahl</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Picker Institut Deutschland gGmbH</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hamburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Helmut</forename><surname>Ellemunter</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">CF Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Medical University Innsbruck</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Innsbruck</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Eberhard</forename><surname>Heuer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">CF Centre Hamburg-Altona</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Silke</forename><surname>Van Koningsbruggen-Rietschel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">CF Centre Cologne</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Melanie</forename><surname>Busche</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Picker Institut Deutschland gGmbH</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hamburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wilhelm</forename><surname>Bremer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Patient Experience Working Group</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">German CF Association (Mukoviszidose e.V.)</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Carsten</forename><surname>Schwarz</surname></persName>
							<email>carsten.schwarz@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">CF Centre Berlin Charite ´</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Physicians Working Group</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charite ´e Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Klinik fu ¨r Pa ¨diatrie m. S. Pneumologie und Immunologie</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Rudolf Virchow Klinikum, Augustenburger Platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Cystic fibrosis (CF) care through the patients&apos; eyes e A nationwide survey on experience and satisfaction with services using a disease-specific questionnaire *</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2014-12-06">6 December 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">8CD8EAF091437859BECC8C53A6E4BAF7</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.rmed.2014.11.007</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 27 August 2014; accepted 19 November 2014</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:17+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>CF care</term>
					<term>Quality of life</term>
					<term>Nationwide survey</term>
					<term>Satisfaction with services</term>
					<term>Disease specific questionnaire</term>
					<term>Chronic illness</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>The patients' perspective is an important aspect of quality management.</s><s>A newly developed disease-specific questionnaire was used to assess the patients' experiences with care provided in specialised cystic fibrosis (CF) care centres.</s><s>Methods: 90 CF centres in Germany were invited to participate.</s><s>Centre staff collected patient consent forms and sent the patients' addresses to the study centre.</s><s>The questionnaires for adults and parents had 100 and 104 items respectively, with 3e6 response categories each.</s><s>Items were dichotomised into "problem scores" (PS), indicating the presence or absence (PS 0%) of a reported problem.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>In 2005, the European Cystic Fibrosis Society published standards to ensure high quality medical care for patients with cystic fibrosis and their families <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[1]</ref>.</s><s>Experts recommended to treat patients at specialised CF centres, and they defined the kind and number of multi-professional staff and resources needed to provide good care.</s><s>Further aspects contributing to good treatment are guidelines, standardised procedures and processes, and patient databases.</s></p><p><s>National and international patient registries reveal the medical situation of patients with cystic fibrosis, and differences between countries and centres have been identified <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">3]</ref>.</s><s>However, there is a lack of information on how patients and parents assess the services and treatments they receive at the CF centre.</s><s>The patients' perspective is an important aspect of total quality management.</s><s>Moreover, good services increase the proportion of satisfied patients, and satisfied patients will adhere better to treatment <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref>.</s><s>Good treatment adherence is particularly important in a life-long chronic disease such as cystic fibrosis which requires daily treatment at home.</s><s>Thus, CF centres should provide care that is focused on their patients' needs.</s></p><p><s>The board of the physicians working group (AGAM) in the German CF association (Mukoviszidose e.V.) started an initiative in 2007 to develop a CF-specific patient experience of care questionnaire.</s><s>A project group was established with the Picker Institute Germany as a major partner.</s><s>The Picker Institute Germany is a not-for-profit organisation and a subsidiary of Picker Institute Europe.</s><s>It has more than 30 years experience in conducting patient satisfaction/experience surveys.</s><s>In the present study the Picker Institute also served as the study centre.</s></p><p><s>After a successful pilot study in four centres, the draft questionnaire was revised <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>, and the final version was used for a nationwide survey which started in 2011.</s><s>The present article describes how a cohort of more than 2000 patients and parents assessed the quality of multiprofessional care in German CF centres.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Development of a CF-specific patient experience of care questionnaire</head><p><s>For generating the questionnaire, we combined newly developed items covering specific aspects of CF care with widely-used, reliable generic items from the Picker Institute which are relevant to patients with all kinds of medical problems <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref>.</s><s>Importantly, the Picker method implies that participants report on their care experiences, rather than rating their satisfaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref>, since the latter type is prone to positive bias <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref>.</s><s>An example of a reporting style question is "Are you told about medication side effects to watch for?</s><s>Yes, always e Yes, frequently e Sometimes e Nearly never/ never".</s><s>A detailed description of the methods is presented elsewhere <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>.</s><s>In brief, we first interviewed experts from multi-professional CF teams on the specific medical needs of patients with cystic fibrosis.</s><s>In the next step we conducted focus groups of adult CF patients and parents of minors (below 18 years of age) with CF.</s><s>The results from these discussions were used to draft the first questionnaire, which was tested in a pilot study at four CF centres (Hamburg, Berlin, Innsbruck, Ko ¨ln) in 2009.</s><s>Feedback from the pilot study was used to create the final questionnaire.</s><s>Two slightly different versions were constructed, one for adult patients with cystic fibrosis and one for parents of minors with CF.</s><s>The parent and the adult versions comprised 104 and 100 closed-ended questions, respectively, including 14 items on demographic and clinical parameters (since the survey was anonymous) and 3 open ended questions.</s><s>Responses to open questions such as "If you had a wish and you could change anything in the CF centre, what would it be?" were included in the report to the individual CF centre, but are not part of the present study.</s><s>The CF-specific topics in the questionnaire were related to hygiene, staff of the multi-professional team, CF treatment and care, services and facilities at the centre, accessibility, and inpatient treatment on the ward.</s><s>Parents with more than one child with CF replied by referring to their oldest child.</s></p><p><s>In addition to adults and parents, adolescents aged 12e17 years were surveyed using a different questionnaire which focussed on the health care preferences of chronically ill adolescents <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref>.</s><s>This instrument was amended to ask not only for preferences, but also for the respondents' health care experiences <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref>.</s><s>The results of this part will be presented elsewhere.</s><s>However, parents of adolescents replied using the parents' questionnaire, so that their views were also included in this study.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recruiting centres</head><p><s>The nationwide survey was conducted in Germany in 2011.</s><s>Ninety CF centres known to the Mukoviszidose e.V., the German CF association, were invited to take part in the project.</s><s>It was emphasised that participation was voluntary.</s><s>Participating centres agreed to use their results for quality improvement measures and to discuss them with patient representatives.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recruiting and surveying participants</head><p><s>Patients were recruited according to established procedures <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[10]</ref>.</s><s>Clinic staff informed each patient or parent in person about the project.</s><s>During the outpatient visit, an information leaflet was handed out, and patients were asked to provide written consent for transmitting their home address to the study centre at the Picker Institute Germany.</s><s>Subjects who signed the consent form will hereafter be referred to as "recruited".</s><s>Once a week, centre staff faxed the patient addresses to the study centre.</s><s>A recruitment sheet was also transmitted, listing the approached patients plus the reasons why persons had declined to take part.</s></p><p><s>Each participant received the questionnaire plus a response postcard by mail.</s><s>Patients filled in the anonymous questionnaire and sent it back in a pre-paid envelope.</s><s>In addition, participants mailed the separate postcard to the study centre to indicate that no reminder is necessary.</s><s>Staff at the study centre monitored the responses and sent out reminders after two and four weeks to subjects who had not returned the postcard in due time.</s><s>After survey termination, the list' of participants' addresses were destroyed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysing data</head><p><s>In order to easily identify suboptimal care, the answers of each item were dichotomised into two categories, indicating either optimum care or a "problem".</s><s>For example, the item "Does your doctor listen to what you have to say?" has the desirable response "Yes, very carefully", while both "To some extent" and "No" would present a problem.</s><s>For each item the percentage of respondents reporting a problem was calculated, thus displaying the problem score (PS) with a score of zero percent being ideal.</s><s>Respondents who did not answer the question were not included in the calculation of the problem scores.</s></p><p><s>To provide summary scores for the different aspects of care factor analysis was performed to group the questionnaire items into factors.</s><s>The factor problem score was calculated as a weighted mean of the problem scores of the respective items.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Online reports</head><p><s>The survey results of each centre were provided online.</s></p><p><s>Centre staff used a code to access their results on the online platform.</s><s>Each centre received three different reports.</s></p><p><s>The first contained the frequency tables showing for each item how many respondents from the CF centre had chosen each of the alternative answers.</s><s>The second report compared the centres' results with the aggregated results of all participating centres in form of a bar chart.</s><s>In order to facilitate the interpretation of this external comparison, means and standard deviation of the aggregated results were provided.</s><s>The third report, a priority matrix, displayed the factors in relation to overall importance and performance.</s><s>Centre staff had no access to individual data from other institutions.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistics</head><p><s>Descriptive results are expressed as means, with standard deviations of the mean in brackets.</s><s>Statistics were calculated using Graph Pad Prism for Windows version 6.02 <ref type="bibr">(March 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Comparisons between groups were made with two-tailed t-tests.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patient characteristics</head><p><s>Of the ninety CF centres which were invited to participate, 56 took part in the survey.</s><s>The participating centres cared for 4265 patients, was equivalent to about 85% of patients documented in the German cystic fibrosis registry in 2009.</s><s>Centre staff recruited 1642 adult CF patients and 1205 parents of minors (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>In parallel, 513 adolescents were recruited to report their experiences using another questionnaire (results will be published elsewhere).</s><s>The response rates were 74% in both adults and parents.</s><s>The two reminders that had been sent out to unresponsive patients increased the response rates by more than one third.</s><s>Patient characteristics are displayed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, as reported from participants.</s><s>Respondents covered the whole spectrum of cystic fibrosis lung disease, although most were mildly to moderately affected.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>General experience with care</head><p><s>In general, participants reported favourable experiences with CF centre care.</s><s>Twenty-three items had very good problem score between 1 and 5%, while 31 questions had problem scores of over 20%.</s><s>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> summarises the items with the lowest problem scores.</s><s>Both parents and adults met friendly staff who spent enough time with patients and gave understandable answers to their questions.</s></p><p><s>When asked about their overall experience, most respondents rated the care as excellent or very good and stated that they would recommend the CF department to friends or family (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>).</s><s>Responses of adult patients and parents were very similar.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CF specific experiences</head><p><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> shows that the best experiences with the lowest problem scores were related to the factors "Physiotherapists" and "PhysicianePatient Interaction".</s><s>On the other end of the spectrum, both inpatient and outpatient "Facilities, Hygiene and Service" had higher median problem scores of around 30%.</s><s>The factors "Inpatient Care on the Ward", "NurseePatient Interaction", and "Information and Training" had problem scores over 15%.</s><s>In spite of favourable overall experience, there were several issues where centre staff did not meet the requirements of the majority of respondents.</s><s>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref> shows the items with the highest problem scores.</s><s>Half of the respondents could not discuss their anxieties and fears with nurses in an appropriate way, although 70% of participants stated they wished to do so.</s><s>There were also problems with respect to informing patients about possible adverse drug reactions, informing about new medical research on CF, and prompt notification of test results.</s></p><p><s>Several of the 32 items that were not covered by one of the ten factors also showed suboptimal care.</s><s>Examples are "If you have urgent medical questions and the contact you want is not available immediately, how long does it usually take for someone to get back to you?", where 48.9% of parents and 32.2% of adults stated they had to wait more than 2 h for a response.</s><s>Another example is "Do you know whom to contact outside CF department hours?" with 30.7% of parents and 34.2% of adults answering with "no".</s></p><p><s>As shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, adults had higher problem scores than parents in eight of the ten factors.</s><s>Answers from adult patients were generally more discerning regarding most of the items, too.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Comparisons with other centres and online reports</head><p><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> shows the median problem scores of the ten factors across centres.</s><s>As reflected by the 25th and 75th percentiles, considerable variation was found between the 56 participating institutions.</s><s>For "Inpatient Care on the Ward" of adult patients, for example, the 14 centres with the best results (lower quartile) had problem scores 9%, while the 14 centres of the upper quartile had problem scores of 25%.</s></p><p><s>All participating centres had online access to the survey results of their clinic.</s><s>Centre data were related to means and standard deviations from all participating institutions, and staff could judge their performance in comparison to that of direct peers.</s><s>An example is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Making use of survey results</head><p><s>All centres had given written consent to evaluate the findings of the survey and to use them for quality improvement efforts.</s><s>Since this was the first patient experience survey in German CF centres, no instructions were given beforehand on how centres should make use of their results.</s><s>A survey in the participating centres was carried out in 2013.</s><s>Results showed that 35 (87.5%) of the 40 responding centres had initiated changes based on the survey results.</s><s>Staff regarded the efforts for recruiting patients as adequate (85%) or low (8%).</s><s>The majority (75%) assessed the online reports displaying the survey results as comprehensible.</s><s>Discussions with patient representatives had taken place in 30 (75%) centres, and 24 (60%) centres reported positive experiences.</s><s>Most centres were interested to participate in a follow-up survey which should preferably be performed in 2015.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>This nationwide survey explored the patients' and parents' views on the care and services provided at German CF centres.</s><s>Respondents reported mostly positive experiences with centre staff, and their overall experience was very positive.</s><s>However, the newly developed, disease-specific questionnaires also revealed a number of shortcomings.</s><s>Major issues were related to communication, information and education, as well as to facilities and services in the outpatient clinic and on the ward.</s><s>To our knowledge, this is the first report on a nationwide patient experience survey using a CF specific questionnaire.</s><s>Two slightly different versions of the instrument were generated for adult patients with cystic fibrosis and for parents of minors with CF.</s><s>The items addressed important areas of health services, communication, and education, and they also displayed the performance of the different professional groups involved in CF care.</s><s>The only other CFspecific experience of care questionnaire we are aware of was developed in the United States <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[11]</ref>.</s><s>It contains 50 questions covering dimensions such as access to care, health team care, and self-care.</s><s>Many topics are common to both the US and the German questionnaires.</s><s>Only the US instrument addresses self-care and self-confidence of patients, while the German questionnaire differentiates between the groups of professional caregivers.</s></p><p><s>We achieved very good response rates: even though the questionnaire contained more than 100 items, 74% of both adult patients and parents took their time to respond.</s><s>These rates compare favourably with other patient surveys, for example the 37% response rate in 51,129 chronically ill patients in the U.S. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[12]</ref> or the 58.5% response rate from patients in 24 Swiss hospitals <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[13]</ref>.</s><s>In addition, we regard the investigated sample as representative for the whole patient cohort, since the 56 participating centres cared for about 85% of patients documented in the German CF patient registry.</s></p><p><s>In the US survey, the response rates were much lower, only between 3% and 23% <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[11]</ref>.</s><s>Subjects responded either via a web-based survey or by using a toll-free phone-line.</s><s>In the present study, staff at the CF centre stressed the importance of getting feedback from their patients.</s><s>Participants received an information leaflet and were requested to sign a consent form.</s><s>A signature represents a much stronger commitment to participate than getting an invitation by e-mail <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[14]</ref>.</s><s>The survey was completely anonymous, and the study centre had neither access to clinical data of individual patients nor to the German CF patient registry.</s><s>We also used further methods which are known to significantly increase the response to postal surveys <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[15]</ref>, namely, an interesting questionnaire topic, assurance of confidentiality, use of stamped return envelopes, and sending out two reminders.</s></p><p><s>Factor analysis revealed ten factors which covered the majority of items and accounted for about 50% of the total variance <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>.</s><s>Patients reported different experiences with respect to these themes.</s><s>Only very few problems with physiotherapists and physicians were reported, while there were several issues regarding facilities in the outpatient After your child is discharged, is the key information about the hospital stay quickly available in the CF department? a N Z 540 (60.6%) parents and N Z 886 (72.6%) adult patients responded to these items.</s><s>clinic and "hotel services" on the ward.</s><s>In the US pilot study, patients had generally positive opinions regarding the health care team <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[11]</ref>.</s><s>Interestingly, only about 50% gave positive responses to the item "Wish you knew more about meds".</s><s>Likewise, in our study a high proportion of respondents complained that they did not receive sufficient information on medication side effects.</s><s>The online reports allowed comparisons between centre results and the aggregated results of all 56 participating institutions.</s><s>The relatively large variances suggest that considerable differences between centres were present.</s><s>In the United States, the 25 item HCAHPS questionnaire (Hospital Consumer Assessment of Healthcare Providers and Systems) is used to assess general medical care in almost 4000 hospitals.</s><s>Comparison charts are regularly published on the internet, grouped by hospital region, location, bed size, teaching status, and ownership and control <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[16]</ref>.</s><s>The data of April 2013 were generated form nearly 3 million patient surveys.</s><s>Compared with a project of that size, our CF specific nationwide survey included only small numbers of participating institutions and patients.</s><s>The potential for external quality management with meaningful centre comparisons was therefore limited.</s><s>In the 27 largest institutions, however, we compared the problem scores of the factor "Organisation and Access", and observed that three centres had significantly better results than the others.</s><s>Thus, the new instrument can be used for statistical comparisons between larger centres.</s><s>Nevertheless, we think that the simple display of centre results compared with means and standard deviations of others will already serve as an important tool for quality management.</s><s>For national comparisons, it would be worthwhile to use translated and adapted versions of this instrument in other countries.</s></p><p><s>The project group has developed disease-specific questionnaires for two other chronic diseases of childhood, namely juvenile rheumatoid arthritis <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[17]</ref> and type 1 diabetes mellitus.</s><s>While nationwide surveys have not been performed so far using these instruments, the concept has the potential to delinate strengths and weaknesses of care across different chronic diseases.</s></p><p><s>The project had some limitations.</s><s>First, although 90 CF centres were approached, only 56 joined in.</s><s>The participating centres however treated about 85% of all patients with cystic fibrosis documented in the German CF registry that year.</s><s>Because participation was optional and was not associated with financial compensation, we had estimated at the outset that about 30 centres would agree to participate.</s><s>In retrospect, it seemed important that the Physicians Working Group AGAM had promoted the project from the very beginning.</s><s>Second, not all patients treated at the centres were recruited, and not all recruited patients returned the questionnaire.</s><s>We cannot exclude that the remaining patients had different views.</s><s>Not all patients visited the centre during the recruitment period.</s><s>Some patients were not invited because of inadequate German language skills, so there is no systematic feedback from this subgroup.</s><s>Ethnic and socio-economic aspects may influence the patients' views, as has been observed in the United Kingdom <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[18]</ref>.</s><s>Third, due to financial and organisational restraints we did not create a questionnaire version specifically for children and adolescents.</s><s>Patients aged 12e17 years were nevertheless surveyed in parallel using a modified and translated version of an established questionnaire on health care preferences and priorities of adolescents <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref>.</s><s>Preliminary results of the adolescents' pilot survey have been presented in poster form <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In conclusion, the newly developed, CF specific questionnaire was used to explore the participants' perspective of the care they receive in CF centres.</s><s>In general, patients' and parents' care experience was positive.</s><s>In spite of this, the instrument showed specific shortcomings related to communication, centre organisation, and facilities.</s><s>The comparison with aggregated results from all participating centres helped to identify which topics were of major importance for quality improvement in each centre.</s><s>In the future, translating the instrument into other languages and adapting it to the conditions of other health care systems would allow international comparisons.</s><s>We suggest that the patients' views should become an integral component of quality management efforts to promote patient-centred care.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1 Problem scores of factors in the participating centres.</s><s>Problem scores of the ten factors in the 56 participating centres.</s><s>The boxes contain the median values (50th percentile), and the error bars stretch from the 25th to the 75th percentiles.</s><s>Light bars reflect the results from parents and dark bars those from adult patients with CF.</s><s>The names of the factors have been abbreviated due to space constraints on the graph.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2 Online report: comparison of centre results with those of all participating centres (means and standard deviations).</s><s>Example of survey results as displayed in the online reports.</s><s>Problematic answers to the question are written in bold italics.</s><s>The upper box shows the problem frequency in the CF centre, the lower box is the mean problem frequency of all 56 participating centres, and the error bars reflect the standard deviations of the mean.</s><s>This way of presenting the data allows centre staff to compare their results with those of other German CF centres.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,51.53,56.69,226.77,138.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Patient characteristics as reported by respondents.</s><s>a</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Parents/children b</cell><cell>Adult patients</cell></row></table><note><p><s>a To assure that the survey was anonymous, there was no link between the questionnaires and medical records.</s><s>b Clinical data are from minors with CF. c Children below 6 years of age had no lung function tests.</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Items with the best results (mean problem score 3% in any group).</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Item</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Items addressing the general impression of patient care.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Frequency (%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Parents</cell><cell>Adult patients</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Overall, how would you rate the care you receive in the CF</cell></row><row><cell>department? (Item 75)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Excellent</cell><cell>32.7</cell><cell>24.9</cell></row><row><cell>Very good</cell><cell>46.1</cell><cell>44.5</cell></row><row><cell>Good</cell><cell>17.5</cell><cell>24.3</cell></row><row><cell>Fair</cell><cell>3.1</cell><cell>4.8</cell></row><row><cell>Poor</cell><cell>0.6</cell><cell>1.4</cell></row><row><cell>(No response)</cell><cell>( 5.0)</cell><cell>( 2.1)</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Would you recommend the CF department to your family</cell></row><row><cell>and friends? (Item 76)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Yes, definitely</cell><cell>71.4</cell><cell>56.8</cell></row><row><cell>Yes, probably</cell><cell>26.1</cell><cell>37.0</cell></row><row><cell>Not really</cell><cell>1.1</cell><cell>4.1</cell></row><row><cell>No</cell><cell>1.4</cell><cell>2.1</cell></row><row><cell>(No response)</cell><cell>( 5.6)</cell><cell>( 2.2)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Items with the highest problem scores grouped by factors.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Factor</cell><cell>Item</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3">na: not applicable.a N Z 341 (38.3%) parents and N Z 213 (17.4%) adults reported contacts with psychosocial staff during the last 12 months.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>We thank all patients and parents who participated in the survey.</s><s>Many thanks to all staff who recruited patients for the project.</s><s>The development of the questionnaire and the nation wide survey in Germany was supported by an educational grant from Mukoviszidose e.V., the German CF Association.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest statement</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Heinrich-Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sextro CF-Zentrum Innsbruck Klinikum Links der Weser Christiane-Herzog-Ambulanz fu ¨r Mukoviszidose HELIOS Klinikums Berlin</title>
		<title level="s">Klinikums Cottbus Mukoviszidose Ambulanz CF-Ambulanz Worms Klinik Schillerho ¨he CF-Ambulanz fu ¨r Erwachsene Mukoviszidose-Ambulanz Wesel Nachsorgeklinik Tannheim CF-Ambulanz Wangen CF-Ambulanz Dr. Niethammer Klinikum Solingen Mukoviszidoseambulanz Luisenhospital Mukoviszidose Ambulanz Sta ¨dtisches Krankenhaus Kiel Mukoviszidose Ambulanz Mukoviszidose-Ambulanz Potsdam Sta ¨dtisches Klinikum Brandenburg Mukoviszidose-Ambulanz Klinik Frankfurt an der Oder Mukoviszidoseambulanz Mukoviszidose-Ambulanz Neubrandenburg Kinderkrankenhaus Park Scho ¨nfeld CF-Ambulanz Dr. med. Szczepanski, Osnabru ¨ck CF-Ambulanz Olgahospital Stuttgart CF-Ambulanz CF-Ambulanz der Ostalb-Kliniken Aalen CF-Ambulanz Siegen Sana Klinikum Lichtenberg Mukoviszidose Zentrum Kinder-und Jugendklinik Erlangen Mukoviszidose-Ambulanz Universita ¨tsklinikums Erlangen CF-Ambulanz fu ¨r Erwachsene CF-Ambulanz Tu ¨bingen Universita ¨tsklinik Heidelberg Mukoviszidose Ambulanz Thoraxklinik Heidelberg Mukoviszidose Zentrum Universita ¨tsklinikum Freiburg Mukoviszidoseambulanz Universita ¨tsklinikum Mu ¨nster Mukoviszidose-Ambulanz Christiane-Herzog-Zentrum Mukoviszidoseambulanz Charite ´Berlin Gemeinschaftspraxis Dr</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Heuer, Dr. Runge, Dr</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Klinikum Zwickau CF-Ambulanz Universita ¨tskinderklinik Dresden CF-Ambulanz Universita ¨tsklinikum Essen Mukoviszidose Zentrum Mukoviszidose-Ambulanz Oldenburg Carl-Thiem ; Ambulanz Universita ¨tsklinikum Essen Mukoviszidose Zentrum Mukoviszidosezentrum Ko ¨ln Universita ¨tsklinikum Mu ¨nchen TU Mu ¨nchen CF-Ambulanz Universita ¨tsmedizin Mainz CF-Ambulanz MHH Kinderklinik Pulmologische Ambulanz Medizinische Hochschule Hannover CF-Ambulanz fu ¨r Erwachsene Universita ¨tsklinikum Halle Mukoviszidose Ambulanz Universita ¨tsklinikum Jena Mukoviszidose Ambulanz Mukoviszidose-Zentrum Mecklenburg Vorpommern Mukoviszidose Ambulanz Rostock Universita ¨tskinderklinik Magdeburg CF-Ambulanz Christiane Herzog CF-Zentrum Frankfurt am Main Universita ¨tskinderklinik Wu ¨rzburg Mukoviszidose-Ambulanz UKSH Kiel Mukoviszidose-Zentrum fu ¨r Erwachsene References</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Buch Mukoviszidose Zentrum Mukoviszidose-Ambulanz HELIOS Kliniken Schwerin Helios Klinikum Krefeld Mukoviszidose-Ambulanz Justus-Liebig-Universita ¨t Gieben &amp; Marburg Mukoviszidose-Ambulanz fu ¨r Erwachsene Universita ¨tsklinikum Gieben &amp; Marburg GmbH Mukoviszidose-Ambulanz des Zentrums fu ¨r Kinderheilkunde CF-Ambulanz Klinik St. Hedwig in Regensburg St. Josef-Hospital Bochum Mukoviszidose</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Standards of care for patients with cystic fibrosis: a European consensus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kerem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Conway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Elborn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Heijerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cyst Fibros</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="e26" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-03">2005 Mar</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A comparison of survival, growth, and pulmonary function in patients with cystic fibrosis in Boston and Toronto</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Corey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mclaughlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Levison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="583" to="e91" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cystic fibrosis across Europe: EuroCareCF analysis of demographic data from 35 countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mehta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Macek</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mehta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cyst Fibros</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="S5" to="e21" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-10-31">2010 Oct 31</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl. 2</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">World Health Organization. Adherence to long-term therapies e evidence for action</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<pubPlace>Geneva</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patient experience in cystic fibrosis care: development of a disease-specific questionnaire</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Stahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Steinkamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ullrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Schulz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Koningsbruggen-Rietschel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Heuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ellemunter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Schwarz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">24973915</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chronic Illn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">1742395314542051</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014-06-27">2014 Jun 27</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Epub ahead of print</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The picker patient experience questionnaire: development and validation using data from in-patient surveys in five countries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jenkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Coulter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bruster</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Qual Health Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="353" to="e358" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-10">2002 Oct</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rating satisfaction research: is it poor, fair, good, very good, or excellent?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Di</forename><surname>Palo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Care Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="422" to="e430" />
			<date type="published" when="1997-12">1997 Dec</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Health care preferences and priorities of adolescents with chronic illnesses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Britto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Devellis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hornung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Defriese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Atherton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Slap</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004-11">2004 Nov</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Health care preferences and satisfaction in adolescents with CF</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ullrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Stahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Abstract 384</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">S99. 2010. Ref Type: Abstract</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010-06">June 2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patients&apos; experiences and satisfaction with health care: results of a questionnaire study of specific aspects of care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jenkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Coulter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bruster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Richards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chandola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Qual Saf Health Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="335" to="e339" />
			<date type="published" when="2002-12">2002 Dec</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development and validation of a cystic fibrosis patient and family member experience of care survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Homa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sabadosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Nelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Qual Manag Health Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="e116" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-04">2013 Apr</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measuring chronic care delivery: patient experiences and clinical performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Sequist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Von</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Safran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Qual Health Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="206" to="e213" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-06">2012 Jun</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple approach to fairer hospital benchmarking using patient experience data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Holzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Minder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Qual Health Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="524" to="e530" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-10">2011 Oct</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Personally addressed hand-signed letters increase questionnaire response: a meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Health Serv Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">111</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Methods to increase response to postal and electronic questionnaires</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Clarke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Diguiseppi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wentz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kwan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">R000008</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Summary of HCAHPS survey results e HCAHPS hospital characteristics comparison charts</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-01-16">2014 Jan 16</date>
			<pubPlace>Baltimore, MD</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Paediatric rheumatology services through the parents&apos; eyes: a pilot study to develop a disease specific questionnaire to monitor deficiencies of care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Thon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mokross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Dressler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Stahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Gu ¨nther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ullrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatr Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Understanding ethnic and other socio-demographic differences in patient experience of primary care: evidence from the English General Practice Patient Survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lyratzopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Elliott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Barbiere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Henderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Staetsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Paddison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ Qual Saf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="e29" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-01">2012 Jan</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
