<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">models. ConClusions: The specified mapping algorithms from the BDI index to the EQ-5D-3L index for patients with depressive disorders are acceptable for usage as approximation in cost-utility analyses. A further validation in independent samples is necessary to obtain more confidence in their performance. PRM141 Issues AffectIng QuAlIty of lIfe And dIseAse BuRden In lIPoPRoteIn lIPAse defIcIency (lPld) -fIRst steP towARds A PRo MeAsuRe In lPld</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stroes</forename><surname>Es</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Southampton</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Southampton</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Vascular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Amsterdam Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Netherlands</addrLine>
									<settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Cardiovascular Trials Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Central Manchester University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Guy´s &amp; St. Thomas´ Hospitals</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="institution">Basurto University Hospital (Osakidetza) -REDISSEC</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bilbao</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff10">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Servicio Canario de la Salud -REDISSEC</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Santa Cruz de Tenerife</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff11">
								<orgName type="institution">Corporació Parc Tauli Clinic</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Sabadell, Barcelona</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff12">
								<orgName type="institution">Costa del Sol Hospital -REDISSEC</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Marbella -Malaga</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Steinhagen</forename><surname>-Thiessen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Southampton</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Southampton</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Endocrinology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Metabolism, Diabetes and Nutrition</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">CarMeN -Research Laboratory in Cardiovascular</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lyon</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Hôpital Pitié Salpêtrière -Charles Foix</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Interdisciplinary Metabolism Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Charité, Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Community Genomic Medicine Centre and Lipid Clinic</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Montréal</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>9 Chiesi Farmaceutici, 10 uniQure B.V., 11 Kantar Health</addrLine>
									<settlement>Chicoutimi, Parma, Amsterdam, Montrouge, 12 Centro regionale delle malattie rare del metabolismo dell&apos; adulto (CERMMET)</settlement>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country>Canada, Italy, The Netherlands, France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Policlinico &quot;P.Giaccone&quot;</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Palermo</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Palermo</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="institution">Basurto University Hospital (Osakidetza) -REDISSEC</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bilbao</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Gorostiza</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Southampton</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Southampton</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="institution">Basurto University Hospital (Osakidetza) -REDISSEC</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bilbao</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Garcia</forename><surname>-Perez</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Southampton</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Southampton</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Vascular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Amsterdam Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Netherlands</addrLine>
									<settlement>Amsterdam</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Cardiovascular Trials Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Central Manchester University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Guy´s &amp; St. Thomas´ Hospitals</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="institution">Basurto University Hospital (Osakidetza) -REDISSEC</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bilbao</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff10">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Servicio Canario de la Salud -REDISSEC</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Santa Cruz de Tenerife</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff11">
								<orgName type="institution">Corporació Parc Tauli Clinic</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Sabadell, Barcelona</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff12">
								<orgName type="institution">Costa del Sol Hospital -REDISSEC</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Marbella -Malaga</settlement>
									<country key="ES">Spain</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">models. ConClusions: The specified mapping algorithms from the BDI index to the EQ-5D-3L index for patients with depressive disorders are acceptable for usage as approximation in cost-utility analyses. A further validation in independent samples is necessary to obtain more confidence in their performance. PRM141 Issues AffectIng QuAlIty of lIfe And dIseAse BuRden In lIPoPRoteIn lIPAse defIcIency (lPld) -fIRst steP towARds A PRo MeAsuRe In lPld</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">174B9F09AB9F5A37EB24C8A74ECE9BBA</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:33+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>objeCtives: LPLD is an ultra-orphan genetic lipid disorder (prevalence 1-2/million).</s><s>It is associated with severe hypertriglyceridemia and an increased risk of acute pancreatitis.</s><s>Other manifestations include eruptive xanthoma, fatigue, difficulty with concentrating and cardiopulmonary symptoms.</s><s>Associated symptoms, complications and the fat-restricted diet affect Quality of Life (QOL).</s><s>Currently no disease-specific measure exists to assess QOL and the burden of LPLD.</s><s>As part of post approval commitments of alipogene tiparvovec, regulatory bodies requested the development of a reliable measure of QOL in LPLD.</s><s>This study evaluates existing EORTC questionnaires QLQ-C30 and QLQ-PAN26, and a new questionnaire of disease burden devised by clinicians with experience in treating LPLD.</s><s>Methods: To date, eight genetically confirmed LPLD-patients from four countries assessed the relevance and importance of each item of the three questionnaires.</s><s>Patients' ratings were discussed during an in-depth, face-to-face interview and the disease burden questionnaire was comprehensively discussed, analyzed and then modified where necessary.</s><s>Results: Quantitative assessment showed that 25 (45%) of the QLQ-C30 and QLQ-PAN26 questions were relevant to the majority of patients.</s><s>The most relevant items were pain ( <ref type="formula">6</ref>), fatigue and sleeping problems (4), digestive and dietary factors (4), work, daily and social activity restrictions (4) and impact on emotional functioning (3).</s><s>Qualitative and quantitative analysis of the new questionnaire highlighted the unpredictability of pancreatitis attacks and the impact of the strict low fat diet on social and emotional factors.</s><s>Less common clinical manifestations of LPLD (xanthoma, dyspnea) were very important to those affected.</s><s>The new questionnaire has been modified and items on alcohol use and painkillers added for ongoing evaluation.</s><s>ConClusions: Five QOL domains relevant to LPLD have been identified using existing questionnaires.</s><s>A new disease-specific questionnaire identifies significant impacts on patients' lives.</s><s>These instruments may help clinicians to effectively use pharmacological and genetic therapy to manage LPLD patients.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>objeCtives: The Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire (MLHFQ) is one of the most widely used health-related quality of life (HRQoL) specific questionnaires for patients with heart failure (HF).</s><s>It provides two dimensions (physical and emotional) and a global score.</s><s>However, there are some concerns about its factor structure, and different alternatives have been proposed, including even a third factor representing a social dimension.</s><s>The objective of the present study was to study the internal structure of the MLHFQ, the unidimensionality of the total score, and to compare the different factor structures raised.</s><s>Methods: We included 2565 patients hospitalized for HF, who were provided with the MLHFQ during hospitalization.</s><s>The structural validity of the questionnaire was studied by confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) for categorical data, and the Rasch rating scale model.</s><s>These two approaches were also applied to the different structures proposed.</s><s>Results: The results of the CFA for the hypothesized model of two latent factors and the Rasch analysis confirmed the adequacy of the physical and emotional dimensions.</s><s>We only found two problematic items within the total score.</s><s>The results of the CFA applied to other two-factor structures proposed were not better than the results of the original structure.</s><s>The Rasch analysis applied to the different social factors showed the best results for Munyombwe's social dimension.</s><s>ConClusions: The results support the validity of using the MLHFQ physical and emotional subscales in patients with HF, as well as the total score.</s><s>In addition, the results confirmed the existence of a third social factor, and we recommend the use of Munyombwe's social factor.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PRM143</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PRM138 IncReMentAl QuAlIty Adjusted lIfe yeARs (QAly) AnAlysIs In ABsence of heAd to heAd And heAlth RelAted QuAlIty of lIfe (hRQol) dAtA: A cAse study In thyRoId cAnceR</head><p><s>Tremblay G 1 , Lloyd A 2 , Majethia U 3 , Pelletier C 1 , Forsythe A 3 , Briggs A 4 1 Eisai, Woodcliff Lake, NJ, USA, 2 Bladon Associates, Oxford, UK, 3 Eisai Inc., Woodcliff Lake, NJ, USA, 4 The University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK objeCtives: In recent years, the healthcare industry has witnessed a trend for regulatory approvals of innovative technologies in oncology without head-to-head clinical trial evidence or Health Related Quality-of-Life (HRQoL) data.</s><s>This yields a challenge to decision-makers who require a cost-effectiveness analysis (CEA) to conduct Health Technology Assessments.</s><s>To demonstrate methodological approaches and potential data sources to address these gaps, we present a case study using recently approved drugs lenvatinib and sorafenib for management of radioiodine-refractory differentiated thyroid cancer (RR-DTC).</s><s>Methods: A vignette study was conducted to elicit utilities for RR-DTC health-states and estimate the impact of toxicities on HRQoL.</s><s>Phase III clinical trial data with crossover correction were used to compare clinicalendpoints of Progression Free Survival (PFS) and Overall Survival (OS) for both lenvatinib and sorafenib.</s><s>Adjustments for study population differences were addressed using Matching-Adjusted Indirect Comparison.</s><s>PFS and OS data were extrapolated to 10 years using proportional hazard, accelerated time failure, individual parametric models and piecewise models and time in health states was estimated from the partitioning of survival time into pre-and post-progression.</s><s>Results: Adjusted HRs for lenvatinib vs. sorafenib were estimated as 0.37(95%CI: 0.25-0.55)</s><s>for PFS and 0.79(0.45-1.37)</s><s>for OS.</s><s>PFS (stable) health-state utilities for each drug were adjusted using tumor response rates and incremental utility gain.</s><s>Combining phase III toxicity rates with utility decrements yielded a total disutility of 0.042 for lenvatinib vs. 0.117 for sorafenib.</s><s>Survival extrapolation (undiscounted) provided estimates of incremental 0.66 LYS and 0.60 QALY for lenvatinib vs. sorafenib.</s><s>ConClusions: This analysis demonstrated that in absence of head-to-head trials and QoL trial data, vignette utility studies and ITC may be used to aid with QALY analysis, especially in orphan diseases where limited data are available.</s><s>Vignette studies and ITC can increase reliability of comparative-effectiveness data and support payers' decision making.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PRM139 RecoMMendAtIons foR AnAlysIs of PAtIent RePoRted outcoMes (PRo) effIcAcy dAtA when evAluAtIng tReAtMent BenefIt</head><p><s>Nixon MJ, Nixon A Chilli Consultancy, Salisbury, UK objeCtives: Lack of rigour in PRO data analysis leads to uncertainty around the quality of results impacting the extent to which conclusions can be drawn from the data.</s><s>This study sought to provide guidelines for PRO efficacy data analysis for study sponsors in order to ensure confidence in PRO results by stakeholder decision makers.</s><s>Methods: A targeted review was undertaken of guidelines for clinical trial and PRO data analysis, and published PRO analysis studies that demonstrated good practice in PRO efficacy analysis.</s><s>The evidence was synthesised by a team comprising statistical and PRO experts experienced in the analysis of PRO efficacy data.</s><s>An 8-step guideline was developed based on the available evidence.</s><s>Results: Eight steps that will ensure high quality analysis of PRO trial efficacy data are (1) avoid unplanned or post analysis by developing a PRO specific SAP prior to data base lock, or document comprehensive PRO data analysis in the clinical trial SAP (2) ensure awareness of differing requirements across stakeholders in PRO data analysis/interpretation and adequately address this in the SAP to ensure (3) specify primary and secondary PRO endpoints and/or approaches to correcting for multiplicity (4) develop and specify appropriate approaches to handling missing data including sensitivity analysis (5) include analysis of PRO score change from baseline (6) specify approaches to interpreting change from baseline data including any benchmarks which will be applied during interpretation (7) implement a 100% double programming approach alongside table review by statistically qualified team members (8) interpret PRO results not only in isolation but alongside other clinical outcomes ConClusions: For PRO data to effectively inform decision making across all stakeholders, high standards of data analysis needs to be mandatory.</s><s>This 8-step guideline, if adhered to, will raise the standard of PRO data analysis reducing the likelihood that PRO data is discounted by decision makers.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PRM140 MAPPIng the Beck dePRessIon InventoRy to the eQ-5d-3l In PAtIents wIth dePRessIve dIsoRdeRs</head><p><s>Grochtdreis T 1 , Brettschneider C 1 , Hajek A 1 , Schierz K 2 , Hoyer J 2 , König H 1 1 University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf, Hamburg, Germany, 2 Technische Universität Dresden, Dresden, Germany objeCtives: For cost-utility analyses, data on health state utilities, as provided by the EQ-5D-3L, is needed but not always available.</s><s>This study specifies a mapping algorithm from the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI) index to the EQ-5D-3L index adjusted for specific socio-demographic variables for patients with depressive disorders.</s><s>Methods: A sample of 1,074 consecutive patients with depressive disorders from a psychotherapeutic outpatient clinic was included in the study.</s><s>Standardized clinical interviews were applied to establish reliable diagnoses.</s><s>For the prediction of the EQ-5D-3L index from the BDI index and selected patient socio-demographic characteristics, ordinary least squares regression with robust standard errors was used.</s><s>Model prediction properties were tested using the root mean squared error and repeated random sub-sampling cross-validation.</s><s>Results: The BDI index predicted the EQ-5D-3L index with a significant proportion of variance explained.</s><s>The highest model goodness of fit was estimated for models with the BDI index and age as independent variables.</s><s>The root mean squared error of the predicted EQ-5D-3L index in the validation samples ranged from 0.225 to 0.228 between the principal components analysis and descending hierarchical classification.</s><s>Results: Steps 1-3: Development and adaptation of a self-reported 44-item questionnaire on a 0-10 scale of fears and beliefs.</s><s>5 domains established a priori: origin of the disease, flares, treatments, disease progression and consequences of disease.</s></p><p><s>Step 4: In the study of 226 patients (161 RA, 65 axSpA), all dimensions were ≥ 0.79 and ≤ 0.93, apart from the domain "origin of the disease" (0.67).</s><s>Principal component analysis identified 6 axes (63.7% of variance explained) and the descending hierarchical analysis identified 9 clusters (63.7% of variance).</s><s>2 clusters were highly correlated (r2= 0.80) and combined into a single cluster.</s><s>Based on the psychometric validation, the following domains were identified: fears of the disease progression/consequences (18 items) and fears about treatment (5); beliefs related to: psychological influence (2), genetic influence (2), physical influence (4), diet influence (4), lifestyle (3) and diverse opinions (4).</s><s>ConClusions: This analysis confirms the internal consistency of the questionnaire developed.</s><s>The scoring results should help physicians to understand their patients' perceptions of their disease better and eventually lead to improved adherence to treatment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PRM146 A vAlIdIty And RelIABIlIty study of the PoveRty RelAted QuAlIty of lIfe QuestIonnAIRe In A tuRkIsh PAtIent PoPulAtIon</head><p><s>Yilmaz F 1 , Numanoglu Tekin R 1 , Malhan S 2 1 Baskent University, ankara, Turkey, 2 Baskent University, Ankara, Turkey objeCtives: Measuring poverty in health care settings may contribute to identifying patients in poverty and subsequently getting appropriate management.</s><s>Although many scales are available to measure poverty in health, less attention has been paid to the poverty related quality of life.</s><s>The purpose of this methodological study was to adapt the Poverty Related Quality of Life Questionnaire developed by Boyer and others (2014) into Turkish and to evaluate its psychometric properties for a Turkish patient population.</s><s>Methods: The scale was adapted into Turkish through a translation and back-translation process.</s><s>The content validity of the scale was assessed using expert approval.</s><s>The psychometric properties of the scale were investigated by collecting data from 300 patients in 3 emergency departments from random selected hospitals in Ankara during the period of 1 April-30 May 2015.</s><s>Results: An exploratory factor analysis identified that the seven-factor structure accounted for 80.1% of the total variance.</s><s>A confirmatory factor analysis indicated a sufficient model fit for the construct validity of the scale: root mean square error of approximation, 0.041; comparative fit index, 0.93; general fit index, 0.97; standardized root mean square residual, 0.050.</s><s>Cronbach's alpha for the total scale was 0.83 and each item achieved the 0.40 standard for item internal consistency.</s><s>Significant associations with socioeconomic and clinical indicators showed good discriminant validity.</s><s>ConClusions: This study supports the validity and reliability of the Turkish version of Poverty Related Quality of Life Questionnaire.</s><s>This instrument can be used to measure multiple aspects of poverty in the health care settings; however, as poverty and quality of life are contextual facts, further work is needed to test the psychometric properties of this scale both in Turkish and different cultures.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PRM147 develoPMent of A PRedIctIon Model of dIseAse ActIvIty In suPPoRt of clInIcAl PRActIce -the AcRodAt exPeRIence</head><p><s>Pleil A 1 , van der Lely AJ 2 , Badia X 3 , Brue T 4 , Buchfelder M 5 , Burman P 6 , Ghigo E 7 , Gomez R 8 , Jorgensen JO 9 , Luger A 10 , van der Lans-Bussemaker J 8 , Webb S 11 , Strasburger C 12 1 Pfizer, Inc, San Diego, CA, USA, 2 Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, The Netherlands, 3 University of Barcelona, Barcelona, Spain, 4 Centre de Recherche Neurobiologie Neurophysiologie, Marseille, France, 5 Universitatsklinikum Erlangen, Erlangen, Germany, 6 Skåne University Hospital, Malmo, Sweden, 7 Univ Degli Studi Di Torino, Torino, Italy, 8 Pfizer, Inc, Tadworth/Surrey, UK, 9 Aarhus University, Aarhus, Denmark, 10 Medical University of Vienna,  Vienna, Austria, 11 Hospital Sant Pau, Barcelona, Spain, 12 Charité Universitätsmedizin, Berlin, Germany objeCtives: The objective of this study was to develop and validate a decision algorithm that replicates expert opinion regarding the level of disease activity in patients with acromegaly.</s><s>Methods: A panel of key experts in endocrinology and outcomes research provided input as to what parameters are critical to assess disease activity.</s><s>The top five parameters where then subsequently defined at three levels of severity.</s><s>A final set of 243 unique health states were developed.</s><s>A group of 21 expert endocrinologists from 5 European countries and Canada was recruited to participate in a discrete choice experiment.</s><s>Each participant was presented with 10 common scenarios and 42 additional scenarios selected at random and asked to indicate whether the hypothetical patient was stable, having mild disease activity needing further evaluation, or having significant disease activity requiring clinical action.</s><s>Concordance in decisions based on the 10 common scenarios was tested using Fleiss Kappa and a set of linear prediction models tested to predict outcome.</s><s>Results:</s></p><p><s>The five parameters included: 1) IGF-I level (SDS score); 2) tumor status (change on MRI); 3) comorbidities (number and severity); 4) signs and symptoms (Patient Acromegaly Symptom Questionnaire score); and 5) health-related quality of life (scored on a disease specific measure).</s><s>The Inter-rater reliability was adequate (Kappa = 0.52).</s><s>Based on a CART analysis, the decision model of best fit was disjunctive with IGF-1 and Tumor status primarily predicting the health status.</s><s>The remaining three parameters were instructive but not deterministic.</s><s>ConClusions: Biochemical and tumor status are the primary predictors of disease activity, with the patient's perceived disease state playing a secondary role.</s><s>This may highlight the need for a more patient-centered approach to acromegaly disease management.</s><s>To enable clinical use of the model, a disease specific tool named ACRODAT (ACROmegaly Disease Activity Tool) is currently in further development.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PRM148 PhysIcAl functIonIng And PAIn In chRonIc low BAck PAIn: A systeMAtIc RevIew of PsychoMetRIc PRoPeRtIes of vARIous outcoMes MeAsuRes</head><p><s>Kanukula R 1 , Vsn M 1 , Ganji K 2 , Likhar N 1 , Dang A 1 1 Leeds University, Leeds, UK, 2 Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA, 3 Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany, 4 Hospital for Special Surgery, New York, NY, USA, 5 UCLA, Los Angeles, CA, USA, 6 Paris-Sud University, Paris, France, 7 UCB Pharma, Brussels, Belgium, 8 UCB Pharma, Durham, NC, USA, 9 Brigham and Women's Hospital, Boston, MA, USA objeCtives: To assess effects of CZP+MTX vs placebo (PBO)+MTX on patient reported outcomes in DMARD-naïve patients with severe, active and progressive RA.</s><s>Methods: Patients in this double-blind randomized study (NCT01519791) were DMARD-naïve with active RA&lt; 1yr diagnosis at baseline (BL), fulfilling 2010 ACR/EULAR criteria; ≥ 4 swollen and ≥ 4 tender joints; DAS28[ESR]≥ 3.2; CRP≥ 10mg/L and/or ESR≥ 28mm/hr, rheumatoid factor/ACPA positive.</s><s>Patients were randomized 3:1 to CZP (400mg Wks 0,2,4 then 200mg Q2W to Wk52)+MTX or PBO+MTX.</s><s>MTX was initiated at 10mg/wk, increased up to 25mg/wk by Wk8, maximum tolerated dose maintained to Wk52.</s><s>HAQ-DI, PtGADA, Pain VAS, %pts achieving normative physical function (HAQ-DI≤ 0.5), health-related QoL (SF-36, EQ-5D-3L) were assessed.</s><s>At Wk52 changes from baseline (CFB) were analyzed using ANCOVA (LOCF imputation); categorical variables were analyzed using logistic regression (non-responder imputation).</s><s>Data are LS mean CFB (SE) unless otherwise specified.</s><s>Results: 660 (CZP+MTX) and 219 (PBO+MTX) patients were randomized; 655 vs 213 in the full analysis set (patients with baseline and post-baselineL DAS28 <ref type="bibr">[ESR]</ref>).</s><s>Baseline characteristics were balanced between study arms; mean (SD) HAQ-DI= 1.6 (0.6), <ref type="bibr">Pain VAS= 66.1 (22.4),</ref><ref type="bibr">PtGADA= 65.3 (22.0)</ref>.</s><s>At Wk52, greater improvements from baseline were observed with CZP+MTX vs PBO+MTX in HAQ-DI (-1.0 [0.0] vs -0.8 [0.0], p&lt; 0.001; 48.1% vs 35.7% patients reached normative function), pain <ref type="bibr">(-48.5 [1.0] vs -44.0 [1.7]</ref>, p&lt; 0.05), PtGADA <ref type="bibr">(-46.7 [1.0] vs -42.0 [12.5]</ref>, p&lt; 0.05) and health-related QoL measured by  vs 10.7 [0.6], p&lt; 0.01; mental component summary score= 8.2 [0.5] vs 6.8 [0.7]).</s><s>Numerically higher proportions of CZP+MTX patients reported no problems in domains of the EQ-5D-3L vs PBO+MTX patients, including mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression.</s><s>ConClusions: In DMARD-naïve patients with severe, active and progressive RA, CZP+MTX showed greater improvements at 1-year in physical function, pain, disease activity and health-related QoL compared to PBO+MTX.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PRM144 cultuRAl AdAPtAtIon Into sPAnIsh (sPAIn) of the QuestIonnAIRe "oveRActIve BlAddeR -fAMIly IMPAct MeAsuRe (oAB-fIM)"</head><p><s>Arlandis-Guzmán S 1 , Martínez-Cuenca E 1 , Martínez-García R 2 , Bonillo-García M 1 , Broseta-Rico E 2 , Rejas J 3 1 Hospital Universitario La Fé, Valencia, Spain, 2 Hospital Universitario Clínico Valencia, Valencia,   Spain, 3 Pfizer, Alcobendas, Spain objeCtives: To carry-out the cultural adaptation into Spanish (for Spain) of the questionnaire "Overactive Bladder -Family Impact Measure (OAB-FIM)".</s><s>Methods:</s></p><p><s>The adaptation included linguistic validation through forward and back translations in duplicate, reviewed by a panel experts and a debriefing with relatives of OAB patients, and a phase of preliminary measurement of psychometric properties in OAB patients and their relatives of habitual coexistence, of both genders, ≥ 18 years of age, newly diagnosed and on-therapy for their symptoms of OAB.</s><s>Conceptual and linguistic equivalences, internal consistency (α -Cronbach), content validity (the inter-rater Rovinelli-Hambleton index of item congruence) and construct validity were measured.</s><s>Construct validity included concurrent validity (with scales ZARIT and OABq-SF), and validity of known groups according to the benefit of treatment with TBS scale.</s><s>Feasibility and burden of administration were also measured.</s><s>Results: 25 couples of patients [mean (SD): 57.2 (16.0) years, 60% women] and relatives [63.0 (14.3) years, 44% women] were enrolled.</s><s>The OAB-FIM was equivalent conceptually and linguistically to the original, remaining the six initial domains: activities, travel, concern, irritation, sleep and sex.</s><s>Missing items was low (2.95%).</s><s>Floor and ceiling effects varied, respectively, between 20%-28%, and 0%-16%.</s><s>The average time of completion was 5.2 (2.8) minutes.</s><s>24.0% needed some help to complete the questionnaire.</s><s>The Rovinelli-Hambleton index ranked correctly all items in its domain, except for the item 10 which ranked in domains irritation and concern.</s><s>α -Cronbach varied between 0.948-0.839.</s><s>Correlations of OAB-FIM with ZARIT were high-to-moderate (0.407-0.753) and moderate-to-small with the OABq-SF (0.004-0.423).</s><s>Relatives whose patients showed treatment benefit showed scores lower on the scale (lowest impact).</s><s>ConClusions: A Spanish version of the OAB-FIM conceptually and linguistically equivalent to the original has been obtained.</s><s>The questionnaire has shown good internal consistency, content validity and construct validity, together with feasibility in the Spanish culture.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PRM145 develoPMent And vAlIdAtIon of A QuestIonnAIRe AssessIng the feARs And BelIefs of PAtIents suffeRIng fRoM chRonIc RheuMAtIc dIseAses</head><p><s>Gossec L 1 , Saraux A 2 , Hudry C 3 , Mathoret-Philibert F 3 , Poussière M 4 , de Chalus T 5 , Russo-Marie F 6 , Joubert J 7 , Chauvin P 8 , Berenbaum F 9 1 Sorbonne Universités, Université Pierre et Marie Curie, AP-HP, Hôpital Pitié Salpêtrière, Paris, France, 2 CHU de la Cavale-Blanche, Brest Cedex, France, 3 AP-HP Hôpital Cochin, Paris, France,  4 Independent Researcher, Paris, France, 5 UCB Pharma, Colombes, France, 6 Arthritis Fondation   Courtin, Neuilly-sur-Seine, France, 7 UCB Pharma, Paris, France, 8</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>IMPRoveMents In PAtIent-RePoRted outcoMes followIng 52 weeks of tReAtMent wIth ceRtolIzuMAB Pegol In coMBInAtIon wIth MethotRexAte In dMARd-nAIve PAtIents wIth seveRe, ActIve And PRogRessIve RheuMAtoId ARthRItIs: Results fRoM the c-eARly RAndoMIzed, douBle-BlInd, contRolled PhAse 3 study Emery P 1 , Bingham C 2 , Burmester G 3 , Bykerk V 4 , Furst D 5 , Mariette X 6 , Purcaru O 7 , Coteur G 7 , Vanlunen B 8 , Weinblatt M 9 last-visit versions, whilst other items should be scored individually.</s><s>The last-visit version discriminates treatment response.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>French National Institute of Health and Medical Research (INSERM), Paris, France, 9 Sorbonne Universités, Université Pierre et Marie Curie, AP-HP, Hôpital Saint-Antoine, Paris, France objeCtives: To develop and validate a patient-reported questionnaire assessing the fears and beliefs of patients suffering from rheumatoid arthritis (RA) or spondyloarthritis (SpA), that could improve educational programs.</s><s>Methods: Step 1: Qualitative research (individual patient interviews: 25 RA, 25 axial SpA [axSpA]).</s><s>Step 2: All fears and beliefs appearing in more than 10% of interviews rephrased as questions by an expert group including a patient-partner.</s><s>Each question scored 0-10 (10= higher fears/stronger beliefs).</s><s>Step 3: Preliminary questionnaire tested by cognitive debriefing (5 RA, 5 axSpA patients), and reproducibility through a test-retest procedure among 28 patients (13 RA, 15 axSpA).</s><s>Step 4: Psychometric validation through a crosssectional study of 226 patients.</s><s>Internal consistency assessed by Cronbach's alpha,</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
