<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Is pooled data analysis of ventral and incisional hernia repair acceptable?</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-05-12">12 May 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tzu-An</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Chun-Chih</forename><surname>Chao</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Ferdinand</forename><surname>Köckerling</surname></persName>
							<email>ferdinand.koeckerling@vivantes.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Centre for Minimally Invasive Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Vivantes Hospital Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Academic Teaching Hospital of Charité Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Christine</forename><surname>Schug-Paß</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Centre for Minimally Invasive Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Vivantes Hospital Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Academic Teaching Hospital of Charité Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Daniela</forename><surname>Adolf</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">StatConsult GmbH</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Magdeburg, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wolfgang</forename><surname>Reinpold</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Wilhelmsburger Hospital Groß-Sand</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Academic Teaching Hospital of University Hamburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hamburg, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bernd</forename><surname>Stechemesser</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Hernia Center Cologne</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cologne</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Taiwan Landseed Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Ankara University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="TR">Turkey</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Taiwan Landseed Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="TW">Taiwan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Centre for Minimally Invasive Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Vivantes Hospital Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Academic Teaching Hospital of Charité Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Neue Bergstrasse 6</addrLine>
									<postCode>13585</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Is pooled data analysis of ventral and incisional hernia repair acceptable?</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-05-12">12 May 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">1623FA53E5E5E7AE39771D7D1923326E</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fsurg.2015.00015</idno>
					<note type="submission">This article was submitted to Visceral Received: 10 March 2015 Accepted: 25 April 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:34+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>incisional hernia</term>
					<term>umbilical hernia</term>
					<term>epigastric hernia</term>
					<term>ventral hernia</term>
					<term>primary ventral hernia</term>
					<term>complications</term>
					<term>recurrence</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>In meta-analyses and systematic reviews comparing laparoscopic with open repair of ventral hernias, data on umbilical, epigastric, and incisional hernias are pooled.</s><s>Based on data from the Herniamed Hernia Registry, we aimed to investigate whether the differences in the therapy and treatment results justified such an approach.</s></p><p><s>Methods: Between 1st September 2009 and 31st August 2013, 31,664 patients with a ventral hernia were enrolled in the Herniamed Hernia Registry.</s><s>The implicated hernias included 16,206 umbilical hernias, 3,757 epigastric hernias, and 11,701 incisional hernias.</s><s>Data on the surgical techniques, postoperative complication rates, and 1-year follow-up results were subjected to statistical analysis to identify any significant differences between the various hernia types.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results:</head><p><s>The laparoscopic IPOM technique was used significantly more often for incisional hernia than for epigastric hernia, 31.3 vs. 24.0%,</s><s>respectively, and was used for 12.9% of umbilical hernias (p &lt; 0.0001).</s><s>Likewise, the open technique with suturing of defect was used significantly more often for umbilical hernia than for epigastric hernia, 56.1 vs. 35.4%,</s><s>respectively, and was used for 12.5% of incisional hernias (p &lt; 0.0001).</s><s>The postoperative complication rates of 3.2% for umbilical hernia and 3.5% for epigastric hernia were significantly lower than for incisional hernia, at 9.2% (p &lt; 0.0001).</s><s>That was also true for the reoperation rates due to postoperative complications, of 1.0 vs. 1.2 vs. 4.2% (p &lt; 0.0001).</s><s>The 1-year follow-up revealed significantly higher recurrence rates as well as rates of chronic pain needing treatment of 6.3 and 7.9%, respectively, for incisional hernia, compared with 4.1 and 4.3%, respectively, for epigastric hernia, and 2 and 1.9%, respectively, for umbilical hernia (p &lt; 0.0001).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion:</head><p><s>Since significant differences were identified in the therapy and treatment results between umbilical hernia, epigastric hernia, and incisional hernia, scientific studies should be conducted comparing the various surgical techniques only for a single hernia type.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>This meant that when analyzing the results no distinction was made between primary ventral hernias and incisional hernias <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref> nor was any information given on the proportion of umbilical hernias, epigastric hernias, and incisional hernias identified in the entire patient group analyzed.</s><s>It was only at the beginning of 2015 that Awaiz et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> published the first meta-analysis and systematic review on laparoscopic vs. open incisional hernia repair.</s></p><p><s>Stirler et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref> were the first to point to significant differences in the results obtained for primary ventral hernias compared with incisional hernias.</s><s>They concluded that continued pooling of data on primary ventral hernias and incisional hernias, as a combined entity, seemed incorrect.</s><s>Based on data from the Herniamed Registry <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>, this paper now aims to identify the differences between umbilical, epigastric, and incisional hernias in respect of the surgical techniques employed, postoperative outcome, and 1-year follow-up.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patients and Methods</head><p><s>Herniamed is a multicenter, Internet-based hernia registry in which 358 participating clinics and surgeons in private practice from Germany, Austria, and Switzerland (status: 31 August 2013) have prospectively registered their patients who had undergone hernia operations <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>.</s><s>This present analysis now examines the prospective data of all patients who had undergone open or laparoscopic umbilical, epigastric, or incisional hernia repair between 1st September 2009 and 31st August 2013.</s><s>In total, 31,664 patients were enrolled (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>The implicated hernias included 16,206 umbilical hernias (26% female), 3,757 epigastric hernias (48% female), and 11,701 incisional hernias (52% female).</s><s>The age distribution shows a peak level for umbilical and epigastric hernias between 50 and 60 years and for incisional hernias between 70 and 80 years.</s></p><p><s>The following were calculated separately for each hernia type: the surgical techniques employed; the postoperative complication rates; reoperation rates due to postoperative complications; and the recurrence rates and rates of chronic pain needing treatment as identified on 1-year follow-up <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Using SAS 9.2 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NY, USA), a chi-square test was performed to investigate the differences between the various hernia types in respect of the surgical techniques employed, the postoperative complication rates, and the 1-year follow-up results.</s><s>The results are expressed as a p-value (unadjusted analysis in each case up to the full significance level of 5%).</s><s>Pairwise comparison of the individual hernia types was done on the basis of unadjusted estimate of an exact 95% confidence interval for each probability.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Analysis of the surgical techniques employed showed significant differences between the hernia types.</s><s>For example, the laparoscopic IPOM technique was used significantly more often for incisional hernia, in 31.3% of cases (p &lt; 0.0001), than for epigastric hernia, at 24.0%, and for umbilical hernia, at 12.9% (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>Likewise, there was also a highly significant difference between umbilical hernia and epigastric hernia (p &lt; 0.0001).</s><s>The open technique with suturing of defect was also used significantly more often, in 56.1% of cases, for umbilical hernia than for epigastric hernia, at 35.4%, and for incisional hernia, at 12.5% (p &lt; 0.0001).</s><s>Likewise, there were significant differences in the use of the open Sublay mesh technique between epigastric hernia and incisional hernia, which was 18.5 vs. 31.1%,</s><s>respectively (p &lt; 0.0001), as well as in the open Onlay technique, which was 5.5% for incisional hernia, 4.1% for umbilical hernia, and 3.3% for epigastric hernia (p &lt; 0.0001).</s></p><p><s>As regards the postoperative complication rates, comparable results were obtained for umbilical hernia, with a rate of 3.2%, and epigastric hernia, at 3.5%, but these differed significantly for incisional hernia with a rate of 9.2% (p &lt; 0.0001) (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>).</s><s>The same was true for the complication-related reoperation rates of 1.0% for umbilical hernia, 1.2% for epigastric hernia, and 4.2% for incisional hernia (p &lt; 0.0001).</s></p><p><s>The differences in the treatment results between umbilical hernia, epigastric hernia, and incisional hernia were even more pronounced on 1-year follow-up.</s><s>Accordingly, a significant difference was discerned in the recurrence rate of 2% for umbilical hernia, 4.1% for epigastric hernia, and 6.3% for incisional hernia (p &lt; 0.0001).</s><s>Equally, marked differences were noted in the rate of chronic pain needing treatment, which was 1.9% for umbilical hernia, 4.3% for epigastric hernia, and 7.9% for incisional hernia (p &lt; 0.0001) (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Based on the available registry data, it has been possible to identify significant differences in the utilization rates of the surgical techniques employed for the various ventral hernia types, i.e., umbilical hernia, epigastric hernia, and incisional hernia.</s><s>Likewise, differences were found regarding the treatment results achieved for the various hernia types based on the postoperative complication rates, complication-related reoperation rates as well as recurrence rates, and rates of chronic pain needing treatment on 1-year follow-up.</s><s>That highlights the fact that, when assessing the effectiveness of the various surgical techniques, the use of pooled analysis of the treatment results obtained for umbilical hernias, epigastric hernias, and incisional hernias can lead to incorrect results.</s><s>Pooled data produce a result that is also dependent on the combination ratio between umbilical hernia, epigastric hernia, and incisional hernia.</s><s>Therefore, the treatment results obtained for the various surgical techniques should only be compared for a single hernia type; that distinction was correctly made in the most recent meta-analysis, which focused only on incisional hernia, as conducted by Awaiz et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>.</s><s>All the other meta-analyses and systematic reviews published to date have compared laparoscopic with open repair for ventral and incisional hernias <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>.</s><s>For these meta-analyses, it is not possible to ascertain what influence was exerted on the detailed results by the combination ratio of the hernia types experienced by the enrolled patient group.</s><s>However, the study design to be used in future for prospective randomized trials and meta-analyses should ensure that comparison of the various surgical techniques employed is limited to one single clearly defined hernia type.</s><s>As such, studies aimed at treatment optimization should be conducted separately for umbilical hernia, epigastric hernia, and incisional hernia.</s></p><p><s>Only in this way, a difference between the various surgical techniques can be properly identified for a specific ventral hernia type.</s><s>In addition to prospective randomized comparative studies and meta-analyses, hernia registries can make an important contribution toward achieving that goal.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE 1 | Comparison of the surgical techniques employed in umbilical, epigastric and incisional hernia repair.</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Umbilical hernia n = 16,206</cell><cell>Epigastric hernia n = 3,757</cell><cell>Incisional hernia n = 11,701</cell><cell>p</cell></row><row><cell>Open suture</cell><cell>56.1% (n = 9,084) [55.3; 56.8]</cell><cell>35.4% (n = 1,330) [33.9; 36.9]</cell><cell>12.5% (n = 1,463) [11.9; 13.1]</cell><cell>&lt;0.0001</cell></row><row><cell>Open sublay</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>18.5% (n = 695) [17.3; 19.7]</cell><cell>31.1% (n = 3,641) [30.3; 32.0]</cell><cell>&lt;0.0001</cell></row><row><cell>Open onlay a</cell><cell>4.1% (n = 658) [3.8; 4.4]</cell><cell>3.3% (n = 123) [2.7; 3.9]</cell><cell>5.5% (n = 645) [5.1; 5.9]</cell><cell>&lt;0.0001</cell></row><row><cell>Open IPOM</cell><cell>14.8% (n = 2,399) [14.3; 15.4]</cell><cell>10.9% (n = 410) [9.9; 11.9]</cell><cell>13.2% (n = 1,549) [12.6; 13.9]</cell><cell>&lt;0.0001</cell></row><row><cell>Component separation b</cell><cell>1.5% (n = 250) [1.4; 1.7]</cell><cell>0.8% (n = 31) [0.6; 1.2]</cell><cell>1.6% (n = 184) [1.4; 1.8]</cell><cell>0.0022</cell></row><row><cell>Open others</cell><cell>10.7% (n = 1,726) [10.2; 11.1]</cell><cell>7.1% (n = 268) [6.3; 8.0]</cell><cell>4.8% (n = 562) [4.4; 5.2]</cell><cell>&lt;0.0001</cell></row><row><cell>Laparoscopic IPOM</cell><cell>12.9% (n = 2,089) [12.4; 13.4]</cell><cell>24.0% (n = 900) [22.6; 25.3]</cell><cell>31.3% (n = 3,657) [30.4; 32.1]</cell><cell>&lt;0.0001</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 2 | Comparison of the perioperative and 1-year outcome of umbilical, epigastric, and incisional hernia repair. Umbilical hernia n = 16,206 Epigastric hernia n = 3,757 Incisional hernia n = 11,701 p 1-year follow-up: n = 12,428/16,206 1-year follow-up: n = 2,895/3,757 1-year follow-up: 9,181/11,701</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>1-year Follow-up rate</cell><cell>76.7% (n = 12,428/16,206)</cell><cell>77.1% (n = 2,895/3,757)</cell><cell>78.7% (n = 9,181/11,701)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Postoperative complications a</cell><cell>3.2% (n = 515/16,206) [2.9; 3.5]</cell><cell>3.5% (n = 133/3,757) [3.0; 4.2]</cell><cell cols="2">9.2% (n = 1,075/11,701) [8.7; 9.7] &lt;0.0001</cell></row><row><cell>Reoperation rate for complications a</cell><cell>1.0% (n = 170/16,206) [0.9; 1.2]</cell><cell>1.2% (n = 44/3,757) [0.9; 1.6]</cell><cell>4.2% (n = 486/11,701) [3.8; 4.5]</cell><cell>&lt;0.0001</cell></row><row><cell>Chronic pain needing treatment</cell><cell>1.9% (n = 240/12,428) [1.7; 2.2]</cell><cell>4.3% (n = 124/2,895) [3.6; 5.1]</cell><cell>7.9% (n = 729/9,181) [7.4; 8.5]</cell><cell>&lt;0.0001</cell></row><row><cell>Recurrence rate</cell><cell>2.0% (n = 249/12,428) [1.8; 2.3]</cell><cell>4.1% (n = 119/2,895) [3.4; 4.9]</cell><cell>6.3% (n = 578/9,181) [5.8; 6.8]</cell><cell>&lt;0.0001</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">a Post hoc: overlapping of unadjusted 95% confidence intervals between umbilical and epigastric hernias.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Frontiers in Surgery | www.frontiersin.org May 2015 | Volume 2 | Article 15</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">a Post hoc: overlapping of unadjusted 95% confidence intervals between umbilical and epigastric hernias.b  Post hoc: overlapping of unadjusted 95% confidence intervals between umbilical and incisional hernias.Frontiers in Surgery | www.frontiersin.org May 2015 | Volume 2 | Article 15</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Laparoscopic versus open repair of incisional/ventral hernia: a meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sajid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bokhari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mallick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cheek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Baig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.amjsurg.2007.12.051</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">197</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="64" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Laparoscopic ventral hernia repair: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Pham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Perera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Watkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Maddern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00464-008-0182-8</idno>
		<idno>doi:10.1007/ s00464-008-0182-8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surg Endosc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials comparing open and laparoscopic ventral and umbilical hernia repair with mesh</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Forbes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Eskicioglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mcleod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Okrainec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/bjs.6668</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="851" to="858" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Laparoscopic versus open surgical techniques for ventral or umbilical hernia repair</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sauerland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Walgenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Habermalz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Seiler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Miserez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/14651858.CD007781.pub2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">D007781</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Laparoscopy versus laparotomy in the repair of ventral hernias: systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pmv</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Rabelato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ggr</forename><surname>Monteiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Del Guerra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mazzurana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Alvarez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1590/S0004-2803201400030008</idno>
		<idno>doi:10.1590/ S0004-2803201400030008</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arq Gastroenterol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="211" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Laparoscopic versus open incisional and ventral hernia repair: a systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jin</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00268-014-2578-z</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World J Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2233" to="2240" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metaanalysis and systematic review of laparoscopic versus open mesh repair for elective umbilical hernia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Awaiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rahman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hossain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Yunus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Memon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10029-015-1351-z</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hernia</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Laparoscopic repair of primary and incisional ventral hernias: the differences must be acknowledged</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vma</forename><surname>Stirler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ejp</forename><surname>Schoenmaeckers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>De Haas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jtfj</forename><surname>Raymakers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Radic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00464-013-3243-6</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Surg Endosc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="891" to="895" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Herniamed: an internet-based registry for outcome research in hernia surgery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Stechemesser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jacob</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Schug-Paß</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Köckerling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10029-012-0908-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hernia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="269" to="272" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
