<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Shockwaves prevent from heart failure after acute myocardial ischaemia via RNA/protein complexes</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tepek</forename><forename type="middle">€</forename><surname>Can</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Uwe</forename><surname>Oyl € U A</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department for Cardiac Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Medical University of Innsbruck</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Innsbruck</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Primessnig</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charit e University Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Leo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department for Cardiac Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Medical University of Innsbruck</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Innsbruck</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Graber</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department for Cardiac Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Medical University of Innsbruck</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Innsbruck</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Daniela</forename><surname>Lobenwein</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department for Cardiac Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Medical University of Innsbruck</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Innsbruck</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Elke</forename><surname>Kirchmair</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department for Cardiac Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Medical University of Innsbruck</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Innsbruck</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Elisabeth</forename><surname>Pechriggl</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department for Cardiac Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Medical University of Innsbruck</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Innsbruck</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Clinical and Functional Anatomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Anatomy, Histology and Embryology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Innsbruck Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Innsbruck</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Grimm</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department for Cardiac Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Medical University of Innsbruck</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Innsbruck</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>M.D.</roleName><forename type="first">Johannes</forename><surname>Holfeld</surname></persName>
							<email>johannes.holfeld@i-med.ac.at</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department for Cardiac Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Medical University of Innsbruck</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Innsbruck</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Shockwaves prevent from heart failure after acute myocardial ischaemia via RNA/protein complexes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">AF9BCE03F1751E7711306B6C778A79F1</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/jcmm.13021</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: June 14, 2016; Accepted: September 27, 2016</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:34+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>shock wave therapy myocardial regeneration inflammation myocardial infarction</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Shock wave treatment (SWT) was shown to induce regeneration of ischaemic myocardium via Toll-like receptor 3 (TLR3).</s><s>The antimicrobial peptide LL37 gets released by mechanical stress and is known to form complexes with nucleic acids thus activating Toll-like receptors.</s><s>We suggested that SWT in the acute setting prevents from the development of heart failure via RNA/protein release.</s><s>Myocardial infarction in mice was induced followed by subsequent SWT.</s><s>Heart function was assessed 4 weeks later via transthoracic echocardiography and pressure-volume measurements.</s><s>Human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs) were treated with SWT in the presence of RNase and proteinase and analysed for proliferation, tube formation and LL37 expression.</s><s>RNA release and uptake after SWT was evaluated.</s><s>We found significantly improved cardiac function after SWT.</s><s>SWT resulted in significantly higher numbers of capillaries and arterioles and less left ventricular fibrosis.</s><s>Supernatants of treated cells activated TLR3 reporter cells.</s><s>Analysis of the supernatant revealed increased RNA levels.</s><s>The effect could not be abolished by pre-treatment of the supernatant with RNase, but only by a sequential digestion with proteinase and RNase hinting strongly towards the involvement of RNA/protein complexes.</s><s>Indeed, LL37 expression as well as cellular RNA uptake were significantly increased after SWT.</s><s>We show for the first time that SWT prevents from left ventricular remodelling and cardiac dysfunction via RNA/protein complex release and subsequent induction of angiogenesis.</s><s>It might therefore develop a potent regenerative treatment alternative for ischaemic heart disease.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Myocardial ischaemia with consequent loss of cardiomyocytes can cause left ventricular remodelling including development of fibrotic scar tissue, thinning of the myocardium and decreased systolic function resulting in heart failure.</s><s>Affected patients suffer from dyspnoea, fatigue and oedema, show high morbidity and mortality and represent a major socio-economic health burden for Western countries <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>.</s><s>Current treatment strategies provide symptomatic relief <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s>However, no currently available treatment option is able to avoid ventricular remodelling with subsequent development of heart failure after myocardial injury.</s></p><p><s>Shock waves are mechanical pressure waves which have been used in medicine for kidney stone lithotripsy for more than 30 years <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>In lower energies, they were shown to induce tissue regeneration via induction of angiogenesis <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, mobilization of progenitor cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref> and alteration of inflammatory response <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s><s>Therefore, they have been used successfully in clinical routine for regenerative purposes, for example in bone non-unions <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, soft tissue wounds <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and burn injuries <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</s><s>Cardiac SWT application showed induction of angiogenesis <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, improved function and caused symptom relief in patients suffering from chronic ischaemic heart disease <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s><s>The exact working mechanism remains not fully understood.</s></p><p><s>We could describe only recently that the regenerative effects of SWT are mediated via RNA release and subsequent TLR3 activation.</s><s>SW effects were missing completely in TLR3 À/À animals <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s><s>However, extracellular self-RNA is degraded immediately to avoid immunogenic response <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>.</s><s>Therefore, it remains unknown how extracellular RNA released upon SWT (1) escapes from degradation and (2) can activate intracellular TLR3.</s></p><p><s>Extracellular RNA mainly occurs in protein-complexed forms, and thus escapes degradation <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</s><s>Thereby, the cationic antimicrobial peptide LL37 has been described to be released upon mechanical stress, to form complexes with ribonucleic acids, to pass the cellular membrane and to subsequently activate intracellular TLRs <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</s><s>We therefore suggested that SWT causes release of LL37.</s><s>The peptide forms complexes with extracellular RNA, passes the cell membrane and activates TLR3.</s></p><p><s>In this study, we aimed to investigate whether (1) SWT in the acute setting of myocardial infarction prevents from the development of ischaemic heart failure, and (2) SWT effects are indeed mediated via LL37/RNA complexes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials and methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Animal experiments</head><p><s>The experiments were approved by the institutional animal care and use committee at Innsbruck Medical University and by the Austrian ministry of science.</s><s>The investigation conformed to the 'Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals' published by the U.S. National Institutes of Health (NIH Publication No. 85-23, revised 1996; available from: www.nap.edu/catalog/5140.html).</s><s>Male, 12-to 14-week old C57/BL6 mice (Charles River, Sulzfeld, Germany) weighing 25-30 g were randomly divided into two groups (shock wave therapy group = SWT and untreated control group = CTR, n = 6).</s><s>SWT animals received shock wave therapy directly after LAD ligation.</s><s>CTR animals were left untreated.</s><s>The animals were killed 4 weeks after therapy for harvesting of the heart.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Induction of myocardial infarction</head><p><s>Myocardial infarction was induced as it is the standard model for the induction of ischaemic cardiomyopathy.</s><s>It was performed as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>.</s><s>Briefly, animals were anesthetized by an intraperitoneal injection of ketamine hydrochloride (Graeub, Bern, Switzerland; 80 mg/kg bodyweight) and xylazine hydrochloride (aniMedica, Senden, Germany; 5 mg/kg bodyweight).</s><s>A left lateral thoracotomy was performed in the fourth intercostal space for exposure of the heart.</s><s>The left anterior descending artery (LAD) was ligated at the level of the pulmonary artery using 7-0 polypropylene sutures (Ethicon, Somerville, NJ, USA).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SWT</head><p><s>Animals were anesthetized for SWT as described above.</s><s>Commercially available ultrasound gel was used for coupling.</s><s>The commercially available Orthogold 180 with the hand-held applicator CG050-P (TRT LLC, Tissue Regeneration Technologies, Woodstock, GA, USA), which was specifically designed for cardiac shock wave therapy, was used for the treatment.</s><s>Three-hundred impulses were delivered to the heart through the thorax aiming at the ischaemic area at an energy flux density of 0.38 mJ/mm 2 at a frequency of 5 Hz.</s><s>At these energy levels, no adverse effects could be observed.</s><s>However, for all in vitro experiments, 250 impulses with an energy flux density of 0.08 mJ/mm 2 at a frequency of 3 Hz were used.</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> The rationale of the treatment parameters is our experience from previous studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Haemodynamic pressure-volume measurements</head><p><s>Haemodynamic pressure-volume analysis and transthoracic echocardiography were performed, as the combination of these methods allows exact measurement of cardiac function.</s><s>Invasive haemodynamic measurements and the analysis of pressure-volume (PV) loops were performed as terminal procedure according to established protocols described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> using a pressure-volume conductance system (MPVS Ultra; Millar Instruments, Houston, TX, USA) connected to the PowerLab 8/35 data acquisition system, United Kingdom, and analysed using LabChart7pro software system (AdInstruments, Colorado Srpings, CO, USA), United Kingdom.</s><s>Mice were anaesthetized (3% isoflurane and 96-97% O 2 ), intubated and ventilated by a small rodent ventilator.</s><s>The animals were placed on a temperature-controlled heating platform, and the core temperature was maintained at 37.5°C.</s><s>Anaesthesia was reduced and kept at 1.5% isoflurane and 98.5% O 2 .</s><s>A polyethylene catheter was inserted into the right external jugular vein for saline calibration (10% NaCl) at the end of the experiment to calculate the parallel volume.</s><s>The 1.4-F PV conductance catheter (SPR-839; Millar) was inserted into the right carotid artery and advanced into the ascending aorta.</s><s>Aortic (systemic) blood pressure and heart rate were recorded after stabilization for 5 min.</s><s>Then, the catheter was advanced into the LV under pressure control through the aortic valve.</s><s>Parameters of systolic and diastolic function, including LV end-diastolic pressure (LVEDP), LV end-systolic volume (LVESV), LV end-diastolic volume (LVEDV), ejection fraction (EF), maximal slope of LV systolic pressure increment (dP/dt max) and maximal slope of diastolic pressure decrement (dP/dt min), were measured and calculated according to standard formulas.</s><s>After baseline measurements, transient occlusion of the inferior vena cava was performed and used to derive end-systolic (Ees) and end-diastolic pressure-volume relationships (EDPVR) as load-independent measures of cardiac contractility and relaxation, respectively.</s><s>Heart rate (HR) was separately measured via surface ECG electrodes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Echocardiography</head><p><s>Transthoracic echocardiography was performed using standardized protocols for the assessment of heart function and morphometry as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20]</ref>.</s><s>Briefly, lightly anaesthetized mice (0.5% isoflurane and 99.5% O 2 ) were placed on a temperature-controlled warming pad (kept at 37.5°C) and imaged in the supine position using a high-resolution micro-imaging system equipped with a 30-MHz linear array transducer (Vevo770TM Imaging System; VisualSonics Inc., Toronto, Ontario, Canada), respectively.</s><s>Standard 2D-and M-mode tracings of the left ventricle (LV; long axis and short axis at papillary muscle level) were recorded, and ejection fraction was averaged from three consecutive cardiac cycles under stable conditions.</s><s>M-Mode pictures were recorded in the mid-papillary portion as standard in the Teichholz measuring technique.</s><s>The investigator was blinded to the treatment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cell culture and in vitro assays</head><p><s>Cell culture and in vitro assays were performed to investigate underlying mechanisms of SW-induced angiogenesis.</s><s>For this purpose, human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs) were cultured as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</s><s>Permission was given from the ethics committee of Innsbruck Medical University (No. UN4435).</s><s>Cells were used until passage 5.</s><s>All in vitro experiments were performed in triplicates.</s></p><p><s>In all experiments, 250 impulses were applied to the SWT group at an energy flux density of 0.08 mJ/mm 2 and a frequency of 3 Hz.</s><s>These parameters were chosen due to our experience from previous experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>For assessment of proliferation, a BrdU assay (Roche, Rotkreuz, Switzerland) was performed as recommended by the manufacturer.</s><s>Tube formation assay was performed as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>.</s><s>Tube formation was analysed using the ImageJ plugin Angiogenesis Analyzer as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>.</s><s>Both assays are recognized assays for the assessment of in vitro angiogenesis.</s><s>For reporter cell assays, a HEK reporter cell line (TLR3/ISRE LUCPorter; Imgenex, San Diego, CA, USA) was purchased and used as suggested by the manufacturer.</s><s>Cells were treated with SWT as described above.</s><s>24 hrs after treatment, cells were washed with PBS and luminescence was analysed using a Luciferase Assay System (Promega, Fitchburg, WI, USA).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RNA content and uptake</head><p><s>RNA content was measured as described previously, as it represents a feasible technique for RNA content measurement <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s><s>Rhodamine labelled polyinosinic:polycytidylic acid (poly (I:C)) (Invivogen, San Diego, CA, USA) was added to HUVEC supernatant prior to SWT treatment.</s><s>Twenty-four hours after, SWT cells were washed with PBS, cell membranes were stained using wheat germ agglutinin (WGA; Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and nuclei were visualized using DAPI.</s><s>Rhodamine fluorescence was quantified using ImageJ.</s><s>This method has proven useful for the investigation of RNA uptake <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</s><s>Results are depicted as positive area.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Western blot</head><p><s>Western blot for protein expression was performed as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s><s>The blots were probed with LL-37 antibody (Abcam, Cambridge, UK).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Immunofluorescence and histological staining</head><p><s>Immunofluorescence staining was performed as described previously to analyse proliferation and number of vessels <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s><s>Histological sections of the heart were incubated with monoclonal rat anti-CD31 (nova, Hamburg, Germany) rabbit polyclonal anti-alpha smooth muscle actin antibodies (Abcam), rabbit anti-Ki 67 or rabbit anti-LL37 over night at 4°C.</s><s>Masson-Goldner trichrome staining was performed as suggested by the manufacturer (Carl Roth GmbH, Karlsruhe, Germany) to quantify postinfarctional fibrosis.</s><s>The area of fibrosis and total area of the left free ventricle were measured using ImageJ (NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA).</s><s>Values are shown as the ratio of fibrotic area to total left ventricular free wall as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref>.</s><s>Five areas per sample were analysed.</s><s>Three random pictures per sample were analysed.</s><s>Sections were examined with a Zeiss Axioplan 2 (Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany) and a Leica SP5 confocal microscope (Leica, Wetzlar, Germany).</s><s>Images were analysed using ImageJ software (National Institutes of Health) and processed with Adobe Photoshop CS5.1 for Mac (Adobe Systems Inc., San Jose, CA, USA).</s><s>Analyses were performed by a single blinded researcher.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ELISA</head><p><s>A LL-37 ELISA kit was used to analyse LL37 release to the supernatant (Hycult Biotech, Uden, the Netherlands).</s><s>The assay was performed as recommended by the manufacturer.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical analysis</head><p><s>All results are expressed as mean + S.E.M. Statistical comparisons between two groups were performed by Student's t-test or Mann-Whitney U-test as appropriate.</s><s>Multiple groups were analysed by two-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni's multiple comparison test to determine statistical significance.</s><s>Probability values &lt;0.05 were considered statistically significant.</s><s>All experiments were repeated at least in triplicate.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SWT prevents from heart failure after acute myocardial infarction</head><p><s>The design of the in vivo experiment is depicted in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>(A).</s><s>Baseline echocardiography showed no difference between the groups before treatment (ejection fraction (EF) in %: CTR 45.25 AE 1.11 versus SWT 46.2 AE 0.66, P = 0.47; Fig. <ref type="figure">1B</ref>).</s><s>Four weeks after induction of myocardial infarction and subsequent shockwave treatment, transthoracic echocardiography showed significantly improved ejection fraction in treated animals compared with untreated control animals (LVEF in %: CTR 35.25 AE 1.11 versus SWT 46 AE 2.83, P = 0.0122; Fig. <ref type="figure">1B and C</ref>).</s><s>This finding could be confirmed by haemodynamic pressure-volume measurement (LVEF in %: CTR 36.25 AE 1.70 versus SWT 45.25 AE 2.43, P = 0.0029; Fig. <ref type="figure">1D and  E</ref>).</s><s>In addition, a decreased left ventricular end-diastolic pressure (LVEDP) following SWT was found (Fig. <ref type="figure">1F</ref>; mmHg: CTR 15.75 AE 0.85 versus SWT11.75</s><s>AE 1.38, P = 0.0485).</s><s>Myocardial contractility was increased in treated animals (Fig. <ref type="figure">1G and I</ref>; dP/dt max in mmHg/sec.: CTR 6222 AE 157.7 versus SWT 7236 AE 313.5, P = 0.0276; dP/dt min in mmHg/sec.: CTR À5906 AE 368 versus SWT À6396 AE 289, P = 0.3354).</s><s>Moreover, left ventricular end-diastolic volume (Fig. <ref type="figure">1H</ref>; LVEDV) was decreased and left ventricular end-systolic volume (LVESV) was increased after SWT, however, not significantly (Fig. <ref type="figure">1J</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SWT induces angiogenesis and avoids myocardial scar formation</head><p><s>In a next step, we aimed to clarify whether SWT resulted in angiogenesis and reduction in the fibrotic scar (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2A</ref>).</s><s>Treated hearts showed significantly increased numbers of capillaries (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2B</ref>; capillaries per HPF: CTR 1.5 AE 0.23 versus SWT 7.17 AE 0.76, P &lt; 0.0001) and arterioles (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2C</ref>; arterioles per HPF: CTR: 1.1 AE 0.21 versus SWT 4.23 AE 0.32, P &lt; 0.0001).</s><s>In addition, we found significantly decreased amounts of fibrosis after SWT (% of free LV: CTR AE 2.76 versus SWT 8.97 AE 3.08, P = 0.0132; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2D  and E</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SWT causes RNA release and promotes cellular uptake</head><p><s>Endothelial cells were treated with SWT and analysed for proliferation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3A</ref>).</s><s>We found increased proliferation after treatment (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3B</ref>; % of Ki67-positive cells: CTR 2.46 AE 1.25 versus SWT 12.51 AE 3.10, P = 0.0047).</s><s>Next, we aimed to clarify whether the observed effect was due to a factor that was released into the supernatant.</s><s>Treatment with pre-conditioned medium indeed resulted in higher proliferation rates (compared to cells treated with unconditioned medium; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3C</ref>; arbitrary units: CTR 0.07 AE 0.01 versus SWT 1 hr 0.07 AE 0.003, P = 0.28; SWT 6 hrs 0.11 AE 0.01, P = 0.0019 versus CTR; SWT 24 hrs 0.07 AE 0.004, P = 0.86 versus CTR).</s><s>Next, we analysed the RNA content in treated supernatants.</s><s>We found a significantly increased amount of total RNA in supernatants after SWT compared to untreated controls (ng/ml: CTR 20.21 AE 2.56 versus SWT 47.7 AE 6.97, P = 0.0023; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3D and E</ref>).</s><s>Addition of pre-marked RNA to cell culture supernatants prior to SWT showed an increased uptake 3 hrs after treatment (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3F and G</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RNA/protein complexes mediate SW effect</head><p><s>Next, we added either RNase or proteinase and a combination of both to the endothelial cells prior to SWT and again analysed for proliferation.</s><s>RNase alone did not abolish the SWT effect (arbitrary units: CTR 0.22 AE 0.08, SWT 0.48 AE 0.04, P = 0.02 versus CTR; SWT + RNase 0.52 AE 0.06, P = 0.02 versus CTR).</s><s>However, SW effects were abolished in the presence of proteinase (SWT + Proteinase 0.17 AE 0.03, P = 0.5312 versus CTR; Fig. <ref type="figure">4A</ref>).</s><s>The results were confirmed in a tube formation assay showing increased number of segments (Fig. <ref type="figure">4B</ref>; segments per HPF: CTR 320.8 AE 13.78 versus SWT 462.5 AE 22.26, P = 0.0015), junctions (Fig. <ref type="figure">4C</ref>; junctions per HPF: CTR 263.5 AE 9.82 versus SWT 369.7 AE 16.4,</s><s>P = 0.0013) and nodes (Fig. <ref type="figure">4D</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Increased LL37 expression after SWT</head><p><s>LL37 expression was increased after SWT as shown by Western blot analysis (Fig. <ref type="figure">5A and B</ref>; arbitrary units: CTR 40.35,</s><s>SWT 30' 39.13, SWT 1 hr 29.15, SWT 2 hrs 25.25, SWT 5 hrs 49.14, SWT 24 hrs 61.18, SWT 48 hrs 77.59) as well as immunofluorescence analysis (Fig. <ref type="figure">5C and D</ref>; arbitrary units: CTR 47,496 AE 10,690 versus SWT 139,243 AE 22,250, P = 0.0054).</s><s>In addition, LL37 content in the supernatant was also increased after SWT (Fig. <ref type="figure">5E</ref>; ng/ml: CTR 1.17 AE 0.0005 versus SWT 0 hr 1.65 AE 0.008, P &lt; 0.0001, SWT 2 min.</s><s>1.30 AE 0.006, P &lt; 0.0001 versus CTR; SWT 1 hr 1.41 AE 0.002, P &lt; 0.0001 versus CTR; SWT 6 hrs 1.52 AE 0.008, P &lt; 0.0001 versus CTR; SWT 24 hrs 1.32 AE 0.005, P &lt; 0.0001).</s></p><p><s>Finally, we transferred pre-treated supernatant onto TLR3 reporter cells.</s><s>Supernatant from SW-treated cells caused TLR3 activation (arbitrary units: CTR 8728 AE 3138 versus SWT 131,874 AE 12,328, P &lt; 0.0001).</s><s>This effect could again not be abolished by pre-treatment with RNase (arbitrary units: SWT+RNase 110,171 AE 14,482, P = 0.0005 versus CTR), but only with additional proteinase treatment (arbitrary units: SWT+Prot+RNase 877 AE 380.8, P = 0.089 versus CTR) or sole proteinase treatment (arbitrary units: SWT+Prot Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> Shock wave treatment (SWT) prevents from heart failure after acute myocardial infarction.</s><s>(A) Myocardial infarction was induced via LAD ligation.</s><s>Subsequently, baseline measurement was preformed via echocardiography.</s><s>Animals were treated with SWT immediately thereafter.</s><s>Four weeks later, cardiac function was assessed via transthoracic echocardiography and pressure-volume measurement.</s><s>(B) Baseline echo showed no difference between the groups before treatment.</s><s>However, treated animals showed significantly improved left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) 4 weeks after treatment compared with untreated controls.</s><s>(C) Representative M-mode images from the transthoracic echocardiographies.</s><s>The left ventricular anterior wall shows improved contractility after SWT compared to untreated controls.</s><s>(D) Cardiac function was assessed in more detail using pressure-volume measurements.</s><s>(E) Improved LVEF after SWT could be confirmed in pressure-volume measurements.</s><s>In addition, treated animals showed decreased left ventricular end-diastolic pressure (LVEDP; F), higher dP/dt max (G), decreased left ventricular end-diastolic volume (LVEDV; H), dP/dt min.</s><s>(I) and left ventricular end-systolic pressure (LVESV; J).</s><s>Overall, diastolic and systolic function as well as myocardial contractility showed improvement after SWT.</s><s>n = 6, *P &lt; 0.05.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Heart failure due to ischaemic heart disease represents a global socio-economic burden <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[25]</ref>.</s><s>Currently, there are no treatment options available for preventing its development after myocardial infarction.</s><s>SWT represents a promising therapeutic tool for the treatment and regeneration of ischaemic myocardium <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s>In the present study, we treated hearts after induction of myocardial infarction and evaluated cardiac function 4 weeks later.</s><s>Untreated animals developed poor cardiac function with low ejection fraction, impaired contractility and deteriorated systolic and diastolic function.</s><s>These results could be shown in transthoracic echocardiography and confirmed in haemodynamic pressure-volume measurements.</s><s>However, functional analyses showed that left ventricular function and myocardial contractility were significantly improved after SWT.</s><s>In addition, treated animals showed significantly decreased amount of fibrosis of the left ventricle after SWT.</s><s>These results show clearly a protective effect of SWT concerning ventricular remodelling and cardiac function after myocardial infarction.</s></p><p><s>Cardiac regeneration after chronic ischaemia has been shown in small and large animal models via induction of angiogenesis <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26]</ref>.</s><s>In addition, cardiac SWT caused improvement of symptoms in patients suffering from chronic ischaemic heart disease.</s><s>However, we show for the first time that SWT after acute myocardial infarction attenuates the decrease in cardiac function concerning contractility, diastolic and systolic function.</s></p><p><s>We found increased numbers of capillaries as well as arterioles in treated myocardium.</s><s>This might be a hint that the protective effect of SWT after myocardial infarction is due to early induction of angiogenesis.</s><s>The fact that we found increased numbers of arterioles shows that SWT indeed induces the formation of long-term stable vessels.</s></p><p><s>Our group recently showed that the SW effect is mediated via TLR3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s><s>However, it remains unclear how the receptor is activated  upon mechanical stimulation with SWT.</s><s>Supernatant from cells preconditioned with SWT showed similar effects on proliferation as the direct application of SWT to cells does.</s><s>This gave us a strong hint that whatever causes the SWT effect is released into the supernatant.</s><s>TLR3 is known to be activated by RNA <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref>.</s><s>We therefore measured RNA content in the supernatants and could show that it is indeed increased after SWT.</s><s>However, it remained unclear how the extracellular RNA escapes degradation and passes the cellular membrane to activate intracellular TLR3.</s><s>The fate of RNA is known to be determined by RNA-binding proteins <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</s><s>We therefore suggested that released Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref> Increased LL37 expression after SWT.</s><s>(A) Western blot analysis was performed to assess LL37 expression.</s><s>(B) SW-treated cells showed significantly increased LL37 expression after SWT compared to untreated controls.</s><s>(C) Immunofluorescence staining for LL37 of HUVECs with and without treatment was performed.</s><s>(D) After SWT, LL37 expression was significantly increased.</s><s>(E) To assess LL37 release upon SWT, a LL37 ELISA of pre-conditioned supernatants was performed.</s><s>We found significantly increased amount of LL37 1 hr after SWT.</s><s>(F) Finally, TLR3 activation after SWT was measured using a reporter cell assay.</s><s>TLR3 activation was significantly increased after SWT.</s><s>The effect was not abolished upon RNase addition, but only with addition of proteinase.</s><s>Experiments were performed at least in triplicates and repeated at least twice.</s><s>*P &lt; 0.05.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref> RNA/protein complexes mediate SW effect.</s><s>(A) SWT enhanced proliferation in HUVECs.</s><s>The effect could not be abolished via RNase pre-treatment, but only with additional proteinase treatment.</s><s>(B) SWT resulted in increased segment formation, formation of junctions (C) and enhanced node formation (D) in a tube formation assay.</s><s>Again, the effect could not be abolished by RNase treatment, but only with proteinase addition.</s><s>(E) We found significantly more tubes after SWT of HUVECs.</s><s>Experiments were performed at least in triplicates and repeated at least twice.</s><s>*P &lt; 0.05.</s><s>RNA binds to a protein and thus passes the cellular membrane.</s><s>To test this hypothesis, we applied SWT to a tube formation assay in the presence of RNase and proteinase.</s><s>Interestingly, RNase treatment did not abolish the SWT effect, but only additional treatment with proteinase did indicating the existence of a RNA/protein complex.</s></p><p><s>In a next step, we aimed to specify which protein is responsible for the observed effects.</s><s>Gilliet et al. have identified LL37 as a key player in the development of psoriasis.</s><s>Thereby, this antimicrobial peptide gets released upon mechanical stimulation, binds nucleic acids and activates intracellular nucleic acid TLRs <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref>.</s><s>We analysed treated cells for LL37 release and LL37 expression and found both increased after SWT.</s><s>When we added the pre-marked RNA analogon Poly(I:C) to cells prior to treatment, we found significantly increased uptake of RNA after SWT.</s><s>These results hint towards involvement of LL37 after SWT.</s><s>However, it remains unknown whether other proteins/RNA complexes are also involved.</s></p><p><s>Finally, we analysed whether TLR3 activation after SWT was indeed accomplished by protein/RNA complexes.</s><s>For this purpose, we performed a TLR3 reporter cell assay.</s><s>SWT leads to the activation of TLR3, which could not be abolished by RNase treatment, but only with additional proteinase treatment showing that indeed RNA/protein complexes lead to TLR3 activation after SWT.</s></p><p><s>Summarizing, we could show for the first time that SWT after acute myocardial infarction prevents from left ventricular remodelling and cardiac dysfunction via induction of angiogenesis.</s><s>In addition, we found that the cellular response upon SWT is mediated via RNA/protein complexes with involvement of the antimicrobial peptide LL37 activating TLR3.</s><s>SWT could develop a potent therapeutic tool for the treatment of acute myocardial ischaemia and the prevention of ischaemic heart failure.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>ª</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>2016 The Authors.</s><s>Journal of Cellular and Molecular Medicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd and Foundation for Cellular and Molecular Medicine.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>18,713 AE 11,018, P = 0.46 versus CTR; Fig.5F) clearly indicating the pivotal role of a RNA/protein complex in SW-induced TLR3 stimulation.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 2 Shock wave treatment (SWT) induces angiogenesis and avoids myocardial scar formation.</s><s>(A) Representative images of myocardium analysed for capillaries (CD31) and arterioles (aSMA) via immunofluorescence staining.</s><s>(B) SWT resulted in significantly increased numbers of capillaries in the myocardium.</s><s>(C) In addition, animals showed an increased amount of arterioles after treatment.</s><s>(D) Masson's trichrome staining was used to quantify the amount of fibrosis of the left ventricle.</s><s>(E) We found a significantly decreased amount of fibrosis in treated animals.</s><s>n = 6, *P &lt; 0.05, ****P &lt; 0.0001.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,68.03,101.28,459.36,308.87" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 3 Shock wave treatment (SWT) causes RNA release and promotes cellular uptake.</s><s>(A) Representative images of HUVECs treated with SWT and analysed for proliferation using Ki67 staining.</s><s>(pink = Ki67, blue = DAPI, scale bar = 100 lm; B) SWT resulted in proliferation of HUVECs compared to untreated control cells.</s><s>(C) Pre-conditioned supernatant obtained from SW-treated cells showed the same effect as direct SW application.</s><s>(D) HUVECs were treated with SWT and analysed for RNA content (green = Syto16, scale bar = 100 lm).</s><s>(E) We found significantly increased amounts of RNA in the supernatant of SW-treated cells compared with untreated control supernatant.</s><s>(F) Pre-marked RNA was added to HUVECs prior to SWT.</s><s>Subsequently, SWT was applied and RNA uptake quantified (red = poly(I:C), scale bar = 100 lm).</s><s>(G) Cellular RNA uptake was significantly increased after SWT.</s><s>Experiments were performed at least in triplicates and repeated at least twice.</s><s>*P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,68.03,99.21,459.36,503.39" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>ª</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>2016 The Authors.</s><s>Journal of Cellular and Molecular Medicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd and Foundation for Cellular and Molecular Medicine.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>; LVEDV in ll: CTR 22.25 AE 2.78 versus SWT 19.256 AE 1.49, P = 0.3785; LVESV in ll: CTR 14.25 AE 2.10 versus SWT 10.5 AE 0.65, P = 0.1382).</s></p></div></figDesc><table /><note><p><s>ª 2016 The Authors.</s><s>Journal of Cellular and Molecular Medicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd and Foundation for Cellular and Molecular Medicine.</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>; arbitrary units: 1 hr: CTR 1855 AE 824.7 versus SWT 5007 AE 1061, P = 0.0625; 3 hrs: CTR 31.67 AE 28.17 versus SWT 19,757 AE 1054, P = 0.0001; 6 hrs: CTR 545.7 AE 81.62 versus SWT 453.3 AE 44.67, P = 0.3722; 24 hrs: CTR 10,387 AE 1261 versus SWT 8249 AE 3862, P = 0.6267).</s></p></div></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>; nodes per HPF: CTR 891.3 AE 25.96 versus SWT 1292 AE 60.11, P = 0.0029) after SWT.</s><s>The effects could not be reversed by addition of RNase, only treatment with additional proteinase resulted in abolished SW effects (segments per HPF: SWT+RNase: 440 AE 31.42,</s><s>P = 0.0186 versus CTR; SWT+Proteinase: 208 AE 73.37, P = 0.136 versus CTR; SWT+Protei-nase+RNase: 170 AE 16.56, P = 0.0009 versus CTR; junctions per HPF: SWT+RNase: 354.2 AE 21.29, P = 0.0113; SWT+Proteinase: 182 AE 53.03, P = 0.1357 versus CTR; SWT+Prot+RNase: 159 AE 12.11, P = 0.0005 versus CTR; nodes per HPF: SWT+RNase 1246 AE 77.42, P = 0.0175 versus CTR; SWT+Proteinase 572 AE 170.9, P = 0.1771 versus CTR; SWT+Proteinase+RNase 554.8 AE 29.93, P = 0.0005 versus CTR).</s></p></div></figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">ª 2016 The Authors. Journal of Cellular and Molecular Medicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd and Foundation for Cellular and Molecular Medicine.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>We kindly thank Annabella Knab for performing tissue sections.</s><s>This work was in part supported by a research grant of Medizinischer Forschungsfonds Tirol (MFF) [project no.</s><s>220] and by a research grant provided by TRT-Tissue Regeneration Technologies LLC., Woodstock, Georgia, USA, both to J.H.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p><s>None.</s><s>The authors confirm that there are no conflicts of interest.</s><s>The sponsors of this study had no role in study design, data collection, analysis and decision to publish or prepare the manuscript.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author contributions</head><p><s>C.T. and J.H. designed the experiments and wrote the manuscript.</s><s>C.T., M.G., U.P. and D.L. performed animal experiments.</s><s>C.T., L.P. and E.K. performed in vitro experiments.</s><s>C.T., U.P., E.K., E.J.P. and F.N. performed analyses.</s><s>M.G. revised the manuscript.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heart failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jessup</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brozena</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">348</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2007" to="2018" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heart disease and stroke statistics-2012 update: a report from the American Heart Association</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Roger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Go</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lloyd-Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="e2" to="220" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ESC Guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of acute and chronic heart failure 2012: the Task Force for the Diagnosis and Treatment of Acute and Chronic Heart Failure 2012 of the European Society of Cardiology. Developed in collaboration with the Heart Failure Association (HFA) of the ESC</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mcmurray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Adamopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Anker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1787" to="1847" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shock-wave lithotripsy for renal calculi</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Pearle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">367</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracorporeal cardiac shock wave therapy markedly ameliorates ischemia-induced myocardial dysfunction in pigs in vivo</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nishida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Shimokawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Oi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3055" to="3061" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lowenergy shock wave for enhancing recruitment of endothelial progenitor cells: a new modality to increase efficacy of cell therapy in chronic hind limb ischemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Heeschen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sasaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2823" to="2830" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shock wave treatment induces angiogenesis and mobilizes endogenous CD31/CD34-positive endothelial cells in a hindlimb ischemia model: implications for angiogenesis and vasculogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tepekoylu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kozaryn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">146</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="971" to="978" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shock wave treatment protects from neuronal degeneration via a toll-like receptor 3 dependent mechanism: implications of a first-ever causal treatment for ischemic spinal cord injury</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lobenwein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tepekoylu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kozaryn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Heart Assoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e002440</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracorporeal shock wave therapy for nonunion of the tibia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Elster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stojadinovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Forsberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Orthop Trauma</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shock wave therapy for acute and chronic soft tissue wounds: a feasibility study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Schaden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Thiele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kolpl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Surg Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">143</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prospective randomized phase II Trial of accelerated reepithelialization of superficial second-degree burn wounds using extracorporeal shock wave therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ottomann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stojadinovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Lavin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">255</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extracorporeal cardiac shock wave therapy ameliorates myocardial ischemia in patients with severe coronary artery disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Fukumoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Uwatoku</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Coron Artery Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toll-like receptor 3 signalling mediates angiogenic response upon shock wave treatment of ischaemic muscle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Holfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tepekoylu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Reissig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cardiovasc Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="343" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intracellular localization of Toll-like receptor 9 prevents recognition of self DNA but facilitates access to viral DNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Barton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kagan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Medzhitov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-RNA-antimicrobial peptide complexes activate human dendritic cells through TLR7 and TLR8</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ganguly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Chamilos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lande</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Exp Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">206</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1983" to="1994" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Insights into RNA biology from an atlas of mammalian mRNA-binding proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Castello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Eichelbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">149</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1393" to="1406" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neuroligin 1 induces blood vessel maturation by cooperating with the alpha6 integrin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Samarelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Riccitelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bizzozero</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">289</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19466" to="19476" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shock wave application to cell cultures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Holfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tepekoylu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kozaryn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3791/51076</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Vis Exp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Novel pathomechanisms of cardiomyocyte dysfunction in a model of heart failure with preserved ejection fraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Primessnig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schonleitner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Holl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Heart Fail</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="987" to="997" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AMPactivated protein kinase alpha1 regulates cardiac gap junction protein connexin 43 and electrical remodeling following pressure overload</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Alesutan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Voelkl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Stockigt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Physiol Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="406" to="418" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Low energy shock wave therapy induces angiogenesis in acute hind-limb ischemia via VEGF receptor 2 phosphorylation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Holfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tepekoylu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Blunder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e103982</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shockwave therapy differentially stimulates endothelial cells: implications on the control of inflammation via toll-Like receptor 3</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Holfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tepekoylu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kozaryn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inflammation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The angiogenic factor secretoneurin induces coronary angiogenesis in a model of myocardial infarction by stimulation of vascular endothelial growth factor signaling in endothelial cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Albrecht-Schgoer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Schgoer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Holfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2491" to="2501" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">G-CSF prevents cardiac remodeling after myocardial infarction by activating the Jak-Stat pathway in cardiomyocytes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Harada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Qin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Takano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="311" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heart disease and stroke statistics-2015 update: a report from the</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mozaffarian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Benjamin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Go</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Heart Association. Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="e29" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epicardial shock-wave therapy improves ventricular function in a porcine model of ischaemic heart disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Holfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zimpfer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Albrecht-Schgoer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/term.1890</idno>
		<idno>doi: 10.1002/ term.1890</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Tissue Eng Regen Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Epub ahead of print</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathogen recognition and innate immunity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Akira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Uematsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Takeuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="783" to="801" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plasmacytoid dendritic cells sense self-DNA coupled with antimicrobial peptide</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gregorio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Facchinetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">449</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="564" to="569" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Authors</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Cellular and Molecular Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd and Foundation for Cellular and Molecular Medicine</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
