<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Lab resource: Stem cell line Generation of an iPS cell line from bone marrow derived mesenchymal stromal cells from an elderly patient</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-10-09">9 October 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Matthias</forename><surname>Megges</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Stem Cell Research and Regenerative Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Heinrich Heine University Duesseldorf</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Moorenstr. 5</addrLine>
									<postCode>40225</postCode>
									<settlement>Duesseldorf</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institut für Molekulare Genetik</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>63-73, 14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Ihnestraße, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Biology, Chemistry and Pharmacy</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Chemistry and Biochemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Freie Universität Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Thielallee 63</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sven</forename><surname>Geissler</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Berlin-Brandenburger Centrum für Regenerative Therapien</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Augustenburger Platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Georg</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Duda</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Berlin-Brandenburger Centrum für Regenerative Therapien</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Augustenburger Platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Julius Wolff Institut</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><surname>Adjaye</surname></persName>
							<email>james.adjaye@med.uni-duesseldorf.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Stem Cell Research and Regenerative Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Heinrich Heine University Duesseldorf</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Moorenstr. 5</addrLine>
									<postCode>40225</postCode>
									<settlement>Duesseldorf</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institut für Molekulare Genetik</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>63-73, 14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Ihnestraße, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Lab resource: Stem cell line Generation of an iPS cell line from bone marrow derived mesenchymal stromal cells from an elderly patient</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-10-09">9 October 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">468174DBC56F9D11EF61A6D47F973AB5</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.scr.2015.10.003</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 29 September 2015 Accepted 6 October 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:34+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>An induced pluripotent stem cell line was generated from primary human bone marrow derived mesenchymal stromal cells of a 74 year old donor using retroviruses harboring OCT4, SOX2, KLF4 and c-MYC in combination with the following inhibitors TGFβ receptor-SB 431542, MEK-PD325901, and p53-Pifithrin α.</s><s>Pluripotency was confirmed both in vitro and in vivo.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Resource details</head><p><s>pMX vector-based retroviral delivery of the reprogramming factors OCT4, SOX2, KLF4 and c-MYC was used in combination with the TGFβ receptor inhibitor SB431542, MEK inhibitor PD325901 and the p53 inhibitor Pifithrin α to induce pluripotency in the parental primary bone marrow derived mesenchymal stromal cells (parental hBM MSC).</s><s>The expression of pluripotency-associated proteins was confirmed in the iPS cell line generated from parental hBM MSC (MSC-iPSC ( <ref type="formula">74</ref>)) (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>).</s><s>The expression of pluripotency-associated genes was comparatively confirmed in MSC-iPSC (74) and hESC H1 using real time PCR (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>).</s><s>In addition, microarray-based transcriptome profiling revealed a high similarity between MSC-iPSC (74), hESC H1 and hESC H9 compared to the parental hBM MSC (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C and D</ref>).</s><s>The somatic origin of MSC-iPSC 74 and the absence of cross-contamination with embryonic stem cell lines H1 and H9 were confirmed by DNA fingerprinting (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1E</ref>).</s><s>Karyotype analysis revealed a normal female karyotype (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1F</ref>).</s><s>In addition, pluripotency in MSC-iPSC (74) was confirmed in vitro using embryoid body based differentiation and. in vivo using the teratoma assay (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A and B</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Materials and methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Ethics statement</head><p><s>Mesenchymal stromal cells, used for generation of the induced pluripotent stem cell line, were isolated from the bone marrow of a 74-year-old female donor after written informed consent of the patient.</s><s>The corresponding protocol was approved by the research ethics board of the Charite-Universitätsmedizin, Berlin (IRB approval EA2/126/07).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Cell culture</head><p><s>Parental hBM MSC were isolated from human bone marrow by density separation using Histopaque ® -1077 (Sigma-Aldrich) and  <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Dominici et al., 2006)</ref>.</s><s>In this regard, parental hBM MSC were positive (N95%) for CD73, CD105, and CD90, and negative (b 2%) of CD14, CD19, CD34, CD45, CD79α, and human leukocyte antigen-DR (HLA-DR).</s><s>The capacity of parental hBM MSC to differentiate into osteogenic, adipogenic, and chondrogenic lineage was confirmed by addition of appropriate media as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Glaeser et al., 2010)</ref>.</s><s>Human embryonic stem cell (hESC) lines H1 and H9 (WiCell (#WA01 and #WA09, respectively)) as well as the generated MSC- iPSC (74) were expanded in pluripotent stem cell medium containing KO-DMEM with 20% knockout serum replacement, L-glutamine, nonessential amino acids, sodium pyruvate, penicillin/streptomycin, 0.1 mM β-mercaptoethanol (all from Life Technologies).</s><s>Basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF) (Preprotech) was added with a final concentration of 8 ng/mL.</s><s>The cultures were passaged with a split ratio of 1:3 using a syringe needle, pipette and binocular microscope.</s><s>The pluripotent cells were cultured on mitomycin-C-inactivated mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs) seeded on cell culture dishes coated with Matrigel (Beckton Dickinson).</s><s>All cultures were carried out in a humidified atmosphere at 37 °C as well as 5% O 2 and 5% CO 2 .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Derivation of iPSCs</head><p><s>Parental hBM MSC were seeded at a density of 2 × 10 5 cell per well of a six well plate for transduction with retroviruses expressing OCT4, SOX2, KLF4 and c-MYC.</s><s>Viral particles were generated in 293T cells using a conventional CaCl 2 transfection protocol.</s><s>After transduction, parental hBM MSC were split 1:3 onto Matrigel-coated cell culture dishes on which inactivated MEFs were seeded as a feeder layer.</s><s>The transduced cells were further cultured for seven days in pluripotent stem cell medium supplemented with 8 ng/mL bFGF.</s><s>After day seven, the cells were further cultured in a medium pre-conditioned with inactivated MEF and supplemented with 0.5 μM of the MEK inhibitor PD325901 (Stemgent, 04-0006), 2 μM of the TGFβ receptor inhibitor SB431542 (Sigma, S4317) and 10 μM of the p53 inhibitor Pifithrin α (Stemgent, 04-0038) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Hong et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Lin et al., 2009)</ref> and with daily medium changes.</s><s>Colonies with hESC-looking morphology were mechanically detached and transferred to a new Matrigel and feeder cell coated culture dish for expansion and characterization as previously described.</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Hossini et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Takahashi et al., 2007)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">DNA fingerprinting analysis</head><p><s>To confirm the somatic origin of MSC-iPSC (74) and rule out cross contamination with hESCs, 50 ng of genomic DNA was amplified by PCR 94 °C for 1 min, 55 °C for 1 min, 72 °C for 1 min, for 40 cycles, in a Dyad thermal cycler (BioRad) as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Prigione et al., 2010)</ref>.</s><s>PCR products were resolved in 3% agarose gels to visualize  amplicon size patterns for each primer set: D7S796, D10S1214.</s><s>The primer sequences are listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.">Quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction</head><p><s>Expression analysis of pluripotency marker genes was carried out using SYBR ® Green PCR Master Mix (Life Technologies).</s><s>The PCR was performed with an ABI PRISM ® 7000 Sequence Detection System (Life Technologies).</s><s>The software ABI PRISM SDS was used for data analysis.</s><s>Primer sequences are listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>.</s><s>The data were analyzed according to the ΔΔCt method.</s><s>The Log 2 of relative expression measured in  or hESC H1 over the relative expression measured in parental hBM MSC with three technical replicates was calculated.</s><s>The three samples were pooled before reverse transcription of the RNA was carried out.</s></p><p><s>3.6.</s><s>Embryoid body based in-vitro test of pluripotency MSC-iPSC (74) was split and seeded onto a 60 mm ultra low attachment culture dish (Corning) and cultured in DMEM supplemented with 10% FCS, nonessential amino acids, L-glutamine, penicillin/streptomycin and sodium pyruvate (all from Life Technologies) without additional bFGF to generate embryoid bodies (EBs).</s><s>After 10 days EBs were seeded onto gelatine-coated culture dishes and grown another 10 days in the same medium.</s><s>Subsequently, the cells were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde and germ layer specific markers were visualized by immunofluorescence-based staining.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.7.">Immunofluorescence-based analyses of pluripotency associated proteins</head><p><s>To detect pluripotency-specific or germ layer-specific marker expression, MSC-iPSCs (74) were fixed using phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) with 4% paraformaldehyde (Science) for 20 min at room temperature.</s><s>The pluripotency markers OCT4, SOX2, KLF4, c-MYC, SSEA1, SSEA4, TRA-1-60, TRA-1-81, and NANOG and the germ layer specific markers α Fetoprotein (AFP) Smooth-Muscle-Actin (SMA), SOX17, PAX6, NESTIN, β-TubulinIII (TUJ1) and Brachyury (T) were visualized by immunofluorescence labeling as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Hossini et al., 2015)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.8.">Confirmation of pluripotency in vivo</head><p><s>To test the pluripotency of MSC-iPSC (74) in vivo, teratoma assays were carried out by EPO-Berlin GmbH, Berlin-Buch, Germany.</s><s>Undifferentiated cells were detached by trypsinization, washed with PBS and subsequently injected into NOD.Cg-Prkdcscid Il2rgtm1Wjl/SzJ mice, which are known as NOD scid gamma (NSG) mice.</s><s>The tumor was harvested and analyzed for the presence of structures of endodermal, ectodermal and mesodermal origin.</s><s>The analysis was carried out at the Institute for Animal Pathology, Berlin, Germany.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.9.">Microarray based gene expression analysis</head><p><s>Total RNA was isolated using a combined DNA, RNA, and Protein extraction Kit (Roboklon, Berlin Germany).</s><s>The RNA quality was analyzed using a Nanodrop spectrophotometer (Nanodrop).</s><s>500 ng of total RNA was used to produce biotin-labeled cRNA with a linear amplification kit (Ambion).</s><s>The Illumina BeadStation 500 platform (Illumina) was used to further process the samples following the manufacturer's instruction for hybridization and Cy3-streptavidin staining.</s><s>cRNA samples were hybridized onto HumanHT-8 v3.0 Gene Expression BeadChips.</s><s>The clustering dendrogram comparing the expression data and the correlation values were calculated using the Gene Expression Module of the software GenomeStudio (Illumina).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.10.">Karyotype analysis</head><p><s>GTG banding analysis was performed at Human Genetic Centre, Berlin, Germany.</s><s>33 metaphases of MSC-iPSC (74) were analyzed.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1.</s><s>Characterization of the iPS line.</s><s>A) Confirmation of pluripotency marker expression and the absence of the differentiation marker SSEA1 in MSC-iPSC (74).</s><s>Immunofluorescence staining, red/green: detected marker; blue: DAPI to visualize nuclei.</s><s>B) Confirmation of the mRNA expression of pluripotency-associated genes in MSC-iPSC (74) and hESC H1, which served as the control.</s><s>The bars represent the Log 2 of the mean value of the detected relative expression in MSC-iPSC (74) or hESC H1 over the detected relative expression in the parental hBM-MSC.</s><s>The error bars represent the standard deviation of three technical replicates.</s><s>C) Clustering dendrogram generated with the software GenomeStudio (Illumina) based on the Pearson correlation between the transcriptomes of parental hBM MSC, MSC-iPSC (74), hESC H1 and hESC H9.</s><s>The mRNA expression values were detected using an Illumina Bead Chip microarray.</s><s>D) Values of the Pearson correlation co-efficient between the transcriptomes of the same samples compared in the clustering dendrogram.</s><s>The correlation values were calculated using the software GenomeStudio (Illumina).</s><s>E) Confirmation of the somatic origin of MSC-iPSC (74) by DNA fingerprinting using microsatellite-specific primers in a PCR with genomic DNA of 1: MSC-iPSC (74), 2: parental hBM MSC, 3: hESC H1 and 4: hESC H9.</s><s>F) Karyotyping analysis of MSC-iPSC (74).</s><s>The analysis revealed a normal female karyotype.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,65.88,53.18,454.68,503.09" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 2. Confirmation of ability to give rise to lineages of all three germ layers.</s><s>A) Embryoid body-based in vitro test of pluripotency.</s><s>MSC-iPSC (74) gave rise to cell lineages expressing endodermal markers (SOX17) and α Fetoprotein (AFP), mesodermal markers Brachyury (T) and Smooth-Muscle-Actin (SMA) and ectodermal markers NESTIN and β-TubulinIII (TUJ1).</s><s>Detection by immunofluorescence staining.</s><s>red/green: detected marker; blue: DAPI to visualize nuclei.</s><s>B) Pluripotency confirmation by teratoma assay.</s><s>MSC-iPSC (74) gave rise to structures representative of the three germ layers.</s><s>Expt 1: endoderm: tubular gland-like structure; mesoderm: bone; ectoderm: mucous gland.</s><s>Expt 2: endoderm: gut-like epithelium; mesoderm: bone; ectoderm: neuroepithelial structure.</s><s>Hematoxylin and eosin staining of the teratoma tissue.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,88.84,53.18,426.57,288.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Primer sequences used for DNA fingerprinting and real time PCR.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Gene</cell><cell>Forward primer sequence (5′-3′)</cell><cell>Reverse primer sequence (5′-3´)</cell></row><row><cell>D7S796</cell><cell>TTTTGGTATTGGCCATCCTA</cell><cell>GAAAGGAACAGAGAGACAGGG</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">D10S1214 ATTGCCCCAAAACTTTTTTG</cell><cell>TTGAAGACCAGTCTGGGAAG</cell></row><row><cell>DNMT3B</cell><cell>GCTCACAGGGCCCGATACTT</cell><cell>GCAGTCCTGCAGCTCGAGTTTA</cell></row><row><cell>DPPA4</cell><cell>TGGTGTCAGGTGGTGTGTGG</cell><cell>CCAGGCTTGACCAGCATGAA</cell></row><row><cell>FGF4</cell><cell>CCCTTCTTCACCGATGAGTGC</cell><cell>CATTCTTGCTCAGGGCGATG</cell></row><row><cell>GDF3</cell><cell>TTGGCACAAGTGGATCATTGC</cell><cell>TTGGCACAAGTGGATCATTGC</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>AATGTGTCATTGTTTACTTGTCCT</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>LEFTY1</cell><cell>GTC</cell><cell>CAGGTCTTAGGTCCAGAGTGGTG</cell></row><row><cell>NANOG</cell><cell>CCTGTGATTTGTGGGCCTG</cell><cell>GACAGTCTCCGTGTGAGGCAT</cell></row><row><cell>OCT4</cell><cell>GTGGAGGAAGCTGACAACAA</cell><cell>ATTCTCCAGGTTGCCTCTCA</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>TCCTAGTCTTAAAGAGGCAGCA</cell></row><row><cell>SOX2</cell><cell>GTATCAGGAGTTGTCAAGGCAGAG</cell><cell>AAC</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>GAGGTGTCACCAACAAGAAATC</cell></row><row><cell>TERT</cell><cell>ACGGCGACATGGAGAACAAG</cell><cell>ATC</cell></row><row><cell>LIN28</cell><cell>GCACCAGAGTAAGCTGCACA</cell><cell>ATGGATTCCAGACCCTTGGC</cell></row><row><cell>LEFTY2</cell><cell>CTCCCGCGGAAAGAGGTTC</cell><cell>CAGCGCGGCCTCCGA</cell></row><row><cell>TDGF1</cell><cell>AGGGAACAATGACAGAGTGTGA</cell><cell>CCCGGCAACTAATCCCAGTT</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p><s>JA acknowledges the support from the medical faculty of Heinrich-Heine Universität Düsseldorf, Germany and the BMBF grant number 01GN1005.</s><s>SG acknowledges support from the BMBF grant number 01EC1402B.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minimal criteria for defining multipotent mesenchymal stromal cells. The international society for cellular therapy position statement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dominici</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cytotherapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="317" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modulation of matrix metalloprotease-2 levels by mechanical loading of three-dimensional mesenchymal stem cell constructs: impact on in vitro tube formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Glaeser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Tissue Eng. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3139" to="3148" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Suppression of induced pluripotent stem cell generation by the p53-p21 pathway</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">460</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7259</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1132" to="1135" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Induced pluripotent stem cell-derived neuronal cells from a sporadic Alzheimer&apos;s disease donor as a model for investigating AD-associated gene regulatory networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hossini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A chemical platform for improved induction of human iPSCs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="805" to="808" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The senescence-related mitochondrial/oxidative stress pathway is repressed in human induced pluripotent stem cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Prigione</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stem Cells</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="721" to="733" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Induction of pluripotent stem cells from adult human fibroblasts by defined factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Takahashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="861" to="872" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
