<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Mitochondrial Networks in Cardiac Myocytes Reveal Dynamic Coupling Behavior</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Felix</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kurz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Massachusetts General Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Cardiovascular Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Harvard Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Charlestown</settlement>
									<region>Massachusetts</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neuroradiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Heidelberg University Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Heidelberg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Derungs</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Massachusetts General Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Cardiovascular Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Harvard Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Charlestown</settlement>
									<region>Massachusetts</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Experimental and Clinical Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max-Delbru ¨ck Center for Molecular Medicine and Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Miguel</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johns Hopkins University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>Maryland</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Brian</forename><surname>O'rourke</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johns Hopkins University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>Maryland</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Antonis</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Armoundas</surname></persName>
							<email>aarmoundas@partners.org</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Massachusetts General Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Cardiovascular Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Harvard Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Charlestown</settlement>
									<region>Massachusetts</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Mitochondrial Networks in Cardiac Myocytes Reveal Dynamic Coupling Behavior</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">90275405ED8E69117081D1DF5AEF6FBF</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.bpj.2015.01.040</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted December 22, 2014, and accepted for publication January 13, 2015.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:50+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Oscillatory behavior of mitochondrial inner membrane potential (DJ m ) is commonly observed in cells subjected to oxidative or metabolic stress.</s><s>In cardiac myocytes, the activation of inner membrane pores by reactive oxygen species (ROS) is a major factor mediating intermitochondrial coupling, and ROS-induced ROS release has been shown to underlie propagated waves of DJ m depolarization as well as synchronized limit cycle oscillations of DJ m in the network.</s><s>The functional impact of DJ m instability on cardiac electrophysiology, Ca 2þ handling, and even cell survival, is strongly affected by the extent of such intermitochondrial coupling.</s><s>Here, we employ a recently developed wavelet-based analytical approach to examine how different substrates affect mitochondrial coupling in cardiac cells, and we also determine the oscillatory coupling properties of mitochondria in ventricular cells in intact perfused hearts.</s><s>The results show that the frequency of DJ m oscillations varies inversely with the size of the oscillating mitochondrial cluster, and depends on the strength of local intermitochondrial coupling.</s><s>Time-varying coupling constants could be quantitatively determined by applying a stochastic phase model based on extension of the well-known Kuramoto model for networks of coupled oscillators.</s><s>Cluster size-frequency relationships varied with different substrates, as did mitochondrial coupling constants, which were significantly larger for glucose (7.78 Â 10 À2 5 0.98 Â 10 À2 s À1 ) and pyruvate (7.49</s><s>Â 10 À2 5 1.65 Â 10 À2 s À1 ) than lactate (4.83 Â 10 À2 5 1.25 Â 10 À2 s À1 ) or b-hydroxybutyrate (4.11 Â 10 À2 5 0.62 Â 10 À2 s À1 ).</s><s>The findings indicate that mitochondrial spatiotemporal coupling and oscillatory behavior is influenced by substrate selection, perhaps through differing effects on ROS/redox balance.</s><s>In particular, glucose-perfusion generates strong intermitochondrial coupling and temporal oscillatory stability.</s><s>Pathological changes in specific catabolic pathways, which are known to occur during the progression of cardiovascular disease, could therefore contribute to altered sensitivity of the mitochondrial network to oxidative stress and emergent DJ m instability, ultimately scaling to produce organ level dysfunction.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p><s>Oscillatory behavior in mitochondria was reported more than 40 years ago and DJ m instability, ranging from localized flickers to synchronized mitochondrial network oscillations, has been observed in intact cells subjected to oxidative, ischemic, or metabolic stress by numerous investigators (for review, see Aon et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>).</s><s>In cardiac myocytes, the latticelike morphological organization of the mitochondrial network lends itself to complex spatiotemporal phenomena, including DJ m oscillations and waves (2), oscillations of individual <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4)</ref> or clusters of mitochondria ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>), and network-wide limit-cycle oscillations in cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref> and tissues <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>.</s><s>Reactive oxygen species (ROS)-induced ROS release <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> among neighboring mitochondria, leading to self-organized synchronization of oscillators, is the leading mechanistic explanation for this type of intermitochondrial communication <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11)</ref>, although Ca 2þ -dependent coupling might also occur during cellular Ca 2þ overload <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>.</s><s>Pathophysiological conditions can render the mitochondrial network hypersensitive to widespread DJ m collapse or selforganized oscillation, a state referred to as ''mitochondrial criticality'' <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14)</ref>.</s><s>When such a threshold is crossed, mitochondrial oscillators organize into clusters that can span a subregion of the cell or the whole volume of the myocyte <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16)</ref>.</s><s>Understanding how DJ m oscillations are organized in time and space is important because the magnitude of the effects of DJ m loss on cardiac electrophysiology <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18)</ref>, excitation-contraction coupling <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>, and cell survival <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref> increases as more and more of the network becomes depolarized, potentially scaling to whole organ dysfunction, for example, causing lethal arrhythmias or myocardial injury during ischemia reperfusion <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Mitochondrial synchronization phenomena (i.e., DJ m waves or oscillations) have been demonstrated previously for mitochondria in myocytes of intact perfused hearts <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>, where the cells are physically and electrically connected through gap junctions; however, it is not known whether the same spatiotemporal mitochondrial network properties apply.</s><s>Additionally, little is known about the effects of different metabolic substrates on mitochondrial cluster frequency dynamics.</s><s>The latter might be relevant to the known changes in energy substrate utilization in heart failure <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> and diabetic cardiomyopathy <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>To address these questions, we have developed waveletbased analyses of DJ m (TMRE fluorescence) oscillations of individual mitochondria in cardiac myocytes under pathophysiological conditions, which can provide a dynamic frequency for each oscillating mitochondrion <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref>.</s><s>This allows for detailed classification and analysis of the cluster organization of mitochondria with similar frequencies <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>.</s><s>For mitochondria belonging to the major frequency cluster, the overall cluster size was found to be inversely correlated with the cluster's mean frequency, suggesting that cluster synchronization to a common oscillatory mode takes longer for larger clusters due to diffusion-mediated processes within the coupling medium <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>To quantify how coupling strength contributes to synchronization among mitochondrial oscillators, we take the analysis further by applying an extended Kuramoto-type model for weakly coupled oscillators to determine coupling constants of the network under different metabolic conditions.</s><s>Recent studies have used this approach to explain how circadian networks are synchronized through intrinsic frequencies that drift in time <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26)</ref>.</s><s>Most of these models describe phase dynamics through a sinusoidal phase coupling term with a time-independent coupling constant; however, for cardiac myocytes, the observed dynamic transitions in the organization of mitochondrial oscillations suggest that there is time-varying mitochondrial coupling as well, which we take into consideration in this study.</s></p><p><s>These methods are applied to determine whether mitochondrial oscillations in the intact heart are similar to those in isolated myocytes, and whether substrate selection differentially modulates the dynamics of mitochondrial oscillations.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MATERIALS AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental methods</head><p><s>All experiments have been conducted on intact guinea pig hearts or freshly isolated adult guinea pig ventricular myocytes according to previously described protocols <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27)</ref> and in accordance with the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals (No. 85-23, 1996, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD) and The Johns Hopkins Animal Care and Use Committee (for more information, we refer to the Supporting Material).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Intact heart experiments</head><p><s>DJ m imaging data (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1 A</ref>) corresponds to a retrogradely-perfused heart imaged using a laser scanning two-photon microscope, as described in detail in Slodzinski et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>.</s><s>In brief, the cationic potentiometric fluorescent dye TMRE (tetramethylrhodamine ethyl ester) was used to monitor DJ m and images were recorded with a two-photon laser-scanning microscope (MRC-1024MP; Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA) with an excitation at 740 nm (Tsunami Ti:Sa laser; Spectra-Physics, Santa Clara, CA) and an emission band at 605 5 45 nm.</s><s>Contractile motion was arrested by perfusion with Tyrode solution containing 20 mM BDM (butanedione monoxime) to suppress contraction (see Whole Heart Preparation in the Supporting Material), and single laser flashes were applied to the region marked by the yellow boxes in Figs. 1 A and S1 A in the Supporting Material.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Isolated cardiomyocyte experiments</head><p><s>Freshly isolated myocytes (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1 B</ref>) were loaded with 100 nM TMRE at 37 C in a thermostatically controlled flow chamber mounted on the stage of an upright epifluorescence microscope (BX61WI; Olympus, Waltham, MA).</s><s>Their oscillatory behavior was assayed in the presence of different metabolic substrates.</s><s>Myocytes were visualized with an objective 25Â/ 1.05 W MP and images were acquired using a multiphoton-excited fluorescence Fluoview FV1000 MPE (Olympus) and a Deep Sea ultrafast system scanning laser (Mai Tai, Waltham, MA).</s><s>Images were recorded with excitation at 740 nm and the red emission of TMRE collected at 605 nm using a 578-630 nm band-pass filter.</s></p><p><s>For imaging, myocytes were perfused with Tyrode solution (pH 7.5) containing 1 mM Ca 2þ in the presence of 10 mM: glucose or pyruvate or lactate or b-hydroxybutyrate, as indicated.</s><s>Oscillations were triggered with a localized (5 Â 5 mm) laser flash, as previously described in Aon et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Selection and processing of individual mitochondrial TMRE signals</head><p><s>Epicardial images of the perfused heart were examined and cells showing mitochondrial DJ m oscillations, defined by a decrease of &gt;10% in the whole cell TMRE fluorescence, were analyzed (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1 A</ref>).</s><s>Myocyte borders along sarcolemma and intercalated disks were manually applied on a pixelby-pixel basis and grid templates representing the minimal mitochondrial cluster size (typical 1-2 mitochondria per sarcomere), excluding the nuclear region, were constructed for each selected myocyte (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1 A</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Individual mitochondrial TMRE signals were extracted from stacks of recorded frames of an isolated myocyte by manually applying a grid template to heart myocytes on time-averaged stack images.</s><s>Further spatiotemporal processing was done using wavelet analysis (7,23) (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1 C</ref>), as previously described in Kurz et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23)</ref>.</s><s>Selection of wavelet parameters, cutoff frequencies, normalization of mitochondrial TMRE signals, and determination of maximal wavelet power frequencies were carried out as described previously in Kurz et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23)</ref>.</s><s>(A more detailed description can be found in Selection and Processing of TMRE Fluorescence from Individual Mitochondria in Isolated Cardiac Myocytes in the Supporting Material.)</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Computational model</head><p><s>To study mitochondrion-to-mitochondrion coupling within clustered and nonclustered mitochondria, we sought to develop a minimum-order model that employs two parameters to characterize coupling: a mitochondrion-tomitochondrion coupling constant, and the intrinsic oscillatory frequency.</s></p><p><s>Identification of mitochondrial nearest neighbors was used as in Kurz et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> to determine the mitochondrial network's structural morphology.</s><s>To examine the network's connectivity properties, intermitochondrial coupling was only considered for local nearest-neighbor environments.</s></p><p><s>Wavelet phases were extracted from each individual mitochondrial TMRE (for more details, see Selection and Processing of TMRE Fluorescence from Individual Mitochondria in Isolated Cardiac Myocytes in the Supporting Material.)</s><s>Wavelet frequencies are nondifferentiable in time at points of frequency change (phase singularity), therefore, wavelet frequencies were taken as dynamical wavelet phase updates with the value of the actual wavelet frequency as the starting point.</s><s>The resulting updated wavelet frequency was median-filtered to correct for frequency changes at phase singularities.</s></p><p><s>Within the stochastic coupling model of the mitochondrial network, mitochondrial intrinsic frequencies are modeled as Ornstein-Uhlenbeck frequencies that drift in time towards the respective measured mitochondrial frequency <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28)</ref>,</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">du m dt ¼ Àgðu m À m m Þ þ h m ðtÞ;<label>(1)</label></formula><p><s>Biophysical Journal 108 <ref type="bibr">(8) 1922-1933</ref> where m m represents the mean frequency towards which the intrinsic mitochondrial frequency is drifting, h m is a Gaussian white noise source with variance s 2 h ¼ 2gs 2 m , g represents the decay rate, and s 2 m is the amplitude of mitochondrial frequency fluctuations <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26)</ref>.</s><s>The mean frequency m m was chosen as the time-dependent wavelet frequency of the m-th mitochondrion, whereas the free constant g was assumed to be identical for each The majority of mitochondria oscillate between 14 and 16 mHz.</s><s>Some of them also have a highly correlated signal at the same time t, thus constituting the major mitochondrial cluster at time t as used in the text.</s></p><p><s>mitochondrion in the network.</s><s>The frequency fluctuation amplitude measure, s m , for each mitochondrion, was taken as the standard deviation of the measured mitochondrial wavelet frequency.</s><s>Discrete dynamical updates were performed to calculate the mitochondrial intrinsic frequencies <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Local mitochondrial coupling was considered to be of local mean field type, and local mean field parameters R m (t) and j m (t), corresponding to mitochondrion m, are defined as R m ðtÞe 2ipj m ðtÞ ¼ 1 jL m j X j˛Lm e 2ip4 j ðtÞ ;</s></p><p><s>(</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_1">)<label>2</label></formula><p><s>where L m is the set of nearest neighbors of a mitochondrion (compare to Rougemont and Naef <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26)</ref>) and jL m j is the number of nearest neighbors.</s><s>This corresponds to phase differential equations of the form</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_2">v4 m ðtÞ vt ¼ u m ðtÞ þ K m ðtÞR m ðtÞsinð2pðj m ðtÞ À 4 m ðtÞÞÞ (3)</formula><p><s>for each mitochondrion m.</s></p><p><s>Maximum likelihood estimation was applied to optimize the model parameter g within the interval [0,1].</s><s>With the optimal decay rate parameter, the coupling constants K m (t) were evaluated for 10 different starting points u m (0) and 100 different dynamically evolving Ornstein-Uhlenbeck frequencies u m , respectively, as above.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stochastic phase model</head><p><s>Because mitochondrial DJ m oscillations exhibit dynamically changing frequencies, we extended the Kuramoto model to include frequencies that can drift in time.</s><s>This can be done by introducing a second timescale 1/g, g being a measure of the stability of the phase oscillator <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref>, to model frequency dynamics as Ornstein-Uhlenbeck processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In Ornstein-Uhlenbeck processes, the frequency dispersion s m is a measure of frequency noise whereas g is a measure of the intrinsic frequency to adhere to a fixed frequency m m , thus revealing the stability of the oscillator (compare to <ref type="bibr">Lemons (29)</ref>).</s><s>Variation of g follows exponential dynamics: large g-values yield intrinsic frequencies that are more dependent on the Gaussian whitenoise term, and thus show a stronger drift than those with small g <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In addition to dynamically changing intrinsic frequencies, phase coupling was assumed to underlie dynamical changes as well, to be unique for each mitochondrion and, for each mitochondrion and its nearest neighbors, to be of local mean field type (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>).</s><s>Each mitochondrion's wavelet frequency was determined according to protocols established in 2010 <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23)</ref> and each mitochondrion's frequency fluctuation amplitude s m was taken as the standard deviation of the measured mitochondrial wavelet frequency.</s><s>Moreover, the mean frequency toward which the intrinsic frequencies drift in time was taken as the time-dependent mitochondrial wavelet frequency, thus leaving only the decay rate parameter g fixed for all mitochondria in a cardiac myocyte.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistics</head><p><s>The wavelet analysis fitting routines were obtained using the software MATLAB (Ver.</s><s>7.1.0.246,</s><s>R14, The MathWorks, Natick, MA).</s><s>Further statistics were performed using the software ORIGINPRO 8 (SR0 Ver.</s><s>8.0724, B724, OriginLab, Northampton, MA).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Frequency and cluster-size relationship in whole heart</head><p><s>To examine whether the individual mitochondrial TMRE signals in the intact heart exhibit dynamic properties similar to those of isolated cardiac myocyte, the time course of mitochondrial fluorescence was extracted from a handdrawn grid of recorded stack images averaged over time.</s><s>Because the mitochondrial signal is nonstationary in time, wavelet transforms are an adequate time-frequency representation for temporal processing <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(31)</ref>.</s><s>This approach allowed us to filter all mitochondria with similar dynamical frequency behavior in order to identify mitochondrial frequency clusters and examine their spatial correlates <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>.</s><s>In brief, frequency histograms were obtained for each myocyte at every time-point t and the maximum peak of mitochondria with similar frequencies, i.e., mitochondria belonging to a (major) frequency cluster, was determined as the major cluster peak.</s></p><p><s>Subsequently, mitochondria belonging to peaks neighboring the major cluster peak were incorporated into the cluster if their signal at t was highly correlated to the cluster signal.</s><s>More details can be found in Kurz et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> and in Selection and Processing of TMRE Fluorescence from Individual Mitochondria in Isolated Cardiac Myocytes in the Supporting Material.</s><s>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1 D</ref>, the distribution of frequencies for a glucose-perfused isolated myocyte is exemplarily shown in a two-dimensional image at two specific time-points (lower panel; the lower cutoff frequency is 8.2 mHz).</s><s>To achieve this, the values of mitochondrial frequencies were placed at the pixel-positions of the respective mitochondrion and missing intermitochondrial pixels were interpolated using the GRIDDATA function in the software MATLAB (Ver.</s><s>7.6.0.324,</s><s>R2008a).</s><s>For the first time-point, it can be seen that many mitochondria that are distributed all over the cell show similar frequencies between 14 and 16 mHz.</s><s>They belong to the major cluster.</s><s>Yet, the second image at a later time-point shows a slightly different frequency distribution with most frequencies being located at ~14 mHz.</s><s>There is also a newly formed smaller pocket or cluster of mitochondria with frequencies &gt;16 mHz on the right-hand side of the myocyte, that does not necessarily belong to the major frequency cluster.</s></p><p><s>As in the case of isolated cardiac myocytes, major cluster mitochondria were found for each cardiac myocyte with signs of depolarization during TMRE recording of glucose-perfused hearts (N ¼ 2), close to the left anterior descending coronary artery.</s><s>We observed that the inverse relationship between relative cluster area and number, as observed in isolated cardiac myocytes, could be confirmed (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>).</s><s>Therefore, this indicates that large clusters have a longer oscillation period than small clusters, not only in the case of isolated myocytes, but also for connected cardiac myocytes in the intact heart.</s><s>However, an inverse relationship between mean cluster radius and frequency could only be verified for one of the two whole heart preparations.</s><s>The mean cluster radius is found to be in a range approximately one-half the size of that of isolated glucose-treated cardiac myocytes.</s></p><p><s>The rate of change of mean cluster radius with respect to the cluster frequency for glucose-treated myocytes in the intact heart preparation was À0.14 5 0.01 mm/mHz (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> A, and see also Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1 B</ref>).</s><s>Summary statistics of mitochondrial frequency distributions of major cluster mitochondria for all cardiac myocytes of the respective whole heart yields frequency ranges of 10.30-58.1 mHz (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3 C</ref>).</s><s>Evidently, the range of mitochondrial frequencies in intact heart myocytes is significantly broader than in isolated myocytes, i.e., mitochondria generally oscillate at higher frequencies in the intact heart (see also Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1 B</ref>).</s><s>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> A, this leads to a mean cluster radius of ~11-17 mm for this preparation.</s></p><p><s>The rate of change of % area versus frequency for cardiac myocytes was determined as À2.44 5 0.10 %/mHz (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3 B</ref>).</s><s>Likewise, the % number of cluster mitochondria versus frequency gave a rate of change of À2.37 5 0.10 %/mHz (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3 D</ref>).</s><s>Therefore, for recordings with glucoseperfusion, the respective rate of change of % area and number versus frequency in intact heart cardiac myocytes is ~18-19% smaller than in isolated cardiac myocytes.</s><s>Also, the results point out that clusters at whole myocyte level in whole heart preparations have higher frequencies than those in isolated cardiac myocytes.</s><s>Similar results have been achieved with another optical slice of the intact perfused heart (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1, A and B</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Frequency and cluster-size relationship in isolated myocytes</head><p><s>Having demonstrated that mitochondria in the isolated myocyte exhibit properties similar to those in the intact heart, we sought to examine the mitochondrial properties in cardiomyocytes challenged with different substrates.</s></p><p><s>Major cluster mitochondria were determined for myocytes treated with pyruvate, b-hydroxybutyrate, lactate, or glucose, respectively.</s><s>Subsequently, the relative area of cluster mitochondria (quotient of total cluster pixel-count and myocyte pixel-count) was plotted against the mean frequency of the cluster (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>).</s><s>Similarly, the relative number of cluster mitochondria (quotient of the number of cluster mitochondria versus the total number of mitochondria) was plotted against the mean frequency (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S3</ref>).</s><s>Also, measures for cluster size were compared with the mean frequency of the cluster mitochondria by relating the mean cluster radius (the distance of the geometrical center of the cluster to each single cluster mitochondrion's geometrical center averaged over all cluster mitochondria) and the mean frequency of the cluster (see Fig. <ref type="figure">S2</ref>).</s><s>The inverse relationship among mean mitochondrial mean cluster radius, relative cluster area, and number is obvious and has already been shown for glucose-treated cardiac myocytes <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>.</s><s>This suggests that, throughout all sets of myocytes that are treated with respective substrates, large clusters have a longer oscillation period than small clusters.</s><s>Frequency distributions of mitochondria for each specific substrate group were determined as previously described in Kurz et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> (see also Fig. <ref type="figure">S4</ref>).</s><s>For glucose-treated myocytes, this gives a frequency bandwidth of 8.73-22.3</s><s>mHz.</s><s>In comparison, pyruvate-treated myocytes show a more dispersed frequency distribution that ranges from 3.7 to 54.83 mHz, whereas myocytes from the lactate group are more narrowly distributed with frequencies in the range 3.9-15.0</s><s>mHz.</s><s>Finally, myocytes that were treated with b-hydroxybutyrate mostly displayed major cluster oscillations in the low frequency range of 4.0-10.1 mHz.</s></p><p><s>The cluster size can be estimated more precisely by the % area of the cluster (quotient of the area of cluster mitochondria and whole myocyte area, Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>).</s><s>The rate of change of % area versus frequency for glucose-, pyruvate-, lactate-, and b-hydroxybutyrate-treated cardiac myocytes was given as À2.96 5 1.11 %/mHz, À4.01 5 0.07 %/mHz, À2.90 5 0.07 %/mHz, and À4.86 5 0.07 %/mHz, respec-tively.</s><s>Similar results were obtained for the % number of cluster mitochondria (see Frequency and Cluster-Size Relationship in Isolated Myocytes in the Supporting Material).</s><s>It appears that cardiac myocytes from the b-hydroxybutyrate group show the strongest change of % area versus frequency, i.e., ~64% more than glucose-treated myocytes.</s><s>Pyruvatetreated myocytes show a rate of change of % area versus frequency that is ~35% higher than myocytes from the glucose group.</s><s>Cardiac myocytes from either the lactate or the glucose group exhibit similar rates of change of % area versus frequency.</s><s>In addition, myocytes from the b-hydroxybutyrate group show % area versus frequency changes at moderately low frequencies of &lt;20 mHz unlike the other substrates that exhibit % area changes at slightly higher frequencies, especially in glucose-treated cardiomyocytes.</s><s>Interestingly, the two substrates leading to the most reduced redox potential, pyruvate and b-hydroxybutyrate, have a higher % area of the cluster.</s><s>Generally, a more rapid drop in % cluster area in nonglucose substrates indicates smaller clusters and lower frequencies as compared with glucose.</s><s>This is the picture of a more fragmented population of oscillators in smaller clusters, a conclusion reinforced by the higher frequency dispersion exhibited by the oscillators (Fig. <ref type="figure">S4</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cluster oscillation coherence</head><p><s>There is no significant change in the coherence of the cluster mitochondria during the recording across substrate groups, thus indicating high temporal stability of the respective oscillating cluster mitochondria (see Fig. <ref type="figure">S5</ref>).</s><s>However, coherence of cluster mitochondria averaged in time were highest in glucose-treated cardiac myocytes at 0.66 5 0.04, whereas coherence values in the pyruvate-, lactate-, and b-hydroxybutyrate-treated substrate groups were 0.40 5 0.03, 0.49 5 0.04, and 0.49 5 0.03, respectively.</s><s>The coherence values between mitochondria that do not belong to the major cluster were determined to be 0.44 5 0.04, 0.39 5 0.04, 0.46 5 0.04, and 0.39 5 0.03 for glucose-, pyruvate-, lactate-, and b-hydroxybutyrate-treated cardiac myocytes, respectively.</s><s>Thus, noncluster mitochondria coherence properties were similar for different substrates, exhibiting a relatively high degree of coherence.</s><s>As suggested in Kurz et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, this may be due to stable oscillations of noncluster mitochondria at frequencies that are different from the frequencies at which major cluster mitochondria oscillate.</s></p><p><s>The difference in coherence between cluster and noncluster mitochondria for glucose-treated myocytes <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> remains valid for all substrate groups, although it is less pronounced in lactate and pyruvate.</s><s>This might be due to a decreased level of mitochondrial nearest-neighbor coupling during each depolarization/repolarization.</s><s>Specifically, in pyruvate-treated cardiomyocytes, smaller and more topologically dispersed ensembles of major cluster mitochondria were observed.</s><s>This increases the number of mitochondria within the major cluster that have at least one noncluster nearest-neighbor mitochondrion.</s><s>Also, the number of noncluster nearest neighbors for the majority of individual cluster mitochondria is increased, thus, taken together, providing a lower averaged temporal coherence between a cluster mitochondrion and its nearest neighbors.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Forward model and model validation</head><p><s>To study mitochondrion-to-mitochondrion coupling between cluster and noncluster mitochondria, we sought to develop a minimum-order model that employs two parameters to characterize the coupling: a mitochondrionto-mitochondrion coupling constant and the intrinsic mitochondrial oscillatory frequency.</s><s>Such a quantification of intermitochondrial coupling may serve to identify hubs of highly connected mitochondria within ventricular myocytes and thus may contribute to further examine synchronization properties of the mitochondrial network.</s><s>In addition, individual mitochondrial coupling constants can be used to stochastically simulate large mitochondrial networks and identify possible threshold parameters that may characterize the cell's descent towards death.</s></p><p><s>Forward modeling for whole-cell intensity signals with myocyte-specific optimal decay parameter g and mitochondrial coupling constants was performed by cross-correlating the cosine of the whole-cell TMRE signal wavelet phase with the sum of cosines of the forward-modeled phases of the stochastic model (Figs.</s><s><ref type="figure">S8 and S9</ref>).</s></p><p><s>High correlation coefficients indicate the similarity of predicted signals and the recorded signals, providing valid-ity for the acquired coupling constants.</s><s>Correlation coefficients for each cardiac myocyte were determined to be 0.88 5 0.02, 0.64 5 0.05, 0.85 5 0.03, and 0.75 5 0.03 for glucose-, pyruvate-, lactate-, and b-hydroxybutyratetreated myocytes, respectively (Fig. <ref type="figure">S9</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Spatiotemporal properties of local coupling in mitochondrial frequency clusters</head><p><s>Time-dependent coupling constants for each mitochondrion in all cardiac myocytes across different substrate groups were determined using the respective optimal decay rate parameters.</s><s>For each of the substrate-treated myocyte groups, mean decay rate parameters were determined to be 7.13 Â 10 À2 5 1.55 Â 10 À2 s À1 and 6.46 Â 10 À2 5 1.14 Â 10 À2 s À1 for glucose and b-hydroxybutyrate, respectively, whereas pyruvate and lactate showed slightly smaller decay rate parameters (6.10 Â 10 À2 5 1.26 Â 10 À2 s À1 and 6.29 Â 10 À2 5 1.17 Â 10 À2 s À1 , respectively (Fig. <ref type="figure">S7</ref>)).</s></p><p><s>Cluster and noncluster mitochondria for each myocyte were determined as detailed above and, for each recorded point in time, coupling constants were averaged for cluster and noncluster mitochondria, to evaluate the time evolution of their respective coupling constants (Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To compare myocytes with unequal recording time, we set each myocyte's duration of oscillations to 1.</s><s>One observes higher coupling strengths for cluster mitochondria in cardiac myocytes perfused with glucose or b-hydroxybutyrate, whereas differences in averaged coupling constants for cluster and noncluster mitochondria in pyruvate or lactate are less pronounced.</s><s>One can also notice a distinct decrease of cluster coupling constants at the beginning of the recordings for pyruvate-and glucose-perfused myocytes.</s><s>This might be due to a strong drift from cluster frequencies towards the common cluster frequency for those cluster mitochondria whose frequencies are the farthest away from the common cluster frequency according to Eq. 3 (or Eq.</s><s>S3 in the Supporting Material).</s></p><p><s>Averaging in time yields a mean coupling constant of 7.78 Â 10 À2 5 0.98 Â 10 À2 s À1 for cluster and 4.40 Â 10 À2 5 0.64 Â 10 À2 s À1 for noncluster mitochondria, respectively, in glucose-perfused isolated cardiac myocytes.</s><s>Pyruvate perfusion gave a similar time-averaged mean coupling constant for cluster mitochondria (7.49</s><s>Â 10 À2 5 1.65 Â 10 À2 s À1 ) whereas lactate and b-hydroxybutyrate were found to have lower time-averaged cluster coupling constants (4.83 Â 10 À2 5 1.25 Â 10 À2 s À1 and 4.11 Â 10 À2 5 0.62 Â 10 À2 s À1 , respectively).</s><s>However, averaged coupling constants for noncluster mitochondria gave 6.56 Â 10 À2 5 1.60 Â 10 À2 s À1 , 4.24 Â 10 À2 5 1.10 Â 10 À2 s À1 , and 2.49 Â 10 À2 5 0.34 Â 10 À2 s À1 for pyruvate, lactate, and b-hydroxybutyrate, respectively.</s><s>Distributions of coupling constants were compared across substrates for cluster and noncluster mitochondria, respectively, and found to be significantly different from each other (p &lt; 0.006).</s><s>In Biophysical Journal 108 <ref type="bibr">(8) 1922-1933</ref> accordance with Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>, lower mitochondrial cluster coupling can be attributed to smaller cluster areas for cell perfusion with b-hydroxybutyrate and lactate.</s><s>For pyruvate and lactate, lower coupling constants for cluster compared to noncluster mitochondria suggest similar spatiotemporal contiguity properties of the mitochondrial clusters.</s><s>This contiguity might underlie other metabolic control mechanisms, as in glucose or b-hydroxybutyrate.</s></p><p><s>However, cluster coherence in b-hydroxybutyrateperfused cells is higher than for pyruvate (see Fig. <ref type="figure">S5</ref>).</s><s>In Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>, the mean cluster coupling constant for each myocyte was plotted against its corresponding mean cluster coherence value, across all substrates.</s><s>One observes that glucose-perfused clusters exhibit an increase in cluster coupling for higher cluster coherence, the rate of change being 0.32 5 0.03 s À1 .</s><s>The same relation, but to a lesser degree and in line with decreasing cluster size (see Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>), can be observed for b-hydroxybutyrate and pyruvate perfusion.</s><s>Here, rates of change of cluster coupling versus cluster coherence are 0.09 5 0.01 s À1 and 0.08 5 0.03 s À1 for b-hydroxybutyrate and pyruvate, respectively.</s><s>However, for pyruvate-perfused myocytes, some outliers are noticeable that can be attributed to the early decrease of coupling strength (Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>).</s><s>For pyruvate perfusion, coherence levels at this point are low, i.e., mitochondria might rapidly drop in and out of the cluster whereas glucose perfusion features the same distinct decrease of early coupling strength for high coherence levels.</s><s>Generally, larger cluster areas show stronger cluster coupling constants, resulting in more coherent cluster oscillations.</s><s>Yet for small cluster areas, as in the case of lactate-perfusion, cluster coupling does not in-crease with cluster coherence: the rate of change is in this case À0.01 5 0.01 s À1 .</s><s>Therefore, even though a smaller amount of cluster mitochondria might be more coherent, cluster coupling does not necessarily increase as well, indicating a greater influence of spatial than temporal coupling on mitochondrial networks.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>To our knowledge, this study is the first to quantitatively characterize the effects of different substrates on spatiotemporal FIGURE 5 Mean mitochondrial cluster coupling constants (in units [s À1 ]) versus mean noncluster coupling constants for each point in time for cardiac myocytes perfused with pyruvate, b-hydroxybutyrate, lactate, or glucose.</s><s>To allow statistical comparison among myocytes with unequal recording time, the duration of the oscillations of each recording was normalized.</s><s>For pyruvate and lactate, lower ratios of averaged coupling constants for cluster to noncluster mitochondria suggest similar spatiotemporal contiguity properties of the mitochondrial clusters.</s><s>This contiguity might underlie different metabolic control mechanisms as compared to glucose or b-hydroxybutyrate (compare to Fig. <ref type="figure">S5</ref>).</s><s>Also, the higher values of cluster coupling constants obtained with pyruvate or glucose might be attributed to larger cluster areas as suggested by Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>. FIGURE 6 Mean mitochondrial cluster coupling constant K versus mean cluster coherence.</s><s>For pyruvate-, b-hydroxybutyrate-, and glucose-perfused myocytes, higher cluster coupling values increase with higher cluster coherence values.</s><s>However, the rate of increase lessens with the size of cluster area (see Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>).</s><s>For small cluster areas as in the case of lactate-perfused myocytes, cluster coupling does not increase with cluster coherence.</s><s>Linear fit curves are displayed in their corresponding substrate colors.</s><s>To see this figure in color, go online.</s></p><p><s>Biophysical Journal 108 <ref type="bibr">(8) 1922-1933</ref> organization of stress-induced mitochondrial oscillations in the pathophysiological regime.</s><s>To our knowledge, we have made several novel advances by this study.</s><s>First, the wavelet-based method demonstrates that mitochondria in the intact heart exhibit properties similar to those in isolated myocytes, thus establishing the isolated myocyte as a reliable model for studying time-dependent frequency modulation of oscillating mitochondria, as well as mitochondrion-to-mitochondrion coupling.</s><s>Second, different cluster organization properties in response to metabolic status are uncovered, therefore indicating different spatiotemporal properties of the mitochondrial network.</s><s>Third, a stochastic phase model was introduced that provides a measure of the stability of mitochondrial phase oscillators by quantifying intermitochondrial coupling through a locally defined coupling constant for each individual mitochondrion.</s><s>Fourth, the phase model reveals significant correlations among intermitochondrial coupling, mitochondrial cluster area, and cluster coherence.</s></p><p><s>Stress-induced mitochondrial DJ m oscillations have previously been shown to occur not only in isolated cardiac myocytes but also for intact hearts <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>.</s><s>These findings extend prior results obtained in single cardiac myocytes <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15)</ref> and computational models <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">32)</ref> to the whole heart.</s><s>Here, we show that mitochondrial collective behavior for clusters of mitochondria with similar frequencies seems to be analogous to that in isolated cardiomyocytes.</s><s>This could be an indication that metabolic, molecular, and electrical communication via gap junctions between cardiac myocytes does not significantly modify mitochondrial network dynamics under stress.</s><s>Interestingly, we observed depolarizations within myocytes of the intact heart to be partly spontaneous in some cardiac myocytes after laser-flashing of neighboring myocytes, thus indicating relay properties for mitochondrial coupling agents at intercellular junctions, similar to earlier findings in isolated myocyte pairs <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Substrate dependence of mitochondrial network dynamics</head><p><s>Animal models of heart failure show increased myocardial glucose dependence and utilization, compared to fatty acids in the normal heart <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">33)</ref>.</s><s>However, the role of glucose in either aiding the myocyte to adapt to increased ATP demand or as a metabolic maladaptive response (while flexibility in substrate utilization remains limited), is still unclear <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">35)</ref>.</s><s>Furthermore, the data concerning the energetic substrate switch in human heart failure remain inconsistent <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref>.</s><s>The main question behind possible substrate dependence of the mitochondrial network is whether glucose keeps higher synchronicity across the network as compared with other substrates.</s><s>As shown, glucose-perfused cardiac myocytes demonstrate larger percentiles of cluster area versus myocyte area than other energy suppliers (compare to Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>) whereas cardiac myocytes perfused with b-hy-droxybutyrate demonstrated the strongest change in % cluster size versus mean cluster frequency.</s><s>Also, mitochondrial frequencies were found to be within a narrower low-frequency range in glucose than in the other substrates (Fig. <ref type="figure">S4</ref>).</s><s>Dispersion in cluster size and frequencies may indicate heterogeneity and less synchrony.</s><s>Dynamic mitochondrial clusters would form more rapidly during ROSinduced ROS release by recruiting other mitochondrial oscillators, which in turn would leave fewer clusters with different frequencies, thus narrowing the mitochondrial frequency distribution.</s><s>This finding relates to the problem of synchronization: higher slope and larger frequency distribution represent a signature of desynchronization due to dynamic heterogeneity.</s></p><p><s>The model presented herein attributes this fundamental feature to time-dependent drifting frequencies of the oscillators.</s><s>Mechanistically, time-dependent drifting frequencies can be explained by local dynamics of ROS production and ROS scavenging systems involving mitochondrial matrix and the extramitochondrial compartment <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(36)</ref>.</s><s>Interestingly, the two substrates leading to the most reduced redox potential, pyruvate and b-hydroxybutyrate, have higher % area of the cluster than lactate.</s><s>b-hydroxybutyrate-perfused cardiac myocytes still show lower cluster coupling than cells with pyruvate or glucose perfusion.</s><s>Metabolically, the major difference between pyruvate and lactate is that cytosolic redox status is bestowed with less (pyruvate) or more (lactate) reducing equivalents available, although both would likely lead to more reduced matrix NADH than in glucose, feeding NADH oxidase.</s><s>This would concur with an increase in ROS levels and hence higher intermitochondrial coupling rates.</s><s>Mean coupling for lactate and pyruvate is lower than for glucose, thus indicating more complex redox relations or spatiotemporal coupling properties, as discussed below.</s><s>However, additional studies will be required to determine the exact role of ROS in substratedependent redox processes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Modeling of large-scale synchronization in mitochondrial dynamics</head><p><s>The concept of scale-free mitochondrial networks has been introduced over the last decade to describe intermitochondrial coupling across different spatiotemporal domains in cardiac myocytes <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">37)</ref>.</s><s>Recent work extends these findings to mitochondrial networks from other organs such as salivary glands in live animals <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>.</s><s>Using intravital twophoton microscopy, these authors showed ROS-dependent cell-and tissue-wide synchronized mitochondrial oscillations under basal conditions.</s><s>Weak temporal organization under physiological conditions is strengthened in the pathophysiological regime where the mitochondrial oscillators mostly lock-in low frequency and large amplitude oscillations <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27)</ref>.</s><s>In this regard, cardiac mitochondria, like yeast, have been proposed to possess inherent Biophysical Journal 108 <ref type="bibr">(8) 1922-1933</ref> characteristics of a biological clock <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">38)</ref>.</s><s>Mathematical descriptions of the transition of such multiple oscillator networks to synchrony have been addressed by several authors <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(39,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">40)</ref>.</s><s>These studies show that coupling starts in a synchronized nucleus of excited oscillators that can then recruit new oscillators until a critical mass of oscillators induces spontaneous self-synchronization across the network <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">40)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The introduction of time-drifting frequencies to model circadian network behavior as an extended Kuramoto model with intrinsic Ornstein-Uhlenbeck frequencies <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26)</ref> closely applies to mitochondrial frequency dynamics.</s><s>This is because, in cardiac myocytes, mitochondrial phase dynamics are subject to time-dependent diffusionmediated intermitochondrial coupling processes involving ROS production and consumption of antioxidant reserves <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27)</ref>.</s><s>Because ROS scavenging in the cytoplasm restricts the long-range diffusion of the primary coupling agent, signaling of the oscillatory behavior is locally restricted, hence, there is an inherent frequency stiffness towards the actual mitochondrial frequency for each individual mitochondrial oscillator.</s><s>The proposed model, however, does not consider randomly excitable mitochondria that might suddenly start oscillating or flickering during the course of recording (see, for example, Nivala et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>).</s><s>This will have an effect on myocytes where the major cluster only constitutes a minority of the network mitochondria as in the case of cardiac myocytes perfused with pyruvate or lactate (see below).</s><s>However, we show that varying coupling strength has a similar effect on the cluster frequency behavior for all considered myocytes (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S11</ref>), an effect that is in agreement with Chiang et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(41)</ref>, where it is shown that a control of the common frequency of a network can be achieved by changing the strength of coupling between its constituents.</s></p><p><s>Frequency drifts are governed by the value of the decay rate parameter g at a fixed frequency dispersion of the mitochondrial network; the collective response groups are locked into distinct and incoherent clusters whose formation depends on the proximity of individual frequencies to each other <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>.</s><s>On the other hand, large decay rate parameters decrease the frequency distribution and contribute to equalization of dynamic cluster properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26)</ref>.</s><s>Therefore, our results for the decay rate parameter g indicate that cardiac myocytes perfused with substrates like pyruvate and lactate, which possess slightly smaller g than glucose or b-hydroxybutyrate, show a greater variety of frequency-locked clusters to some extent.</s><s>Even though the differences are not significant, this would be consistent with the notion of similar temporal coherence properties of the major frequency cluster and noncluster mitochondria for pyruvate and lactate, and also with spatiotemporal cluster properties that are derived from the relation of % cluster area and mean cluster frequency (see also the Supporting Material).</s></p><p><s>Mitochondrial ROS-induced ROS release adds to basal ROS concentrations and significantly increases local ROS density for small areas of highly contiguous phase-locked mitochondrial oscillators <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(42)</ref>.</s><s>Because growing clusters lose contiguity and their mean frequency decreases (Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3  and 4</ref>), the frequency of local ROS release declines along with ROS levels in nearest-neighbor environments, thus decreasing intermitochondrial coupling (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S10</ref>).</s><s>However, formation of cell-wide spanning clusters <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27)</ref> slightly increases the overall basal ROS concentration, therefore increasing local intermitochondrial coupling as well.</s></p><p><s>Our results suggest that the correlation between local mitochondrial coupling and mitochondrial cluster frequency is mainly driven by early cluster formation where the averaged coupling constant is mildly (b-hydroxybutyrate and lactate) to strongly (glucose and pyruvate) higher (compare to Fig. <ref type="figure">5</ref>) than for the rest of the recording.</s><s>On the other hand, local coupling and % cluster area are mostly determined through low coupling constants at the end of the recordings where most mitochondria have been integrated into the spanning cluster, and cytoplasmic ROS levels increase with % cluster area.</s><s>Generally, larger cluster areas show stronger intermitochondrial coupling, even though cluster coherence might be low (as in the case of pyruvate).</s><s>The cluster area is largest when myocytes are perfused with glucose and therefore shows the largest averaged cluster coupling and largest increase in coupling strength for increasing cluster coherence.</s><s>In addition, because an increase in mitochondrial cluster frequency leads to stronger cluster coupling for all substrates (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S11</ref>), and cluster areas in lactate-perfused cells are smaller than for all other examined substrates, these findings indicate that spatial coupling has a greater effect on synchronized mitochondrial networks than temporal coupling.</s></p><p><s>Coupling agent ROS in the normal heart is involved in the regulation of homoeostatic and stress response pathways <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(43)</ref> and it has been shown that ROS levels and activity are increased under pathological conditions such as ischemiareperfusion injury <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(44)</ref> and diabetic cardiomyopathy <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">45)</ref>.</s><s>The above results suggest that there is a decrease in intermitochondrial coupling under certain metabolic conditions such as preferred supply of substrates like lactate as opposed to glucose.</s><s>Such reduced redox-based coupling in mitochondrial networks might impair cardiac energy utilization and may therefore exacerbate heart failure (compare to Ventura-Clapier et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(46)</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p><s>In conclusion, for ventricular cardiac myocytes within the pathophysiological regime of stress-induced synchronized DJ m oscillations, this study shows that % cluster area is inversely correlated with cluster mean frequency not only for isolated myocytes perfused with different energy suppliers but also for connected myocytes in the intact heart.</s></p><p><s>The results therefore underline the universality of this correlation that reflects the importance of spatial and temporal organization on network functionality.</s><s>Also, the study quantifies intermitochondrial coupling by introducing a stochastic phase model that accurately describes mitochondrial network dynamics, and provides insights into changes in mitochondrial network functional topology under different metabolic conditions.</s><s>Specifically, it is shown that glucose perfusion, in particular, has strong effects on the mitochondrial oscillatory network, generating high intermitochondrial coupling and coherence, and that spatial intermitochondrial coupling is preferred over temporal coupling.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SUPPORTING MATERIAL</head><p><s>Supporting Materials and Methods, 11 figures, and two tables are available at http://www.biophysj.org/biophysj/supplemental/S0006-3495(15)</s><s>00179-4.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIGURE 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 1 Oscillating mitochondria in two-photon images of TMRE-fluorescent intact guinea-pig heart tissue and isolated cardiomyocytes.</s><s>(A) Within the optical slice of the perfused heart, cardiac myocytes were selected according to observed depolarizations.</s><s>Myocyte borders along the sarcolemma and intercalated disks as well as mitochondrial grids were manually applied on a pixel-by-pixel basis.</s><s>(Yellow boxes) Laser-flashed regions of the myocytes.</s><s>(B) Isolated cardiac myocyte (left side of panel) and the same myocyte with an overlaid grid to consider single mitochondria (right side of panel), e.g., mitochondrion 112 (mitochondrion 112 denotes the numerical identifier of the selected mitochondrion).</s><s>(C) TMRE intensity time plot of mitochondrion 112 from (B) and the corresponding absolute squared wavelet transform (lower panel).</s><s>Visibly, the mitochondrion oscillates between 20 and 40 mHz during the recording.</s><s>(D) Frequency distribution maps obtained from a different cardiac myocyte.</s><s>(Upper panel) Time evolution of the averaged frequency of all mitochondria.</s><s>For two time-points (red dots), the mitochondrial frequency distribution is shown (lower panels): mitochondrial frequency values are put in the respective mitochondrial position and missing pixels are interpolated (see main text for details).The majority of mitochondria oscillate between 14 and 16 mHz.</s><s>Some of them also have a highly correlated signal at the same time t, thus constituting the major mitochondrial cluster at time t as used in the text.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,53.39,85.33,270.79,566.83" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>4 KFIGURE 2</head><label>42</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 2 Schematic of local intermitochondrial coupling.</s><s>In the stochastic phase model, intermitochondrial coupling was only considered for the local nearest-neighbor environment, thus providing an average coupling constant K for each mitochondrion (symbolized by the light-colored cloud).</s><s>To see this figure in color, go online.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>FIGURE 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 3  Mitochondrial major cluster properties of cardiac tissue of a guinea pig heart.</s><s>Depicted are the results obtained from the analysis of seven myocytes for (A) mean cluster radius versus frequency; (B) cluster area normalized by the full myocyte area versus frequency; (C) distribution of mitochondrial frequencies for all cluster mitochondria across all myocytes; and (D) cluster mitochondria count normalized by the total number of mitochondria for the major cluster versus frequency.</s><s>In the plots, we have (black) mean curve; (red) standard error bars.</s><s>The apparent discrepancy between the frequency range in (A) and in (B)-(D) is due to interpolation errors in (A).</s><s>A similar figure for another optical slice of perfused heart tissue can be found in Fig.S1.</s><s>To see this figure in color, go online.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>F</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>.T.K. and A.A.A. designed research; F.T.K., M.A.A., and B.O'R. performed research; F.T.K. contributed analytic tools; F.T.K. and T.D. analyzed data; and F.T.K., M.A.A., B.O'R., and A.A.A. wrote the article.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Biophysical Journal Volume 108 April 2015 1922-1933</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Biophysical Journal 108(8) 1922-1933   </note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>The work was supported by a Boehringer Ingelheim Fonds fellowship given to F.T.K.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SUPPORTING CITATIONS</head><p><s>References <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(47)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(48)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(49)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(50)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(51)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(52)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(53)</ref> appear in the Supporting Material.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mitochondrial oscillations in physiology and pathophysiology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cortassa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>O'rourke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Exp. Med. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">641</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="98" to="117" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subcellular metabolic transients and mitochondrial redox waves in heart cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Romashko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Marban</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>O'rourke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1618" to="1623" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imaging in five dimensions: time-dependent membrane potentials in individual mitochondria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Loew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Tuft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Fay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2396" to="2407" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Laser-stimulated fluorescence of submicrometer regions within single mitochondria of rhodamine-treated myocardial cells in culture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Siemens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Walter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Berns</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A reaction-diffusion model of ROS-induced ROS release in a mitochondrial network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>O'rourke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1000657</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cortassa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Encyclopedia of Molecular Cell Biology and Molecular Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>Wiley</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatio-temporal oscillations of individual mitochondria in cardiac myocytes reveal modulation of synchronized mitochondrial clusters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kurz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Armoundas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14315" to="14320" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network biology: understanding the cell&apos;s functional organization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Baraba ´si</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Oltvai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="113" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vivo tissue-wide synchronization of mitochondrial metabolic oscillations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Porat-Shliom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Weigert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="514" to="521" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mitochondrial ROS-induced ROS release: an update and review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Zorov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Juhaszova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sollott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1757</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="509" to="517" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linking flickering to waves and whole-cell oscillations in a mitochondrial network model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nivala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Korge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2102" to="2111" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mitochondria are excitable organelles capable of generating and conveying electrical and calcium signals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ichas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jouaville</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mazat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1145" to="1153" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Percolation and criticality in a mitochondrial network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cortassa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>O'rourke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4447" to="4452" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mitochondrial criticality: a new concept at the turning point of life or death</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cortassa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>O'rourke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1762</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="240" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synchronized whole cell oscillations in mitochondrial metabolism triggered by a local release of reactive oxygen species in cardiac myocytes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cortassa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>O'rourke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">278</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44735" to="44744" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oscillations of membrane current and excitability driven by metabolic oscillations in heart cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>O'rourke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ramza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Marban</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">265</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="962" to="966" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mitochondrial origin of postischemic arrhythmias</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Akar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>O'rourke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clin. Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3527" to="3535" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From mitochondrial dynamics to arrhythmias</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cortassa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>O'rourke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Biochem. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1940" to="1948" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What yeast and cardiomyocytes share: ultradian oscillatory redox mechanisms of cellular coherence and survival</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cortassa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Integr. Biol. (Camb)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glutathione oxidation as a trigger of mitochondrial depolarization and oscillation in intact hearts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Slodzinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>O'rourke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Cell. Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="650" to="660" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Myocardial substrate metabolism in the normal and failing heart</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Stanley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Recchia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lopaschuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiol. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1093" to="1129" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GSH or palmitate preserves mitochondrial energetic/redox balance, preventing mechanical dysfunction in metabolically challenged myocytes/hearts from type 2 diabetic mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tocchetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Caceres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabetes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3094" to="3105" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wavelet analysis reveals heterogeneous time-dependent oscillations of individual mitochondria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kurz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Armoundas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Physiol. Heart Circ. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">299</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="H1736" to="H1740" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synchronization of Kuramoto oscillators in random complex networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">387</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1669" to="1674" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Collective synchronization in populations of globally coupled phase oscillators with drifting frequencies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rougemont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Naef</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. E Stat. Nonlin. Soft Matter Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11104</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamical signatures of cellular fluctuations and oscillator stability in peripheral circadian clocks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rougemont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Naef</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">93</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The fundamental organization of cardiac mitochondria as a network of coupled oscillators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cortassa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>O'rourke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4317" to="4327" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling a synthetic multicellular clock: repressilators coupled by quorum sensing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Garcia-Ojalvo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Elowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Strogatz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10955" to="10960" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An Introduction to Stochastic Processes in Physics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lemons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<publisher>The Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Baltimore, MD</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Resilient circadian oscillator revealed in individual cyanobacteria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Mihalcescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hsing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Leibler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">430</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="85" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophysical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1922" to="1933" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transforms associated to square integrable group representations. I. General results</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Grossmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Morlet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Paul</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Phys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2473" to="2479" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A mitochondrial oscillator dependent on reactive oxygen species</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cortassa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>O'rourke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2060" to="2073" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The energy substrate switch during development of heart failure: gene regulatory mechanisms (Review)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Sack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Mol. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="24" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Substrate utilization by the failing human heart by direct quantification using arterio-venous blood sampling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Funada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Betts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Karpe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e7533</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linking gene expression to function: metabolic flexibility in the normal and diseased heart</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Taegtmeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Golfman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Van Arsdall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. NY Acad. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1015</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="202" to="213" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrating mitochondrial energetics, redox and ROS metabolic networks: a two-compartment model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kembro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cortassa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="332" to="343" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The scale-free dynamics of eukaryotic cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Roussel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e3624</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Is There a Mitochondrial Clock</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cortassa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>O'rourke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From Kuramoto to Crawford: exploring the onset of synchronization in population of coupled oscillators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Strogatz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. D</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">143</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Emerging Science of Spontaneous Order</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Strogatz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Frequency enhancement in coupled noisy excitable elements</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Lai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">254102</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How mitochondria produce reactive oxygen species</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">417</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Redox signaling in cardiac physiology and pathology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Burgoyne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mongue-Din</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circ. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1091" to="1106" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increased myocardial NADPH oxidase activity in human heart failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Heymes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Bendall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Coll. Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2164" to="2171" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Restoring redox balance enhances contractility in heart trabeculae from type 2 diabetic rats exposed to high glucose</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bhatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cortassa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Physiol. Heart Circ. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">308</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="H291" to="H302" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Energy metabolism in heart failure</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ventura-Clapier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Garnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Veksler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">555</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanism of force inhibition by 2,3-butanedione monoxime in rat cardiac muscle: roles of [Ca 2þ ] i and cross-bridge kinetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Backx</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Marban</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">476</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="487" to="500" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An excitable gene regulatory circuit induces transient cellular differentiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Su ¨el</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Garcia-Ojalvo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">,</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Elowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">440</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="545" to="550" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kuramoto model of coupled oscillators with positive and negative coupling parameters: an example of conformist and contrarian oscillators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Strogatz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">54102</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Chemical Oscillations, Waves, and Turbulence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kuramoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Berlin, Germany</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Near-optimal parameters for Tikhonov and other regularization methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>O'leary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM J. Sci. Comput</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1161" to="1171" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determination of an optimal regularization factor in system identification with Tikhonov regularization for linear elastic continua</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Numer. Methods Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1211" to="1230" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imaging superoxide flash and metabolism-coupled mitochondrial permeability transition in living animals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1295" to="1304" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
