<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">LRP2 Acts as SHH Clearance Receptor to Protect the Retinal Margin from Mitogenic Stimuli</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-10-01">October 1, 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Annabel</forename><surname>Christ</surname></persName>
							<email>annabel.christ@mdc-berlin.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Max-Delbrueck-Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anna</forename><surname>Christa</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Max-Delbrueck-Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>, ...,</roleName><forename type="first">Julia</forename><surname>Klippert</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Max-Delbrueck-Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Valerie</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Toronto Western Research Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Health Network</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>M5T 2S8</postCode>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Annette</forename><surname>Hammes</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Max-Delbrueck-Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Willnow</surname></persName>
							<email>willnow@mdc-berlin.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Max-Delbrueck-Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Corinna</forename><surname>Eule</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Small Animal Clinic</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Free University Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>14163</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sebastian</forename><surname>Bachmann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Vegetative Anatomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´University Medicine Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">LRP2 Acts as SHH Clearance Receptor to Protect the Retinal Margin from Mitogenic Stimuli</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-10-01">October 1, 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">95D5122EED87BEA40CFD5E01DABBB3E8</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.devcel.2015.09.001</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: November 13, 2014 Revised: August 21, 2015 Accepted: September 7, 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:50+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Highlights d LRP2 modulates the SHH pathway in a context-dependent manner d LRP2 clears and degrades SHH ligand from the murine retinal margin d LRP2 activity keeps the ciliary marginal zone in a quiescent state d Margin excess proliferation may underlie buphthalmos in LRP2-deficient patients</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>In Brief <ref type="bibr">Christ et al.</ref> show that LRP2 mediates endocytic clearance of SHH in the murine retinal margin rather than acting as an auxiliary receptor.</s><s>This context-specific function protects retinal progenitor cells from mitogenic stimuli and keeps them quiescent.</s><s>Loss of LRP2 function leads to ectopic proliferation in the progenitor niche.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p><s>The low-density lipoprotein receptor-related protein (LRP) 2 is a member of the LDL receptor gene family, a group of structurally related cell surface receptors with important roles in embryonic development (reviewed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Willnow et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>Earlier, we uncovered the function of LRP2 as an auxiliary sonic hedgehog (SHH) receptor required for mammalian forebrain formation <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Christ et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>At neurulation, LRP2 is expressed in neuroepithelial cells where it forms a complex with Patched (PTCH) 1 enabling SHH binding and signal reception in the rostral diencephalon ventral midline (RDVM), the major forebrain organizer region.</s><s>Loss of LRP2 activity in mouse models results in the inability of SHH to induce its target field in the ventral midline, and, consequently, in midline formation defects and in holoprosencephaly <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Christ et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>Holoprosencephalic features are also seen in patients with Donnai-Barrow syndrome, an auto-somal recessive disorder caused by LRP2 defects, documenting the conservation of receptor function across species <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Kantarci et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Rosenfeld et al., 2010)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>To explore the significance of LRP2 for SHH activity in paradigms other than forebrain patterning, we focused on retina development, a process dependent on SHH signals <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Neumann and Nuesslein-Volhard, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Wang et al., 2002)</ref>.</s><s>Our choice was guided by large eye phenotypes seen in LRP2-deficient humans <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Pober et al., 2009)</ref> and mouse and zebrafish models <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Gajera et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Veth et al., 2011</ref>).</s><s>Yet, the mechanism of LRP2 action during eye development and whether it functions as SHH binding protein in this context remained unclear.</s></p><p><s>Here, we show that LRP2 is expressed in the peripheral margin of the murine embryonic retina where it modulates SHH signaling during retinal differentiation.</s><s>However, in contrast to the situation in the RDVM, in the retinal margin, LRP2 acts as an inhibitory receptor that mediates cellular clearance of SHH, protecting the retinal margin from detrimental mitogenic stimuli by this morphogen.</s><s>Absence of LRP2 in gene targeted mice results in ectopic induction of SHH signaling and aberrant expansion of the progenitor cell pool in the margin of the retina and in hyperplasia of peripheral retina tissue.</s><s>These studies identified a clearance function of LRP2 as a mechanism to control SHH signaling in vivo and suggest excessive proliferation of the retinal margin as cause of the large eye phenotype in LRP2-deficient patients and mouse models.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hereditary Buphthalmos in LRP2-Deficient Mice</head><p><s>We explored a role for LRP2 in the functional integrity of the mammalian eye, a process disturbed by receptor deficiency in humans and mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Gajera et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Pober et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Storm et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>We carried out our analyses using two different Lrp2 null alleles that disrupt LRP2 synthesis in mice.</s><s>Analyses of embryonic stages were performed in mice with targeted Lrp2 gene disruption (Lrp2 À/À ) on a C57BL/6N background <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Spoelgen et al., 2005)</ref>.</s><s>For analysis of postnatal and adult stages, Lrp2 +/À animals were crossed with the ENU line 267 that carries a premature stop codon in the sequence encoding the extracellular domain of LRP2 (Lrp2 267/+ ) <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Zarbalis et al., 2004)</ref>.</s><s>Compound heterozygous mice (Lrp2 267/À ) exhibit a higher rate of perinatal survival compared to Lrp2 À/À animals due to the (FVB/NJ 3 C57BL/6J) background of line 267 <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Gajera et al., 2010)</ref>.</s><s>For both alleles, LRP2-deficient animals (Lrp2 À/À or Lrp2 267/À ) were compared to their respective heterozygous or wild-type littermates (jointly referred to as controls).</s></p><p><s>As reported previously, adult LRP2-deficient mice are characterized by craniofacial malformations, including a shortened snout and an open frontal fontanel, indicative of mild holoprosencephaly (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A-1D</ref>).</s><s>However, adult Lrp2 mutant mice also exhibit enlarged and exophthalmic eyes (buphthalmos) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1E</ref>), a defect not typically seen in holoprosencephalic syndrome.</s><s>Enlarged globes are already apparent at postnatal day (P) 10 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1F</ref>), with a 17% increase in axial length (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1G</ref>).</s><s>Histological analyses (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1H</ref>) confirmed enlargement of Lrp2 267/À adult (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1H, b</ref>) and P10 eyes (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1H, d</ref>) compared to controls (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1H, a and c</ref>).</s><s>In both age groups, mutant eyes showed thinning of the retina, but with normal stratification (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1H, e-h</ref>).</s><s>In adults, the retina pathology was advanced with glaucomatous changes that included cell loss in the retinal ganglion cell layer (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1A and S1B</ref>) and disorganization of the nerve fiber layer in the area of the optic cup (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1D</ref>).</s><s>An additional morphological abnormality in adult and P10 mutant eyes was the hyperplasia of the non-pigmented epithelium of the ciliary body (CB) <ref type="bibr">(Figures 1H,</ref><ref type="bibr">j and l)</ref>.</s><s>This tissue is the main expression site of LRP2 in the postnatal mouse eye <ref type="bibr">(Figures 1H,</ref><ref type="bibr">m and o)</ref>.</s><s>In neonatal mutants, the eye size and anatomy of the retina was normal as shown by histology (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1I</ref>) and by immunodetection of photoreceptor cells and retinal ganglion cells (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1E</ref>).</s><s>Still, an increase in CB mass was apparent when compared to control eyes (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1, e and f</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LRP2 Deficiency Causes Ectopic Induction of SHH Signals in the Retinal Margin</head><p><s>Because CB hyperplasia was seen at early postnatal stages in LRP2-deficient mice, we suspected a developmental defect as cause of this phenotype.</s><s>Thus, we characterized the expression of LRP2 in wild-type embryos.</s><s>Around E10.5, invagination of the neuroepithelium in the optic pits forms the bi-layered optic cup (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2A</ref>).</s><s>Expression of LRP2 on the apical surface of the neuroepithelium at E10.5 is retained during optic cup invagination, resulting in receptor localization to the inner layer of the optic cup epithelium (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2B</ref>).</s><s>Initially present throughout the entire optic cup epithelium at E12.5, LRP2 expression becomes restricted to the peripheral margin as retina differentiation proceeds.</s><s>At E16.5, LRP2 is largely confined to the ciliary marginal zone (CMZ), which will give rise to the CB and iris in the postnatal eye (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2B and S2C</ref>).</s><s>In the CMZ, LRP2 is positioned at the apical surface of non-pigmented ciliary epithelial cells (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2B-S2D</ref>).</s></p><p><s>In the mammalian eye, SHH is produced by retinal ganglion cells.</s><s>It provides inductive signals to retinal progenitor cells (RPC), resulting in patterning of the neural retina in a central to peripheral direction <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Neumann and Nuesslein-Volhard, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Wang et al., 2002)</ref>.</s><s>SHH activity is absent from the CMZ that, in turn, receives signals from WNT ligands and bone morphogenetic proteins (BMP) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Cho and Cepko, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Zhao et al., 2002)</ref>.</s><s>To test whether loss of LRP2 impairs SHH-dependent patterning of the neural retina, we analyzed markers of retinal differentiation.</s><s>The histological appearance of the neural retina was comparable in control and Lrp2 À/À eyes at E16.5 (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2A and 2B</ref>).</s><s>Also, expression of Shh in the retinal ganglion cell layer (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2C-2F</ref>) and of the neurogenic marker Math5 (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2G-2J</ref>) was normal.</s><s>Overall correct patterning of the mutant neural retina was confirmed by immunodetection of Zic2 and Isl2, markers of postmitotic retinal cell types (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2K-2P</ref>).</s><s>However, a subtle, but consistent, alteration was seen for the retinal ganglion cell marker Brn-3b.</s><s>Expression of this marker was pronounced in the central retina in both genotypes, but seemed to extend into more distal regions of the retina in mutants (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2U and 2V</ref>) compared to controls (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2R and 2S</ref>).</s><s>Although the neurogenic marker Math5 was not induced in the mutant CMZ, the findings on Brn-3b suggested that this niche might adopt a partial neurogenic character when LRP2 activity is lost.</s><s>To further substantiate changes in Brn-3b expression, we dissected the neural retina and CMZ from E16.5 eyes for quantitative (q) RT-PCR.</s><s>Transcripts of Brn-3b and Lrp2 were prominent in the neural retina and CMZ, respectively, documenting proper tissue dissection (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2E</ref>).</s><s>In line with the observations made by immunodetection, transcript levels of Brn-3b, but not of Zic2 and Isl2, were increased in the LRP2-deficient CMZ (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2E</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Our data suggested a distal shift of the boundary between the central retina and CMZ in LRP2-deficient eyes.</s><s>A role for LRP2 in specification of the retinal margin was confirmed by investigating morphogen pathways in the CMZ by in situ hybridizations (ISH).</s><s>At E16.5, CMZ markers Bmp4, Msx1, and Otx1 were expressed at the correct position in mutant eyes, indicating proper establishment of the CMZ at the retinal periphery (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3A</ref>).</s><s>However, the SHH targets Hes1 and Gli1, which were not expressed in the CMZ of control eyes (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3B, b</ref>, f, and j), were ectopically induced in the Lrp2 À/À CMZ (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3B, d, h, and l</ref>).</s><s>Also, Ptch1 levels were increased (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3C</ref>).</s><s>Significantly elevated transcript levels for Gli1 and Ptch1 in the mutant CMZ, but not in the neural retina, were confirmed by qPCR (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3D</ref>).</s><s>Transcript levels of Shh were not changed in the neural retina or CMZ of the mutants (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3D</ref>), in line with findings obtained by ISH in Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2E and 2F</ref> above.</s></p><p><s>Aberrant induction of the SHH pathway in the mutant CMZ was confirmed by crossing the Lrp2 null allele with the Gli1_LacZ reporter line <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Bai et al., 2002)</ref>.</s><s>In E16.5 control eyes, GLI1-dependent lacZ activity was restricted to the neural retina, but absent from the CMZ (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3E, a and b</ref>).</s><s>In contrast, in Lrp2 À/À eyes, lacZ activity was ectopically induced in the CMZ (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3E, c and d</ref>).</s><s>Induction of the SHH pathway in the Lrp2 À/À CMZ coincided with loss of WNT activity in this tissue as shown by crossing the Lrp2 null allele with the Tcf/Lef_LacZ reporter strain <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Mohamed et al., 2004)</ref>.</s><s>As seen in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3E</ref>, expression (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3E, i-j</ref>) and activity (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3E, e and f</ref>) of lacZ was seen in the CMZ, but not in the neural retina, of E16.5 control mice.</s><s>In contrast, Tcf/Lef-dependent expression (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3E,  k and l</ref>) and activity (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3E, g and h</ref>) of lacZ was significantly reduced in the Lrp2 À/À CMZ.</s><s>Loss of WNT activity in the E16.5 mutant eye was not due to earlier defects, as components of the WNT pathway, such as Wnt7b and G protein coupled receptor 177, were normally expressed in the mutant eye at E10.5-11.5 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S3A</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Eye development not only depends on SHH, but also on the related morphogen indian hedgehog (IHH) produced by the choroid adjacent to the RPE <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Dakubo et al., 2008)</ref>.</s><s>Expression of Ihh in the choroid was unchanged in Lrp2 À/À mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S3B</ref>).</s><s>Also expression of Pitx2, an IHH target in the choroid  was not altered (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S3B</ref>), suggesting changes in the activity of SHH (not of IHH) as the cause for induction of the hedgehog pathway in the LRP2-deficient CMZ.</s></p><p><s>BOC, CDON, and GAS1 are also expressed in the CMZ, implicating several SHH binding proteins in formation of the retinal margin.</s><s>Yet, the expression patterns for Boc, Cdon, and Gas1 (C-J) In situ hybridization on sections of E16.5 mouse eyes indicates expression of Shh (arrowheads) and Math5 in the neural retina, but absence from the CMZ (encircled) of control and Lrp2 À/À embryos.</s><s>(K-P) Immunodetection of zinc finger protein 2 (Zic2; red) and insulin-related protein 2 (Isl2; green) in the neural retina of control and Lrp2 À/À E16.5 mouse embryos.</s><s>The coexpression of both proteins in the ventrotemporal crescent of the retina is depicted in (M) and (P) (yellow signal).</s><s>There is no expression seen in the CMZ (arrowheads in M and P).</s><s>(Q-V) Immunodetection of  shows similar patterns in the neural retina of control (Q) and Lrp2 À/À (T) E16.5 mouse embryos.</s><s>However, in the mutants, Brn-3b signals extend further into the distal margin of the retina as shown for the dorsal (U) and ventral (V) tip.</s><s>The brackets mark the distal margin free of Brn-3b signals in control and LRP2-deficient eyes.</s><s>The scale bars represent 100 mm.</s><s>See also Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2</ref>.</s></p><p><s>were indistinguishable comparing LRP2deficient and control E16.5 eyes by ISH (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S3C</ref>) and qPCR (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S3D</ref>), excluding defects in expression of these proteins in the pathology of Lrp2 À/À eyes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Expansion of the RPC Pool in the LRP2-Deficient Retinal Margin</head><p><s>In the rodent retina, SHH acts as a potent mitogen that promotes RPC proliferation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Jensen and Wallace, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Levine et al., 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Wang et al., 2002)</ref>.</s><s>The absence of Hh activity from the CMZ contributes to the quiescence of RPC in this niche in the mammalian eye <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Moshiri and Reh, 2004)</ref>.</s><s>In line with this assumption, aberrant spread of SHH activity into the CMZ of the Lrp2 À/À retina resulted in the expansion of the RPC pool in the retinal margin as documented by detection of progenitor cell markers SOX2 and VSX2 by immunohistology and qPCR.</s><s>In wild-types, the expression domains for both progenitor cell markers sharply decreased distal to the boundary between the neural retina and CMZ (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4A</ref>).</s><s>In mutants, the signals were prominently induced in the CMZ (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4A</ref>).</s><s>Elevated levels of SOX2 and VSX2 in the CMZ (but not in the neural retina) were confirmed by quantification of immunosignals (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4B</ref>) and by qPCR (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4C</ref>).</s></p><p><s>In addition to increased RPC numbers, the mutant CMZ also showed enhanced proliferative capacity as verified by the quantification of cells in S phase using in utero labeling with BrdU (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4D and 4E</ref>), immunodetection of mitotic marker phosphohistone H3 (PH3) (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4D and 4F</ref>), or cell-cycle marker Ki67 (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4D and 4G</ref>).</s><s>In all assays, the numbers of proliferating cells were 3-fold higher in the LRP2-deficient compared to the control CMZ.</s><s>The number of mitotic cells in the neural retina was unchanged (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S4A and S4B</ref>).</s><s>Hyperproliferation of the mutant CMZ continued into the postnatal period as shown by BrdU labeling in P0.5 mice (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S4C and S4D</ref>).</s><s>BrdU+ cells costained for SOX2, suggesting proliferation of RPCs as a cause of the enhanced mitotic activity in the Lrp2 À/À CMZ (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S4E</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LRP2 Deficiency Enhances SHH-Dependent Cell Proliferation in the CMZ</head><p><s>We applied a retinal explant model to dissect the pathways underlying the enhanced mitogenic potential of the LRP2-deficient CMZ at E16.5 (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S5A and S5B</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Liu et al., 2007)</ref>.</s><s>Retinal explants were cultured for up to 48 hr, retaining their identity as judged by expression of LRP2 and Msx1 in the CMZ, and of Brn-3b in the neural retina (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S5C</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Initially, we investigated whether the LRP2-deficient CMZ in retinal explants showed higher proliferative capacity as seen in vivo.</s><s>Applying BrdU labeling in explants cultured for 24 hr, we confirmed an increase in BrdU+ cells in the mutant compared to the control CMZ (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5A and 5B</ref>).</s><s>Enhanced proliferation in the mutant CMZ was dependent on SMO activity, as application of the inhibitor KAAD-cyclopamine decreased the number of BrdU+ cells in mutants to wild-type levels (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5B</ref>).</s><s>Impaired proliferative response in the control CMZ was not due to a lack of SHH pathway components, as application of Smoothened agonist (SAG) stimulated proliferation to similar levels in control and mutant tissues (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5C</ref>).</s><s>Application of SAG also caused loss of WNT signals in the CMZ of control explants from Tcf/Lef_ LacZ mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5D</ref>), arguing that the reduction of WNT activity in the Lrp2 À/À CMZ is a consequence of ectopic SHH activation.</s></p><p><s>To exclude loss of WNT activity as the primary cause of hyperproliferation in the Lrp2 mutant CMZ, we treated wild-type retinal explants from the Tcf/Lef_LacZ line with the WNT inhibitor JW55 <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Waaler et al., 2012)</ref> (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5E</ref>).</s><s>Application of JW55 caused loss of WNT activity in the CMZ (as shown by lacZ staining; Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5E, c</ref>), but failed to induce cell proliferation above levels in buffer-treated explants (shown by BrdU incorporation; Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5E,  d</ref>).</s><s>However, induction of cell proliferation was achieved in JW55-treated explants by coapplication of SAG (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5E, f</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LRP2 Mediates Clearance of SHH to Antagonize Morphogen Activity</head><p><s>Having established an explant model that faithfully recapitulates features of the LRP2-deficient CMZ in vivo, we tested the The expression domains for Bmp4 (a-d), Msx1 (e-h), and Otx1 (i-l) are identical in control and Lrp2 À/À E16.5 embryos.</s><s>(B) ISH on E16.5 mouse eyes using probes for targets of SHH signaling.</s><s>The Lrp2 À/À mouse eyes exhibit an aberrant induction of Hes1 (as shown for two individuals; arrowheads in d and h) and of Gli1 (arrowheads in l) as compared to controls (b, f, and i).</s><s>The ectopic induction was seen in three out of five (Hes1) and in four out of five (Gli1) embryos analyzed.</s><s>(C) ISH indicates elevated levels of Ptch1 in the CMZ (encircled) of mutant compared to control E16.5 eyes.</s><s>(D) qRT-PCR for Gli1, Ptch1, and Shh transcripts in the CMZ and neural retina of mice.</s><s>The levels of transcripts are given relative to the control retina (set to 1).</s><s>The levels for Ptch1 and Gli1 are significantly increased in the CMZ, but not in the neural retina of mutant embryos (n = 7-12 animals per group; Student's t test).</s><s>The data are depicted as fold changes ± error.</s><s>(E) Staining for lacZ activity (arrowheads) on sections of E16.5 mouse eyes from Gli1_LacZ (a-d) and Tcf/Lef_LacZ (e-h) reporter lines.</s><s>The mice express (control) or lack LRP2 (Lrp2 À/À ).</s><s>In the LRP2-deficient CMZ, the activity of the GLI1dependent LacZ reporter is aberrantly induced (d) as compared to the control tissue (b) (seen in nine out of 16 embryos).</s><s>The activity of the Tcf/Lef-dependent lacZ reporter gene is diminished in the mutant (h) compared to the control (f) CMZ (in seven out of nine embryos).</s><s>The reduction of Tcf/Lef-dependent lacZ expression in Lrp2 À/À (l) compared to the control CMZ (j) was confirmed by ISH for lacZ (i-l).</s><s>The arrowheads highlight the CMZ.</s><s>The scale bars represent 100 mm.</s><s>See also Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S3</ref>.</s><s>expression of SHH pathway components in this tissue in the presence and absence of LRP2.</s><s>Primary cilia were abundantly present in the neural retina and, to a lesser extent, in the CMZ as shown by staining for the ciliary marker Arl13b (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6A</ref>).</s><s>In the control CMZ, LRP2 localized to the base of the primary cilium (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6A</ref>, inset in d).</s><s>No difference in the number of Arl13b+ cilia in the CMZ was seen comparing genotypes (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6C</ref>).</s><s>However, a striking difference was noted when cilia were costained for GLI2 and SMO as an indicator of pathway activation (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6B</ref>).</s><s>In controls, SMO signals were observed in GLI2+ primary cilia in the neural retina (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6B</ref>, a), but were absent from cilia in the CMZ (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6B, b</ref>).</s><s>In contrast, robust ciliary staining for SMO was seen in the mutant CMZ (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6B, d</ref>).</s><s>An approximate 3-fold increase in SMO+ cilia in the CMZ was confirmed by quantification (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6C</ref>), documenting aberrant activation of the SHH pathway in the LRP2-deficient retinal margin.</s><s>The extent of SHH pathway activation matched well with a similar 3-fold increase in mitogenic stimuli received by the Lrp2-deficient CMZ (as shown by quantification of BrdU+, Ki67+, and PH3+ cells; Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4D-4G</ref>).</s><s>As well as in retinal explants, this increase in SMO+ primary cilia in the mutant CMZ was also confirmed on histological sections of the E16.5 mouse eye (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6A and S6B</ref>).</s><s>Aberrant pathway activation in the CMZ coincided with a clear change in the distribution of endogenous SHH ligand in the mutant eye as shown by western blot analysis of dissected tissues.</s><s>Although the levels of SHH protein were slightly lower in the neural retina, they were almost 2-fold increased in the CMZ of Lrp2 À/À compared to control eyes (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6D</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To explore the reason for accumulation of endogenous SHH in the mutant CMZ, we investigated the fate of the morphogen in the retina.</s><s>When we incubated control explants with a recombinant fusion protein of SHH-N and GST, intracellular accumulation of the ligand was detected in the CMZ, but not in the neural retina (that does not express LRP2) (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6E, a</ref> and b and e and f).</s><s>Uptake was mediated by LRP2 as no uptake of GST-SHH-N was seen in the LRP2-deficient CMZ (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6E, c and d</ref>).</s><s>No internalization was observed for GST only (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6C</ref>).</s><s>When costained for endocytic markers, LRP2 localized to clathrin-coated pits (AP2), early endosomes (Rab4), and recycling endosomes (Rab11), but not to lysosomes (Lamp1) in the control CMZ (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6F</ref>, upper).</s><s>This pattern is consistent with the recycling fate of an endocytic receptor.</s><s>In contrast, internalized GST-SHH-N localized to early endosomes (Rab4) and lysosomes (Lamp1 and cathepsin B), but not to recycling endosomes (Rab11) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6F</ref>, lower).</s><s>This subcellular distribution of GST-SHH-N was surprising because in the RDVM, LRP2 delivers SHH to the Rab11+ recycling compartment, but not to lysosomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Christ et al., 2012)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>To substantiate lysosomal targeting of SHH in the CMZ, we performed uptake assays in control explants.</s><s>First, we tested intracellular localization of GST-SHH-N in explants treated with chloroquine, an inhibitor of lysosomal degradation that causes swelling of the lysosomes.</s><s>Application of chloroquine resulted in accumulation of large vesicles in the CMZ that costained for LRP2 and GST-SHH-N.</s><s>This pattern was distinctly different from the apical vesicular signals seen for LRP2 and GST-SHH-N in untreated tissue (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6D</ref>).</s><s>Second, we coincubated control explants with GST-SHH-N and lactoglobulin, a ligand delivered to lysosomes.</s><s>Both proteins colocalized in intracellular vesicles in the control CMZ (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6E</ref>).</s><s>To confirm lysosomal sorting, we purified lysosomes from control explants incubated with GST-SHH-N for 4 hr.</s><s>As shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6F</ref>, GST-SHH-N present in the postnuclear supernatant efficiently copurified with Lamp1.</s></p><p><s>Conceivably, LRP2-mediated lysosomal catabolism of SHH antagonizes morphogen activity in target cells.</s><s>This hypothesis was tested by luciferase reporter assay.</s><s>To do so, conditioned media from HEK293 cells secreting SHH-Np were incubated at 37 C for 14-16 hr in empty 24-well plates or in 24-well plates containing a monolayer of rat choriocarcinoma (BN16) cells.</s><s>BN16 cells express LRP2 and are commonly used to test the endocytic activity of this receptor.</s><s>Western blot analysis confirmed depletion of SHH-Np from the supernatant of BN16 cells compared to the empty well control (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6G</ref>; SHH-Np).</s><s>Clearance of SHH-Np from the supernatant was also seen when non-immune serum was added to the conditioned medium (SHH-Np + non-IgG), but was blocked when anti-LRP2 antiserum was applied (SHH-Np + a-LRP2).</s><s>Finally, clearance was inhibited by application of chloroquine, indicating lysosomal involvement in SHH-Np depletion (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6H</ref>).</s><s>When the remaining SHH activity in the media was scored by GLI-dependent firefly luciferase reporter assay in Shh Light II cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Taipale et al., 2000)</ref>, the relative firefly luciferase activity was reduced in medium incubated with BN16 cells compared to empty well incubations.</s><s>This effect was seen for medium containing SHH-Np alone or SHH-Np with non-immune IgG (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6I</ref>).</s><s>However, no difference in SHH activity in Shh Light II cells comparing The explants in (C) were incubated in 800 nM SAG or buffer (n = 5-12 per genotype) (not significant: n.s.; **p &lt; 0.01; ***p &lt; 0.001; and two-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni post test).</s><s>The values are mean ± SD. (D) Loss of lacZ activity in the CMZ (arrowheads) of control explants of the Tcf/Lef-lacZ line treated for 36-48 hr with 800 nM SAG as compared to buffertreated tissues (seen in three out of six explants analyzed).</s><s>(E) Wild-type retinal explants of the Tcf/Lef-lacZ line were treated for 24 hr with buffer (a and b), 5 mM JW55 (c and d), or 5 mM JW55 and 800 nM SAG (e and f).</s><s>The suppression of WNT signaling in JW55-treated explants (reduced lacZ signal in c) does not increase cell proliferation in the CMZ (encircled) above levels in the buffer control as shown by BrdU staining (b and d; seen in eight out of eight explants).</s><s>However, induction of proliferation in the CMZ is seen in JW55-treated explants that received SAG (f; seen in three out of three explants analyzed) (lens: le).</s><s>The scale bar represents 75 mm.</s><s>See also Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S5</ref>.</s></p><p><s>BN16-and empty-well incubations was seen in the presence of anti-LRP2 antiserum (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6I</ref>).</s></p><p><s>LRP2 Increases the Threshold for SHH Signals to Suppress Mitogenic Stimuli in the CMZ Data in Figures 6 and S6 provided cumulative evidence that LRP2 facilitates clearance of SHH by cells in the CMZ, thereby antagonizing morphogen activity in the retinal margin.</s><s>To put this concept to the test, we compared the response of control and LRP2-deficient CMZ explants to SHH-Np (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">S7A</ref>).</s><s>Incorporation of BrdU served as a measure of the mitogenic potential of SHH in these tissues (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">S7B</ref>).</s><s>To do so, we used 48 hr incubations of retinal explants contrary to the analyses of endogenous SHH activity in experiments after 24 hr (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5A-5C</ref>).</s><s>In explants treated with blank medium for 48 hr, the proliferative capacity was low, reaching comparable levels in control and mutant CMZ.</s><s>This residual proliferation was not inhibited by KAAD-cyclopamine (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7C</ref>; condition 0 mg/ml SHH-Np).</s><s>This finding is in line with earlier observations that loss of retinal ganglion cells depletes the source for SHH from retinal explants incubated for an extended period of time <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Wang et al., 2002)</ref>.</s><s>Still after 48 hr, explants of both genotypes responded to exogenous SHH-Np from conditioned media by induction of proliferation in the CMZ as shown by BrdU incorporation.</s><s>Proliferation was blocked by .</s><s>Foremost, these data confirmed the ability of both genotypes to activate the ligand-dependent SHH pathway in the CMZ.</s><s>(C) Quantification of primary cilia positive for Arl13b and SMO in control and Lrp2 À/À CMZ explants (as exemplified in A and B).</s><s>The cilia per histological section was determined in n = 11-13 animals.</s><s>(not significant: n.s.; ***p &lt; 0.001; and Mann-Whitney U test).</s><s>The values are mean ± SD. (D) Levels of endogenous SHH are slightly decreased in the neural retina, but increased in the CMZ of Lrp2 À/À compared to control eyes as documented by western blotting of dissected tissues (exemplified in the inset) and by densitometric scanning of replicate blots (n = 4-7 pools per genotype; eight eyes per pool for the CMZ, two to five eyes per pool for the neural retina).</s><s>The SHH levels in the mutant tissues were corrected for the tubulin loading control and are given as % signal of the respective control pool (set to 100%; column statistics and one sample t test).</s><s>(E) Immunodetection of LRP2 (green) and SHH (red) in control and Lrp2 À/À retinal explants treated with GST-SHH-N.</s><s>The overviews (a, c, e, and g) as well as higher magnifications (b, d, f, and h) of the neural retina and CMZ are shown.</s><s>In controls, robust uptake of GST-SHH-N is seen in the CMZ (a and b), but not in the neural retina (e and f).</s><s>No uptake of GST-SHH-N into the CMZ (c and d) or the neural retina (g and h) is seen in the Lrp2 À/À explants.</s><s>(F) Control explants were incubated with 5 mg/ml GST-SHH-N and subsequently stained for LRP2 (upper) or GST-SHH (lower) and the indicated markers.</s><s>The LRP2 (green) localizes with markers (red) of clathrin-coated pits (AP2), early (Rab4), and recycling (Rab11) endosomes, but not lysosomes (Lamp1).</s><s>In contrast, internalized GST-SHH-N (red) colocalizes with markers (green) of early endosomes (Rab4) and lysosomes (Lamp1 or cathepsin B [CatB]), but not with recycling endosomal marker Rab11.</s><s>The scale bars represent 5 mm (A, c; B, a) and 25 mm.</s><s>See also Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6</ref>.</s></p><p><s>An intriguing difference between control and Lrp2 À/À explants was noted when their response to defined concentrations of exogenous SHH-Np was scored.</s><s>At 0.05 mg/ml of SHH-Np, both genotypes reacted with an increase in BrdU+ cells in the CMZ as compared to blank medium or KAAD-cyclopamine treated tissues, but this increase was significantly higher in Lrp2 À/À as compared to control explants (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7C</ref>).</s><s>This difference was not seen using 4-fold higher concentrations of SHH-Np, when both genotypes responded equally (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7C</ref>; 0.2 mg/ml).</s><s>To provide a quantitative description of the sensitivity to SHH, we scored the response of control and mutant explants to a range of SHH concentrations (determined by semiquantitative western blotting; Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">S7A</ref>).</s><s>When the dose-response curves were determined, the effective concentration of SHH-Np to elicit a half-maximal proliferative response (EC 50 ) was 0.06 mg/ml in controls, but 0.02 mg/ml in the Lrp2 null CMZ (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7D</ref>; p = 0.018).</s><s>Thus, LRP2 activity in the control CMZ increased the threshold required to elicit a mitogenic response.</s></p><p><s>In the RDVM, LRP2-mediated internalization of SHH results in concurrent internalization of PTCH1, a prerequisite for pathway activation <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Christ et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>Accordingly, we explored the cellular fate of PTCH1 in the CMZ in the presence or absence of SHH ligand.</s><s>The specificity of the PTCH1 antiserum was confirmed on E16.5 eyes from mice with conditional inactivation of Ptch1 in the retina (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">S7C</ref>).</s><s>In the CMZ, PTCH1 was present at the apical cell surface and in intracellular vesicles (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7E, a and b</ref>).</s><s>Treatment of explants with SAG results in enrichment of PTCH1 in GLI2+ cilia, an activity of PTCH1 documented in other cell types before <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Rohatgi et al., 2007)</ref>  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">(Figures 7E, c  and d</ref>).</s><s>No discernable difference in PTCH1 localization was observed comparing control and LRP2-deficient CMZ.</s><s>Surprisingly, no colocalization of PTCH1 and LRP2 was noted in the control CMZ treated with buffer or SAG (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7E, e and g</ref>).</s><s>Such colocalization of LRP2 and PTCH1 was clearly noticeable in the RDVM (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7E</ref>, inset in e) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Christ et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>In line with the lack of colocalization, LRP2-dependent internalization of GST-SHH-N in the control CMZ failed to efficiently cointernalize PTCH1 with the ligand (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7F, c</ref>), whereas cointernalization of PTCH1 and GST-SHH-N was obvious in the RDVM (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7F, g</ref>).</s><s>These findings suggested distinct cellular mechanisms in the CMZ and RDVM that distinguish the ability of LRP2 to functionally interact with PTCH1 and to direct SHH to lysosomal versus recycling fates.</s></p><p><s>In conclusion, our data substantiated a role for LRP2 in control of SHH signaling that extends forebrain formation.</s><s>In the retina, the endocytic activity of this receptor limits the distal spread of the SHH activity domain and protects RPC in the CMZ from mitogenic stimuli, a process that otherwise results in hyperplasia of the CB and in hereditary buphthalmos.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>LRP2 Deficiency Causes Ectopic Induction of SHH Activity in the Retinal Margin SHH is essential for several steps of mammalian eye development.</s><s>Initially, SHH secreted from the prechordal plate induces formation of the optic primordia from a single eye field <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Zhao et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>At subsequent stages of eye development, SHH produced locally by retinal ganglion cells assumes an important function in patterning of the neural retina by acting on RPC <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Wang et al., 2005)</ref>.</s><s>In LRP2-deficient mice, formation of the optic pits proceeds normally as judged by the presence of two laterally placed eyes <ref type="bibr">(Figures 1C and 1D)</ref>.</s><s>Proper establishment of bilateral eye structures is likely due to the fact that LRP2 deficiency does not impact production of SHH in the prechordal plate <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Christ et al., 2012)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>While LRP2 deficiency does not impair SHH-dependent patterning of the optic pits, it affects local SHH activity during later stages of retina development.</s><s>The source and the activity domain of SHH in the neural retina are not altered by LRP2 deficiency, as Shh and markers of postmitotic retinal cell types are properly expressed (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>).</s><s>Also, the postnatal retina shows correct stratification (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1H and S1E</ref>).</s><s>However, LRP2 deficiency causes a shift of the peripheral boundary of the SHH activity domain into the distal retinal margin.</s><s>This fact was documented by increased signals for retinal ganglion cell marker <ref type="bibr">2V,</ref><ref type="bibr">and S2E)</ref>, as well as for progenitor cell markers SOX2 and VSX2 (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4A-4C</ref>) in the mutant CMZ.</s><s>Enhanced SHH activity is the likely cause of this phenotype, as increased levels of downstream targets Gli1, Hes1, and Ptch1 (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3B-3D</ref>), and of Gli1-lacZ activity (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3E</ref>) are seen in this tissue.</s><s>As a consequence of increased SHH signal, the RPC pool in the mutant CMZ is expanded and the proliferative capacity of the retinal margin enhanced (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>).</s><s>Expression levels for Zic2 and Isl2, marking ipsilateral and contralateral projecting ganglion cells, respectively, are not significantly altered in the Lrp2 À/À eye (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2E</ref>).</s><s>A decrease in ipsilateral projections had been documented in mice lacking Boc before (Sa ´nchez- <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Arrones et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Thus, LRP2 activity mainly impacts the size of the progenitor cell pool in the CMZ, while differentiation to more specialized retinal cell types may require additional regulatory signals.</s><s>LRP2-dependent expansion of the RPC pool may occur through SHH-induced proliferation of multipotent progenitor cells as suggested by double labeling of cells for BrdU and SOX2 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S4E</ref>).</s><s>Alternatively, CMZ cell types may adopt a partial RPC fate in response to SHH.</s></p><p><s>A function for LRP2 in the retinal margin is supported by its predominant expression in the CMZ (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2</ref>).</s><s>The SHH pathway is the target of receptor (dys)function, as other morphogen pathways are not altered (e.g., Ihh and Bmp4) <ref type="bibr">(Figures 3A and S3B)</ref> or decreased secondarily as shown by downregulation of WNT activity by SAG (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5D</ref>).</s><s>Enhanced RPC proliferation as a consequence of increased Hh signaling is also seen in mice heterozygous for the Ptch1 gene defect <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Moshiri and Reh, 2004)</ref> or in animals lacking Sufu, an inhibitor of the SHH pathway <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Cwinn et al., 2011)</ref>.</s><s>In contrast, a WNT signaling defect in mice lacking b-catenin in the retina causes a decrease, rather than an increase, in the progenitor cell pool <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Liu et al., 2007)</ref>.</s><s>Also, blockade of WNT activity by JW55 in this study failed to induce cell proliferation in the CMZ (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5E</ref>).</s><s>Consistent with the main role of SHH to stimulate proliferation <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Sakagami et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Wang et al., 2005)</ref>, ectopic SHH activity in the Lrp2 À/À CMZ enhances proliferative capacity, impairing the quiescent character of RPCs in the CMZ (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LRP2 Defines the Boundary of the SHH Activity Domain in the Retina</head><p><s>All components of the SHH signaling machinery, including primary cilia, SMO, PTCH1, and GLI2 are present in the wild-type CMZ as documented by ISH, immunohistology, and qPCR.</s><s>Also, the wild-type CMZ avidly reacts to SHH-Np (Figures 7A-7D and S7B) and SAG (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5C</ref>) with proliferative responses equaling that of Lrp2 À/À tissue.</s><s>The fact that SMO is excluded from primary cilia in the control CMZ indicates lack of sufficient SHH signal in the retinal margin of the wild-type eye.</s><s>This hypothesis was confirmed by quantitative description of the response of the CMZ to exogenous SHH-Np.</s><s>In control tissue, the EC 50 is increased 3-fold, but the maximum level of response is unchanged as compared to the Lrp2 À/À CMZ (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7D</ref>).</s><s>This kinetic is representative of a competitive inhibitor (LRP2) present in the control, but absent from the mutant condition.</s></p><p><s>Because LRP2 delivers SHH to lysosomes in CMZ cells (Figures 6F and S6C-S6E) and antagonizes SHH signaling in trans in luciferase reporter assays (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6I</ref>), we propose a model whereby the endocytic activity of this receptor provides a morphogen sink that depletes the ligand from the peripheral margin.</s><s>Most importantly, this model is supported by the accumulation of endogenous SHH protein in the mutant CMZ (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6D</ref>).</s><s>Accumulation of SHH in the CMZ is not caused by increased expression, as levels of SHH in the neural retina or levels of Shh transcripts in the neural retina or CMZ are not increased in the Lrp2 À/À compared to control eyes.</s><s>In nonmammalian systems, the ability of Hh binding proteins to contain the spread and activity of this mophogen has been shown in the wing disc <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Bilioni et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Yan et al., 2010)</ref> and ovaries <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Hartman et al., 2010)</ref> of the fruit fly or in the optic vesicle of zebrafish and chick embryos <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Cardozo et al., 2014)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Loss of Quiescence Results in Hyperproliferation of the Retinal Margin and in Eye Pathology</head><p><s>Aberrant proliferation of the CMZ in Lrp2 mutant mice proceeds into the postnatal period (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S4C and S4D</ref>) and coincides with hyperplasia of the CB in newborn mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1I</ref>).</s><s>The increase in postnatal eye size in Lrp2 À/À animals is most likely caused by hyperproliferation of the embryonic CMZ, as mice with conditional Lrp2 inactivation in the adult lack eye pathology <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Storm et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>High myopia (nearsightedness), a defect caused by increased axial length, is also a consistent feature seen in individuals with Donnai-Barrow syndrome <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Pober et al., 2009)</ref>.</s><s>While intraocular pressure cannot be determined accurately in neonatal mice, glaucomatous changes, such as thinning of the retina and loss of retinal ganglion cells, argue for an increased pressure as the cause of the buphthalmos in Lrp2 null animals.</s><s>This conclusion is supported by the identification of mutations in lrp2 in zebrafish in ENU screens for glaucoma genes <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Veth et al., 2011)</ref>.</s><s>Possibly, quiescence of the mammalian CMZ assures integrity of the CB that produces the vitreous and causes glaucoma when dysfunctional.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Context-Dependent Function of LRP2 in the SHH Pathway</head><p><s>The ability of LRP2 to antagonize SHH signaling in the CMZ is surprising, considering its role as an activator of this pathway in the RDVM <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Christ et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>What may be the molecular concept that determines context-dependent stimulation or repression of the SHH pathway by this receptor?</s><s>Based on analysis of endogenous SHH pathway components, two concurrent mechanisms seem plausible, namely, the cell-type specific control of trafficking of SHH and of PTCH1 by LRP2 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7G</ref>).</s><s>In the RDVM, LRP2 closely colocalizes with PTCH1 on the apical cell surface.</s><s>Binding of SHH to LRP2 results in efficient internalization of ligand and PTCH1, and in subsequent pathway activation.</s><s>SHH internalized by LRP2 is delivered to recycling endosomes, possibly destined for re-secretion to increase local morphogen concentration in the target field <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Christ et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>In the CMZ, SHH internalized by LRP2 awaits a different fate as it is directed to lysosomes, depleting the ligand from the retinal margin.</s><s>Also, LRP2 fails to induce cointernalization of PTCH1 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">7F</ref>), preventing recruitment of SMO into cilia (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6B</ref>).</s><s>A role for LRP2 as SHH clearance receptor is supported by the accumulation of endogenous SHH in the mutant CMZ (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6D</ref>).</s><s>Obviously, binding of SHH to PTCH1 in the mutant CMZ results in cellular uptake of morphogen and receptor as judged from ectopic pathway activation in this tissue.</s><s>However, the low levels and the relatively poor clearance capacity of PTCH1 as compared to the highly efficient endocytic receptor LRP2 likely precludes intracellular accumulation of endogenous SHH or exogenously added GST-SHH-N in the mutant CMZ to levels detectable by immunohistology.</s><s>Also, much of the SHH ligand building up in the mutant CMZ may be dispersed in the intercellular space due to lack of a clearance pathway, further impeding immunodetection.</s></p><p><s>The capability of LRP2 to act in a context-dependent manner is shown by its association with distinct cytosolic adaptors that determine routing of the receptor through cell type specific sorting pathways <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Shah et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Concerning control of LRP2 and PTCH1 interaction, a similar mechanism is operable in the WNT pathway with transmembrane proteins Kremen 1 and 2 blocking the ability of LRP5/6 to functionally interact with the WNT receptor frizzled <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Mao et al., 2002)</ref>.</s><s>Further identification of factors that govern the cell-type specific interaction of LRP2 with SHH and PTCH1 will shed light on an important molecular concept whereby this SHH binding protein assumes functions as activator or inhibitor to fine-tune the target response to SHH.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mouse Models</head><p><s>Mice carrying Lrp2 null alleles due to targeted <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Spoelgen et al., 2005)</ref> or ENUinduced <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Zarbalis et al., 2004)</ref> gene disruption have been described before.</s><s>Where applicable, these lines were crossed with the Gli1_LacZ (JAX; Stock 008211) or the Tcf/Lef_LacZ reporter lines <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Mohamed et al., 2004)</ref>.</s><s>Experiments involving animals were performed according to institutional guidelines following approval by local authorities (X9017/12).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Retinal Explant Cultures</head><p><s>Retinal explants were isolated from E16.5 mouse eyes as published <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Liu et al., 2007)</ref>.</s><s>The explants were cultured for 24-48 hr at 37 C, with 5% CO 2 and 95% humidity.</s><s>Where indicated, the culture medium <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Wang et al., 2005)</ref> was supplemented with 1-5 mM KAAD-cyclopamine (Calbiochem), 800 nM SAG (Alexis Biochemicals), 5 mM tankyrase inhibitor JW55 (Calbiochem), or 0.05-0.20 mg/ml SHH-Np in conditioned medium from HEK293 cells stably secreting SHH-Np (SHHN-293 cells; provided by M. Kato, Stanford School of Medicine).</s><s>For ligand uptake, retinal explants were incubated for 2 hr with 5 mg/ml GST-SHH-N (produced in BL21 bacteria using vector pSh1-2tk) or with 10 mg/ml lactoglobulin (labeled with Alexa-488 using the Protein Labeling Kit; Life Technologies).</s><s>Thereafter, explants were washed and fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) in PBS for 20 min at room temperature and processed for routine cryo-sectioning.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BrdU Labeling In Utero and in Explants</head><p><s>For BrdU incorporation experiments in retinal explants, the tissue was pulsed with 10 mM BrdU (Sigma) for 1 hr.</s><s>To label proliferating cells in the CMZ of E16.5 embryos, BrdU was injected intraperitoneally into pregnant females at 50 mg/kg body mass and the animals sacrificed 1 hr later.</s><s>For quantification of BrdU+ cells, cryo-sections of eyes or explants were subjected to standard immunohistology using rat anti-BrdU antibody (1:100; AbD Serotec), followed by biotin-streptavidin amplification procedure.</s><s>The number of BrdU+ cells in the CMZ of retinal explants was counted on two sections through the medial plane of the lens per retinal explant for a total of 5-12 animals per genotype</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>LRP2 Deficiency Causes Hereditary Buphthalmos</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,62.82,101.59,484.29,546.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>(A-D) Adult Lrp2 267/À mouse and littermate control.</s><s>Note the exophthalmic eyes (buphthalmos) in the Lrp2 267/À animal (C and D).</s><s>(E and F) Eye size at 10 weeks of age (E) and postnatal day (P) 10 (F).</s><s>The scale bar represents 1 mm.</s><s>(G and H) (G) Axial length and lens thickness as determined on transverse sections of P10 eyes (exemplified in H, c).</s><s>The axial length is increased in Lrp2 267/À compared to control animals (n = 5 per genotype; **p &lt; 0.01; and Mann-Whitney U test).</s><s>The values are mean ± SEM (H).</s><s>The H&amp;E-stained transverse sections of adult and P10 eyes showing increased globe diameter (a-d), thinning of the retina (e-h), as well as hyperplasia of the non-pigmented epithelium of the CB (arrows; i-l) in Lrp2 267/À animals in both age groups.</s><s>The lines in (c) indicate the measurement of the axial length and lens thickness as quantified in (G).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Loss of LRP2 Does Not Impact Stratification of the Retina (A and B) H&amp;E stained sections of neural retina and CMZ (brackets) in E16.5 embryos.(C-J)</s><s>In situ hybridization on sections of E16.5 mouse eyes indicates expression of Shh (arrowheads) and Math5 in the neural retina, but absence from the CMZ (encircled) of control and Lrp2 À/À embryos.</s><s>(K-P) Immunodetection of zinc finger protein 2 (Zic2; red) and insulin-related protein 2 (Isl2; green) in the neural retina of control and Lrp2 À/À E16.5 mouse embryos.</s><s>The coexpression of both proteins in the ventrotemporal crescent of the retina is depicted in (M) and (P) (yellow signal).</s><s>There is no expression seen in the CMZ (arrowheads in M and P).</s><s>(Q-V) Immunodetection of shows similar patterns in the neural retina of control (Q) and Lrp2 À/À (T) E16.5 mouse embryos.</s><s>However, in the mutants, Brn-3b signals extend further into the distal margin of the retina as shown for the dorsal (U) and ventral (V) tip.</s><s>The brackets mark the distal margin free of Brn-3b signals in control and LRP2-deficient eyes.</s><s>The scale bars represent 100 mm.</s><s>See also FigureS2.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,53.12,101.71,321.55,556.27" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. Ectopic Induction of SHH Signaling and Loss of WNT Activity in the LRP2-Deficient CMZ (A) ISH on sections of E16.5 mouse eyes using probes for the indicated CMZ markers.</s><s>The overviews of the eyes are shown in the left, while enlarged views of the CMZ are given in the right.The expression domains for Bmp4 (a-d), Msx1 (e-h), and Otx1 (i-l) are identical in control and Lrp2 À/À E16.5 embryos.</s><s>(B) ISH on E16.5 mouse eyes using probes for targets of SHH signaling.</s><s>The Lrp2 À/À mouse eyes exhibit an aberrant induction of Hes1 (as shown for two individuals; arrowheads in d and h) and of Gli1 (arrowheads in l) as compared to controls (b, f, and i).</s><s>The ectopic induction was seen in three out of five (Hes1) and in four out of five (Gli1) embryos analyzed.</s><s>(C) ISH indicates elevated levels of Ptch1 in the CMZ (encircled) of mutant compared to control E16.5 eyes.</s><s>(D) qRT-PCR for Gli1, Ptch1, and Shh transcripts in the CMZ and neural retina of mice.</s><s>The levels of transcripts are given relative to the control retina (set to 1).</s><s>The levels for Ptch1 and Gli1 are significantly increased in the CMZ, but not in the neural retina of mutant embryos (n = 7-12 animals per group; Student's t test).</s><s>The data are depicted as fold changes ± error.</s><s>(E) Staining for lacZ activity (arrowheads) on sections of E16.5 mouse eyes from Gli1_LacZ (a-d) and Tcf/Lef_LacZ (e-h) reporter lines.</s><s>The mice express (control) or lack LRP2 (Lrp2 À/À ).</s><s>In the LRP2-deficient CMZ, the activity of the GLI1dependent LacZ reporter is aberrantly induced (d) as compared to the control tissue (b) (seen in nine out of 16 embryos).</s><s>The activity of the Tcf/Lef-dependent lacZ reporter gene is diminished in the mutant (h) compared to the control (f) CMZ (in seven out of nine embryos).</s><s>The reduction of Tcf/Lef-dependent lacZ expression in Lrp2 À/À (l) compared to the control CMZ (j) was confirmed by ISH for lacZ (i-l).</s><s>The arrowheads highlight the CMZ.</s><s>The scale bars represent 100 mm.</s><s>See also FigureS3.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,59.75,101.71,322.79,321.51" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. Aberrant Expansion of the Retinal Progenitor Cell Pool in the LRP2-Deficient CMZ (A) Immunohistological detection of RPC markers SOX2 and VSX2 documenting upregulation in the mutant compared to the control E16.5 CMZ (circled by white lines).</s><s>(B) The increase in SOX2 signal in the mutant as compared to the control CMZ (as exemplified in A) was quantified as relative fluorescence intensity (n = 5-7 eyes per genotype).</s><s>(C) Increased transcript levels for Vsx2 in the CMZ, but not in the neural retina of Lrp2 À/À compared to control E16.5 eyes.</s><s>The transcript levels are given relative to the control retina (set to 1) (n = 7-8 animals per group; Student's t test).</s><s>The data are depicted as fold changes ± error.</s><s>(D) In utero labeling with BrdU or immunodetection of PH3 or Ki67 documented an increase in the number of mitotic cells in the LRP2-deficient compared to the control E16.5 CMZ region (circled by white lines).</s><s>(E-G) Quantification of cells positive for BrdU (E), PH3 (F), and Ki67 (G) in the LRP2-deficient compared to the control CMZ (as exemplified in D).</s><s>The number of BrdU+ cells was quantified as relative fluorescence intensity (n = 7-12 eyes per genotype).</s><s>The numbers for PH3+ and Ki67+ cells are given as average cell count per CMZ section (n = 5-10 eyes per genotype) (*p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; 0.01; and Mann Whitney U test).</s><s>The values are mean ± SEM.</s><s>The scale bars represent 50 mm.</s><s>See also Figure S4.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,53.12,101.71,321.55,506.44" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. LRP2 Deficiency Enhances SHH-Dependent Cell Proliferation in the CMZ(A) Immunodetection of BrdU+ cells in the CMZ of E16.5 control and Lrp2 À/À retinal explants cultured for 24 hr.</s><s>The CMZ is encircled by a white line.</s><s>The BrdU+ cells in the neural retina (arrowhead) and lens (asterisks) are indicated.</s><s>(B and C) Quantification of BrdU+ cells in the CMZ of control and Lrp2 À/À retinal explants after 24 hr incubation.</s><s>The explants in (B) were incubated in 3 mM KAAD-cyclopamine or in solvent DMSO only.</s><s>The explants in (C) were incubated in 800 nM SAG or buffer (n = 5-12 per genotype) (not significant: n.s.; **p &lt; 0.01; ***p &lt; 0.001; and two-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni post test).</s><s>The values are mean ± SD. (D) Loss of lacZ activity in the CMZ (arrowheads) of control explants of the Tcf/Lef-lacZ line treated for 36-48 hr with 800 nM SAG as compared to buffertreated tissues (seen in three out of six explants analyzed).</s><s>(E) Wild-type retinal explants of the Tcf/Lef-lacZ line were treated for 24 hr with buffer (a and b), 5 mM JW55 (c and d), or 5 mM JW55 and 800 nM SAG (e and f).</s><s>The suppression of WNT signaling in JW55-treated explants (reduced lacZ signal in c) does not increase cell proliferation in the CMZ (encircled) above levels in the buffer control as shown by BrdU staining (b and d; seen in eight out of eight explants).</s><s>However, induction of proliferation in the CMZ is seen in JW55-treated explants that received SAG (f; seen in three out of three explants analyzed) (lens: le).</s><s>The scale bar represents 75 mm.</s><s>See also FigureS5.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,59.75,101.71,321.55,293.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6.</s><s>LRP2 Mediates Lysosomal Catabolism of SHH to Antagonize Morphogen Activity (A) Immunodetection of Arl13b in CMZ and neural retina of Lrp2 À/À and control E16.5 retinal explants.</s><s>The Arl13+ primary cilia (red) are seen in the neural retina and to a lesser extent in the CMZ (indicted by white lines) in both genotypes as shown in overview (a and b) and in higher magnification micrographs (c-f).</s><s>The asterisks in (a) and (b) mark primary cilia in the lens.</s><s>The insets show localization of LRP2 (green) at the ciliary base in control (d), but not Lrp2 À/À (f) CMZ tissue.</s><s>(B) Immunodetection of SMO (red) and ciliary marker GLI2 (green) identifies cilia positive for SMO (arrowheads) in the mutant (d), but not in the control (b) CMZ.</s><s>In the neural retina, SMO+ cilia are seen in both genotypes (a and c).(C)</s><s>Quantification of primary cilia positive for Arl13b and SMO in control and Lrp2 À/À CMZ explants (as exemplified in A and B).</s><s>The cilia per histological section was determined in n = 11-13 animals.</s><s>(not significant: n.s.; ***p &lt; 0.001; and Mann-Whitney U test).</s><s>The values are mean ± SD. (D) Levels of endogenous SHH are slightly decreased in the neural retina, but increased in the CMZ of Lrp2 À/À compared to control eyes as documented by western blotting of dissected tissues (exemplified in the inset) and by densitometric scanning of replicate blots (n = 4-7 pools per genotype; eight eyes per pool for the CMZ, two to five eyes per pool for the neural retina).</s><s>The SHH levels in the mutant tissues were corrected for the tubulin loading control and are given as % signal of the respective control pool (set to 100%; column statistics and one sample t test).</s><s>(E) Immunodetection of LRP2 (green) and SHH (red) in control and Lrp2 À/À retinal explants treated with GST-SHH-N.</s><s>The overviews (a, c, e, and g) as well as higher magnifications (b, d, f, and h) of the neural retina and CMZ are shown.</s><s>In controls, robust uptake of GST-SHH-N is seen in the CMZ (a and b), but not in the neural retina (e and f).</s><s>No uptake of GST-SHH-N into the CMZ (c and d) or the neural retina (g and h) is seen in the Lrp2 À/À explants.</s><s>(F) Control explants were incubated with 5 mg/ml GST-SHH-N and subsequently stained for LRP2 (upper) or GST-SHH (lower) and the indicated markers.</s><s>The LRP2 (green) localizes with markers (red) of clathrin-coated pits (AP2), early (Rab4), and recycling (Rab11) endosomes, but not lysosomes (Lamp1).</s><s>In contrast, internalized GST-SHH-N (red) colocalizes with markers (green) of early endosomes (Rab4) and lysosomes (Lamp1 or cathepsin B [CatB]), but not with recycling endosomal marker Rab11.</s><s>The scale bars represent 5 mm (A, c; B, a) and 25 mm.</s><s>See also FigureS6.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,56.41,101.59,483.58,283.81" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 7. LRP2 Increases the Threshold for SHH Signaling to Suppress Mitogenic Stimuli in the Peripheral Retina (A and B) Immunodetection of BrdU+ cells (red) in the CMZ of control and Lrp2 À/À retinal explants cultured for 48 hr in the presence of 0.05 mg/ml (A) or 0.2 mg/ml (B) SHH-Np.</s><s>Where indicated, the medium also included 1 mM KAAD-cyclopamine or the solvent DMSO.</s><s>The CMZ is encircled by a white line.</s><s>The scale bar represents 75 mm.</s><s>(C) Quantification of the number of BrdU+ cells per CMZ section (as in A and B) for retinal explants incubated for 48 hr in the absence (0 mg/ml) or in the presence of the indicated concentrations of SHH-Np (as exemplified in A and B).</s><s>The SHH-Np-induced stimulation of proliferation is blocked by 1 mM KAAD-cyclopamine in both genotypes (n = 3-14 per genotype) (*p &lt; 0.05 and two-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni post test).</s><s>(D) Dose-response curve of the number of BrdU+ cells in control and Lrp2 À/À CMZ explants treated with the indicated concentrations of SHH-Np for 48 hr.</s><s>The curves were fitted assuming a sigmoidal dose-response (variable slope).</s><s>The comparison of fits: F (5.64; 1.54).</s><s>The concentration of SHH-Np required to elicit half maximal response (EC 50 ; dotted lines) is given (n = 5-9 per condition and genotype; p = 0.018).</s><s>The values are mean ± SEM. (E) Immunodetection of PTCH1 and GLI2 in the CMZ of retinal explants treated with buffer or SAG.</s><s>In control and Lrp2 À/À tissues, PTCH1 is present in apical vesicles and at the cells surface (a and b) and enriched in GLI2+ cilia upon SAG stimulation (arrowheads in c and d).</s><s>No colocalization is seen for LRP2 (green) and PTCH1 (red) in buffer (e) or SAG treated (g) CMZ explants.</s><s>For comparison, the inset in (e) depicts colocalization of LRP2 and PTCH1 in the E10.5 RDVM.</s><s>The scale bar represents 5 mm.</s><s>(F) Explants of E16.5 CMZ or E8.5 RDVM were incubated with GST or GST-SHH-N for 2 hr and immunostained for PTCH1 (red) and ligand (green).</s><s>The efficient uptake of GST-SHH-N is seen in control CMZ (c) and RDVM (g), but not in LRP2-deficient tissues (d and h).</s><s>No uptake of GST is seen in any condition (a, b, e, and f).</s><s>The LRP2-mediated uptake of GST-SHH-N results in cointernalization of PTCH1 in the RDVM (yellow signals in g), but fails to cointernalize PTCH1 in the CMZ (green signals in c).</s><s>The scale bar represents 10 mm (a) or 50 mm (b).</s><s>(G) Modulation of SHH signaling by LRP2.</s><s>Under basal conditions (a), binding of SHH to PTCH1 results in internalization of PTCH1 and in pathway activation.</s><s>In the RDVM (b), LRP2 promotes signaling by interacting with PTCH1 to facilitate high-affinity binding and internalization of PTCH1/SHH complexes.</s><s>The SHH is recycled via Rab11+ sorting pathways.</s><s>In the CMZ (c), LRP2 fails to interact with PTCH1 and directs lysosomal catabolism of the internalized morphogen (c).</s><s>See also Figure S7.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,95.07,101.59,419.73,344.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="1,55.16,173.14,285.82,285.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Developmental Cell 35, 36-48, October 12, 2015 ª2015 Elsevier Inc. 41</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Developmental Cell 35, 36-48, October 12, 2015 ª2015 Elsevier Inc. 43</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="44">Developmental Cell 35, 36-48, October 12, 2015 ª2015 Elsevier Inc.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Developmental Cell 35, 36-48, October 12, 2015 ª2015 Elsevier Inc. 45</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>We are indebted to Mohammad Shahidullah (University of Arizona), Erin Bassett, and Chantal Mazerolle (Ottawa Hospital Research Institute) for expert advice and to Anne-Sophie Carlo and Vanessa Schmidt for help with the statistical analysis.</s><s>Claire Li, Melanie Liekweg, Kristin Kampf, and Maria Schmeisser provided expert technical assistance.</s><s>Studies were funded by SFB665 (to T.E.W. and A.H.) and the HGF Postdoctoral Fellowship Program (to A. Christ).</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>and condition.</s><s>In embryonic eyes, the CMZ was defined as the region of interest and immunofluorescence intensities quantified using LAS AF software.</s><s>Signal intensities were determined on 3-4 sections per eye for a total of 5-12 animals per genotype and condition.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Analysis</head><p><s>Statistical significance was calculated using GraphPad Prism 5/6 software.</s><s>Results comparing two groups were analyzed either by Student's t test <ref type="bibr">(Figures 3D and 4C)</ref> or by Mann-Whitney U test (Figures <ref type="figure">1G, 4B</ref>, 4E-4G, 6C, S1B, S2E, S3D, S4A, S4B, S4D, and S6I).</s><s>Results in which more than two groups and different treatments were compared to each other were analyzed by two-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni post test (Figures <ref type="figure">5B, 5C, and 7C</ref>).</s><s>Results shown in Figure <ref type="figure">6D</ref> were analyzed using one sample t test.</s><s>Data in Figure <ref type="figure">7D</ref> were analyzed using a sigmoidal dose-response (variable slope) equation.</s><s>Values are indicated in the figure legends.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION</head><p><s>Supplemental Information includes Supplemental Experimental Procedures and seven figures and can be found with this article online at http://dx.doi.</s><s>org/10.1016/j.devcel.2015.09.001.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</head><p><s>A.C., A. Christa, J.K., and S.B. performed experiments and evaluated data.</s><s>A. Christ, J.C.E., V.A.W., A.H., and T.E.W. conceived experiments and evaluated data.</s><s>T.E.W. wrote the manuscript.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gli2, but not Gli1, is required for initial Shh signaling and ectopic activation of the Shh pathway</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Auerbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stephen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Joyner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4753" to="4761" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bilioni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Sa ´nchez-Herna ´ndez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Callejo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gradilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Iba ´n ˜ez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mollica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Carmen Rodrı ´guez-Navas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Guerrero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Balancing Hedgehog, a retention and release equilibrium given by Dally, Ihog, Boi and shifted/DmWif</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">376</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="198" to="212" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cdon acts as a Hedgehog decoy receptor during proximal-distal patterning of the optic vesicle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cardozo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sa ´nchez-Arrones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sandonis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sa ´nchez-Camacho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gestri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Guerrero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bovolenta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4272</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wnt2b/beta-catenin-mediated canonical Wnt signaling determines the peripheral fates of the chick eye</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cepko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3167" to="3177" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LRP2 is an auxiliary SHH receptor required to condition the forebrain ventral midline for inductive signals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Christ</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Christa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Lioubinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bachmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Willnow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hammes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="268" to="278" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Suppressor of fused is required to maintain the multipotency of neural progenitor cells in the retina</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cwinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mazerolle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mcneill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ringuette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Thurig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5169" to="5180" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Indian hedgehog signaling from endothelial cells is required for sclera and retinal pigment epithelium development in the mouse eye</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Dakubo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mazerolle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Furimsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>St-Jacques</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mcmahon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">320</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="242" to="255" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LRP2 in ependymal cells regulates BMP signaling in the adult neurogenic niche</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Gajera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Emich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Lioubinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Christ</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Beckervordersandforth-Bonk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yoshikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bachmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Christensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Go ¨tz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kempermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1922" to="1930" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drosophila Boi limits Hedgehog levels to suppress follicle stem cell proliferation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hartman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zinshteyn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Schofield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Nicolas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Okada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Reilly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">191</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="943" to="952" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expression of Sonic hedgehog and its putative role as a precursor cell mitogen in the developing mouse retina</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="371" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutations in LRP2, which encodes the multiligand receptor megalin, cause Donnai-Barrow and facio-oculo-acoustico-renal syndromes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kantarci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Al-Gazali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Donnai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Black</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bieth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Chassaing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lacombe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Devriendt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Teebi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="957" to="959" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sonic hedgehog promotes rod photoreceptor differentiation in mammalian retinal cells in vitro</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Roelink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Reh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6277" to="6288" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ciliary margin transdifferentiation from neural retina is controlled by canonical Wnt signaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mazerolle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Thurig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Coles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Taketo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Van Der Kooy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">308</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kremen proteins are Dickkopf receptors that regulate Wnt/beta-catenin signalling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Davidson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Marhold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mechler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Delius</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hoppe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stannek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Walter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">417</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="664" to="667" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Beta-catenin signaling marks the prospective site of primitive streak formation in the mouse embryo</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mohamed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Clarke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dufort</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Dyn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">231</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="416" to="424" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Persistent progenitors at the retinal margin of ptc+/-mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Moshiri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Reh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="237" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patterning of the zebrafish retina by a wave of sonic hedgehog activity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Neumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nuesslein-Volhard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">289</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2137" to="2139" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A review of Donnai-Barrow and facio-oculo-acoustico-renal (DB/FOAR) syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Pober</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Longoni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Noonan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Birth Defects Res. A. Clin. Mol. Teratol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="81" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patched1 regulates hedgehog signaling at the primary cilium</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rohatgi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Milenkovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">317</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="372" to="376" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical characterization of individuals with deletions of genes in holoprosencephaly pathways by aCGH refines the phenotypic spectrum of HPE</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rosenfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ballif</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Aylsworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bejjani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Torchia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Shaffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="421" to="440" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinct effects of Hedgehog signaling on neuronal fate specification and cell cycle progression in the embryonic mouse retina</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sakagami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yang</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6932" to="6944" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shh/Boc signaling is required for sustained generation of ipsilateral projecting ganglion cells in the mouse retina</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sa ´nchez-Arrones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Nieto-Lopez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sa ´nchez-Camacho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Carreres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Herrera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Okada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bovolenta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8596" to="8607" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ARH directs megalin to the endocytic recycling compartment to regulate its proteolysis and gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Baterina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Taupin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Farquhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">202</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="127" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LRP2/megalin is required for patterning of the ventral telencephalon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Spoelgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hammes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Anzenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zechner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Andersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Jerchow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Willnow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="405" to="414" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Megalindeficiency causes high myopia, retinal pigment epithelium-macromelanosomes and abnormal development of the ciliary body in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Storm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Heegaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Christensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Tissue Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">358</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="107" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Effects of oncogenic mutations in</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Taipale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Milenkovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Beachy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Developmental Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="48" />
			<date>October 12. 2015 ª2015</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier Inc. 47</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Smoothened and Patched can be reversed by cyclopamine</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">406</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1005" to="1009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Veth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Willer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Collery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Willer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mullins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Udvadia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W M</forename><surname>John</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutations in zebrafish lrp2 result in adult-onset ocular pathogenesis that models myopia and other risk factors for glaucoma</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1001310</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel tankyrase inhibitor decreases canonical Wnt signaling in colon carcinoma cells and reduces tumor growth in conditional APC mutant mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Waaler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Machon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tumova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Dinh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Korinek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Paulsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pedersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Eide</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Machonova</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2822" to="2832" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development of normal retinal organization depends on Sonic hedgehog signaling from ganglion cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dakubo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Howley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Campsall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mazarolle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Shiga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mcmahon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="831" to="832" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Retinal ganglion cell-derived sonic hedgehog locally controls proliferation and the timing of RGC development in the embryonic mouse retina</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Dakubo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Thurig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mazerolle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5103" to="5113" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Endocytic receptor-mediated control of morphogen signaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Willnow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Christ</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hammes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4311" to="4319" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The cellsurface proteins Dally-like and Ihog differentially regulate Hedgehog signaling strength and range during development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Belenkaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lin</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2033" to="2044" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A focused and efficient genetic screening strategy in the mouse: identification of mutations that disrupt cortical development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Zarbalis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>May</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ekker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rubenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Peterson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">E219</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BMP signaling is required for development of the ciliary body</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Overbeek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4435" to="4442" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disruption of SoxB1-dependent Sonic hedgehog expression in the hypothalamus causes septo-optic dysplasia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Zevallos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Rizzoti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Jeong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lovell-Badge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Epstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="585" to="596" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
