<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Microbiological findings in bronchoalveolar lavage fluid from lung transplant patients in Sweden</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Anna</forename><forename type="middle">Stjärne</forename><surname>Aspelund</surname></persName>
							<email>anna.stjarne_aspelund@med.lu.se</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-7391-268X</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Infection Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hospital of Helsingborg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Helsingborg</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Infection Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Clinical Sciences Lund</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Skåne University Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Lund University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lund</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Helena</forename><surname>Hammarström</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Infectious Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sahlgrenska Academy at University of Gothenburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Göteborg</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">|</forename><surname>Malin Inghammar</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Infection Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Clinical Sciences Lund</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Skåne University Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Lund University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lund</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hillevi</forename><surname>Larsson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Clinical Sciences Lund, Respiratory Medicine and Allergology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Skåne University Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Lund University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lund</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">|</forename><surname>Lennart Hansson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Clinical Sciences Lund, Respiratory Medicine and Allergology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Skåne University Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Lund University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lund</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">|</forename><surname>Gerdt</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Riise</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Respiratory Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sahlgrenska University Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Göteborg</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Vanda</forename><surname>Friman</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Infectious Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sahlgrenska Academy at University of Gothenburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Göteborg</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bertil</forename><surname>Christensson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Infection Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Clinical Sciences Lund</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Skåne University Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Lund University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lund</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lisa</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Påhlman</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Infection Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Clinical Sciences Lund</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Skåne University Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Lund University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lund</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Infection Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hospital of Helsingborg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Helsingborg</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Microbiological findings in bronchoalveolar lavage fluid from lung transplant patients in Sweden</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">1EECDCDBDDF7A79B40229084F4851F27</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/tid.12973</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 2 March 2018 | Revised: 19 July 2018 | Accepted: 25 July 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:50+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>bronchoalveolar lavage fluid</term>
					<term>lung infections</term>
					<term>lung transplantation</term>
					<term>microbiology</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Background: Lung transplant patients experience a high risk of airway infections and microbial colonization of the lung due to constant exposure to the environment through inhaled microorganisms, denervation, reduced ciliary transport, and decreased cough.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods:</head><p><s>In this nationwide prospective study on Swedish lung transplant patients, we evaluated the microbiological panorama of bacteria, fungi, and virus found in bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF) obtained the first year after lung transplantation (LTx).</s><s>Differences in microbiological findings depending of concomitant signs of infection and background factors were assessed.</s><s>Results: A total of 470 bronchoscopies from 126 patients were evaluated.</s><s>Sixty-two percent (n = 293) of BALF samples had positive microbiological finding(s).</s><s>Forty-six percent (n = 217) had bacterial growth, 29% (n = 137) fungal growth, and 9% (n = 43) were positive in viral PCR.</s><s>In 38% of BALF samples (n = 181), a single microbe was found, whereas a combination of bacteria, fungi or virus was found in 24% (n = 112) of bronchoscopies.</s><s>The most common microbiological findings were Candida albicans, Pseudomonas aeruginosa and coagulase negative Staphylococcus (in 42 (33%), 36 (29%), and 25 (20%) patients, respectively).</s><s>Microbiological findings were similar in BALF from patients with and without signs of lung infection and the frequency of multidrug resistant (MDR) bacteria was low.</s><s>No significant association was found between background factors and time to first lung infection.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion:</head><p><s>This study gives important epidemiologic insights and reinforces that microbiological findings have to be evaluated in the light of clinical symptoms and endobronchial appearance in the assessment of lung infections in lung transplant patients.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">| INTRODUC TI ON</head><p><s>Lung transplantation (LTx) increases as a treatment option for end stage lung disease.</s><s>Although mortality post transplantation has decreased with modern surgical techniques and pharmaceutical regimes, 5-year mortality has been reported to be around 50%, of which infections are the predominant cause of death during the first year post LTx. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> The constant exposure to the environment through inhaled microorganisms together with denervation, reduced ciliary transport and decreased cough, increase the risk of lung infections.</s></p><p><s>Moreover, heavy immunosuppressive therapy leads to decreased immune defense.</s><s>Bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL), including microbiological cultures and PCR, are performed in lung transplant patients for surveillance and in response to clinical symptoms to guide antibiotic therapy.</s><s>As the microbiological panorama differs by geographical region, especially with regards to multidrug resistant bacteria (MDR), it is important to map the local epidemiology.</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> Moreover, most studies of lung infections in lung transplant patients are single center reports with a small number of patients.</s><s>In Sweden, LTx is performed at two centers only, Skåne University Hospital, Lund and Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Gothenburg.</s><s>The primary aim of this nationwide prospective study was to examine the microbiological panorama in BALF of lung transplant patients in Sweden during the first-year post transplantation and to compare findings in patients with and without signs of lung infection.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">| MATERIAL AND ME THODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">| Study setting and patient population</head><p><s>This prospective cohort study included all adult patients accepted for LTx during May 2012 to December 2014 in Gothenburg and October 2012 to December 2014 in Lund.</s><s>Patients under 18 years of age and patients with post-operative follow up at other sites were excluded.</s><s>All patients were followed up for 1 year after transplantation.</s><s>Written informed consent was obtained from all study participants.</s><s>The study was approved by the Regional Ethics Committee (Reg nr 433-08) and performed in accordance with the ethical standards of the 1964 declaration of Helsinki and its later amendments.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">| Immunosuppressive and prophylactic strategies</head><p><s>Standard protocol for immunosuppression included induction therapy with ATG (anti-thymocyte globulin), followed by tacrolimus or ciclosporin, mycophenolate mofetil, and steroids.</s><s>All lung transplant recipients received Pneumocystis prophylaxis with co-trimoxazole.</s></p><p><s>Cytomegalovirus (CMV) prophylaxis with valganciclovir was given to all participants, with the exception of patients in Gothenburg when both donor and recipient were CMV negative.</s><s>In Lund, patients received fungal prophylaxis with fluconazole for 3-6 months, whereas patients in Gothenburg received oral nystatin for at least 3 weeks.</s><s>Standard perioperative antibiotic treatment was cefotaxime in Gothenburg and imipenem in Lund.</s><s>Post-operative modifications or termination of antibiotic treatment was done according to perioperative donor and recipient cultures.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">| Sample collection and microbiology analyses</head><p><s>During the LTx procedure, bacterial and fungal cultures were obtained from the donor and recipient lungs.</s><s>The recipients were then followed during the first year after LTx with routine bronchoscopies at 3, 6, and 12 months post transplantation, and additional bronchoscopies were performed in response to clinical symptoms.</s><s>BAL procedure followed standardized protocols.</s><s>Microbiology analyses were performed at the Microbiological Department, Skåne University Hospital and Sahlgrenska University Hospital according to standard protocols. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref></s><s>All BALF samples were analyzed with bacterial and fungal cultures, including microscopy for fungal elements and PCR for Mycoplasma pneumoniae, Chlamydia pneumoniae and Legionella pneumophila.</s><s>MDR Pseudomonas aeruginosa was defined as resistance against meropenem and at least one agent in three or more categories of anti-pseudomonal antibiotics.</s><s>The definition is based on criteria published by Magiorakos et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> , with the modification that resistance against meropenem had to be present.</s><s>A panel of airway viruses was analyzed with multiplex PCR, including; Parainfluenza 1, 2 and 3, Respiratory Syncytial Virus (RSV), Influenza A and B, Adenovirus, Metapneumovirus, Coronavirus (OC 43, 229E, NK-63, HKU1), Enterovirus, Rhinovirus, and Bocavirus. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref></s><s>In Lund, additional PCR for herpes simplex virus (HSV) 1 and 2 was performed with an in-house method.</s><s>Presence of Pneumocystis jiroveci was analyzed with PCR <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> or immunofluorescence of BALF.</s><s>CMV in blood or plasma was determined with quantitative PCR.</s><s>All BALF samples from Lund were routinely stained and cultured for mycobacteria.</s><s>BALF samples from Gothenburgh were analyzed for mycobacteria when there was a pretransplant history of mycobacterial infection.</s></p><p><s>Transbronchial biopsies (TBB) were analyzed at the Department of Pathology at Skåne University Hospital and Sahlgrenska University Hospital.</s><s>Rejection was defined and graded A0-A3 according to the International Society for Heart &amp; Lung Transplantation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">| Clinical data and definitions</head><p><s>Bronchoscopies with positive microbiological finding(s) were classified as pneumonia in the presence of at least one of the following clinical criteria; new or increased cough, dyspnea, increased sputa, fever &gt;38°C, worsening gas exchange, or white blood cell count &gt;15 × 10 9 /L, together with new (within 7 days before or after bronchoscopy) infiltrates in chest radiology (x-ray or CT scan).</s></p><p><s>Bronchoscopies with positive microbiological finding(s) were classified as tracheobronchitis in the presence of clinical signs as above with no infiltrates on chest radiology but one or more of the following macroscopic endobronchial abnormalities: inflamed endobronchial</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">| 3 of 8 STJÄRNE ASPELUND ET AL.</formula><p><s>mucosa, endobronchial lesion (white/yellow) with/without necrotic changes, and purulent secretion.</s><s>Pneumonia and tracheobronchitis are referred to as bronchoscopies with "signs of infection" in the text.</s><s>CMV pneumonitis was defined as airway symptoms as described above, &gt;1000 CMV copies/mL in blood, and findings of inclusion bodies in TBB.</s><s>A minimum of 30 days between lung infections were allowed to be considered a new episode.</s><s>Bronchoscopies with positive microbiological finding(s) were classified as "no infection" in the absence of clinical and/or radiologic or macroscopic pathology.</s></p><p><s>Growth of pharyngeal flora was considered as contamination and classified as negative microbiology.</s><s>Clinical data were recorded at time of bronchoscopy in a study protocol, and retrieved retrospectively from patient records.</s><s>Time after transplantation was categorized: &lt;1 month, 1-3 months, 3-6 months, 6-9, and 9-12 months after LTx.</s><s>Microbiological findings were grouped into Gram-negative bacteria (G−), Gram-positive bacteria (G+), yeast, mold, and virus.</s><s>P. aeruginosa was analyzed separately.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">| Statistical analysis</head><p><s>Numerical data are presented as median and range.</s><s>Chi-squared, rank sum, Kruskall-Wallis tests, logistic regression and analysis of variance were used to assess the distribution of background factors among different bacterial groups, lung infections and time periods.</s></p><p><s>Since participants underwent varying numbers of bronchoscopies in the study, and several patients had recurrent findings of the same pathogen in BALF, the frequency of individual microbes is reported as the total number of patients with the actual finding.</s><s>Grouped microbiological findings during the first year are presented as percent of patients with a bronchoscopy within the specified time period.</s><s>In contrast to overall microbiological findings, lung infections are presented as number of episodes and not as a proportion of patients.</s></p><p><s>The association between background data (gender, age at LTx, type of LTx and underlying disease, type of immunosuppression, positive or negative donor cultures) and time to first lung infection was estimated with Cox regression.</s><s>All statistical tests were two-sided, and 95% CIs that did not overlap 1.0 and P-values less than 0.05 were considered statistically significant.</s><s>Analyses were performed using</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">| RE SULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">| Patient cohort and bronchoscopies</head><p><s>In total, 135 of 146 (92%) patients eligible for inclusion were consecutively included in the study.</s><s>Nine patients were unable to give informed consent, one patient declined participation and one patient was not included for unknown reasons.</s><s>Nine patients died before any bronchoscopy was performed, resulting in 126 patients (97 from Gothenburg and 29 from Lund) prospectively followed up for 1 year after LTx.</s></p><p><s>The participants had a median age of 57 years, 52% were women, 85% underwent double lung transplantation, and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) was the most common underlying disease.</s><s>For detailed patient characteristics, see Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</s><s>Eightyeight patients (70%) received post-transplant immunosuppression with ciclosporin and 38 (30%) with tacrolimus.</s><s>Patients with cystic fibrosis were more likely to receive tacrolimus than ciclosporin (72% vs 23%, P &lt; 0.01).</s><s>No other differences in choice of immunosuppression depending on background diagnosis were found.</s></p><p><s>During the study period, 470 bronchoscopies were performed with a median of three per patient (range 1-10).</s><s>Two hundred and eleven bronchoscopies (45%) were routine procedures, whereas 259 (55%) were performed on clinical indication.</s><s>The bronchoscopies were distributed over the first post-operative year as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>.</s><s>All samples were analyzed for bacterial and fungal growth, including microscopy for fungal elements, and with PCR for Mycoplasma, Chlamydia, and Legionella.</s><s>Multiplex PCR for airway viruses were analyzed in 342 samples (73%).</s><s>Pneumocystis was analyzed in 416 samples (89%).</s><s>Nineteen patients (15% of the total study population) had negative BALF cultures/PCRs throughout follow up.</s><s>Of the remaining 107 patients with positive microbiology, 50 patients had no episode with signs of lung infection.</s><s>Fifty-seven patients had at least one episode with signs of lung infection, of which 38 patients had at least one pneumonia and 19 patients had at least one episode of tracheobronchitis but no pneumonia.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">| Microbiology results</head><p><s>In total, 177 (38%) BALF samples had negative microbiological results, including 75 samples with growth of pharyngeal flora   The proportion of patients with bacterial findings in BALF increased over the first 6 months and then declined (Figure <ref type="figure">3A</ref>).</s><s>Yeast was most common within the first month after LTx, whereas mold peaked at 3-6 months (Figure <ref type="figure">3B</ref>).</s><s>The proportion of viral findings increased over time with a maximum of 20% of patients at 6-9 months (Figure <ref type="figure">3C</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Gram-positive bacteria were significantly more common in samples from patients receiving immunosuppression with ciclosporin compared to patients receiving tacrolimus (27% and 18%, P = 0.03).</s><s>In contrast, more Gram-negative bacteria were found in samples from patients receiving tacrolimus, 30% and 19%, respectively, yielding an OR of 2.0 (95% CI 1.3-3.3).</s><s>However, patients with cystic fibrosis were more frequently treated with tacrolimus, and no significant association between Gram-negative bacteria and tacrolimus was found when adjusting for cystic fibrosis, OR 1.4 (95% CI 0.8-2.4).</s><s>No significant differences were noted for mold, yeast, or virus (P = 0.06, P = 0.84 and P = 0.55, respectively).</s></p><p><s>In the analysis by underlying pulmonary conditions, growth of P. aeruginosa, as well as other Gram-negative bacteria, were more common findings in patients with cystic fibrosis compared to any other underlying diseases (41% vs 17%, P &lt; 0.01 and 42% vs 19% P = 0.01, respectively).</s><s>Patients with alpha-1-antitrypsin deficiency had significantly more Gram-positive bacteria (34% vs 22%, P = 0.04), and less Gram-negative bacteria (11% vs 25%, P &lt; 0.01) and mold (6% vs 23%, P = 0.01) compared to other underlying di-</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>agnoses. Patients with underlying pulmonary fibrosis had more</head><p><s>Gram-positive bacteria (30% vs 21%, P = 0.03) and less growth of P. aeruginosa in BALF (8% vs 27%, P &lt; 0.01) compared to other underlying diagnoses.</s></p><p><s>Peri-operative recipient cultures were obtained from 121 patients (96%).</s><s>In all, 34 patients (28%) had positive recipient cultures.</s></p><p><s>Sixteen patients (13%) had growth of P. aeruginosa, and the remain-</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">| Signs of lung infection</head><p><s>In  were grade A1 and one grade A2.</s><s>The remaining 159 BALF samples with positive microbiological findings were regarded as no infection (Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>).</s></p><p><s>In BALF from patients with concomitant signs of lung infections the most common Gram-negative, Gram-positive, fungal, and viral organisms were P. aeruginosa, Stenotrophomonas, coagulase negative</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Staphylococcus, S. aureus, C. albicans, Aspergillus fumigatus, Rhinovirus</head><p><s>and Coronavirus (in 32 (28%), 9 (8%), 13 (11%) 12 (11%), 24 (21%), 9 (8%), 8 (7%), and 6 (5%) samples, respectively).</s><s>One patient with signs of lung infection had simultaneously &gt;1000 CMV copies/mL in blood and inclusion bodies in TBB and thus considered as a possible CMV pneumonitis.</s><s>Median time to first episode with signs of lung infection was 37 days (range 5-383), and the incidence decreased over time during the first year after LTx.</s></p><p><s>In 32 (28%) of BALF samples from patients with signs of infection, no previous bronchoscopy had been performed within the study.</s><s>In the remaining 81 (72%) samples, the same microbe was identified in previous BALF in 43 samples (53%), of which 20 (46%) revealed growth of P. aeruginosa.</s></p><p><s>When comparing microbiological findings with and without signs of infection, the frequency of Gram-negative bacteria, Gram-positive bacteria, mold and virus were not significantly different (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>).</s><s>Yeast was significantly more frequent in signs of infection (32% and 19%, P = 0.01).</s><s>However, Candida was found as a single microbe in only 17 samples (15%) with signs of lung infection, all of which had concomitant macroscopic findings consistent with tracheobronchitis.</s><s>Fourteen of 17 samples (82%) were obtained within 1 month after LTx and 10 samples (59%) were</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. albicans.</head><p><s>The total number of bronchoscopies with several microbiological findings did not significantly differ between samples from patients with signs of infection and samples from patients with no infection (34% and 40%, respectively.</s><s>P = 0.32).</s><s>Neither did type of immunosuppression significantly differ between samples from patients with and without signs of infection (P = 0.42).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">| Donor cultures, background data and lung infections</head><p><s>During the lung transplantation procedure, bacterial and fungal cultures were obtained from donor lungs in 119 patients (94%).</s><s>Donor cultures were positive in 79 patients (63%), of which 70 (55%) had growth of bacteria and 18 (14%) had fungal growth.</s><s>The most frequent bacterial and fungal microbiological findings in donor lungs were S. aureus and Candida species (47 (37%) and 17 (13%), respectively).</s><s>Sixty-five patients with positive donor cultures underwent bronchoscopy within 1 month post Tx.</s><s>Cultures from 14 BALF samples (22%) yielded the same microbial species as found in the donor cultures, of which 11 were Candida.</s><s>In the first post-operative month, Candida was significantly more common in BALF from patients with Candida in donor cultures compared to BALF from patients with donor lungs negative for Candida (79% and 38%, respectively; P = 0.04).</s></p><p><s>No significant association was found between background factors and time to first lung infection as estimated by Cox regression; hazard ratio (HR) for positive donor cultures was: 1.5; 0.9-2.7;</s></p><p><s>HR for gender was 1.5; 0.9-2.6;</s><s>HR for age at LTx was 1.0; 0.8-1.3 per 10-year increase; HR for single vs double lungs LTx was: 0.9; 0.4-1.9;</s><s>HR for type of immunosuppression was: 1.4; 0.8-2.4;</s><s>and HR for cystic fibrosis as compared to other underlying diseases was: 1.3; 0.6-2.7.</s></p><p><s>In a secondary analysis, patients with no microbial growth in BALF throughout follow up were compared to patients with positive microbial findings.</s><s>No differences in underlying factors were found, data not reported.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">| D ISCUSS I ON</head><p><s>Lung transplanted patients undergo bronchoalveolar lavage several times during their first year after transplantation.</s><s>Most studies on microbiology in lung transplant patients evaluate infection episodes, but very few report all microbiological findings in BALF.</s><s>In this prospective study, we analyzed for the first time the total microbiological panorama found in BALF in Swedish lung transplant recipients.</s></p><p><s>We found that 85% of patients had samples with positive microbiologic finding(s), and only 15% of patients remained negative throughout their bronchoscopies.</s><s>In line with our findings, Charlson et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> found that lung transplant recipients have a higher bacterial burden in BALF than healthy control subjects, regardless of underlying indication for transplantation.</s><s>The single most common bacterium was P. aeruginosa, both overall and in samples with signs of lung infection.</s></p><p><s>P. aeruginosa is previously well described as an important pathogen in lung transplanted patients.</s><s>Forty-five percent of patients experienced at least one episode with symptoms of lung infection during the first year after transplantation.</s><s>A limitation of the study is that we did not take additional cultures/PCR from blood, sputum or nasopharyngeal into account.</s><s>Another limitation is that we did not evaluate patients with culture-negative samples for signs of infection, which is why the true frequency of lung infections may be underestimated.</s></p><p><s>Although, our results are comparable to other studies that report a frequency of lung infections between 30% and 70%. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref></s><s>e incidence of lung infections in our study decreased over time.</s></p><p><s>Similar results have been reported in other studies, where the first three post-operative months have been defined as the critical period for infections in lung transplanted patients, especially for bacterial etiology. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref></s><s>Consistent with previous studies, we found no significant association between positive donor cultures and later microbiological findings in the absence or presence of lung infections. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26</ref></s><s>e microbiologic panorama found in BALF from patients with clinical signs of lung infection was similar to that found in samples from patients without symptoms in our study.</s><s>However, it is important to note that we did not evaluate the probable causative pathogen.</s><s>Since several microbiologic agents were found in 40% of BALF from patients with signs of lung infection, the causative microbe was difficult to determine.</s><s>In addition, we lack information about concomitant antimicrobial treatment that may interfere with microbiological results, as well as how treatment of specific patho-</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_1">gens</formula></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>the STATA/SE (version 13.1 for Windows; StataCorp LP, College Station, TX, USA), Graphpad Prism 6 (GraphPad Software; La Jolla, CA, USA) and SPSS (version 20.0; SPSS, Armonk, NY, USA).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>F I G U R E 1 a</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Total number of bronchoscopies and number of patients with a bronchoscopy performed during the specified time interval.</s><s>In total, 103 (22%) bronchoscopies were performed less than 1 mo after LTx, 98 (21%) 1-3 mo, 140 (30%) 3-6 mo, 47 (10%) 6-9 and 82 (17%) 9-12 mo after transplantation F I G U R E 2 Flowchart of samples in the study cohort and subsequent classification according to microbiological results in BALF and clinical signs of infection at the time of sampling TA B L E 2 (ABC) Microbial findings in BALF during first year expressed as total number of patients (percent of patients, n total=126).</s><s>Owing to bronchoscopies with several microbiological findings the figures do not sum up to 100% Positive in PCR (no sample positive in IF).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>two Escherichia coli and one Enterobacter cloacae), one patient (1%) of a multiresistant Burkholderia and nine patients (7%) of multiresistant P. aeruginosa.</s><s>No methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA), ESBL-and carbapenemase-producing Enterobacteriaceae or vancomycin-resistant Enterococcus (VRE) was found.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>ing 18 patients had findings of S. aureus, E. coli, Candida and other Gram-negatives.</s><s>All 16 patients with Pseudomonas in recipient cultures had subsequent positive cultures for Pseudomonas at some point during the follow up period.</s><s>No significant difference in time to first positive Pseudomonas culture was found between patients with (n = 16) and without (n = 20) growth of pseudomonas in recipient cultures (mean time to positive Pseudomonas culture 135 and 140 days, respectively (P = 0.86)).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>134 of 293 bronchoscopies with positive microbiological findings, the patients had clinical signs of lung infection (pneumonia or tracheobronchitis) at the time of bronchoscopy.</s><s>Twenty-one BALF samples from 17 patients with signs of infection were obtained less than 30 days apart, and thus considered as the same lung infection episode.</s><s>This left 113 samples, of which 61 samples were from patients with concomitant symptoms consistent with pneumonia and 52 with tracheobronchitis.</s><s>Six samples had also signs of acute rejection in TBB, which may add to the clinical presentation.</s><s>Five F I G U R E 3 (ABC) Microbiological findings in BALF the first year after LTx expressed as percent of patients with a bronchoscopy performed within each time interval.</s><s>A, Gram-negative bacteria (G−) and Gram-positive (G+) bacteria; B, Yeast and mold; C, Virus</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>influences the clinical outcome.</s><s>About half of the patients with signs of lung infection had a previous bronchoscopy with the same microbe found in BALF, suggesting that the microbiology results of a previous bronchoscopy could guide antibiotic treatment in about half of the cases.</s><s>In particular, previous cultures with P. aeruginosa should be targeted in empiric treatment.In conclusion, a majority of bronchoscopies from lung transplant patients during the first year after LTx had positive microbiologic findings, often with several pathogens.</s><s>Previous BAL cultures, in particular findings of P. aeruginosa, could guide empiric treatment of airway infections, which suggests a role for surveillance bronchoscopies.</s><s>The frequency of MDR bacteria was low in our study, indicating that empiric therapy does not need to include MDR bacteria at present in Sweden.</s><s>Microbiological findings were similar in BALF from patients with and without signs of lung infection.</s><s>The results reinforce that microbiological findings have to be evaluated in the light of clinical symptoms and endobronchial appearance in the assessment of lung infections in lung transplant patients.</s><s>and ethical considerations, all authors revised the material, discussed the results, and contributed to the final manuscript.O RCI DAnna Stjärne Aspelundhttp://orcid.org/0000-0002-7391-268XR E FE R E N C E S</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>TA B L E 1 Patient characteristics</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">(Figure 2). These were excluded from further analyses. The remain-</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Total patients n ing 293 (62%) samples had positive microbiological findings, of 126</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Gender male/female n which 217 (46%) BALF had bacterial growth, 137 (29%) had fungal 61/65</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Age at tx. years median (range) growth, and 43 (9%) were positive in viral PCR. A single microbe was 57 (18-70)</cell></row><row><cell>Transplantation</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Single n (%)</cell><cell>18 (14)</cell></row><row><cell>Double n (%)</cell><cell>108 (85)</cell></row><row><cell>Underlying diagnosis n patients (%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</cell><cell>33 (26)</cell></row><row><cell>Pulmonary fibrosis</cell><cell>31 (25)</cell></row><row><cell>Cystic fibrosis</cell><cell>18 (14)</cell></row><row><cell>Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency</cell><cell>17 (13)</cell></row><row><cell>Pulmonary arterial hypertension</cell><cell>7 (6)</cell></row><row><cell>Re-transplantation</cell><cell>6 (5)</cell></row><row><cell>Sarcoidosis</cell><cell>2 (2)</cell></row><row><cell>Bronchiectasis</cell><cell>2 (2)</cell></row><row><cell>Bronchiolitis obliterans syndrome</cell><cell>2 (2)</cell></row><row><cell>Emphysema</cell><cell>2 (2)</cell></row><row><cell>Other</cell><cell>6 (5)</cell></row></table><note><p><s>found in 181 (38%) BALF samples, whereas 112 (24%) BALF had a combination of bacteria, fungi, or virus.Bronchoscopies performed within 3 months after transplantation had more poly-microbial findings compared to later bronchoscopies (44% vs 33%, P = 0.04).The most common microbiological findings were Candida albicans, P. aeruginosa and coagulase negative Staphylococcus (in 42 (33%), 36 (29%), and 25 (20%) patients, respectively); see Table2for all microbiological findings.</s><s>Three patients (2%) had growth of extended spectrum beta-lactamase (ESBL)-producing bacteria in BALF</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>2,5,14Not surprisingly, P. aeruginosa, and other Gram-negative bacteria, were significantly more frequent in patients with cystic fibrosis.</s><s>The fact that the study participants underwent varying numbers of bronchoscopies may result in overrepresentation of individual microbes.</s><s>However, by presenting the TA B L E 3 Microbiological findings in BALF from patients with and without symptoms of lung infection</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>data as the proportion of patients with the microbiological finding,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>we have tried to avoid bias.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Gram-negative bacteria were more common among patients</cell><cell></cell><cell>No</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>receiving tacrolimus. However, this association was confounded by</cell><cell>Grouped microbio-</cell><cell>infection</cell><cell>Signs of infection</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>a high proportion of patients with cystic fibrosis receiving tacroli-</cell><cell>logical findings</cell><cell>n (%)</cell><cell>n (%)</cell><cell>P-value</cell></row><row><cell>mus. The total number of infection episodes did not significantly</cell><cell>Gram-positive</cell><cell>70 (44)</cell><cell>41 (36)</cell><cell>0.20</cell></row><row><cell>differ between patients receiving tacrolimus compared to ciclospo-</cell><cell>bacteria</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>rin. In line with our data, Hachem et al and Zuchelman et al found</cell><cell>Gram-negative</cell><cell>64 (40)</cell><cell>48 (43)</cell><cell>0.71</cell></row><row><cell>no difference in frequency of infections depending on type of</cell><cell>bacteria</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>immunosuppression. 15,16</cell><cell>Yeast</cell><cell>30 (19)</cell><cell>36 (32)</cell><cell>0.01</cell></row><row><cell>The low prevalence of MDR bacteria in our study reflects that</cell><cell>Mold</cell><cell>43 (27)</cell><cell>28 (25)</cell><cell>0.41</cell></row><row><cell>Sweden still has a favorable situation regarding antimicrobial resis-</cell><cell>Virus</cell><cell>22 (14)</cell><cell>18 (16)</cell><cell>0.48</cell></row><row><cell>tance compared to most countries. In comparison, Kovatz et al de-</cell><cell cols="4">Samples from patients with positive microbiology and no infection (n</cell></row><row><cell>scribed a MRSA prevalence of 25% in lung transplant patients in the</cell><cell cols="4">total = 159) vs samples from patients with signs of lung infection (n</cell></row><row><cell>first post-operative year, 17 and Tebano et al 18 found MDR strains in</cell><cell cols="4">total = 113) within defined microbiological groups. Owing to bronchos-</cell></row><row><cell>respiratory samples in 90 of 179 lung transplanted patients (51%). In a recent publication, Rodrigo-Troyano et al 19 describes the serious</cell><cell cols="4">copies with several microbiological findings in BALF the figures do not sum up to 100%.</cell></row><row><cell>threat posed by Gram-negative MDR bacteria in respiratory infec-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>tions. In fact, management of MDR bacteria in solid organ trans-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>planted patients is a major issue of concern in most countries.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>21In our samples, most Gram-negative bacteria were susceptible to carbapenem treatment and no MDR Gram-positive bacteria were found.Thus, our results indicate that the peri-operative antibiotic prophylaxis and later empiric antibiotic therapy at present not necessarily has to include specific targeting of MDR bacteria in Swedish lung transplant patients.Candida dominated in BALF-cultures the first post-operative month.In line with our data, Kovats et al17report a high Candida burden the first months after LTx. Ca</s><s> present in 32% of all samples with concomitant signs of lung infection, but only 15% had Candida as a single pathogen.All had signs of tracheobronchitis, which corresponds to an incidence of Candida tracheobronchitis of 12%, assuming that Candida was the causative pathogen.This number is high compared to a study on 384 heart and/or lung transplant recipients, where an overall incidence of invasive Candida infections of 8.3% was described, of which tracheobronchitis represented 38% and pneumonia 3.1%.21However,</s><s>a broad antimicrobial postoperative treatment the first month after LTx may cause negative bacterial BALF cultures and promote Candida dominance in lung infections in our study.</s></p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACK N OWLED G EM ENTS</head><p><s>We wish to thank the staff at the transplantation and bronchoscopy units in Lund and Gothenburg for assistance with patient inclusion,</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D I SCLOS U R E S</head><p><s>The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare in relation to the material presented.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AUTH O R CO NTR I B UTI O N S</head><p><s>ASA planned the study, compiled data, performed statistical calculations, and wrote the manuscript.</s><s>In accordance with editorial policies</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The registry of the International Society for heart and lung transplantation: thirty-third adult lung and heart-lung transplant report-2016; focus theme: primary diagnostic indications for transplant</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Yusen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Dipchand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Heart Lung Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1170" to="1184" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bacterial and fungal pneumonias after lung transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Campos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Caramori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Teixeira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transplant Proc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="822" to="824" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incidence of nosocomial pneumonia and risk of recurrence after antimicrobial therapy in critically ill lung and heart-lung transplant patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dudau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Camous</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Marchand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Infections after lung transplantation: time of occurrence, sites, and microbiologic etiologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Yun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Jo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Korean J Intern Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="506" to="514" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Early and late infections in lung transplantation patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Parada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sepulveda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transplant Proc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical spectrum of gram-positive infections in lung transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Valentine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Walker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transpl Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="424" to="431" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Breakpoint tables for interpretation of MICs and zonediameters. Version 8.0</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.eucast.org" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The European Committee on Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018-03-01">2018. March 1. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Manual of Clinical Microbiology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>ASM Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multidrug-resistant, extensively drug-resistant and pandrug-resistant bacteria: an international expert proposal for interim standard definitions for acquired resistance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Magiorakos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Srinivasan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Carey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Microbiol Infect</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="268" to="281" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prospective evaluation of a novel multiplex real-time PCR assay for detection of fifteen respiratory pathogens-duration of symptoms significantly affects detection rate</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Brittain-Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Westin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Olofsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Virol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="267" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High prevalence of dihydropteroate synthase mutations in Pneumocystis jirovecii isolated from patients with Pneumocystis pneumonia in South Africa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Dini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Du Plessis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Frean</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2016" to="2021" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Revision of the 1996 working formulation for the standardization of nomenclature in the diagnosis of lung rejection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Fishbein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Snell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Heart Lung Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1229" to="1242" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lung-enriched organisms and aberrant bacterial and fungal respiratory microbiota after lung transplant</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Charlson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Diamond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bittinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">186</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="536" to="545" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pneumonia after lung transplantation in the RESITRA Cohort: a multicenter prospective study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aguilar-Guisado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Givalda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ussetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1989" to="1996" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A randomized controlled trial of tacrolimus versus cyclosporine after lung transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hachem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Yusen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chakinala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Heart Lung Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1012" to="1018" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cyclosporine A versus tacrolimus in combination with mycophenolate mofetil and steroids as primary immunosuppression after lung transplantation: one-year results of a 2-center prospective randomized trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zuckermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Reichenspurner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Birsan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="891" to="900" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Airway pathogens during the first year after lung transplantation: a single-center experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Kovats</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Sütto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Muraközy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transplant Proc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1290" to="1291" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epidemiology and risk factors of multidrug-resistant bacteria in respiratory samples after lung transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tebano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Geneve</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transpl Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="22" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The respiratory threat posed by multidrug resistant Gram-negative bacteria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rodrigo-Troyano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Sibila</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Respirology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1288" to="1299" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Management of multidrug resistant Gram-negative bacilli infections in solid organ transplant recipients: SET/GESITRA-SEIMC/REIPI recommendations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Aguado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fernandez-Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transplant Rev (Orlando)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trends in invasive disease due to Candida species following heart and lung transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Schaenman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rosso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Austin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transpl Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="112" to="121" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Infectious complications of lung transplantation. Impact of cystic fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Flume</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Egan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Paradowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">149</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1601" to="1607" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Infectious complications in heart-lung transplantation. Analysis of 200 episodes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kramer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Starnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch Intern Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2010" to="2016" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of time-dependent risks for infection, rejection, and death after pulmonary transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bando</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Paradis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Komatsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="106" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of donor lung organisms on post-lung transplant pneumonia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Bonde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Patel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Borja</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Heart Lung Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="105" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of positive perioperative donor and recipient respiratory bacterial cultures on early post-transplant outcomes in lung transplant recipients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Howell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Paciullo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transpl Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e12760</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microbiological findings in bronchoalveolar lavage fluid from lung transplant patients in Sweden</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stjärne Aspelund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hammarström</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Inghammar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transpl Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e12973</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/tid.12973</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1111/tid.12973" />
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
