<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Thrombus aspiration in STEMI revisited: impact on coronary microcirculation?</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-06-17">17 June 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Georg</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fröhlich</surname></persName>
							<email>georg.froehlich@gmx.at</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Benjamin Franklin</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Benjamin Franklin</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ulf</forename><surname>Landmesser</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Benjamin Franklin</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Thrombus aspiration in STEMI revisited: impact on coronary microcirculation?</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-06-17">17 June 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F3E9F0402846AC035F6C9752F03FE6D8</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1136/openhrt-2015-000274</idno>
					<note type="submission">Accepted 5 June 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:12+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Fröhlich GM, Landmesser U</term>
					<term>Thrombus aspiration in STEMI revisited: impact on coronary microcirculation?</term>
					<term>Open Heart 2015;2:e000274</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>In this issue of Open Heart, Hoole et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> present the IMPACT trial.</s><s>The authors investigate the effect of thrombus aspiration (TA) on changes in microvascular function during primary percutaneous coronary intervention (PPCI) for ST elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI).</s><s>However, no difference between the TA group and the control group receiving balloon angioplasty first line could be verified.</s><s>This is a timely topic indeed, since the impact of TA on coronary microcirculation was an important rationale to suggest prognostic benefits in patients with STEMI in the past.</s></p><p><s>Early data from smaller and medium-sized randomised controlled trials (RCT) fuelled substantial enthusiasm about the concept of coronary thrombectomy with a view to reduce the thrombus burden, and avoid distal embolisation and consecutive 'no reflow' in PPCI. <ref type="bibr">2 3</ref> Of note, 'no reflow' following PPCI has been observed frequently in this patient cohort. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>This phenomenon has been closely associated with microvascular obstruction and increased myocardial infarct size, with worse adverse clinical outcome. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref></s><s>imilarly, dislodged debris from the culprit lesion, consisting of conglomerates of platelets and neutrophil granulocytes, may congest the microvasculature and deteriorate the 'no reflow'. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s>This is also a feature of the reperfusion injury (RI), which occurs after restoration of blood flow in the infarcted vessel. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s>Notably, this RI has been estimated to account for up to 50% of the final infarct size, and efforts to mitigate the RI and 'no reflow' appear therefore as an appealing therapeutic approach. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s>nfortunately, more recent larger RCTs investigating manual thrombectomy in the setting of PPCI yielded rather disappointing results.</s><s>Earlier this year, the largest RCT in this field was published. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>More than 10 000 patients referred for PPCI were randomised to receive TA or balloon angioplasty followed by stenting. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>Neither the primary composite end point of cardiovascular death, cardiogenic shock, New York Heart Association (NYHA) class IV or recurrent myocardial infarction nor cardiovascular death after 6 months were improved by TA. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> Notably, 87% of patients had a significant thrombus burden. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>Some concern was raised over a slightly increased stroke rate in the TA group, however, very few events were observed in this patient cohort. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>hrombectomy was also tested on top of intracoronary abciximab (glycoprotein, GPIIb/IIIa inhibition) administration in the INFUSE-AMI trial. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref></s><s>While abciximab reduced the infarct size as assessed by cardiac MRI, this was not confirmed for thrombectomy. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref></s><s>everal other strategies to reduce distal embolisation and microvascular obstruction were investigated, mostly in smaller pilot trials.</s><s>Sezer et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> suggested applying low-dose streptokinase after PPCI to open the microvasculature and improve microvascular function.</s><s>They repeated coronary angiography 2 days after the index event, and reassessed the coronary flow reserve and the index of microvascular resistance.</s><s>Importantly, all outcome measures of microvascular function were significantly improved in the streptokinase group as compared to the control group.</s><s>After 6 months, there was no difference in left ventricular function between the study groups. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref></s><s>However, this was a pilot study with a limited sample size of 40 patients, so no definitive conclusions could be drawn. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref></s><s>he evaluation of the microvasculature by measuring the index of microvascular resistance and coronary flow are well established surrogate parameters to assess microvascular function, and are closely associated to outcome.</s><s>Cuculi et al 10 assessed microvascular resistance and coronary flow reserve as well as microvascular obstruction on cardiac MRI in patients undergoing primary PCI.</s><s>The authors observed a severely dysfunctional microvasculature in those patients with evidence of microvascular obstruction. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref></s><s>The same authors could demonstrate that an improvement in microcirculatory function within 24 h after PPCI is associated with improved left ventricular ejection fraction at 6 months. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref></s><s>These results support the concept that distal embolisation and microvascular obstruction are relevant factors for long-term outcome after STEMI.</s></p><p><s>As discussed above, the more recent large RCTs have failed to demonstrate a difference in clinical outcome between manual TA and first line balloon angioplasty in PPCI (table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>Hoole and colleagues sought to investigate alterations in microvascular resistance during PPCI.</s><s>Selected surrogate parameters might perhaps be more sensitive than hard clinical end points to detect any benefits favouring the principle of thrombectomy.</s><s>The authors found that manipulation within the culprit vessel will lead to distal embolisation and affect the microvasculature, regardless of whether a thrombectomy device or a balloon inflation is used first.</s><s>In patients with a relatively low index of microcirculatory resistance (IMR) &lt;32 (where 12 or lower is considered as being normal) at baseline, the authors noted a significant increase of IMR after the first device was used. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref></s><s>This group may represent the patient subset with only modest thrombus burden and little distal embolisation per se, as these patients did have improved left ventricular function at follow-up.</s><s>This finding might favour the idea of direct stenting or the use of mesh covered stents such as the MGuard device, rather than lesion preparation. <ref type="bibr">12 13</ref></s><s>n essence, patients with only modest thrombus burden might not benefit from TA at all, or TA might even be harmful in this subset of STEMI patients.</s></p><p><s>A limitation of the present study is its small sample size, which does not allow the detection of any differences in terms of clinical end points.</s><s>There was a trend towards a superior left ventricular ejection fraction in the thrombectomy group, as well as an improved early and late microvascular obstruction (MVO), but again, the sample size was not sufficient to address such end points.</s><s>Moreover, only patients with restored blood flow (≥thrombolysis in myocardial infarction (TIMI) I) after wiring of the culprit vessel could be included.</s><s>Patients with TIMI 0 flow and high thrombus burden after wiring were excluded.</s><s>But these patients, in particular, might yield the greatest benefit from TA.</s><s>Another limitation is the exclusive use of clopidogrel, while ticagrelor and prasugrel might also have had a favourable impact on spontaneous restoration of blood flow before PPCI and microvasculature.</s></p><p><s>Although the available data from most RCTs discourage the regular use of TA, it is important to keep a balanced perspective, given the fact that TA is only one intervention that is part of the complex PPCI approach.</s><s>In general, only a handful of interventions that are commonly considered to be beneficial (eg, balloon angioplasty before stenting) translate into an improved clinical outcome.</s><s>From our experience, patients with significant thrombus burden might still benefit.</s></p><p><s>In conclusion, the authors present an interesting study that failed to demonstrate any benefit on coronary microvascular function of TA over sole balloon angioplasty in PPCI.</s><s>The results are in line with data from recent large RCTs.</s><s>The growing data in this field do not support the routine use of TA in PPCI, which will rather be limited to certain indications with large thrombus burden.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Selected randomised trials to investigate thrombectomy versus first line balloon angioplasty in patients undergoing PPCI</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Number of</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Study/year</cell><cell>patients</cell><cell>Main conclusion</cell></row><row><cell>TOTAL 2015 7</cell><cell>10 732</cell><cell>No difference in cardiovascular death, recurrent myocardial infarction, cardiogenic shock,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>or NYHA class IV heart failure within 180 days but increased risk of stroke at 30 days</cell></row><row><cell>TASTE 2014 14</cell><cell>7244</cell><cell>No difference in death, or death, rehospitalisation for MI or ST after 12 months</cell></row><row><cell>TROFI 2013 15</cell><cell>141</cell><cell>Similar flow and stent area, as assessed by OCT</cell></row><row><cell>EXPORT 2008 16</cell><cell>249</cell><cell>No differences at 30 days in the rate of major adverse cardiac and cerebral events</cell></row><row><cell>NONSTOP 2004 17</cell><cell>258</cell><cell>No difference in no-reflow or slow flow phenomena</cell></row><row><cell>PIHRATE 2010 18</cell><cell>196</cell><cell>No difference in ST resolution 60 min after PPCI, no difference in mortality at 6 months</cell></row><row><cell>ITTI 2012 19</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>No difference in 6-month MACE rate (death, reinfarction, target lesion revascularisation</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>and stroke)</cell></row><row><cell>MUSTELA 2012 20</cell><cell>208</cell><cell>In patients with high thrombus load, TA yielded better postprocedural STR and reduced</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>MVO at 3 months, but was not associated with a reduction in infarct size and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>transmurality</cell></row><row><cell>INFUSE-AMI 2012 8</cell><cell>452</cell><cell>In patients with large anterior STEMI undergoing PPCI with bivalirudin, infarct size at</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>30 days was significantly reduced by bolus intracoronary abciximab delivered to the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>infarct lesion site but not by manual aspiration thrombectomy</cell></row><row><cell>VAMPIRE 2008 2</cell><cell>355</cell><cell>Reduced MACE rate after 8 months in the TA group</cell></row><row><cell>TAPAS 2008 3</cell><cell>1,071</cell><cell>Improved ST-segment resolution and clinical outcome</cell></row></table><note><p><s>MACE, major adverse cardiac event; MI, myocardial infarction; MOV, microvascular obstruction; NYHA, New York Heart Association; OCT, optical coherence tomography; PPCI, primary percutaneous coronary intervention; STEMI, ST elevation myocardial infarction; STR, ST-segment resolution; TA, thrombus aspiration.</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Fröhlich GM, Landmesser U.Open Heart 2015;2:e000274. doi:10.1136/openhrt-2015-000274 Open Heart on May 17, 2022 by guest. Protected by copyright. http://openheart.bmj.com/ Open Heart: first published as 10.1136/openhrt-2015-000274 on 17 June 2015. Downloaded from</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">on May 17, 2022 by guest. Protected by copyright. http://openheart.bmj.com/ Open Heart: first published as 10.1136/openhrt-2015-000274 on 17 June 2015. Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Contributors GMF drafted the manuscript and UL revised it.</s></p><p><s>Competing interests UL: honoraria or research grants by Orbus Neich, Terumo and St Jude.</s></p><p><s>Provenance and peer review Commissioned; internally peer reviewed.</s></p><p><s>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work noncommercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial.</s><s>See: http:// creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Serial assessment of the index of microcirculatory resistance during primary percutaneous coronary intervention comparing manual aspiration catheter thrombectomy with balloon angioplasty (IMPACT study): a randomised controlled pilot study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hoole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jaworski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/openhrt-2015-000238</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Open Heart</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e000238</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Upfront thrombus aspiration in primary coronary intervention for patients with ST-segment elevation acute myocardial infarction: report of the VAMPIRE (VAcuuM asPIration thrombus REmoval) trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ikari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sakurada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kozuma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcin.2008.06.004</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JACC Cardiovasc Interv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="424" to="431" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thrombus aspiration during primary percutaneous coronary intervention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Svilaas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vlaar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Van Der Horst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/NEJMoa0706416</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">358</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="557" to="567" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coronary no-reflow phenomenon: from the experimental laboratory to the cardiac catheterization laboratory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Rezkalla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kloner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/ccd.21715</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Catheter Cardiovasc Interv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="950" to="957" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prevention and treatment of microvascular obstruction-related myocardial injury and coronary no-reflow following percutaneous coronary intervention: a systematic approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jaffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Strauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcin.2010.05.004</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JACC Cardiovasc Interv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="695" to="704" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Myocardial reperfusion injury: looking beyond primary PCI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Frohlich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Meier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/eurheartj/eht090</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1714" to="1722" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Randomized trial of primary PCI with or without routine manual thrombectomy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jolly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cairns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yusuf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/NEJMoa1415098</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">372</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1389" to="1398" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intracoronary abciximab and aspiration thrombectomy in patients with large anterior myocardial infarction: the INFUSE-AMI randomized trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Maehara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Witzenbichler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jama.2012.421</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JAMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">307</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1817" to="1826" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intracoronary streptokinase after primary percutaneous coronary intervention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sezer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Oflaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Goren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/NEJMoa054374</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">356</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1823" to="1834" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of microvascular obstruction on the assessment of coronary flow reserve, index of microcirculatory resistance, and fractional flow reserve after ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cuculi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Maria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Meier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jacc.2014.07.987</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1894" to="1904" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reference interval for the index of coronary microvascular resistance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Solberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ragnarsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kvarsnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4244/EIJV9I9A181</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eurointervention</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1069" to="1075" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prospective, Randomized, Multicenter Evaluation of a Polyethylene Terephthalate Micronet Mesh-Covered Stent (MGuard) in ST-Segment Elevation Myocardial Infarction: the MASTER Trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Abizaid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Silber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jacc.2012.09.004</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1975" to="1984" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of direct stenting on outcome of patients with ST-elevation myocardial infarction transferred for primary percutaneous coronary intervention (from the EUROTRANSFER registry)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dziewierz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Siudak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Rakowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/ccd.25266</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Catheter Cardiovasc Interv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="925" to="931" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thrombus aspiration during ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Frobert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Lagerqvist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Olivecrona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/NEJMoa1308789</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">369</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1587" to="1597" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Randomized study to assess the effect of thrombus aspiration on flow area in patients with ST-elevation myocardial infarction: an optical frequency domain imaging study-TROFI trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Onuma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Thuesen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Geuns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/eurheartj/ehs456</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1050" to="1060" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic primary aspiration in acute myocardial percutaneous intervention: a multicentre randomised controlled trial of the export aspiration catheter</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Chevalier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gilard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Lang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4244/EIJV4I2A40</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eurointervention</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="222" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lack of efficacy of intracoronary thrombus aspiration before coronary stenting in patients with acute myocardial infarction: a multicenter randomized trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kunii</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kijima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Araki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">245A</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thrombus aspiration followed by direct stenting: a novel strategy of primary percutaneous coronary intervention in ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction. Results of the Polish-Italian-Hungarian RAndomized ThrombEctomy Trial (PIHRATE Trial)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dudek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Mielecki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Burzotta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ahj.2010.07.024</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">160</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="966" to="972" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Additive benefit of glycoprotein IIb/ IIIa inhibition and adjunctive thrombus aspiration during primary coronary intervention: results of the Initial Thrombosuction and Tirofiban Infusion (ITTI) trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Chiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ijcard.2010.10.129</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">156</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="174" to="179" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A prospective randomized trial of thrombectomy versus no thrombectomy in patients with ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction and thrombus-rich lesions: MUSTELA (MUltidevice Thrombectomy in Acute ST-Segment ELevation Acute Myocardial Infarction) trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>De Carlo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Aquaro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Palmieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcin.2012.08.013</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JACC Cardiovasc Interv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1223" to="1230" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
