<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Allergen and allergy risk assessment, allergen management, and gaps in the European Food Information Regulation (FIR)* Are allergic consumers adequately protected by current statutory food safety and labelling regulations?</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Imke</forename><surname>Reese</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Nutritional Counselling and Therapy</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Allergology, Munich</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Holzhauser</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Allergology Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Paul-Ehrlich-Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Langen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sabine</forename><surname>Schnadt</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">German Allergy and Asthma Association</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Mönchengladbach</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sabine</forename><surname>Dölle</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Dermatology, Venereology and Allergology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité Allergy Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Charité University Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jörg</forename><surname>Kleine-Tebbe</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Westend Allergy and Asthma Centre</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Raithel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Dermatology, Venereology and Allergology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité Allergy Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Charité University Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Medical Clinic 1</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Gastroenterology</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Functional Tissue Diagnostics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Interventional Endoscopy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Erlangen University Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Erlangen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Torsten</forename><surname>Zuberbier</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Dermatology, Venereology and Allergology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité Allergy Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Charité University Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stefan</forename><surname>Vieths</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Allergology Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Paul-Ehrlich-Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Langen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">DGAKI German Society for Allergology and Clinical Immunology (Deutsche Gesellschaft für Allergologie und klinische Immunologie</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Allergen and allergy risk assessment, allergen management, and gaps in the European Food Information Regulation (FIR)* Are allergic consumers adequately protected by current statutory food safety and labelling regulations?</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">37C1859DCEEE295528663A9194D4057C</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s40629-015-0066-0</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted May 11, 2015 Accepted May 26, 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:12+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Individuals su ering from IgE-mediated food allergies are obliged to systematically eliminate the culprit allergen from their diet.</s><s>To support allergic consumers in avoiding food allergens to make informed and safe purchasing choices, the European Union (EU) Food Information Regulation (FIR) imposes a requirement to label the 13 most common allergenic foods (food groups) as ingredients in pre-packed and non-pre-packed foods.</s></p><p><s>e as yet unregulated labelling of unintended presence of allergens has lead to a widespread use of precautionary allergen labelling (PAL) -despite established allergen management in many companies.</s><s>is PAL signi cantly hampers making a safe food choice, or renders it largely unfeasible, since it is not possible to estimate the actual extent to which allergens are present in a product.</s><s>Not only food-allergic consumers, but also the food industry, physicians, dieticians/nutritionists, as well as food regulators and law enforcement o cers would bene t from a standardized labelling regulation for unintended presence of allergens.</s></p><p><s>e following position paper highlights the chances of such a regulation on the basis of avail-</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Key words</head><p><s>food allergylabellingprecautionary labellingun intended presence of allergens -allergen risk assessmentreference doses</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>able data and the analytical methods for detecting allergenic components in the context of e ective allergen management.</s><s>On the basis of evidencebased allergen and allergy-risk assessment, the use of PAL should be restricted to only those allergens that are unavoidable and which represent an unacceptable risk for allergic consumers, e. g., when allergens are present at levels that exceed a clinically meaningful reference dose or in the case of unintended presence of particulate allergens (e. g., nuts or sesame seeds).</s></p><p><s>Cite this as Reese I, Holzhauser T, Schnadt S, Dölle S, Kleine-Tebbe J, Raithel M, Worm M, Zuberbier T, Vieths S. Allergen and allergy risk assessment, allergen management, and gaps in the European Food Information Regulation (FIR) -Are allergic consumers adequately protected by current statutory food safety and labelling regulations?</s><s>Allergo J Int 2015;24:180-4 DOI: 10.1007/s40629-015-0066-0</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p><s>Causal treatments o ering the prospect of a cure for food allergies are still lacking today.</s><s>erefore, the only treatment option to date -in the case of a known trigger -is the temporary or life-long avoidance of food allergens.</s><s>ose at risk of severe reactions need to keep their emergency medication ready to use at all times in order to be able to self-medicate in the event of the inadvertent intake of the culprit food.</s></p><p><s>In order to enable a ected individuals to make informed and safe purchasing choices, the European Union has responded as follows: existing labelling regulations for pre-packed foods under the Food Information Regulation (FIR) have been improved and additionally extended to food sold loose (nonpre-packed foods).</s><s>However, the current FIR only regulates labelling of ingredients, but does not give information on unintented presence of allergens.</s><s>us, the food-allergic consumer remains unable to identify whether or not unintended presence of allergens is present in relevant amounts.</s><s>Food manu facturers can only implement e ective allergen management once allergen risk has been quanti ed and reliable threshold values/reference doses are set.</s><s>e reference dose indicates the amount of protein in an allergenic food below which most individuals with food allergies will not develop an objective reaction.</s></p><p><s>In contrast, the now widespread practice of stating possible unintended exposure to allergens, also called trace labelling ("may contain traces of ...") or cross-contamination, creates considerable uncertainty among a ected individuals.</s><s>e term "trace" in this context refers to the presence of allergens that have been unintentionally included in the relevant food during production, transport, or storage and which are not considered an ingredient.</s><s>However, neither the presence nor the absence of a "may contain ..." label permits reliable risk assessment by the allergic consumers in terms of whether or not the product is "safe".</s><s>What is more important, the term "traces" in relation to allergenic foods is not de ned, making it impossible to assess the amount and consequentlythe risk.</s><s>For this reason, the term "traces" is deliberately avoided in the following paper, and replaced with the term "unintended presence of allergens".</s></p><p><s>e "Food Allergy and Anaphylaxis" working group of the European Academy of Allergology and Clinical Immunology (EAACI) addressed the problem of unintented presence of allergens in an extensive position paper at the end of 2014 <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>Based on this European position paper, the "Food Allergy" working group of the German Society for Allergology and Clinical Immunology (DGAKI) now intends to increase awareness of this important issue, too.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scant data on unintended presence of allergens</head><p><s>Unintended presence of allergens in a food can occur in many ways during the entire production process -resulting from ingredients itself, processing or packaging.</s><s>Only scant data on the prevalence and extent of cross-contamination of this kind are available.</s><s>Tests on pre-packed foods have been published in the annual reports of the food monitoring body of the German federal state of Baden-Württemberg since 2005 [2, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">5]</ref>.</s><s>ese reports show that unlabelled allergens were detected in 5 %-18 % of products tested.</s><s>e majority of cases involved non-labelled unintended presence of allergens rather than ingredients.</s><s>Since 2009, only those ndings that exceeded a provisional, internally set assessment value have been included in the statistics on positive samples. is partially explains the marked fall in "positive" samples to 5 %-11 % in the years since 2009 compared with 2005-2008 (13 %-17 %).</s><s>In December 2014, the internal action levels for allergen monitoring were revised and adjusted under a resolution of the German Working Group of Food Allergo J Int 2015; 24: 180-4</s></p><p><s>Chemistry Experts (Arbeitskreis Lebensmittelchemischer Sachverständiger, ALS) and the Working Group of Experts in the Field of Food Hygiene and Animal-Derived Food (Arbeitskreis der auf dem Gebiet der Lebensmittelhygiene und der vom Tier stammenden Lebensmittel tätigen Sachverständigen, ALTS).</s><s>Values were based on the reference doses published by Taylor and co-workers <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[7]</ref> for the Voluntary Incidental Trace Allergen Labeling 2.0 (VITAL 2.0) programme (see below).</s><s>e VITAL programme has already started determining references doses on the basis of evidence-based risk assessment in Australia and New Zealand in 2007.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Information for allergic consumers lacking</head><p><s>In most cases positive ndings result from unintended presence of allergens.</s><s>Although these are known to be a health risk for allergic individuals, due to the lack of a legal basis the latter are not able to gain information on a ected products.</s><s>Not least for this reason a legal framework is urgently required.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Precautionary labelling only recommended in cases of relevant risk</head><p><s>On the one hand not all precautionary allergen labeling on products available in the market will represent a risk for food-allergic individuals.</s><s>e allergen management strategies of many -but not allfood manufacturers already exclude unintended presence of allergens in quantities that would be relevant for the majority of allergic consumers.</s><s>However, due to the lack of legal framework and/or reference doses, a zero-tolerance approach is currently adopted.</s></p><p><s>is results in an abundance of precautio nary labels, mostly for product liability reasons.</s><s>On the other hand, particularly in the case of unintended presence of particulate allergens, these can occur in considerable amounts su cient to elicit severe allergic reactions.</s></p><p><s>erefore, there is an urgent need for action to establish uniform standards for the labelling of unintended presence of allergens, thereby developing a risk-based statement.</s><s>Only then food manufacturers will be able to implement an e ective allergen management and allergic consumers can make informed and safe purchasing choices.</s><s>Eventually precautionary allergen labelling relating to unintended presence of allergens would only appear on those products carrying a relevant risk.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The need for education/training is urgent</head><p><s>It is not only the food-allergic consumers themselves that need to be informed, how to interpret the European Food Information Regulation, food manufacturers and providers should also receive sound training in e ective allergen management.</s></p><p><s>In addition to issues relating to compliance with the relevant threshold values, this includes: personnel being made aware of the subject, providing comprehensive information on the raw materials used, ensuring adequate production plants and a highly-developed production process, providing precise and reliable information for the allergic consumer, updating relevant information, as well as guaranteeing an ongoing documentation process.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>De ning threshold values is crucial</head><p><s>It is impossible to provide a 100 % protection from all types of allergic reactions for all allergic individuals or allergic consumers(zero risk) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[8]</ref>.</s><s>De ning threshold values on the basis of evidence-based risk assessment represents a considerable challenge due to the variability of clinical reactions to di erent allergens and amounts of allergens.</s><s>Nevertheless, a systematic and risk-based approach of this kind is crucial to protect the allergic consumer preventively, and to ensure a high quality of life of those a ected.</s><s>Taking the Australian VITAL concept as a starting point, the EAACI's Food Allergy and Anaphylaxis Guidelines Group, in a spirit of pragmatism, has proposed to use already published risk-based threshold values as a basis for e ective allergen management in food manufacturing.</s><s>reshold values were calculated on the basis of provocation data <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">10]</ref>.</s><s>While it was possible to determine reference doses for peanut, milk, eggs, and hazelnut at which 99 % of allergic individuals were protected (ED01 = eliciting dose for 1 % of allergic individuals), the reference doses available for soy, wheat, cashew, mustard, lupin, sesame seed, shrimp, and sh provides protection for 95 % of a ected allergic individuals (ED05 = eliciting dose for 5 % of allergic individuals) (Tab.</s><s>1).</s><s>To date, only clinical threshold data for celery and other edible nuts are lacking.</s></p><p><s>ese data are currently being gathered in research projects (e. g., integrated Approaches to Food Allergen and Allergy Risk Management, iFAAM; contract number 312147) and should be available in the near future.</s><s>According to the available data, 95 %-99 % of allergic individuals would tolerate foods that are assessed with the reference doses proposed by VITAL 2.0.</s><s>e reference doses obtained in clinical investigations (clinical provocation testing for diagnostic purposes, treatment studies on oral tolerance induction, and, to an extent, explicit threshold value determination) were carried out under controlled study conditions.</s><s>However augmentation factors and matrix e ects in everyday life may alter individual allergen thresholds.</s><s>ese aspects are also the subject of current research projects, such as iFAAM and the TRACE Peanut Study.</s></p><p><s>It is also important to point out that the reference doses discussed here and already implemented in Australia only apply when unintended presence of allergens is distributed homogenously.</s><s>In case of a risk of particulate allergen exposure which cannot be reliably identi ed by analytical methods due to limitations of sampling, precautionary allergen labelling continues to be necessary.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analytical methods to detect allergenic components</head><p><s>Allergen risk assessment is an integral part of e ective allergen risk management in industrial food manufacture.</s><s>Risk assessment depends on the one hand on the availability of appropriate clinically validated eliciting thresholds, below which the majority of allergic individuals are not expected to experience an allergic reaction (see below).</s><s>On the other hand, manufacturers require suitable analytical methods to identify and quantify allergenic cross-contamination during the course of food production.</s><s>e same analytical tools then serve to verify the e ciency of measures targeted at allergen reduction, such as cleaning plant and equipment between product changeovers <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[11]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA), which detect proteins and sometimes also allergens, are the most commonly used tests.</s><s>Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) tests, which detect DNA sequences in allergenic foods, are an established alternative.</s><s>Both techniques have method-related advantages and disadvantages in terms of their analytical sensitivity, speci city, and robustness depending on the allergenic food to be detected, the composition of the food (matrix), and its technological processing.</s><s>Modern mass spectroscopy methods are able to detect peptides in allergenic foods.</s><s>However, these techniques are less well established and evaluated compared with ELISA and PCR tests, and are also costly.</s></p><p><s>Compared with calculated threshold values such as reference doses, all available tests should be sensitive enough to analytically verify the presence of allergenic components .</s><s>Due to the varying degree to which analytical methods are susceptible to effects arising from the food matrix and food technological processing, suitable reference materials are required in order to obtain comparability between quantitative results <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[12]</ref>.</s><s>e current challenge in terms of allergen analysis is to keep on developing methods aiming at quantitatively verifying threshold values, as well as to have validated reference materials available.</s><s>erefore the availability of relevant threshold values is essential for the further development of detection methods and reference materials.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>Despite gaps in our knowledge and the current problems, the advantages of harmonized regulations on labelling of unintended presence of allergens predominate for everyone concerned (allergic consumers, the food industry, physicians/nutritional specialists, law enforcement o cers).</s><s>Compared with risk assessments in other elds, the topic of allergens present in foods has the advantage that no data from animal models are required.</s><s>e available data are based on the results of controlled provocation testing in allergic individuals.</s><s>e reference doses proposed should, for the present, form the basis for the establishment of threshold values for unintended presence of allergens.</s><s>e vast majority of allergic individuals (99 % or 95 %, respectively) would bene t if the determined reference doses were implemented, as in the VITAL concept.</s><s>e use of precautionary allergen labelling should be carried out exclusively on the basis of evidence-based allergen risk assessment.</s><s>us, the application of precautionary allergen labelling should be restricted to those cases where unintended allergen exposure exceeds the reference dose or is unavoidable, such as in the case of particulate allergens.</s><s>In the view of the authors, a consensus on an acceptable residual risk, as well as a discussion on the</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Tab. 1 :*</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Reference doses for allergenic foods (modi ed from [1]) Eliciting dose for 1 % of food allergic population (ED01) **Eliciting dose for 5 % of food allergic population (ED05) ***Provisional dataAllergo J Int 2015; 24: 180-4</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Allergo J Int 2015; 24: 180-4</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Position paper Allergen and allergy risk assessment, allergen management</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Allergo J Int 2015; 24: 180-4Position paper Allergen and allergy risk assessment, allergen management</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>grade of severity (of a clinical reaction) which should be avoided by a threshold value is desirable.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dr. Imke Reese</head><p><s>Ansprengerstr. 19 80803 Munich, Germany E-Mail: info@ernaehrung-allergologie.de</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Con ict of interests</head><p><s>The authors declare that there are no con icts of interest.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cite this as</head><p><s>Reese I, Holzhauser T, Schnadt S, Dölle S, Kleine-Tebbe J, Raithel M, Worm M, Zuberbier T, Vieths S. Allergen and allergy risk assessment, allergen management, and gaps in the European Food Information Regulation (FIR) -Are allergic consumers adequately protected by current statutory food safety and labelling regulations?</s><s>Allergo J Int 2015;24:180-4 DOI: 10.1007/s40629-015-0066-0</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Protecting consumers with food allergies: understanding food consumption, meeting regulations and identifying unmet needs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Muraro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ho Mann-Sommergruber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Holzhauser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Poulsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gowland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Akdis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1464" to="1472" />
			<pubPlace>Allergy</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Überwachung von Lebensmitteln, Bedarfsgegenständen, Kosmetika, Trinkwasser und Futtermitteln -Jahresberichte</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005-2008</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Ministerium für Ernährung und Ländlichen Raum Baden Württemberg</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Ministerium für Ländlichen Raum, Ernährung und Verbraucherschutz; Überwachung Lebensmittel, Bedarfsgegenstände, Kosmetika, Trinkwasser</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Überwachung</forename><surname>Ministerium Für Ländlichen Raum Und Verbraucherschutz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lebensmittel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bedarfsgegenstände</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kosmetika</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Futtermittel</forename><surname>Trinkwasser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jahresberichte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010-2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Lebensmittel/ALS_ALTS/ALTS_Beschluesse_74_Arbeit-stagung_Dez_2014.pdf?__blob=publicationFile&amp;v=2</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Establishment of Reference Doses for residues of allergenic foods: report of the VITAL Expert Panel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Baumert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kruizinga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Remington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Crevel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brooke-Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Food Chem Toxicol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="17" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Can we de ne a tolerable level of risk in food allergy? Report from a EuroPrevall/UK Food Standards Agency workshop</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Madsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hattersley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Beyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Godefroy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Exp Allergy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Allergen reference doses for precautionary labeling (VITAL 2.0): clinical implications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Remington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Baumert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Crevel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Houben</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brooke-Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="156" to="164" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Translating reference doses into allergen management practice: Challenges for stakeholders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Crevel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Baumert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Luccioli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Baka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hattersley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Hourihane</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Food Chem Toxicol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="287" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pilot plant investigations on cleaning eciencies to reduce hazelnut cross-contamination in industrial manufacture of cookies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Roder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ibach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Baltruweit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Gruyters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Janise</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Suwelack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Food Prot</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2263" to="2271" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A multilaboratory evaluation of a clinically-validated incurred quality control material for analysis of allergens in food</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rigby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dainty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mackie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Immer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Food Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="36" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
