<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Local T/B cooperation in inflamed tissues is supported by T follicular helper-like cells</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-02-26">26 Feb 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Dana</forename><surname>Vu Van</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Chronic Immune Reactions</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">German Rheumatism Research Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">A Leibniz Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charite ´platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Molecular Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Robert Koch Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Nordufer 20</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Katja</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Beier</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Pediatric Pneumology and Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´University Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Augustenburger Platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lea-Jean</forename><surname>Pietzke</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Chronic Immune Reactions</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">German Rheumatism Research Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">A Leibniz Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charite ´platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Molecular Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Robert Koch Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Nordufer 20</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Maysun</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Al Baz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Chronic Immune Reactions</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">German Rheumatism Research Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">A Leibniz Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charite ´platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Molecular Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Robert Koch Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Nordufer 20</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Randi</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Feist</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Chronic Immune Reactions</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">German Rheumatism Research Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">A Leibniz Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charite ´platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Molecular Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Robert Koch Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Nordufer 20</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stephanie</forename><surname>Gurka</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Molecular Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Robert Koch Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Nordufer 20</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Eckard</forename><surname>Hamelmann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Children&apos;s Hospital of Ruhr University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Alexandrinenstrae 5</addrLine>
									<postCode>44791</postCode>
									<settlement>Bochum</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kroczek</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Molecular Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Robert Koch Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Nordufer 20</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Hutloff</surname></persName>
							<email>hutloff@drfz.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Chronic Immune Reactions</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">German Rheumatism Research Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">A Leibniz Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charite ´platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Molecular Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Robert Koch Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Nordufer 20</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Local T/B cooperation in inflamed tissues is supported by T follicular helper-like cells</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-02-26">26 Feb 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">187B56EDA9E7BA4588768608DD93EE9B</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1038/ncomms10875</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 16 Nov 2015 | Accepted 28 Jan 2016 |</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:13+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Autoimmune diseases and other inflammatory conditions are characterized by large lymphocytic tissue infiltrates in which T and B cells can be found in close contact.</s><s>Here, using a murine airway inflammation model, we compare antigen-specific T and B cells in lung tissue versus lung-draining lymph node.</s><s>In the lung we identify a B-cell population exhibiting a classical germinal centre phenotype without being organized into ectopic lymphoid tissue.</s><s>By contrast, classical CXCR5 þ Bcl-6 þ T follicular helper cells are not present.</s><s>Nevertheless, lung-infiltrating T cells exhibit follicular helper-like properties including the potential to provide help to naive B cells.</s><s>The lung tissue is also a survival niche for memory T and B cells remaining in residual peribronchial infiltrates after resolution of inflammation.</s><s>Collectively, this study shows the importance of T/B cooperation not only in lymph nodes but also in inflamed peripheral tissues for local antibody responses to infection and autoimmunity.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>L eukocytic infiltrates in peripheral tissues are frequently found in autoimmune conditions like rheumatoid arthritis, systemic lupus erythematosus, Sjo ¨gren syndrome and multiple sclerosis, but also in the lungs of asthma patients.</s><s>These infiltrates typically contain antigen-specific T and B cells, as well as different cell populations of the innate immune system, and contribute substantially to tissue destruction and immunopathology.</s><s>B cells produce (auto-) antibodies locally and also seem to play a role as antigen-presenting cells for T lymphocytes in the periphery.</s><s>T cells in turn produce proinflammatory cytokines, which attract tissue-destructive granulocytes and also affect non-lymphoid cells, for example, goblet cells to produce mucus in the case of airway inflammation.</s><s>However, an often neglected function of T cells in inflamed tissues is their potential to provide help to antigen-specific B cells.</s></p><p><s>This helper function of T cells is the major role of T follicular helper (TFH) cells, a specialized population of T cells in secondary lymphoid organs (SLOs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> .</s><s>This T-cell population is crucial for B-cell maturation and differentiation in the germinal centre (GC) response <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> .</s><s>Without TFH cells, no affinity-matured long-lived plasma cells and memory B cells are generated.</s><s>These two terminally differentiated B-cell populations are the basis for protective immunity; however, they can pose a major problem when producing autoreactive antibodies.</s><s>Therefore, TFH cells are an attractive target for the treatment of autoimmune and other inflammatory diseases.</s></p><p><s>Under certain conditions, SLO-like structures can develop in inflamed tissues.</s><s>They are known as 'ectopic lymphoid tissue' or as 'induced bronchus-associated lymphoid tissue' in the lungs <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> .</s><s>Ectopic lymphoid tissues represent highly ordered structures with separate T-and B-cell zones.</s><s>Another important characteristic is the presence of follicular dendritic cells (FDCs) similar to follicles in SLO.</s><s>Ectopic lymphoid tissues exhibit many features of SLO, including formation of germinal centres in which T and B cells cooperate <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> .</s></p><p><s>However, the development of ectopic lymphoid tissue in inflamed tissues is an exceptional case, which requires experimental settings with strong stimuli or other facilitators like a viral infection <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> .</s><s>In human autoimmune conditions, fully differentiated ectopic follicles are only rarely observed <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> .</s><s>Nevertheless, FDC-negative lymphocytic infiltrates contain T and B cells in very close contact raising the question whether T/B cooperation can also take place in infiltrates not exhibiting the features of ectopic lymphoid tissue.</s></p><p><s>To analyse the cooperation of antigen-specific T and B cells in inflamed tissues in more detail, we use a novel lung inflammation mouse model, which makes it possible to analyse and compare the interaction of antigen-specific T and B cell simultaneously in inflamed lung tissue, as well as in the lung-draining lymph nodes.</s><s>With this model we identify the inflamed lung tissue as the major reservoir of antigen-specific T and B cells.</s><s>The lung tissue does not only contain antigen-specific plasma cells but also a population of GC-like B cells.</s><s>In contrast, no classical CXCR5 þ Bcl-6 þ TFH cells are present in the lung.</s><s>However, we identify a population of lung-infiltrating helper T cells, which seem to take over the functions of TFH cells.</s><s>Finally, we show that the lung tissue is an important survival niche for antigen-specific memory T and B cells, which might be important for fast local secondary responses.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Antigen-specific T and B cells accumulate in lung tissue.</s><s>The low natural frequency of antigen-specific T and B cells makes it difficult to analyse their interaction in an inflammatory reaction.</s><s>Therefore, we developed an in vivo T/B cooperation system, in which ovalbumin (OVA)-specific T cells were co-transferred with nitrophenol (NP)-specific B cells into immunocompetent recipient mice (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>).</s><s>After adoptive transfer, recipient mice were challenged intranasally (i.n.) with an NP-OVA conjugate as antigen and lipopolysaccharide (LPS) as an adjuvant.</s><s>This system makes it possible to analyse antigenspecific T and B cells simultaneously in lung tissue and lungdraining lymph nodes, using the congenic markers Thy-1.1 and CD45.1 (in all subsequent figures, antigen-specific refers to cells gated on either CD4 þ Lin À Thy-1.</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">1 þ or CD19 þ Lin À CD45.2 À CD45.1 þ ).</formula><p><s>One to two days after antigen challenge, antigen-specific T and B cells accumulated in the lung-draining lymph nodes where they proliferated vigorously.</s><s>Although cells evenly distributed to all SLOs on transfer, no activated antigenspecific T and B cells were found in non-draining organs like the spleen.</s><s>In the lungs, activated antigen-specific T and B cells appeared around day 5 (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>After repeated antigen challenges, a stable population of lung-infiltrating T and B cells developed, which did not change much over time.</s><s>Therefore, we routinely analysed recipient mice on day 17 for antigen-specific T and B cells in the draining lymph nodes versus the inflamed lung.</s><s>At that time, more than 80% of all antigenspecific T and 60% of B cells were found in the lungs, identifying the inflamed tissue as the major reservoir of antigen-specific T and B cells (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Infiltrates harbour T and B cells in intimate contact.</s><s>After repeated i.n.</s><s>challenge with antigen, we observed the typical signs of chronic lung inflammation, such as appearance of large lymphocytic infiltrates and airway narrowing with increased mucus production (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a</ref>).</s><s>Immunohistological examination on day 17 revealed large lymphocytic clusters containing eosinophils and antigen-specific T cells located adjacent to antigen-specific B cells.</s><s>Under chronic inflammatory conditions, lymphocytic infiltrates can develop further into ectopic lymphoid tissue, characterized by the presence of FDC <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> .</s><s>Therefore, we stained the lung infiltrates for CD21/35 (complement receptor 2), which is expressed on FDC at high density.</s><s>More than 96% of infiltrates were negative for CD21/35 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2c</ref> and Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</s><s>Only some very large infiltrates located near the central bronchus stained positive for FDC markers (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2b</ref> and Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</s><s>In contrast to the FDC-negative infiltrates composed of loose aggregates of T and B cells, these CD21/35-positive infiltrates showed highly organized separate T-and B-cell zones (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2b</ref>, lower panel).</s><s>It is well established that T/B cooperation can take place in these SLO-like structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> .</s><s>However, the close contact of antigen-specific T and B cells in the predominating FDC-negative loose aggregates raised the question whether local T/B cooperation might take place there as well.</s></p><p><s>Lung tissue contains B cells with a GC-like phenotype.</s><s>To find indications for T/B cooperation in the inflamed tissue, we compared the phenotype of lung-infiltrating B cells with that of lymph node B cells.</s><s>First, we looked for antibody-secreting cells, which are generated both in the extrafollicular and GC B-cell responses.</s><s>On day 17, up to 30% of antigen-specific B cells in the draining lymph nodes expressed CD138 and had downregulated CD19, a characteristic feature of plasma cells (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a</ref>).</s><s>The lung tissue contained a very similar fraction of antigen-specific plasma cells.</s><s>However, when considering the higher absolute numbers of antigen-specific B cells (compare Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>), the lung tissue turned out to contain eight times more plasma cells than the lungdraining lymph node.</s><s>Intracellular staining of immunoglobulin subclasses revealed that antigen-specific plasma cells from both sites were mainly switched towards IgG1 and IgA, with few cells producing IgG2a and IgE (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>).</s><s>Histological analysis showed that CD138-positive plasma cells were equally found in FDC-positive and -negative infiltrates (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Next, we analysed the generation of GC B cells.</s><s>Around 60% of the transgenic B cells in the lymph node displayed a GC phenotype, defined by staining with peanut agglutinin (PNA) and the monoclonal antibody GL7 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3b</ref>).</s><s>Looking for these classical GC B-cell markers in the lungs, we surprisingly found a prominent population of PNA/GL7 double-positive cells, which only differed by a slightly reduced binding of PNA (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3b</ref>).</s><s>Although their frequency in the lung was lower, their absolute number was similar to that in the lymph node.</s><s>GC B cells have been detected in ectopic lymphoid structures of inflamed tissues <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> .</s><s>However, the high percentage of PNA þ /GL7 þ cells in our inflammation model was unexpected given the fact that the vast majority of lung infiltrates consisted of loose T/B aggregates and not ectopic lymphoid tissue.</s><s>Therefore, we analysed additional markers that are more specific for GC B cells.</s><s>The GL7 þ B cells in the lung expressed the transcription factor Bcl-6, which is a key regulator of GC B-cell differentiation 2 , and had downregulated CD38, another attribute of GC B cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> .</s><s>Moreover, PNA/GL7 double-positive cells in lymph node and lung expressed the activation-induced cytidine deaminase, which is involved in somatic hypermutation of GC B cells (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3b</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To define the localization of the GC-like B cells, we analysed a lung section near the central bronchus, which contained both ectopic lymphoid tissue and unstructured infiltrates (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3c</ref>).</s><s>As expected, some GL7 þ GC B cells were present in ectopic lymphoid tissue containing CD21/35 þ FDC.</s><s>However, most GL7 þ B cells were found in infiltrates without FDC, demonstrating that GC-like B cells can exist outside GC structures (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3c</ref>).</s><s>This explains how up to 40% of lung-infiltrating B cells displayed a GC phenotype although 96% of all lung infiltrates in our model were composed of loose T/B aggregates.</s><s>Staining for the cell cycle marker Ki-67 revealed that B cells within these infiltrates were highly proliferating (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3d</ref>).</s><s>This further indicates that active T/B cooperation takes place within these loose lung infiltrates.</s></p><p><s>Finally, we sequenced the transgenic B-cell receptor heavy chain from FDC-positive and -negative infiltrates obtained by laser microdissection.</s><s>Both types of infiltrates contained hypermutated B cells.</s><s>The ratio of replacement versus silent mutations (1.24 versus 1.33) and also the percentage of clones with the affinity-determining tryptophan to leucine mutation at codon 33 (60% versus 52%) were similar in FDC-positive and -negative infiltrates.</s></p><p><s>Taken together, our data show that B cells in lymph nodes and lung are similar in their phenotype.</s><s>However, in contrast to lymph nodes, where PNA þ /GL7 þ cells are present only in GC, we identified GC-like B cells outside of ectopic lymphoid structures in inflamed lung tissue.</s></p><p><s>Lung-infiltrating T cells are no classical TFH cells.</s><s>As the generation of GC B cells in lymph nodes critically depends on the presence of TFH cells, we analysed the proportion of transgenic T cells expressing the TFH markers CXCR5 and PD-1.</s><s>In the lung-draining lymph nodes about 40% of T cells displayed a TFH phenotype (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4a</ref>).</s><s>In contrast, this population was missing completely in the inflamed lung tissue.</s><s>Interestingly, only CXCR5 was absent on lung T cells, whereas PD-1 was equally expressed on lung as well as on lymph node T cells (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4b</ref>).</s><s>To define TFH cells more precisely we stained their master transcription factor Bcl-6.</s><s>As expected, antigen-specific CXCR5 À PD-1 À T cells in the lymph node were negative for Bcl-6, whereas a significant Bcl-6 expression was found in the CXCR5 þ PD-1 þ subset.</s></p><p><s>In contrast, lung-infiltrating T cells did not express Bcl-6 at all (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4a</ref>, right panel).</s></p><p><s>To further compare lung-infiltrating and lymph node T cells, we analysed additional markers that are typically expressed by TFH cells: the chemokine receptor CCR7, which is also involved in the positioning of TFH cells in the B-cell zones of SLO, and CD40L and ICOS, which are important effector molecules.</s><s>Interestingly, lung-infiltrating T cells had downregulated CCR7 to an even stronger extent than antigen-specific T cells in the lymph node (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4b</ref>).</s><s>At the same time, expression levels of CD40L and ICOS were higher on lung-infiltrating T cells compared with lymph node T cells.</s></p><p><s>T-cell help to B cells is mediated by CD40L and secretion of interleukin (IL)-4 and IL-21.</s><s>To assess the cytokine-producing potential of lung-infiltrating and lymph node T cells, these cell populations were re-stimulated with antigen in vitro.</s><s>IL-4 and IL-21 were the two dominating cytokines, produced by more than 20% of antigen-specific T cells (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4c</ref>).</s><s>While IL-4 was produced to a similar amount by lymph node and lung T cells, IL-21 production by lung-infiltrating T cells was in all experiments significantly higher than by antigen-specific T cells isolated from the draining lymph nodes.</s><s>Interestingly, expression of additional effector cytokines such as IL-5, IL-10, IL-13, IL-17 and interferon (IFN)-g was largely confined to lung T cells with an at least threefold higher expression than antigen-specific T cells from the draining lymph nodes.</s><s>The higher expression of Th2 effector cytokines by lung T cells was associated with a significantly increased expression of the master transcription factor GATA-3 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4d</ref>).</s></p><p><s>In contrast to the classical TFH cells in the lymph node, there was no cell surface marker on lung-infiltrating T cells identifying a subset with particular B helper capacity.</s><s>Therefore, we analysed co-expression of different cytokines.</s><s>IL-21 turned out to be a lead cytokine for lung effector T cells.</s><s>IL-4-, IL-10-, IL-13-and IFN-gproducing cells were highly enriched in the IL-21-positive compared with the IL-21-negative subset (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>).</s><s>As a second cytokine, the IL-21/IL-4 double-positive versus the IL-21 þ IL-4 À subset demarcated cells with highest expression of IL-10 and IL-13.</s></p><p><s>To demonstrate that the B helper potential of lung-infiltrating T cells was not a consequence of the preactivation of OT-II T cells under Th2-polarizing conditions, we ran our airway inflammation model also with the transfer of naive T cells.</s><s>Under these conditions, all previous observations could be reproduced (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>).</s><s>We found a GC-like B-cell population in the lung but no CXCR5 þ TFH cells.</s><s>The cytokine profile partly changed with almost no IL-4-and IL-13-producing cells.</s><s>Instead, a population of up to 30% IL-17-producing cells was generated in the lung, which is a typical reaction for antigens taken up via an intranasal route <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> .</s><s>Importantly, production of IL-21 was unchanged with around 30% IL-21 þ cells.</s><s>Again, IL-21 turned out to be a lead cytokine for lung T cells, with higher IL-17 and IFN-g production in the IL-21-positive versus -negative subset.</s></p><p><s>Collectively, in striking contrast to the presence of GC-like B cells in the lung, no classical CXCR5 þ Bcl-6 þ TFH cells could be found.</s><s>However, regarding other markers, lung-infiltrating T cells shared many similarities with TFH cells and had a high B helper potential by expressing CD40L, IL-4 and especially IL-21.</s><s>Lung-infiltrating T cells produced additional effector cytokines like IL-5, which functions not only as a chemoattractant for eosinophils but is also important for the class-switch of B cells towards IgA <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> .</s></p><p><s>Lung-infiltrating T cells provide help for B cells.</s><s>To functionally test their capacity for B-cell help, antigen-specific T cells from lung-draining lymph nodes or lung tissue were sorted and co-cultured with naive NP-specific B cells in the presence of cognate antigen.</s><s>After 7 days, B cells co-cultured with lung T cells had produced large amounts of IgG1, although not quite to the extent as B cells co-cultured with T cells from lymph nodes (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5a</ref>, upper panel).</s><s>However, production of IgA was similarly high in both groups (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5a</ref>, lower panel).</s><s>Moreover, lung T cells induced the ligands for GL7 and PNA, and the activation marker CD69 on the co-cultured B cells to the same extent as lymph node T cells (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5b</ref>).</s><s>Taken together, lung-infiltrating T cells are fully capable to provide B-cell help, although they lack the prototypic TFH cell markers CXCR5 and Bcl-6.</s></p><p><s>The lung is a major reservoir for memory B cells.</s><s>After looking at T/B cooperation during the effector phase of airway inflammation, we analysed antigen-specific T and B cells during the memory phase.</s><s>Even as late as day 41, 4 weeks after last antigen application, perivascular lymphocytic infiltrates could still be found in the lung (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6a</ref>).</s><s>These infiltrates contained substantial numbers of antigen-specific B cells.</s><s>At the same time, barely any NP-specific B cells were detectable in the lymph node (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6b</ref>).</s><s>In contrast to the effector phase, where activated antigen-specific cells were exclusively found in the lung and lung-draining lymph node, memory B cells were now also present in spleen and bone marrow.</s><s>While the highest frequency of memory B cells was found in the lung, the majority of memory B cells in absolute numbers resided in the spleen taking into account the higher cellularity of this organ (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6b</ref>).</s></p><p><s>We analysed additional markers to characterize these lungresident antigen-specific B cells.</s><s>While during the effector phase almost all antigen-specific B cells in the lungs displayed either a GC or plasma cell phenotype, CD138 þ , intracellular Ig þ or GL7 þ , PNA þ and CD38 low cells were no longer present at this late time (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6c</ref> and Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7</ref>). of the antigenspecific B cells in the lungs expressed surface IgM, whereas the others were class-switched towards either IgG1 or IgA (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6c</ref>).</s><s>Around 40% of all B cells expressed CD80, which is regarded as a marker for highly mutated memory B cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> .</s><s>In addition, we analysed the expression of PD-L2 and CD73, which are also expressed by subsets of memory B cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> .</s><s>Altogether, more than 85% of the B cells expressed PD-L2, CD73 or CD80, and can therefore be regarded as typical memory B cells, identifying the lung as an important niche for antigen-specific memory B cells.</s></p><p><s>Since o10% of the antigen-specific B cell numbers found during the effector phase remained at day 41, we had to take into account the possibility that they might be exclusively located in the FDC-positive infiltrates near the central bronchus.</s><s>However, like in the effector phase, the vast majority of infiltrates were FDC-negative.</s><s>Co-staining of CD45.1 and CD21/35 revealed that also in the memory phase the great majority of antigen-specific B cells resided in FDC-negative infiltrates (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6d</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Memory T and B cells are in close contact in the lung.</s><s>To additionally analyse antigen-specific memory T cells, we switched our system to the adoptive transfer of Smarta T-cell receptortransgenic instead of OT-II T cells, which allows for long-term tracking in vivo <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7a</ref>).</s><s>We co-stained lung sections for antigen-specific T and B cells on day 64 (47 days after the last antigen challenge).</s><s>Like in the effector phase (compare Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a</ref>) both cell types were still found in close contact within the residual infiltrates (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7b</ref>).</s><s>Antigen-specific memory T cells were recovered not only from lung tissue but also from lungdraining lymph node, spleen and bone marrow (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7c</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Consistent with the distribution of the memory B cells, the highest frequency of memory T cells was found in the lung, however, the highest absolute number was in the spleen.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>The interaction of T and B cells in SLO as well as in ectopic lymphoid tissue, which are structurally and functionally similar, has been investigated in great detail in the past.</s><s>However, it is still unclear whether T/B cooperation can also take place in unordered T/B infiltrates lacking the characteristics of SLO, such as clearly separated T-and B-cell zones and the presence of FDC.</s><s>This question is of major interest, because these unstructured T/B aggregates represent the vast majority of infiltrates in inflamed tissues in autoimmune and allergic diseases.</s><s>While early studies reported the presence of FDC-positive ectopic lymphoid tissue in around 25% of all synovial biopsies from rheumatoid arthritis patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> , a more recent study found fully differentiated follicles in only 6% of the biopsies <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> .</s><s>The predominant type of infiltrates was characterized as either diffuse T-and B-cell infiltrates or T/B aggregates lacking FDC structures.</s><s>Similar observations were made in studies analysing T/B infiltrates in kidneys of systemic lupus erythematosus patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> .</s></p><p><s>To study T/B cooperation in inflamed tissues, we complemented the well-established murine airway inflammation model based on the adoptive transfer of OVA-specific T cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> by an additional transfer of antigen-specific B cells.</s><s>This novel airway inflammation model allowed us the parallel analysis of antigen-specific T and B cells during early and late phases of the immune response, thus providing new insights into the phenotype and function of T and B cells in peripheral inflamed tissues.</s><s>The adoptive transfer system enabled us to track antigen-specific T and B cells, and showed that in the chronic phase of the immune response the vast majority of antigenspecific T and B cells were not located in the draining lymph nodes but in the inflamed tissue.</s><s>Similar to the situation in autoimmune patients, T/B infiltrates in the lung mainly consisted of loose aggregates lacking FDC and any ordered structures.</s><s>Nevertheless, not only plasma cells but also GC-like B cells were found in these infiltrates.</s><s>This shows that SLO-like structures and FDC are not absolutely necessary for the development of GC-like B cells.</s><s>So far, this only has been shown for the very special case of the so called milky spots in the omentum <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> .</s><s>These structures, important for peritoneal cavity immune responses, completely lack FDC but develop GC B cells on antigen exposure.</s></p><p><s>Despite the presence of GC-like B cells, no classical TFH cells expressing CXCR5 and Bcl-6 were found in the inflamed lung tissue.</s><s>Three recent publications demonstrated the presence of CXCR5-positive TFH cells in inflamed lung tissue.</s><s>However, in one study CXCR5 þ T cells were directly shown to reside in ectopic lymphoid structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> ; in the other two studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> this aspect was not analysed, but both used infection models, where the development of ectopic lymphoid tissue can be presumed.</s><s>We, however, focused on antigen-specific T cells in loose lymphocytic aggregates, and not in ectopic lymphoid tissue.</s><s>These lung-infiltrating T cells lacked classical TFH cell markers, but still had potent B-cell helper capacities and were present in close contact with strongly proliferating GC-like B cells.</s><s>The high frequency of Ki-67-positive B cells indicates that active T/B cooperation takes place.</s><s>Indeed, a recent detailed clonal tree analysis of B cells located in Ki-67 þ but FDC-negative T/B aggregates from lupus nephritis patients revealed ongoing somatic hypermutation <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> .</s><s>These FDC-negative T/B infiltrates in the kidney were first described by our group <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> .</s><s>Already in this early study we had many indications that active T/B cooperation takes place in the infiltrates and leads to the local generation of plasma cells.</s><s>The CXCR5-negative B helper T cells from the lung exhibit some features of other recently described T-cell populations with B helper potential, such as splenic extrafollicular helper T cells found in certain autoimmune mouse models <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> .</s><s>Despite their non-TFH phenotype with very low CXCR5 expression, these extrafollicular T cells exhibited a strong potential for B-cell help through expression of IL-4, IL-21 and CD40L, and might be important for the extrafollicular plasma cell reaction.</s><s>The second example is bone marrow-resident CD4 þ memory T cells that also lack typical TFH features <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> , but are, nevertheless, capable of providing help to B cells for antibody production and affinity maturation.</s><s>In the rheumatoid joint CXCR5-and Bcl-6-negative T cells were shown to be a source of CXCL13, which might be important for the recruitment of B cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref> .</s><s>A very recent publication described CXCR5-negative but IL-21-positive T cells in the inflamed lung <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref> .</s></p><p><s>So why are lung-infiltrating B helper T cells negative for CXCR5?</s><s>Possibly, because they simply do not need this chemokine receptor to get into contact with B cells.</s><s>In the unordered infiltrates with interspersed T and B cells as observed in our model, T cells do not have to migrate from a T-cell area into a B-cell follicle as in the lymph node.</s><s>In addition, expression of the CXCR5 ligand CXCL13 is unlikely in these FDC-negative lung infiltrates, since in the mouse this chemokine is mainly produced by FDC <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref> .</s></p><p><s>Our study did not only identify the lung tissue as a major reservoir for antigen-specific effector cells but also as a niche for long-lived memory B cells.</s><s>Tissue-resident memory T cells were recently recognized as a discrete memory T-cell subset, which facilitates rapid secondary responses directly at the site of antigen entry <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26</ref> .</s><s>Our study now shows that not only antigen-specific T but also B cells are found in close contact in the lung tissue.</s><s>So far, only three studies described the presence of memory B cells in the lung <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[27]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[28]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[29]</ref> , and all were viral infection models, which (different to our model) typically include the development of ectopic lymphoid tissue.</s><s>The persisting T/B infiltrates in the lung might be important in secondary immune responses for the rapid generation of antigen-specific plasma cells directly at the site of antigen entry.</s><s>Interestingly, antigen-specific memory T and B cells additionally distributed to other classical memory cell niches like spleen and bone marrow.</s><s>Therefore, immune responses in the lung can give rise not only to local but also systemic protection.</s></p><p><s>Our detailed analysis of T/B cooperation in inflamed tissues is also highly relevant from a clinical perspective.</s><s>With improved therapeutic options for autoimmune diseases preventing long phases of chronic disease, the development of ectopic lymphoid tissue as a final stage of tissue infiltration is nowadays only rarely observed.</s><s>However, FDC-negative, unstructured lymphocytic tissue infiltrates are a frequent pathological finding, and our study shed more light on the interaction of autoreactive T and B cells in these infiltrates.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p><s>Mice.</s><s>OT-II (Jax stock 004194) and Smarta <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30</ref> T-cell receptor transgenic mice or B1-8i mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31</ref> (additionally crossed with kappa light chain knockout mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32</ref> to ensure NP-specificity of B cells) were crossed to B6PL (Thy-1.1 þ , Jax stock 000406) or Ly-5.1 (CD45.1 þ , Jax stock 002014) mice, respectively.</s><s>Transgenic strains and wild-type C57BL/6 mice were bred under specific pathogen-free conditions in the animal facility of the Federal Institute for Risk Assessment, Berlin.</s><s>For experiments female mice in an age between 8 and 16 weeks were used.</s><s>Animal experiments were conducted according to the German animal protection laws, and approved by the responsible governmental authority (LAGeSo).</s></p><p><s>Airway inflammation model.</s><s>OT-II T cells from spleens were sorted magnetically for CD62L high cells (Miltenyi Biotec), and cultured with splenocytes for 5 days with the addition of OVA peptide, recombinant IL-4, anti-IFN-g and anti-IL-12. 2 Â 10 6 OT-II T and 2 Â 10 6 B1-8i B cells were adoptively transferred into C57BL/6 mice by intravenous injection, 16-24 h later mice were challenged i.n. with 5 mg NP-OVA conjugate and 5 mg LPS (Sigma) as adjuvant.</s><s>Challenge with same amounts of antigen was repeated on day 1, 10 and 13.</s><s>For analysis of memory T cells, naive T cells from Smarta mice were directly co-transferred into recipients.</s><s>Mice were challenged i.n. with NP and the cognate peptide (P13 GP 61-80 ) chemically coupled to mouse serum albumin (20 mg on day 0 and 1, and 5 mg on days 10, 13 and 17) and 5 mg LPS.</s></p><p><s>Cell isolation.</s><s>Lungs were perfused with PBS.</s><s>Bronchial lymph nodes were dissected from the lung tissue under a microscope and prepared separately for flow cytometric analysis by meshing through a 70-mm sieve.</s><s>Single-cell suspensions from lung tissue were prepared using the gentle MACS dissociator (Miltenyi Biotec) and digestion with 0.5 mg ml À 1 collagenase D and 20 mg ml À 1 DNase I (Roche) for 25 min at 37 °C.</s><s>Spleens were meshed through a sieve, and bone marrow was flushed out of femur and tibia of hind legs.</s><s>All cells were counted using a Guava EasyCyte capillary flow cytometer and ViaCount solution (Millipore).</s></p><p><s>T/B co-cultures.</s><s>To compare the B-cell helper qualities of effector T cells from lymph nodes and lung, cells from both organs were enriched with anti-Thy-1.1 microbeads (Miltenyi Biotec) followed by flow-sorting on a FACS ARIA II (BD Biosciences) for CD4 þ Thy-1.1 þ Thy-1.2</s><s>À CD44 high CD8 À B220 À DAPI À cells.</s><s>Naive T cells from spleens of OT-II mice were sorted as CD4 þ Thy-1.1 þ CD62L þ B220 À DAPI À cells.</s><s>Naive B cells were sorted from spleens of B1-8i mice as CD19 þ CD4 À DAPI À cells.</s><s>T and B cells were co-cultured in 96-well round-bottom plates (4-6 individual wells) at a 1:4 ratio in the presence of 10 mg ml À 1 NP-OVA for 7 days.</s></p><p><s>Flow cytometry.</s><s>Single-cell suspensions from lymph node, lung, spleen or bone marrow were stained with different combinations of fluorophore-conjugated antibodies (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">I</ref>).</s><s>Streptavidin-PE-Cy7 (0.25 mg ml À 1 ) or -PerCP (0.5 mg ml À 1 ) were used as secondary reagents for biotinylated Ab.</s><s>Fc receptors were blocked with 20 mg ml À 1 2.4G2 (anti-CD16/32).</s></p><p><s>For analysis of cytokine production, cells were re-stimulated in vitro with OVA peptide for 4.5 h with Brefeldin A added after 1 h.</s><s>Following staining of cell surface antigens, cells were fixed with formaldehyde, permeabilized with saponin and stained intracellularly with anti-cytokine antibodies (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">I</ref>).</s><s>For detection of IL-21, an IL-21R-Fc chimera, followed by Cy5-conjugated goat anti-human Ig (Jackson ImmunoResearch, 1:800), was used.</s></p><p><s>For intracellular staining of transcription factors (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">I</ref>) the FoxP3 Staining Buffer Set from eBioscience was used.</s><s>For activation-induced cytidine deaminase staining, cells were stained intracellularly before surface staining, and Alexa Fluor 647-conjugated goat anti-rat Ig (Invitrogen, 2.5 mg ml À 1 ) was used as secondary reagent.</s><s>For intracellular staining of Ig, cells were fixed with formaldehyde, permeabilized with saponin buffer and stained with fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)-conjugated anti-Ig antibodies (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">I</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To discriminate dead cells, either 4,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) was added to live cells immediately before analysis or cells were stained with 1.34 mM Pacific Orange succinimidyl ester (Invitrogen) before fixation.</s><s>Samples were analysed on an LSR II or LSR Fortessa flow cytometer (BD Biosciences).</s><s>Analysis gates were set on live cells defined by scatter characteristics and exclusion of doublets and dead cells.</s><s>In all figures, antigen-specific T cells are defined as DAPI À B220 À CD4 þ Thy-1.1 þ and B cells as DAPI À CD3/CD8 À CD19 þ CD45.2 À CD45.1 þ .</s><s>Data were analysed with FlowJo Software (Treestar).</s></p><p><s>Enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay.</s><s>NP-specific IgG1 and IgA was measured by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay.</s><s>Plates were precoated with NP-coupled BSA, and bound antibodies were detected by using horseradish peroxidase-coupled antibodies to mouse IgG1 or IgA (Southern Biotechnologies) and tetramethylbenzidine as substrate.</s></p><p><s>Histology.</s><s>Lungs were filled with 50% TissueTek OCT compound via the trachea and snap frozen in ice-cold isopentane.</s><s>The 8-mm cryostat sections of the right lower lobe were cut and fixed with acetone.</s><s>To reduce unspecific signals, peroxidase inactivation and blocking with Casein Solution (Vector Laboratories) was performed.</s></p><p><s>For light microscopy, tissue section was stained with FITC-coupled OX-7 (anti-Thy-1.1,</s><s>1.25 mg ml À 1 ), A20 (anti-CD45.1, 5 mg ml À 1 ), 7G6 (anti-CD21/35, 1 mg ml À 1 ), unconjugated 281-2 (anti-CD138, 5 mg ml À 1 ) or MBP-1 (anti-MBP, kindly provided by J. Lee, Scottsdale, 1:2,500).</s><s>As secondary reagents, peroxidase-conjugated antisera against FITC, digoxygenin (Roche, 1:300) or rat-IgG (Jackson ImmunoResearch, 1:4,000) were used.</s><s>Slides were developed using 3-amino-9-ethylcarbazole as substrate, nuclei were counterstained with haematoxyline.</s><s>A periodic acid-Schiff-staining kit (Carl Roth) was used to stain mucopolysaccharides.</s><s>Slides were analysed on an Axioskop 2 light microscope equipped with an Axiocam (Carl Zeiss).</s><s>(c) Frequencies and absolute numbers of antigen-specific T cells isolated from lymph node (Ln), lung, spleen (Spl) and bone marrow (Bm).</s><s>Representative data from 2 independent experiments with 14 mice total.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 |</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure1| Inflamed lung tissue is the major reservoir of antigen-specific T and B cells.</s><s>(a) General set-up for the airway inflammation model.</s><s>Preactivated OT-II T cells and naive B1-8i/kappa light chain knockout B cells were transferred into syngeneic C57BL/6 mice.</s><s>OT-II cells express a T-cell receptor specific for OVA, B1-8i cells have a knock-in for the germline VH186 heavy chain, which recognizes the hapten NP in combination with any lambda 1 light chain<ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31</ref> .</s><s>On the indicated days, recipient mice were immunized i.n. with an NP-OVA conjugate and LPS.</s><s>Cells from lungs and lung-draining lymph nodes were typically analysed on day 17 when airway inflammation was fully established.</s><s>Antigen-specific T and B cells were identified by flow cytometry using the congenic markers Thy-1.1 and CD45.1, respectively.</s><s>(b) Total numbers of antigen-specific T and B cells in lung-draining lymph node (Ln) and lung tissue on day 17.</s><s>Shown are absolute cell numbers of a representative experiment and the ratio of antigen-specific T and B cells in lymph node versus lung (pooled data from 6 experiments with 34 animals).</s><s>Error bars show s.e.m. ***Po0.001</s><s>by Mann-Witney U-test.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>bFigure 2 |</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2 | Lung infiltrates contain antigen-specific T and B cells in close contact.</s><s>(a) Cryosections from non-inflamed and inflamed lung tissues (day 17) were stained with haematoxylin to visualize cellular infiltrates.</s><s>The images on the right show serial sections of the highlighted perivascular infiltrate or the nearby bronchus in higher magnification.</s><s>Immunostaining (red) for OVA-specific T cells, NP-specific B cells and eosinophils was performed using the indicated markers.</s><s>Production of mucus was visualized by periodic acid-Schiff staining.</s><s>Scales bars, 200 mm for the low-resolution images (original magnification Â 5) and 50 mm for the high-resolution images (original magnification Â 20).</s><s>(b) Ectopic lymphoid tissue was identified by staining of serial cryosections for FDC and antigen-specific T and B cells using the indicated markers.</s><s>Scale bars, 100 mm for the low-resolution images and 20 mm for the high-resolution image (original magnification Â 20).</s><s>Images are representative of 2-4 independent experiments with 10-18 animals total.</s><s>(c) Area of FDC-containing regions as percentage of total infiltrate area, quantified as shown in Supplementary Fig. 2. Each dot represents data from a single pulmonary lobe.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,139.25,248.05,207.02,156.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 |</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3 | Similar phenotype of B cells in lymph node and lung tissue.</s><s>Flow cytometric analysis (day 17) of antigen-specific (CD45.1 þ ) B cells from lung-draining lymph nodes and lung tissue.</s><s>(a) Comparison of plasma cells, defined as CD19 low CD138 þ , from lymph nodes and lungs.</s><s>Shown are flow cytometric plots, and the frequency and absolute numbers of NP-specific B cells with a plasma cell phenotype from a representative experiment and the ratio of plasma cells in lung-draining lymph nodes as pooled data from 3 experiments with 20 animals total.</s><s>(b) Comparison of GC/GC-like B cells from lymph nodes (Ln) and lung tissue.</s><s>Frequency and absolute numbers from a representative experiment, and relative distribution of GL7 þ PNA þ B cells between lymph node and lung as pooled data from 4 experiments with 26 animals.</s><s>For further characterization, cells were co-stained for CD38 and intracellular Bcl-6 or activation-induced cytidine deaminase (AID).</s><s>CD38 expression is shown as histograms on GL7/Bcl-6 double-negative (black) versus double-positive (orange) cells.</s><s>AID expression is shown on GL7/PNA-positive (red line) and -negative (black line) cells relative to an isotype control (filled grey histogram; concatenated flow cytometry data from five animals).</s><s>(c) Staining of lung tissue containing ectopic lymphoid tissue defined by the presence of FDC (CD21/35 þ , yellow) and a greater number of unstructured infiltrates.</s><s>Staining with the GC B-cell marker GL7 is shown in magenta.</s><s>(d) Co-staining of transgenic B cells (magenta) and the cell proliferation marker Ki-67 (yellow) in an FDC-negative infiltrate.</s><s>Scale bars, 100 mm, original magnification Â 20.</s><s>Data are representative for at least two independent experiments.</s><s>Error bars show s.e.m.</s><s>NS, not significant: PZ0.05, *Po0.05,</s><s>**Po0.01 by Mann-Witney U-test.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,235.61,279.01,164.51,158.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 |</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4 | Lung tissue does not contain classical TFH cells.</s><s>Comparison of antigen-specific (Thy-1.1 þ ) T cells from lymph nodes (Ln) and lung tissue.</s><s>(a) Analysis of CXCR5/PD-1 expression.</s><s>The right panel shows intracellular staining for Bcl-6 in lymph node TFH cells (CXCR5 þ /PD-1 þ ) and non-TFH cells (CXCR5 À /PD-1 À ), and in the whole population of lung-infiltrating T cells.</s><s>The inset numbers indicate the mean fluorescence intensity (MFI)± s.e.m.</s><s>(b) Expression of PD-1, CCR7, CD40L (intracellular staining, no restimulation) and ICOS on lymph node (grey-filled histograms) versus lung-infiltrating (black open histograms) T cells.</s><s>(c) Intracellular staining for IL-4, IL-5, IL-10, IL-13, IL-21 and IFN-g after shortterm restimulation with OVA peptide in vitro.</s><s>A representative staining from lung-infiltrating T cells is shown for all cytokines.</s><s>(d) Intracellular staining for GATA-3 comparing the MFI between lymph node and lung T cells (dotted line ¼ GATA-3 staining on non-antigen-specific (endogenous) lymph node CD4 þ T cells).</s><s>Data are representative of 3-4 independent experiments with 7-9 animals per experiment.</s><s>NS, not significant: PZ0.05, *Po0.05,</s><s>**Po0.01,</s><s>***Po0.001</s><s>by Mann-Witney U-test.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 |</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5 | Lung-infiltrating T cells provide B-cell help.</s><s>Sorted antigen-specific (Thy-1.1 þ ) effector T cells (day 17) from lungs or lymph nodes (Ln), or naive OT-II cells were co-cultured with naive NP-specific B cells in the presence of NP-OVA for 7 days.</s><s>Thereafter, (a) NP-specific IgG1 and IgA were measured by ELISA and (b) B cells were stained with PNA, GL7 or anti-CD69, and analysed by flow cytometry.</s><s>Shown are representative results from three independent experiments with six replicates each.</s><s>Error bars show s.e.m.</s><s>NS, not significant: PZ0.05, **Po0.01 by Mann-Witney U-test.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 |</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6 | Lung tissue is a major reservoir for antigen-specific memory B cells.</s><s>Analysis of lung-resident B cells 28 days after the last antigen challenge (day 41).</s><s>(a) Histological analysis of lung tissue showing a peribronchial infiltrate.</s><s>Antigen-specific B cells (CD45.1 þ , green) were preferentially found in the proximity of vessels.</s><s>Br, bronchus, V, vessels.</s><s>Scale bar, 50 mm, original magnification was Â 20.</s><s>(b) Frequencies and absolute numbers of antigenspecific (CD45.1 þ ) B cells isolated from lymph node (Ln), lung, spleen (Spl) and bone marrow (Bm) on day 41.</s><s>(c) Characterization of lung-resident antigen-specific B cells showing representative staining for CD38, IgM, IgG1, IgA and the memory markers PD-L2, CD80 and CD73.</s><s>Representative data from two independent experiments with six mice per experiment are shown.</s><s>(d) Co-staining of antigen-specific B cells (CD45.1) and FDC (CD21/35) in lung tissue on day 42.</s><s>Scale bars, 500 mm in the overview and 100 mm in the detail enlargement.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,80.93,274.33,385.58,103.34" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 7 |</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 7 | Clusters of antigen-specific memory T and B cells remain in the non-inflamed lung.</s><s>(a) Smarta T-cell receptor transgenic (Tg) T cells were co-transferred with B1-8i B cells into C57BL/6 recipients.</s><s>Mice were repeatedly challenged i.n. with NP and Smarta peptide coupled to mouse serum albumin as non-immunogenic carrier and analysed 47 days (d) after the last challenge.</s><s>(b) Histological analysis of lung tissue showing antigenspecific T cells (Thy-1.1 þ ) in yellow and B cells (CD45.1 þ ) in magenta.</s><s>Scale bars, 500 mm in the overview and 50 mm in the detail enlargement.(c)</s><s>Frequencies and absolute numbers of antigen-specific T cells isolated from lymph node (Ln), lung, spleen (Spl) and bone marrow (Bm).</s><s>Representative data from 2 independent experiments with 14 mice total.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:10875 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms10875 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>This study was supported by grants from the German Research Council (DFG) and the Fritz Thyssen Foundation to A.H. We thank Gudrun Steinhauser for help with laser microdissection.</s><s>Klaus Rajewsky generously provided B1-8i and Max Lo ¨hning Smarta mice.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>For immunofluorescence microscopy, sections were stained with FITC-or Alexa Fluor 546-coupled 7G6 (anti-CD21/35, 1 mg ml À 1 ), FITC-coupled A20 (anti-CD45.1, 0.25 mg ml À 1 ), digoxygenin-conjugated OX-7 (anti-Thy-1.1,</s><s>0.25 mg ml À 1 ), digoxygenin-conjugated GL7 (anti-GC B cells, 1 mg ml À 1 ) or hamster anti-Ki-67 (Abcam, 1:100), followed by Alexa Fluor 594-coupled anti-hamster Ig (Invitrogen, 1:500).</s><s>Signals were amplified with peroxidaseconjugated anti-FITC followed by FITC-coupled tyramide (Invitrogen).</s><s>After inactivation of peroxidase, the second antibody was detected with anti-digoxygenin-peroxidase (Roche, 1:300) and Alexa Fluor 647-coupled tyramide.</s><s>Nuclei were counterstained with DAPI.</s><s>Images were captured on an LSM 780 with ZEN2010 imaging software (Carl Zeiss).</s></p><p><s>B-cell receptor sequencing.</s><s>Four FDC-positive and six negative infiltrates (determined by CD21/35 staining on a consecutive section) were isolated from frozen lung sections using an Arcturus Veritas laser capture microdissection system.</s><s>RNA was isolated using the Arcturus PicoPure RNA isolation kit.</s><s>The VH186.2 sequence of the transgenic B1-8i B-cell receptor was amplified from cDNA using a universal primer in the signal peptide (5 0 -GATGGAGCTGTATCA TGCTCTTCTTGGCAG-3 0 ) and specific primers for the heavy chain of IgA (5 0 -CACTGGGTCACTTGACAGAGCTTGTG-3 0 ), IgG1 (5 0 -GCTGCTCAGAGTG TAGAGGTCAGACTGC-3 0 ) and IgM (5 0 -TGAAGGAAATGGTGCTGGGC AGG-3 0 ).</s><s>PCR products were cloned into pJET1.2.</s><s>Sequences from 144 single clones were analysed for somatic hypermutation.</s></p><p><s>Statistical analysis.</s><s>Experimental groups contained at least five animals (randomly assigned), which routinely provides the statistical power to detect biological significant differences in our experimental system.</s><s>Data were analysed using GraphPad Prism 5.</s><s>No data exclusion criteria were used.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author contributions</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional information</head><p><s>Accession codes: Unique B cell receptor sequences from FDC-negative and -positive infiltrates have been deposited at the European Nucleotide Archive (www.ebi.ac.uk/ena) under the accession codes LT159851, LT159852, LT159853, LT159854, LT159855, LT159856, LT159857, LT159858, LT159859, LT159860, LT159861, LT159862, LT159863, LT159864 and LT159865.</s><s>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/</s><s>naturecommunications Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests.</s><s>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</s><s>The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material.</s><s>To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Follicular helper CD4 T cells (TFH)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Crotty</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="621" to="663" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular programming of B cell memory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mcheyzer-Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Okitsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mcheyzer-Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="34" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bronchus-associated lymphoid tissue (BALT) structure and function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Randall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="187" to="241" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tertiary lymphoid organs in infection and autoimmunity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Neyt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Perros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Geurtsvankessel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hammad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Lambrecht</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="305" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of inducible bronchus associated lymphoid tissue (iBALT) in respiratory immunity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Moyron-Quiroz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="927" to="934" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">B lymphocyte autoimmunity in rheumatoid synovitis is independent of ectopic lymphoid neogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Cantaert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">181</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="785" to="794" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In situ B cell-mediated immune responses and tubulointerstitial inflammation in human lupus nephritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">186</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1849" to="1860" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kinetics of establishing the memory B cell population as revealed by CD38 expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ridderstad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tarlinton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">160</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4688" to="4695" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intranasal immunization promotes th17 immune responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Zygmunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rharbaoui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Groebe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Guzman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">183</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6933" to="6938" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential regulation of IgA production by TGF-beta and IL-5: TGF-beta induces surface IgA-positive cells bearing IL-5 receptor, whereas IL-5 promotes their survival and maturation into IgA-secreting cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sonoda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">140</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="158" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New markers for murine memory B cells that define mutated and unmutated subsets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tomayko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ahuja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Haberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Shlomchik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Exp. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">204</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2103" to="2114" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cutting edge: hierarchy of maturity of murine memory B cell subsets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tomayko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Steinel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Shlomchik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">185</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7146" to="7150" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">T-follicular helper cells survive as long-term memory cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fuhrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hutloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981-1988 (2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lymphoid neogenesis in rheumatoid synovitis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Takemura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">167</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1072" to="1080" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Involvement of inducible costimulator in the exaggerated memory B cell and plasma cell generation in systemic lupus erythematosus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hutloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3211" to="3220" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mouse models of allergic airway disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gonzalo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Coyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gutierrez-Ramos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="295" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Omental milky spots develop in the absence of lymphoid tissue-inducer cells and support B and T cell responses to peritoneal antigens</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rangel-Moreno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="731" to="743" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CXCR5( þ ) T helper cells mediate protective immunity against tuberculosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Slight</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clin. Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="712" to="726" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Memory CD4 þ T-cell-mediated protection depends on secondary effectors that are distinct from and superior to primary effectors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Strutt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Mckinstry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Swain</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="E2551" to="E2560" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ICOS and Bcl6-dependent pathways maintain a CD4 T cell population with memory-like properties during tuberculosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Moguche</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Exp. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">212</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="715" to="728" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ICOS-dependent extrafollicular helper T cells elicit IgG production via IL-21 in systemic autoimmunity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Odegard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Exp. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">205</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2873" to="2886" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Professional memory CD4 þ T lymphocytes preferentially reside and rest in the bone marrow</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tokoyoda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="721" to="730" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mature antigen-experienced T helper cells synthesize and secrete the B cell chemoattractant CXCL13 in the inflammatory environment of the rheumatoid joint</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Manzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3377" to="3387" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interleukin-21-producing CD4( þ ) T cells promote type 2 immunity to house dust mites</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Coquet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="318" to="330" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A chemokine-driven positive feedback loop organizes lymphoid follicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ansel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">406</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="314" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Memory T cell subsets, migration patterns, and tissue residence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Mueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gebhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Carbone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Heath</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="161" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Broad dispersion and lung localization of virus-specific memory B cells induced by influenza pneumonia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Joo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Sangster</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3485" to="3490" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Memory B cells in the lung participate in protective humoral immune responses to pulmonary influenza virus reinfection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Onodera</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2485" to="2490" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinct germinal center selection at local sites shapes memory B cell response to viral escape</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Adachi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Exp. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">212</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1709" to="1723" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Virus-specific MHC-class II-restricted TCR-transgenic mice: effects on humoral and cellular immune responses after viral infection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Oxenius</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Bachmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Zinkernagel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hengartner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. J. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="390" to="400" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">B cell development under the condition of allelic inclusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sonoda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene targeting in the Ig kappa locus: efficient generation of lambda chain-expressing B cells, independent of gene rearrangements in Ig kappa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Zou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Takeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Rajewsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="811" to="820" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
