<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">FD-OCT and IVUS for detection of incomplete stent apposition in heavily calcified vessels: novel insights</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-12-23">23 December 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leistner</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin (Campus Benjamin Franklin)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ulf</forename><surname>Landmesser</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin (Campus Benjamin Franklin)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Georg</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fröhlich</surname></persName>
							<email>georg.froehlich@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin (Campus Benjamin Franklin)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin (Campus Benjamin Franklin)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">FD-OCT and IVUS for detection of incomplete stent apposition in heavily calcified vessels: novel insights</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-12-23">23 December 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">6DA6925772D4DEFE853CCBE4719FAC23</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1136/openhrt-2015-000292</idno>
					<note type="submission">Accepted 25 August 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:21+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>In the present issue of Open Heart, Gudmundsdottir and colleagues compare two intracoronary imaging modalities, intravascular ultrasound (IVUS) and FD-optical coherence tomography (FD-OCT), in patients undergoing complex percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) with rotablation for calcific coronary lesions.</s><s>In particular, this study sought to detect incomplete stent apposition (ISA) using these different imaging modalities.</s><s>ISA may play a role in the risk of target vessel failure, for example, stent thrombosis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Intracoronary imaging has become widely available with the advent of IVUS in the early 1990s. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> IVUS-derived images with an axial resolution down to 150 µm have given novel insights into the clinical evolution of coronary artery disease and plaque composition. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s>This technology was rapidly embraced by the interventional cardiology community, mainly to assess coronary lesions of intermediate significance in larger coronary arteries, to size the stent diameter or to monitor optimal stent deployment and exclude coronary dissections post-stenting. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> While this new intracoronary imaging fuelled enthusiasm, to date, limited data exist to demonstrate that IVUS-guided PCI translates into a superior clinical outcome with respect to incomplete stent apposition (table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>However, a large observational analysis comparing IVUS-guided against angiography-guided PCI suggested that IVUS guidance was associated with a reduction in stent thrombosis, myocardial infarction and major adverse cardiac events within 1 year after DES implantation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>oreover, some moderately sized clinical studies suggested an improved performance if IVUS was used, particularly for complex PCI procedures involving the left main stem. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">5</ref></s><s>here are several limitations inherent in this technology.</s><s>First, the spatial resolution may be limited for optimal stent evaluation.</s><s>Second, heavy calcification may cause artefacts and compromise image quality.</s><s>And third, IVUS further increases procedural costs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> Current European Society of Cardiology guidelines suggest a class IIa recommendation for the use of IVUS to optimise stent implantation in selected patients, to assess severity of left main stem disease and optimise left main stenting, and to reveal mechanisms of stent failure (eg, stent thrombosis). <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">6</ref></s><s>he first coronary FD-OCT images in humans were published in 2002. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">7</ref></s><s>A major advantage of this technology is indeed the higher resolution, so that FD-OCT allows for qualitative plaque assessment with respect to plaque cap thickness or rupture. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">8</ref></s><s>However, definitions on plaque vulnerability by FD-OCT are still under development.</s><s>FD-OCT was also referred to as 'virtual histology' due to its excellent axial resolution down to 15 µm. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s>This level of accuracy owes to emission of light of a near infrared spectrum (approximately 1300 nm) and immediate acquisition of backscattering by the FD-OCT probe. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">9</ref></s><s>Optimal image acquisition may only be achieved if red blood cells are cleared sufficiently from the vessel lumen during a flush with transparent contrast die. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">9</ref></s><s>iven the low penetration depth (1.0-1.5 mm) of near infrared light, only the inner vessel layers may be visualised with FD-OCT, while the whole vessel plaque burden can only be estimated with IVUS. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">9</ref> On the other hand, heavy vessel calcification does not necessarily impact on image quality in FD-OCT.</s><s>In summary, the ESC guidelines do recommend FD-OCT to assess mechanisms of stent failure (class IIa) and to optimise stent implantation in selected patients (class IIb). <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">6</ref></s><s>udmundsdottir and colleagues investigated both intracoronary imaging modalities in a subset of patients with heavily calcified coronary lesions who underwent rotablation and PCI. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> The primary outcome measure in this study was the detection of ISA to the vessel wall.</s><s>ISA is defined as the lack of contact of stent struts with the vessel wall. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s>This phenomenon may occur acutely: (1) due to underexpansion of the stent with insufficient inflation pressure; (2) following poor or late selection of stent size during follow-up; (3) which may then be due to thrombus resolution after Primary PCI or (4) because of insufficient radial force of the stent and consecutive recoil. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s>The clinical relevance of improved detection of malapposed stent struts still needs to be better understood.</s><s>Only several small studies investigated this subject with FD-OCT so far (table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>However, two IVUS studies investigating first generation drug eluting stents found an association between ISA with very late stent thrombosis and myocardial infarction. <ref type="bibr">10 11</ref></s><s>This may be explained by the lower resolution of IVUS, where only significant levels of ISA may be detected, but not necessarily single stent strut malapposition, which is not relevant.</s><s>One small study revealed ISA in 74% of patients presenting with late stent thrombosis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">12</ref></s><s>However, the majority of cases were declared as late-acquired ISA, so this likely could not be prevented by stent optimisation at baseline.</s><s>Moreover, in-stent restenosis has been linked to ISA but existing data are rather limited. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">13</ref></s><s>n the present manuscript, however, the clinical relevance of ISA was not the main focus. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Of note, FD-OCT use in these highly calcified vessels allowed for improved detection of ISA as compared to IVUS. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> This finding is in line with previous studies and explained by the higher resolution of FD-OCT.</s><s>Moreover, FD-OCT imaging triggered more intense postdilation, which reduced the extent of ISA from 34% of stent surface area to 19% 1 in this patient group with rotablation, and heavy calcification where ISA is expected, postdilation with a non-compliant balloon, may actually be considered standard procedure.</s><s>If FD-OCT should be repeated after postdilation and if further more intense postdilation might yield superior outcomes was not examined in the present study.</s></p><p><s>In essence, the authors present an interesting study suggesting that FD-OCT provides more detailed information as compared to IVUS and may be a valuable imaging modality in the setting of heavily calcified coronary lesions.</s><s>However, all of the aforementioned potential downsides need to be carefully considered, and more data are needed to determine the clinical role of FD-OCT in detection of ISA and the impact of different degrees of ISA on clinical outcome.</s></p><p><s>Contributors GMF and DML drafted the manuscript and UL revised it.</s></p><p><s>Competing interests UL received honoraria or research grants from Orbus Neich, Terumo and St Jude.</s></p><p><s>Provenance and peer review Commissioned; internally peer reviewed.</s></p><p><s>Open Access This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work noncommercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial.</s><s>See: http:// creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Association of IVUS-guided or OCT-guided PCI with outcome parameters , bare-metal stent; DES, drug-eluting stent; EES, everolimus-eluting stent; ISA, incomplete stent apposition; IVUS, intravascular ultrasound; MI, myocardial infarction; OCT, optical coherence tomography; PES, pacitaxel-eluting stent; SES, sirolimus-eluting stent; ST, stent thrombosis; ZES, zotarolimus-eluting stent.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Assessment</cell><cell>Follow-up</cell><cell>Association of ISA and</cell></row><row><cell>Author (ref)</cell><cell>n</cell><cell>Type of stent</cell><cell>of ISA by</cell><cell>(months)</cell><cell>cardiovascular events</cell></row><row><cell>Cook et al 10</cell><cell>188</cell><cell>SES/PES</cell><cell>IVUS</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>YES (ISA highly prevalent in patients with</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>very late stent thrombosis</cell></row><row><cell>Cook et al 11</cell><cell>194</cell><cell>SES/PES</cell><cell>IVUS</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>YES (presence of ISA after DES associated</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>with higher risk AMI and very late stent</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>thrombosis</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Witzenbichler et al 4 8583</cell><cell>DES</cell><cell>IVUS</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>YES (less ST, MI and MACE)</cell></row><row><cell>Tanabe et al 14</cell><cell>469</cell><cell>PES/BMS</cell><cell>IVUS</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>NO</cell></row><row><cell>Steinberg et al 15</cell><cell>1580</cell><cell>PES/BMS</cell><cell>IVUS</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>NO</cell></row><row><cell>Hong et al 16</cell><cell>557</cell><cell>SES/PES</cell><cell>IVUS</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>NO</cell></row><row><cell>Guagliumi et al 17</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>ZES</cell><cell>OCT</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>NO</cell></row><row><cell>Kubo et al 18</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>SES</cell><cell>OCT</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>NO</cell></row><row><cell>Guagliumi et al 19</cell><cell>77</cell><cell>SES/PES/</cell><cell>OCT</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>NO</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>ZES/BMS</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Guagliumi et al 17</cell><cell>42</cell><cell>EES</cell><cell>OCT</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>NO</cell></row></table><note><p><s>BMS</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">on May 17, 2022 by guest. Protected by copyright. http://openheart.bmj.com/ Open Heart: first published as 10.1136/openhrt-2015-000292 on 23 December 2015. Downloaded from</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optical coherence tomography versus intravascular ultrasound to evaluate stent implantation in patients with calcific coronary artery disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Open Heart</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<publisher>▪▪▪</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Application of a new phased-array ultrasound imaging catheter in the assessment of vascular dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Nissen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Grines</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Gurley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/01.CIR.81.2.660</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In vivo comparison to cineangiography. Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="660" to="666" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanisms, pathophysiology, and clinical aspects of incomplete stent apposition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Attizzani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Capodanno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ohno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">,</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jacc.2014.01.019</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1355" to="1367" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship between intravascular ultrasound guidance and clinical outcomes after drug-eluting stents: the assessment of dual antiplatelet therapy with drug-eluting stents (ADAPT-DES) study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Witzenbichler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Maehara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Weisz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.113.003942</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="463" to="470" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leistner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Landmesser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fröhlich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/openhrt-2015-000292</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Open Heart</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e000292</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Open Heart on May 17, 2022 by guest</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Protected by copyright</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/openhrt-2015-000292on23</idno>
		<ptr target="http://openheart.bmj.com/OpenHeart" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-12">December 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of intravascular ultrasound guidance on long-term mortality in stenting for unprotected left main coronary artery stenosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/CIRCINTERVENTIONS.108.799494</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circ Cardiovasc Interv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="177" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Authors/Task Force members</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Windecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kolh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Alfonso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Guidelines on myocardial revascularization: the Task Force on Myocardial Revascularization of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and the European Association for Cardio-Thoracic Surgery (EACTS)Developed with the special contribution of the European Association of Percutaneous Cardiovascular Interventions (EAPCI)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Esc/Eacts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/eurheartj/ehu278</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2541" to="2619" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of coronary atherosclerotic plaques in patients using optical coherence tomography: comparison with intravascular ultrasound</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bouma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0735-1097(01)01799-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="604" to="609" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical classification of plaque morphology in coronary disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Otsuka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Joner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Prati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nrcardio.2014.62</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="389" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intracoronary optical coherence tomography: a comprehensive review clinical and research applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Bezerra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Guagliumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcin.2009.06.019</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JACC Cardiovasc Interv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1035" to="1046" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of incomplete stent apposition on long-term clinical outcome after drug-eluting stent implantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Eshtehardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kalesan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/eurheartj/ehr484</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1334" to="1343" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incomplete stent apposition and very late stent thrombosis after drug-eluting stent implantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wenaweser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Togni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.106.658237</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2426" to="2434" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intravascular ultrasound findings in patients with very late stent thrombosis after either drug-eluting or bare-metal stent implantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jacc.2009.10.077</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1936" to="1942" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In-stent restenosis associated with stent malapposition: seven year optical coherence tomography findings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Barlis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ijcard.2010.02.068</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="151" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incomplete stent apposition after implantation of paclitaxel-eluting stents or bare metal stents: insights from the randomized TAXUS II trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tanabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Serruys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Degertekin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/01.CIR.0000155607.54922.16</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="900" to="905" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long-term impact of routinely detected early and late incomplete stent apposition: an integrated intravascular ultrasound analysis of the TAXUS IV, V, and VI and TAXUS ATLAS workhorse, long lesion, and direct stent studies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Steinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mintz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mandinov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcin.2010.03.007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JACC Cardiovasc Interv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="486" to="494" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Late stent malapposition after drug-eluting stent implantation: an intravascular ultrasound analysis with long-term follow-up</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mintz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.105.563403</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="414" to="419" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of drug release kinetics on vascular response to different zotarolimus-eluting stents implanted in patients with long coronary stenoses: the LongOCT study (Optical Coherence Tomography in Long Lesions)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Guagliumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ikejima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Sirbu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcin.2011.04.007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JACC Cardiovasc Interv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="778" to="785" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of vascular response after sirolimus-eluting stent implantation between patients with unstable and stable angina pectoris: a serial optical coherence tomography study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kubo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Imanishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kitabata</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcmg.2008.03.012</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JACC Cardiovasc Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="475" to="484" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optical coherence tomography assessment of in vivo vascular response after implantation of overlapping bare-metal and drug-eluting stents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Guagliumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Musumeci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Sirbu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcin.2010.02.008</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JACC Cardiovasc Interv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="531" to="539" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
