<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of the Fam181 gene family during mouse development reveals distinct strain-specific expression patterns, suggesting a role in nervous system development and function</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-09-25">25 September 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Matthias</forename><surname>Marks</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Developmental Genetics Department</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>63-73, 14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Ihnestraße, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Biology, Chemistry and Pharmacy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Free University Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Takustrasse 3</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tracie</forename><surname>Pennimpede</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Developmental Genetics Department</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>63-73, 14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Ihnestraße, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lisette</forename><surname>Lange</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Developmental Genetics Department</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>63-73, 14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Ihnestraße, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Biology, Chemistry and Pharmacy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Free University Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Takustrasse 3</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Phillip</forename><surname>Grote</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Developmental Genetics Department</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>63-73, 14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Ihnestraße, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bernhard</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Developmental Genetics Department</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>63-73, 14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Ihnestraße, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Medical Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-University Medicine Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Benjamin Franklin, Hindenburgdamm 30</addrLine>
									<postCode>12203</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Lars</forename><surname>Wittler</surname></persName>
							<email>wittler@molgen.mpg.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Developmental Genetics Department</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>63-73, 14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Ihnestraße, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Cancer Biology and Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Queen&apos;s University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>10 Stuart St</addrLine>
									<postCode>K7L 3N6</postCode>
									<settlement>Kingston</settlement>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Cardiovascular Regeneration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Goethe University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Theodor-Stern-Kai 7</addrLine>
									<postCode>60590</postCode>
									<settlement>Frankfurt am Main</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of the Fam181 gene family during mouse development reveals distinct strain-specific expression patterns, suggesting a role in nervous system development and function</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-09-25">25 September 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">73C9C34CC1F54C23249B55259E166C1B</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.gene.2015.09.035</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 2 February 2015 Received in revised form 5 June 2015 Accepted 9 September 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Somitogenesis Mouse embryogenesis Neural development Background specificity Notch signaling aa, amino acid</term>
					<term>BAC, bacterial artificial chromosome</term>
					<term>BLAST, basic local alignment search tool</term>
					<term>bp, base pairs</term>
					<term>cDNA, complementary DNA</term>
					<term>cf, compare figure</term>
					<term>chairy, chick hairy homolog 1</term>
					<term>CMV-Cre, cytomegalovirus promoter driven Cre recombinase</term>
					<term>CO 2 , carbon dioxide</term>
					<term>CpG-methylation, cytosine-guanine dinucleotidemethylation</term>
					<term>DAPI, 4′,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole</term>
					<term>DIG, digoxigenin</term>
					<term>Dkk1, dickkopf homolog 1</term>
					<term>Dll1, delta-like 1</term>
					<term>DMEM, Dulbecco&apos;s modified eagle medium</term>
					<term>DNA, deoxyribonucleic acid</term>
					<term>DTT, dithiothreitol</term>
					<term>E, embryonic day</term>
					<term>EDTA, ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid</term>
					<term>EmGFP, emerald GFP</term>
					<term>ES cell (ESC), embryonic stem cell</term>
					<term>Fam181a, family with sequence similarity 181, member A</term>
					<term>Fam181b, family with sequence similarity 181, member B</term>
					<term>FCS, fetal calf serum</term>
					<term>FGF, fibroblast growth factor</term>
					<term>Fig., figure</term>
					<term>FITC, fluorescein isothiocyanate</term>
					<term>FlpE, flippase enhanced</term>
					<term>GFP, green fluorescent protein</term>
					<term>HEK293 cells, human embryonic kidney 293 cells</term>
					<term>Hes1, hairy and enhancer of split 1</term>
					<term>ID, identity</term>
					<term>IgG, immunoglobulin G</term>
					<term>kb, kilo bases</term>
					<term>kDa, kilo dalton</term>
					<term>Lfng, lunatic fringe</term>
					<term>loxP, locus of crossover P1</term>
					<term>lpm, lateral plate mesoderm</term>
					<term>MAMEP, molecular anatomy of the mouse embryo project</term>
					<term>MAPK, mitogen activated protein kinase</term>
					<term>min, minutes</term>
					<term>mM, millimolar</term>
					<term>mRNA, messenger RNA</term>
					<term>μm, micrometer</term>
					<term>NaCl, sodium chloride</term>
					<term>NP cells, neural progenitor cells</term>
					<term>ORF, open reading frame</term>
					<term>ov, otic vesicle</term>
					<term>PBS, phosphate buffered saline</term>
					<term>PCR, polymerase chain reaction</term>
					<term>PFA, paraformaldehyde</term>
					<term>Pmm2, phosphomannomutase 2</term>
					<term>psm, presomitic mesoderm</term>
					<term>qPCR, quantitative PCR</term>
					<term>RNA, ribonucleic acid</term>
					<term>RT-PCR, reverse transcriptase-PCR</term>
					<term>S, somite</term>
					<term>T7, T7 RNA polymerase</term>
					<term>TEAD4, TEA domain family member 4</term>
					<term>TS, Theiler stage</term>
					<term>U, unit</term>
					<term>v/v, volume/volume</term>
					<term>WISH, whole-mount in situ hybridization</term>
					<term>Wnt, wingless-type MMTV integration site family</term>
					<term>wt, wild type</term>
					<term>YAP1, yes-associated protein 1</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>During somitogenesis differential gene expression can be observed for so-called cyclic genes, which display expression changes with a periodicity of 120 min in the mouse.</s><s>In screens to identify novel cyclic genes in murine embryos, Fam181b was predicted to be an oscillating gene in the presomitic mesoderm (psm).</s><s>This gene, and its closely related paralog Fam181a, belong to the thus far uncharacterized Fam181 gene family.</s></p><p><s>Here we describe the expression of Fam181b and Fam181a during murine embryonic development.</s><s>In addition, we confirm oscillation of Fam181b in the psm in-phase with targets of, and regulated by, Notch signaling.</s><s>Fam181b expression in the psm, as well as in the lateral plate mesoderm, was found to be affected by genetic background.</s><s>We show that Fam181a and b exhibit partially overlapping mRNA expression patterns, and encode for proteins containing highly-conserved motifs, which predominantly localize to the nucleus.</s><s>A Fam181b lossof-function model was generated and found to result in no obvious phenotype.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p><s>During development of a complex multicellular organism, the cells which are being constantly generated require temporal and spatial instructions to ensure their correct positioning within the final body structure.</s><s>Throughout embryonic development, cohorts of cells are instructed to collectively adjust their expression profiles, and thus commit and differentiate into tissues and organs.</s><s>These changes in expression can occur at regularly spaced intervalsas in vertebrate segmentation.</s><s>This process, called somitogenesis, leads to the bilateral generation of somites from the anterior end of the presomitic mesoderm (psm).</s><s>The amount of time required for one somitogenic cycle is species-specific.</s><s>In zebrafish, a somite pair buds off from the psm every 30 min, in chicken every 90 min, and every 120 min in the mouse.</s><s>The molecular basis for somitogenesis is provided by morphogen gradients, which confer spatial information to the cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Aulehla et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Dubrulle et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Del Corral et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Moreno and Kintner, 2004)</ref>, along with a molecular oscillator termed the segmentation clock.</s><s>This ensures the correct spatiotemporal formation of somites <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Cooke and Zeeman, 1976)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In 1997, Palmeirim and colleagues provided evidence for the existence of the segmentation clock on a molecular level.</s><s>They showed that changes in the expression of the c-hairy1 gene in the psm were coordinated with somite formation in the developing chicken at 90 min intervals <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Palmeirim et al., 1997)</ref>.</s><s>Since then, a number of additional "cycling genes" have been discovered in various species.</s><s>These have been found to exclusively be targets of either the Notch-Dll <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Palmeirim et al., 1997)</ref>, the canonical Wnt <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Aulehla et al., 2003)</ref>, or the FGF-MAPK signaling pathways <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Dequéant et al., 2006)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Dequéant et al. (2006)</ref> used a microarray-based screen of temporally-aligned mouse embryonic psm samples to perform a large-scale search for novel oscillating genes.</s><s>Both in that study, and in a similar screen performed in our lab (P.</s><s>Grote, L. Wittler, M. Werber, and B.G. Herrmann, unpublished data), the thus-far uncharacterized gene Fam181b (synonym A830059I20Rik) was identified as an oscillating transcript with a possible function during segmentation.</s></p><p><s>The intron-less Fam181b gene is located on mouse chromosome 7 and is predicted to encode a protein with a length of 417 aa (~42 kDa).</s><s>It has one paralog, Fam181a (synonym EG544888), located on mouse chromosome 12, which encodes a protein of 292 aa <ref type="bibr">(~32 kDa)</ref>.</s><s>In this study we analyze the expression patterns of Fam181a and Fam181b during murine embryonic development and in adult organs, and present initial investigations into the function of the gene family members, thus providing the first comprehensive characterization of the murine Fam181 gene family.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Materials and methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Whole-mount in situ hybridization and vibratome sectioning</head><p><s>For whole-mount in situ hybridization (WISH), embryos were processed according to the protocol provided by the MAMEP database (http://mamep.molgen.mpg.de).</s><s>The probe for Fam181b corresponds to nucleotides 882-1813 of NM_021427.2,</s><s>and the probe for Fam181a to nucleotides 606-1343 of NM_001195726.1.</s><s>Probe templates were produced by PCR with a reverse primer containing a T7 site for antisense transcription.</s><s>DIG-labeled probes were generated by in vitro transcription according to standard procedures, and staining was performed using BM Purple (Roche).</s><s>Following the staining reaction, samples were postfixed in 4% PFA/PBS overnight.</s><s>Some specimens were used to generate vibratome sections (35 μm thickness) following a sucrose gradient and embedding in a glycerin/albumin matrix.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">In situ hybridization on paraffin sections</head><p><s>Embryos were fixed in 4% PFA/PBS overnight, processed into paraffin wax by standard procedures and sectioned using a microtome (5 μM).</s><s>In situ hybridization was performed on the sections according to the protocol from <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chotteau-Lelièvre et al. (2006)</ref>, with minor modifications.</s><s>The staining reaction was performed using BM Purple (Roche).</s><s>For each stage examined at least 3 sections from 2 different embryos were analyzed.</s><s>There was no observed variation in the staining pattern, and figures show representative staining.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Tail half cultures</head><p><s>For tail half culture experiments, E9.5 mouse embryos were dissected into ice-cold PBS and their caudal ends bisected along the neural tube using a tungsten needle, leaving several somites anterior to the psm.</s><s>After incubation of both halves for 30 min in DMEM/F12/10% FCS at 37 °C/7.5% CO 2 , one half was fixed in 4% PFA/PBS, while the second half was further incubated for 90 min or 120 min prior to fixation.</s><s>Corresponding halves were then processed simultaneously for WISH as described above.</s><s>For comparisons of gene expression at the same timepoint, both halves were immediately fixed after bisection.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Generation of Fam181b-V5 knock-in and knock-out embryos</head><p><s>To generate a knock-in vector, the genomic region containing the Fam181b transcript and a 2.6 kb 3′ homology arm were amplified by PCR from the RP23-168D4 BAC (BACPAC Resources Center, Oakland, CA, USA).</s><s>The 3′ homology arm contained a repeat of the last 139 bp of the transcript at its 5′ end added by the PCR primer.</s><s>The V5-tag was inserted at the 3′ end of the Fam181b ORF by fusion-PCR.</s><s>Both modified transcript and homology arm were then inserted into the PL451 vector ((Pgk): Frt-Pgk-em7-Neo-Frt-loxP) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Liu et al., 2003)</ref> upstream of the floxed PGK-Neo cassette.</s><s>For the knock-out vector, a 2.9 kb fragment upstream of the Fam181b transcriptional start site was amplified adding a loxP site to the 3′ end.</s><s>This served as 5′ homology arm and was subcloned, together with the Fam181b transcript coding region and the 3′ homology arm, into the PL451 vector upstream of the floxed PGK-Neo cassette.</s><s>Linearized vector for either the knock-in or knockout constructs was then used for targeted integration into the Fam181b locus of G4 mouse embryonic stem (ES) cells (129S6/SvEv × C57BL/6 N background), and correct integration was verified by Southern blot.</s><s>For the knock-in, the selection cassette was subsequently removed by transient transfection of positively targeted ESCs with a FlpE-containing expression plasmid.</s><s>Negative selection and Southern blot verified loss of the cassette.</s><s>Highly chimeric embryos were generated (70-80% chimerism) by morula aggregation <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Eakin and Hadjantonakis, 2006)</ref>.</s><s>To generate knock-out animals, chimeric F0 animals were directly crossed to CMV-Cre animals (C57BL/6 J background) for deletion of the transcript and the selection cassette.</s><s>The offspring were then intercrossed, and the resulting embryos/animals used for analysis.</s><s>All animal procedures were performed in ethical accordance with protocols set out by the Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics, with prior approval of the Berlin Animal Welfare Authorities (LAGeSo).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.">Differentiation of ESCs along the neural lineage</head><p><s>Murine G4 ESCs were grown under feeder-free conditions and subjected to in vitro differentiation into glutamatergic neurons according to the protocol established by <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bibel et al. (2007)</ref>.</s><s>Samples were taken every 2 days after the formation of cellular aggregates.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.">RNA extraction, cDNA synthesis, and quantitative PCR</head><p><s>For RNA extraction, samples were lysed in TRIzol® Reagent (Life Technologies).</s><s>Total RNA was extracted using the RNeasy Plus Mini Kit (Qiagen) and transcribed into cDNA using the QuantiTect® Reverse Transcription Kit (Qiagen), both according to the manufacturer's protocols.</s><s>For real-time quantitative PCR, cDNA and appropriate primer pairs were combined with GoTaq® qPCR Master Mix (Promega) and run on the StepOnePlus Real-Time PCR System (Life Technologies).</s><s>Analysis was performed using either the StepOne software v2.3 (Life Technologies) or the ΔΔct method and q-gene <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Muller et al., 2002)</ref>.</s><s>Pvalues were calculated using a one-tailed, paired Student's t-test.</s><s>For semi-quantitative PCR (RT-PCR), cDNA was used in a standard PCR reaction with GoTaq® Flexi DNA polymerase (Promega).</s><s>The following mouse-specific primers were used: Fam181a fwd: cctatcccgactaagccagc/Fam181a rev: gccaaaagagagagggctga; Fam181b fwd: cttcccagattgtgcgttgc/Fam181b rev: tctccagaggctggggtaaa; Oct4 fwd: tgttcccgtcactgctctgg/Oct4 rev: ttgccttggctcacagcatc; Pax6 fwd: catggcaaacaacctgcctatg/Pax6 rev: gcacgagtatgaggaggtctgac; TrkB fwd: agcagccctggtatcagcta/TrkB rev: cttgatgttcttccgggtgt; Lfng fwd: ctgca ccattggctacattg/Lfng rev: tgctgcaggttctctaggtg; Pmm2 fwd: agggaaaggcc tcacgttct/Pmm2 rev: aataccgcttatcccatccttca; Gapdh fwd: tcaagaaggtggt gaagcag/Gapdh rev: accaccctgttgctgtagcc.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7.">Transient transfection, immunofluorescence, and immunoblotting</head><p><s>Transient transfection of NIH3T3, HEK293, and C2C12 cells (ATCC Germany) was performed using Lipofectamine™ 2000 reagent (Life Technologies) according to the manufacturer's instructions.</s><s>Detection of proteins was performed using an α-V5 primary antibody (Life Technologies; R960-25) at a 1:1000 dilution, or an α-GFP antibody (Life Technologies; A11122) at a 1:500 dilution.</s><s>Secondary antibodies used for immunofluorescence were α-rabbit IgG-Alexa488 conjugated (Life Technologies; A11034), and α-mouse IgG-Alexa546 conjugated (Life Technologies; A11030), both at 1:1000.</s><s>Counterstaining was performed by incubation with FITC-phalloidin at 1:500 (Sigma; P5282), and slides were mounted using VECTASHIELD HardSet Mounting Medium with DAPI (Vector Laboratories).</s></p><p><s>Whole embryo lysates were prepared using TOPEX buffer (300 mM NaCl/50 mM Tris-HCL pH 7.5/0.5% Triton X-100/1 mM DTT/1× complete EDTA-free protease inhibitors (Roche) plus 33.33 U/ml Benzonase® (Sigma; E1014-25KU) at a ratio of 10:1 v/v of embryonic sample.</s><s>Immunoblotting was performed using standard procedures with primary α-V5 at 1:500, and α-mouse Laminin B1 loading-control (Abcam ab16048) diluted 1:3500.</s><s>Secondary antibodies used were α-mouse or α-rabbit HRP-linked IgG (Cell Signaling; 7076 and 70745), both at 1:2000.</s><s>Chemiluminescence detection was performed using the Amersham™ ECL™ Western blotting Detection Reagents (GE Healthcare) and images were acquired on a Fusion SL Vilber Lourmat device (Peqlab).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.8.">Imaging</head><p><s>For imaging of WISH-stained embryos, a MZ16A dissection microscope (Leica) fitted with an AxioCam MRc5 (Carl Zeiss MicroImaging) were used in combination with the AxioVision Software (Carl Zeiss MicroImaging).</s><s>Vibratome sections were imaged using a Zeiss Observer.Z1 microscope with an AxioCam MRc (Carl Zeiss MicroImaging) and the AxioVision Software.</s><s>Fluorescence microscopy was performed on an LSM710 laser-scanning microscope using the ZEN software (Carl Zeiss MicroImaging).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.9.">Phylogenetic analyses</head><p><s>Sequence alignment of human and murine FAM181 proteins was generated using CLC DNA workbench.</s><s>Multiple sequence alignment of the selected vertebrate species was produced using Clustal Omega <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Sievers et al., 2011)</ref> with default settings.</s><s>This alignment was used as input for ClustalW version 2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Larkin et al., 2007)</ref> to generate the phylogenetic tree.</s><s>The distance correction was enabled by the software, while other settings remained default.</s><s>Conversion of the Newick tree into an SVG tree was done using TreeVector (http://supfam.cs.bris.ac.uk/</s><s>TreeVector/index.html).</s><s>Sequence identities were calculated using William Pearson's lalign program (http://www.ch.embnet.org/</s><s>software/LALIGN_form.html).</s><s>The reference sequences used for the alignment and generation of the phylogenetic tree were: Alligator mississippiensis FAM181A XP_006278984.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.10.">Mouse strains</head><p><s>For the analysis of Fam181a and Fam181b expression patterns in embryos, and the characterization of Fam181b oscillation in the psm, the outbred CD1 and NMRI strains were used.</s><s>For expression analysis of Fam181 genes in adult tissues, samples were taken from a 53 week-old CD1 female animal.</s><s>The Dll1 transgenic mouse line (Hrabe de <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Angelis et al., 1997</ref>) was maintained at heterozygosity on a CD1 background.</s><s>The outbred strains C57BL/6J and 129S2SvHsd were used for analysis of the background-dependency of Fam181b expression.</s><s>The Dkk1 mouse line <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Mukhopadhyay et al., 2001)</ref> was maintained heterozygously on both C57BL/6J, and 129S2SvHsd backgrounds.</s><s>Here we used Dkk1 −/− embryos resulting from intercrosses of both strains.</s></p><p><s>Mice were maintained in the animal facility of the Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics, Berlin, in accordance with international standards and protocols.</s><s>Animal maintenance and all procedures performed on mice described here were performed in accordance with the German animal welfare act (Tierschutzgesetz, TSchG) and had prior approval from local authorities (LaGeSo).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results and discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">The FAM181 protein family is highly conserved among vertebrates</head><p><s>In order to classify the mouse Fam181 gene family in a phylogenetic context, we compared the predicted protein sequences of murine Fam181 genes with those from orthologous genes in other species.</s><s>mFAM181A and mFAM181B show 46% similarity on the amino acid level, while multiple sequence alignment with their human homologs showed a similarity of about 77% for both orthologous pairs (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>).</s><s>Within all human and mouse sequences, we found 4 conserved domains (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>, red and green boxed regions).</s><s>To further analyze this conservation, we performed a protein-protein BLAST search with the mouse FAM181s using non-redundant sequences to identify putative orthologs by sequence similarity.</s><s>This analysis illustrated that the FAM181 family is highly conserved among vertebrates.</s><s>In most species the BLAST search revealed two proteins, one more similar to mFAM181A and the other to mFAM181B.</s><s>Next, we performed a multiple sequence alignment for selected species, representing different taxa of vertebrates, which we used to generate a phylogenetic tree (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>) using the starlet sea anemone N. vectensis as an outgroup.</s><s>The existence of both paralogs was found among most vertebrate species.</s><s>In addition, the tree confirmed the conservation of the FAM181 family along the vertebrate phylum, with a large portion of highly conserved aa within 3 of the 4 conserved boxes (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>, orange lettered residues).</s><s>The fourth box, containing a proline-rich stretch (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>, green boxed region), was also found to be conserved, though the exact position and total number of proline residues varied between the species investigated.</s><s>In the nonavian sauropsid A. mississippiensis (American alligator) only a FAM181A ortholog was recovered, likely due to its incomplete genome sequence <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(St John et al., 2012)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The three boxes of highly conserved residues and the proline-rich stretch might play a role in the function of these proteins.</s><s>A structural homology search using the Phyre 2 online tool <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Kelley and Sternberg, 2009)</ref> showed a region of high similarity within FAM181B to a motif from the Hippo signaling effector yes-associated protein 1 (YAP1, Fold library IDs c3kysB and c3juaB), which is required for recognition by the DNA-binding protein TEAD4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Chen et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">reveiwed in Pan, 2010)</ref>.</s><s>This region partially overlapped with the conserved box 3 (residues 209 to 231) and was also found by a BLAST search with the third conserved box against all annotated mouse proteins.</s><s>However, the functional relevance of this finding remains to be evaluated.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">FAM181A/B proteins predominantly localize to the nucleus</head><p><s>The FAM181 proteins were thus-far uncharacterized, aside from their grouping by sequence similarity.</s><s>Since the Ensemble Genome Browser annotates the murine Fam181b gene as a pseudogene (ENSMUSG 00000051515) we wanted to examine whether FAM181B is expressed in vivo.</s><s>Therefore, we integrated a C-terminal V5-tag into one of the endogenous Fam181b alleles in murine ESCs, which were then used to generate chimeric embryos (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>).</s><s>We were able to detect FAM181B-V5 with the expected size (~42 kDa; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>, V5-KI lane) by immunoblotting of whole embryo protein lysates from TS13-14 knock-in embryos, as compared to control embryo lysate.</s><s>This provides strong evidence that Fam181b is a protein-coding gene with the predicted amino acid sequence.</s></p><p><s>We went on to determine the subcellular localization of FAM181B by transiently transfecting NIH3T3 cells with an expression construct encoding N-terminally V5-tagged FAM181B.</s><s>These cells were analyzed by indirect immunofluorescence for V5, and counterstained with DAPI and FITC-phalloidin to visualize the nuclei and the F-actin cytoskeleton, respectively.</s><s>Strong nuclear localization was observed for the tagged protein, with a much weaker signal in the cytoplasm (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2C-C″</ref>).</s><s>This localization was also observed when the V5-tag was located Cterminally (compare to Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D′</ref>), when a GFP-tag was used instead of V5, and also in HEK293 and C2C12 cells (data not shown).</s></p><p><s>Using the antibody HPA001603 from the Human Protein Atlas, hFAM181A was previously found to localize to nucleoli of U-2 OS human osteosarcoma cells, although an siRNA-mediated knock-down of Fam181a in the same study failed to validate this result <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Stadler et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>In order to compare the localization of both homologs in our system, we co-transfected NIH3T3 cells with FAM181B-V5 and FAM181A-EmGFP expression constructs.</s><s>Immunofluorescence with DAPI-counterstaining showed an enrichment in the nucleus with weaker speckles in the cytoplasm for FAM181A (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D-D‴</ref>).</s><s>Thus, although they lack a known nuclear localization signal, both murine FAM181 proteins localize to the nucleus in transiently-transfected cells.</s><s>As previously mentioned, both proteins also share the conserved box 3 region with structural homology to the Yap-Tead4 interaction interface (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>).</s><s>YAP requires TEAD proteins for its nuclear localization and to exert its function <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Vassilev et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Cao et al., 2008)</ref>.</s><s>However, deletion of box 3 from the FAM181B-V5 expression construct did not alter its nuclear localization in transiently-transfected NIH3T3 cells (data not shown).</s><s>Thus, another domain within FAM181B, and likely also FAM181A, must be responsible for the subcellular localization.</s><s>Further experiments are needed to validate the localization of endogenous proteins under physiological conditions and to address their molecular functions.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Fam181b is dynamically expressed during embryonic development</head><p><s>To investigate the expression of Fam181b during murine embryonic development, we performed an extensive analysis by whole-mount in situ hybridization (WISH) on wild type (wt) embryos between embryonic day (E) 6.5 and E12.5.</s><s>We further analyzed the expression domains on a histological level by generating vibratome sections for some of the specimens or performing in situ hybridization on midsagittal paraffin sections at E14.5.</s></p><p><s>Fam181b transcripts first became detectable at E7.5 in the prospective headfold region of late allantoic bud stage embryos (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A/A'</ref>).</s><s>During headfold formation, this domain narrowed to a smaller area (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3B/B'</ref>) which corresponds to the midbrain at later stages (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C</ref>, white dashed line).</s><s>At Theiler stage (TS) 12, Fam181b mRNA was detected in two further regions, one in the psm, and another in the rhombencephalon (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C</ref>/C′, black dashed line and red arrowhead, respectively).</s><s>Both midbrain and psm expression were maintained during all stages of embryonic development investigated (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C-H</ref>), while the rhombencephalic signal was undetectable after TS14 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>).</s><s>In agreement with its identification in screens for oscillatory expressed genes in the psm <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Dequéant et al. 2006</ref> and our unpublished data), we observed that the anteroposterior extension of the Fam181b psm expression domain varied between specimens (also see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7A-A"</ref>), suggesting oscillation of Fam181b transcription during somitogenesis.</s><s>Additional expression domains at TS14 were detected in the telencephalon, in the closed neural tube, and the lateral plate mesoderm (lpm) (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>, solid white line).</s><s>The signal in the neural tube was mainly localized to the medial portion (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4D</ref>/D′) and extended from the caudal end to the otic vesicle (ov).</s><s>The signal detected in the lpm was strongest around the level of the prospective forelimb bud.</s><s>At the morphological onset of formation of the forelimb bud (TS15), strong expression emerged as a single domain in the medial portion of the limb bud, while at the level of the prospective hindlimb bud an additional strong signal was detected in the lpm (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3E</ref>).</s><s>At this stage, a small domain of Fam181b transcriptional activity was also detectable in the anterior portion of the first branchial arch (black star).</s><s>Additionally, neural tube expression was observed in the roof plate, starting in the hindbrain and progressing posteriorly (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3E-G</ref>, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B</ref>/B′, D/D′).</s><s>Notably, while the signal in the medial neural tube was absent from the hindbrain region around the ov (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D″</ref>), the roof plate expression was continuous throughout the hindbrain and trunk (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3E″</ref>, G/G″).</s><s>At TS16 the emerging forelimb bud showed a second, more distal Fam181b expression domain, while the hindlimb bud began to recapitulate the expression pattern seen earlier within the forelimb bud, with a single medial domain (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3F</ref>/F′, red and black arrows).</s><s>From the dorsal side of the neural tube we observed triangular-shaped extensions of the Fam181b signal along the trunk which extended ventrally (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3F′</ref>, asterisks).</s><s>We identified these as cells of the peripheral nervous system, such as those which form the dorsal root ganglia (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4D-E′</ref>).</s><s>Expression was also detected in the dermomyotome (the dorsolateral compartment of differentiating somites) along the length of the trunk (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3F′</ref>, G′/G‴, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4E</ref>/E′).</s></p><p><s>At TS18 the distal expression domain in the forelimb bud was extended (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3G/G′</ref>).</s><s>This was present as a distally positioned stripe and two weaker proximodistally expanded stripes.</s><s>The first corresponds to the position of wrist plate progenitors, while the latter likely correspond to the chondrogenic progenitors of the ulna and radius.</s><s>At this stage, the hindlimb bud also showed a second, more distal, and slightly proximodistally extended Fam181b-expressing area (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3G‴</ref>).</s><s>After formation of hand and foot plate at TS21, both forelimb and hindlimb anlagen exhibited signals in the forming digits (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3H</ref>, black bars).</s><s>While the staining in ulnar and radial regions of the forelimb were undetectable at this stage, the anlagen of tibia and fibula in the hindlimb showed Fam181b expression (compare Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3H″</ref> to Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3H‴</ref>).</s><s>Additional staining appeared in the whisker pads at this stage (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3H</ref>, red arrow).</s></p><p><s>To further examine the differential domains of expression in the limbs, E14.5 forelimbs and hindlimbs were dissected and subjected to WISH for Fam181b, followed by vibratome sectioning.</s><s>This revealed that the expression detectable in the outgrowing digits of E14.5 limbs (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4F/G</ref>) was mainly localized to the cartilaginous regions between the phalanges, corresponding to the prospective joints (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4H-K</ref>).</s><s>In situ hybridization for Fam181b on midsagittal paraffin sections from E14.5 embryos (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4L</ref>-L″″) showed a strong signal within the ventricular zone of the forebrain, midbrain and the neural tube (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4L</ref>), confirmed expression in the dorsal root ganglia (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4L″</ref>), and revealed expression in cranial ganglia and nerves V, VIII, and IX (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4L′</ref>), the placodes of the vibrissal follicles (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4L‴</ref>), and the submandibular gland (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4L″″</ref>).</s><s>Expression was detected in cartilaginous primordia of the hyoid and turbinate bones.</s><s>The simultaneous presence of Fam181b mRNA in ganglia, nerves, and cartilaginous structures points to a common origin for these cells from the neural crest.</s><s>This is compatible with the signals seen at earlier stages within the first branchial arch and extending from the neural tube along the trunk.</s></p><p><s>In summary, Fam181b shows a highly dynamic expression pattern during mouse development, with strong expression domains detected in various neural tissues during all stages investigated.</s><s>Transient expression was also detected in the mesenchymal psm and limb anlagen, especially within its cartilage, and within neural crest derivatives.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Fam181a is differentially expressed during development and partially overlaps with Fam181b</head><p><s>Next we examined expression of the Fam181b paralog, Fam181a, during murine development by performing WISH on wt embryos between E7.5 and E12.5.</s><s>Whereas Fam181b expression was detected in embryos as young as late allantoic bud stage, Fam181a expression first became detectable at the late headfold stage in the prospective midbrain region (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5A</ref>-B′, bracket, cf.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A-B′</ref>).</s><s>Both genes were found to be highly expressed in the developing midbrain.</s><s>Fam181a expression extended throughout the entire neural tube by TS12 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5C</ref>/C′).</s><s>At this time the Fam181b staining was still restricted to the midbrain region, and started to arise in the psm, whereas Fam181a was never detected in the psm at any stage investigated.</s><s>A distinct signal for Fam181a could be detected in the rhombencephalon, anterior to the ov (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5C</ref>/C′, black arrowhead).</s><s>This domain corresponded to a similar expression domain observed for Fam181b (compare to Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C</ref>, red arrowhead).</s><s>At later stages, Fam181a transcription remained limited mainly to the neural tube and the developing brain, except for a domain in the eye anlagen (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5D-H</ref>, red arrowhead).</s><s>At TS14, the Fam181a signals in the brain vesicles and in the neural tube were separated by a small gap at the level of the ov (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5D′</ref>).</s><s>A similar gap was observed for Fam181b neural tube expression, which remained detectable up to TS16 (compare to Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>-F′), while for Fam181a it was only observed at TS14.</s></p><p><s>Between TS16 and TS19, the midbrain domain of Fam181a showed an increased staining intensity, demarcating it from the surrounding neural expression domains (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5F</ref>-H″, white dashed line).</s><s>This is similar to the Fam181b midbrain domain, which was distinctive from other neural expression domains at all stages investigated (compare to Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D-H</ref>).</s><s>Transcription of both paralogs differed within the developing limb buds.</s><s>While Fam181b showed continuous, distinctive limb expression starting at TS15 (see Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3E-H‴, 4C-K</ref>), no signal could be detected for Fam181a in the limbs up to TS21 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5E-J</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Overall, Fam181a transcriptional activity appears mainly to be limited to neural structures, where it shows extensive overlap with Fam181b.</s><s>In line with these findings, the expression of both genes was found to increase during the differentiation of murine ESCs into the neural lineage according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bibel et al. (2007)</ref> (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6A</ref>).</s><s>During the differentiation procedure, the highest expression levels for both genes were observed during differentiation into neural progenitor (NP) cells, while they decreased again during terminal differentiation into neurons.</s><s>The overlapping expression in neural tissues might be indicative of functional redundancy for the paralogs in these tissues.</s><s>In fact, our investigations revealed lack of any obvious morphological phenotype in mice which were homozygous-null for Fam181b alone (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.">Fam181a and b are expressed in various tissues of the adult mouse</head><p><s>In order to examine expression of both Fam181 genes in adult tissues, we performed RT-PCR and real-time qPCR on cDNA from various selected organs isolated from a female mouse (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6B</ref>).</s></p><p><s>The highest expression levels were found in the cerebrum and cerebellum, demonstrating maintenance of the neural expression for both genes after embryonic development.</s><s>Together with the data obtained from the embryos and the in vitro differentiation, this strongly suggests a main role for the Fam181 gene family in neural tissues.</s><s>This notion is further supported by findings from in vitro mouse models for the neurodevelopmental disorders Pitt-Hopkins syndrome and 9q34 deletion syndrome having dysregulated Fam181a expression <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Chen et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>The decreasing expression levels during the terminal differentiation of neural progenitors into neurons might be indicative of a function in non-neuronal cell types of the nervous system.</s><s>In line with this, Fam181b transcripts  <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Downs and Davies (1993)</ref>.</s><s>(A/B) lateral view, (A′/B′) view of anterior end, bracket in B marks emerging expression in prospective midbrain region.</s><s>C-J: Expression of Fam181a in E8.5-E12.5 mouse embryos.</s><s>Staging according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Theiler (1989)</ref>.</s><s>C/C′: Black arrowheads highlight a rhombomeric expression domain anterior to the otic vesicle.</s><s>D-H′: At E9.5 (TS14) expression arises in the eye anlagen and remains detectable up to E11.5 (TS20) (red arrowheads).</s><s>F-J: Around E10.5 (TS16) the midbrain expression domain becomes demarcated by increased staining intensity (white dashed line).</s><s>a, anterior; EHF, early head fold stage; fb, forelimb bud; hb, hindlimb bud; ht, heart tube; l, left; LHF, late head fold stage; nt, neural tube; ov, otic vesicle; p, posterior; r, right; TS, Theiler stage.</s></p><p><s>have been found to be enriched in the transcriptome of astrocytes <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Lovatt et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>Further overlapping expression was found in the ovaries and adrenals (Fam181a only weakly), though at lower levels as compared to the neural expression.</s></p><p><s>Unique expression for Fam181a was observed in the lung.</s><s>Changes in the CpG-methylation of the Fam181a locus have been reported to be associated with asthma <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Gunawardhana et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Wysocki et al., 2014)</ref>, and breathing difficulties is also one of the symptoms of Pitt-Hopkins syndrome.</s><s>This may suggest a link between the dysregulation of Fam181a expression and lung function.</s><s>Unique expression for Fam181b was found in the heart and spleen.</s><s>Very faint bands from the RT-PCR were also detected in liver (Fam181a and b) and kidney (Fam181a), though these were barely detectable by real-time qPCR.</s><s>In general, the expression levels for both Fam181 genes in all tissues investigated were lower than those of the housekeeping gene Pmm2, which was used for normalization.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6.">Fam181b oscillates in the psm in-phase with Notch targets</head><p><s>Fam181b was previously predicted to exhibit oscillatory expression during somitogenesis <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Dequéant et al., 2006)</ref>.</s><s>First we checked whether this oscillation could be visualized by WISH using E9.5 mouse embryos.</s><s>Comparing different embryos we found changes in the anteroposterior extension of Fam181b mRNA within the psm, varying from a broad domain extending throughout the posterior psm, to a narrow domain of expression at the level of the prospective somite S-II (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7A</ref>-A″, white bracket).</s><s>Expression in the caudal end/tail bud was never found to be stronger than in more anterior regions of the PSM, as it is the case for other oscillating genes like Lfng <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Forsberg et al., 1998)</ref> and Dkk1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Dequéant et al., 2006)</ref>.</s><s>To verify that the observed changes were due to oscillating expression, we went on to perform tail-half cultures, wherein the caudal trunk of TS13-15 embryos was split at the midline and one half was fixed (t = 0), while the second half was further cultured for 90 min or 120 min before fixation.</s><s>Both halves were then simultaneously subjected to in situ-hybridization for Fam181b.</s><s>After 90 min, 8 out of 8 samples showed changes in Fam181b mRNA distribution (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7B</ref>).</s><s>In contrast, after 120 min, the time for one complete somitogenic cycle in the mouse, a comparable pattern was observed between the cultured halves and their counterparts (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7B′, n = 4</ref>).</s><s>This verifies that Fam181b is indeed expressed in an oscillatory manner during somitogenesis.</s></p><p><s>Next, to address which signaling pathway the Fam181b oscillations were associated with, we prepared tail halves from E9.5 mouse caudal ends and subjected the two halves to in situ-hybridization for Fam181b, and either Dkk1 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7C</ref>/C′) or Lfng (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7D</ref>/D′).</s><s>During the phase when the transcriptional domain of the Wnt-target Dkk1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Niida et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Dequéant et al., 2006)</ref> was expanded throughout the posterior 2/3 of the psm, Fam181b mRNA was restricted to a small stripe at the level of the prospective somite S-II (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7C</ref>).</s><s>When Dkk1 expression was turned off, the Fam181b signal was expanded through the psm (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7C′</ref>).</s><s>In contrast, Fam181b expression could be detected around the level of S-II when the mRNA of the Notch target gene Lfng (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Forsberg et al., 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">McGrew et al., 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Aulehla and Johnson, 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Morales et al., 2002)</ref> was restricted to the S-I prospective somite region (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7D</ref>).</s><s>When Lfng was strongly expressed in the caudal end and posterior psm (with a stripe in the anterior half of the S0 somite), the Fam181b domain extended more posteriorly (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7D′</ref>).</s><s>This demonstrates that oscillation of Fam181b is in-phase with the Notch-target gene Lfng and out-of-phase with the canonical Wnt-target Dkk1.</s><s>In the anterior psm, Lfng expression becomes stabilized as a stripe of expression through the activity of the transcription factor MESP2, thereby inhibiting Notch signaling in the S0 region <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Morimoto et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Oginuma et al., 2010)</ref>.</s><s>Interestingly, Fam181b is absent from this region (red line in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7D′</ref>), suggesting a direct regulation by Notch signaling.</s></p><p><s>To investigate whether Notch signaling activity has a regulatory impact on Fam181b transcription, we performed WISH on loss-of-function mutants for Dll1 (Hrabe de <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Angelis et al., 1997)</ref> and their heterozygous and wild-type control littermates.</s><s>Dll1, a ligand for the Notch receptor, is expressed in the psm and in the central nervous system, with a strong domain in the developing forebrain <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Tax et al., 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bettenhausen and Gossler, 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Bettenhausen et al., 1995)</ref>.</s><s>Homozygous mutants can be discriminated from their wild-type and heterozygous counterparts by defects in segmental patterning, which become overt from E8.5 onwards (Hrabe de <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Angelis et al., 1997)</ref>.</s><s>In E9.5 wild-type and heterozygous control embryos, Fam181b expression was present as described above (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7E</ref>, compare to Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>).</s><s>In contrast, Fam181b transcripts were absent from the psm of Dll1 −/− embryos (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7E'</ref>) and expression in the telencephalon was restricted to its dorsal aspect (black arrowhead in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7E′</ref>, compare to Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7E</ref>).</s><s>Taken together, this suggests a regional dependency of Fam181b expression on Notch signaling, especially in the psm and the telencephalon.</s><s>It has been previously shown that cyclic activity of the Notch pathway leads to a salt-and-pepperlike oscillatory expression of Dll1 and Hes1 in neural progenitor cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Kageyama et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Shimojo et al., 2008)</ref>.</s><s>It remains to be investigated whether Fam181b activity also displays oscillatory expression in this cell type.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.7.">The psm and lpm expression of Fam181b is dependent on genetic background</head><p><s>To gain further insight into the regulation of Fam181b transcription, we analyzed the Fam181b expression pattern in Dkk1 loss-of-function embryos <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Mukhopadhyay et al., 2001)</ref>.</s><s>While most expression domains appeared unaltered, presomitic and lateral plate mesoderm expression of Fam181b was undetected in all of the embryos investigated, irrespective of their genotype (data not shown).</s><s>Our Fam181b expression analysis was performed in embryos from CD1 and NMRI outbred strains, and the Dll1 mouse line was maintained on a CD1 background, whereas the Dkk1 mutation is maintained on 129S2SvHsd or C57BL/6J backgrounds.</s><s>Assimilating this information, we presumed that the genetic background may be impacting the Fam181b expression pattern.</s><s>To investigate this notion further, we analyzed E10.5 embryos from C57BL/ 6J and 129S2SvHsd inbred strains by WISH.</s><s>In contrast to CD1 embryos, which were processed and stained in parallel (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8A</ref>/A′), neither C57BL/6 J (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8B</ref>/B′) nor 129S2SvHsd embryos (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8C</ref>/C′) exhibited expression of Fam181b in the psm or lpm.</s><s>All other domains of Fam181b expression described above, including those in the mesodermal-derived limb anlagen, were maintained (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>) and were of comparable staining intensity with respect to CD1 controls.</s><s>This argues for a partial dependency of mesodermal Fam181b expression on genetic background.</s><s>In support of our results, such backgroundspecific differences for Fam181b between mouse strains were also identified in a transcriptome analysis by <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Kong et al. (2014)</ref>.</s><s>These results underpin that the use of a particular genetic background is an important consideration for the comparability of experiments in the mouse, especially, although not exclusively, with respect to the interpretation and validation of expression data.</s><s>For instance, the screens that identified Fam181b as an oscillatory gene were done using either the CD1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Dequéant et al., 2006)</ref> or the NMRI outbred strain (P.</s><s>Grote, L. Wittler, M. Werber, and B.G. Herrmann, unpublished data).</s><s>In contrast, functional analyses are predominantly performed using inbred strains, such as C57BL/6.</s><s>Although the exact genetic mechanism of this tissue-specific background-dependency remains to be investigated, to our knowledge this is the first description of a cycling gene exhibiting backgrounddependent oscillatory expression.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.8.">Loss of Fam181b does not result in an overt morphological phenotype</head><p><s>To investigate the function of the Fam181b gene, we generated a conditional allele by homologous recombination in murine ESCs, which was then used to generate a loss-of-function model (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9A-B</ref>).</s><s>Embryos homozygous for deletion of Fam181b displayed no obvious developmental defects when examined up to E17.5 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9C-D′</ref>).</s><s>Homozygous-null offspring were vital, fertile, and displayed normal morphology (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9E</ref>).</s><s>Interestingly, Fam181a expression levels were significantly reduced in brain and neural tube tissues of Fam181b null embryos compared to heterozygous littermates (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9F</ref>).</s><s>Additionally, there were no changes in the expression of the neural marker genes TrkB and Pax6 in the adult cerebellum, where strong Fam181b expression is observed, and expression of the Notch target gene Lfng was similarly unaffected in heterozygous and homozygous Fam181b knock-out animals (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9G</ref>).</s><s>In this adult tissue, a significant decrease in Fam181a expression levels was also detected similarly to that observed in the embryonic tissues (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9G</ref>, compare to Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">9F</ref>).</s><s>These findings suggest that FAM181B positively regulates its paralog in these tissues.</s><s>It remains to be investigated how this observation extends to other tissues.</s><s>Given their similarity and partially overlapping mRNA expression patterns in developing and adult neural structures, we cannot exclude that the FAM181 proteins exhibit functionally redundant roles in the nervous system, and may also play redundant roles in a developmental context.</s><s>Considering our previous data, we also cannot completely rule out the possibility of backgrounddependent phenotypic differences within the psm or lpm.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusions</head><p><s>In summary, we have shown that the Fam181 genes constitute a novel gene family that is conserved among vertebrates with two paralogs, namely Fam181a and Fam181b, per species.</s><s>Both genes display highly dynamic and specific expression patterns during murine embryonic development.</s><s>Their expression is most prominent in neural tissues, where Fam181a is exclusively expressed during  The Fam181b-null allele resulted from excision of the loxP-flanked region following crossing F1 chimeric animals with the CMV-Cre general deletor strain.</s><s>An additional HindIII restriction site in the conditional allele (HindIII*) allowed for discrimination of the null allele from the wt allele.</s><s>B: Southern blot analysis with HindIII-digested genomic DNA and an external 5′ probe in order to detect the wildtype allele (8.5 kb) and the Fam181b-null allele (6.8 kb) in offspring from intercrosses of Fam181 +/− animals.</s><s>C-C′: No Fam181b transcript was detected at E9.5 by whole-mount in situ hybridization of homozygous mutants (C′) as compared to heterozygous littermates (C).</s><s>D-D′: At E17.5, heterozygotes (D) and homozygous-null fetuses (D′) were morphologically indistinguishable.</s><s>E: Heterozygous (+/−) and homozygous (−/−) adult offspring were viable, fertile, and indistinguishable by external morphology.</s><s>F: Analysis of Fam181a/b expression levels in head and neural tube samples (blue and purple, respectively) from Fam181b heterozygous and homozygous knock-out embryos at E9.5 by qPCR.</s><s>In both sample types, Fam181a levels were significantly reduced in homozygous-null embryos ( ⁎⁎: P ≤ 0.05, ⁎⁎⁎: P ≤ 0.01, n = 2).</s><s>The embryo schematic illustrates the dissected tissues.</s><s>G: Quantitative real-time PCR on cerebella from heterozygous (dark gray bars) and homozygous adult females (light gray) confirms the absence of detectable Fam181b transcripts in the homozygous-null animals.</s><s>While the levels of the Notch target gene Lfng and markers of neural differentiation (TrkB, Pax6) are unchanged, Fam181a expression is significantly reduced in the cerebellum (P ≤ 0.01, n = 2).</s><s>Normalization for qPCR was relative to Pmm2 and expression of the heterozygous samples set to 1. embryonic development, while Fam181b shows additional areas of transcriptional activity in mesoderm-derived tissues.</s><s>We confirmed the oscillation of Fam181b transcription in mouse psm during somitogenesis, cycling in-phase with, and regulated by, the Notch-Dll pathway.</s><s>Interestingly, the oscillating Fam181b psm expression, along with lpm expression, was found to be dependent on genetic background.</s><s>The FAM181 proteins localize to the nucleus, though the responsible signal and mechanism remains to be identified.</s><s>Despite its specific and diverse expression pattern, loss of Fam181b does not produce any obvious morphological phenotype in a loss-of-function mouse model, possibly due to functional redundancy with Fam181a and/or genetic background effects.</s><s>Further studies are required to elucidate the functions of these proteins.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1.</s><s>FAM181 family conservation in vertebrates.</s><s>A: Multiple sequence alignment of mouse and human FAM181 protein homologs.</s><s>Conserved residues between murine and human FAM181B are highlighted in light gray, amino acids conserved in 3 proteins by a dark gray background, and white lettered residues with a black background are those conserved in all 4 homologs.</s><s>Red and green dashed boxes outline highly conserved motifs.</s><s>Orange letters on a black background indicate residues conserved in all vertebrate species investigated in B. B: Phylogenetic tree from selected vertebrate species.</s><s>The Cnidaria Nematostella vectensis was used as outgroup.</s><s>FAM181B proteins are highlighted in green, FAM181A proteins in blue.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,142.70,52.21,318.67,565.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 2. FAM181 protein expression and localization.</s><s>A: Schematic representation of the construct for knock-in of V5-tagged Fam181b into the endogenous locus.</s><s>The Neomycin resistance cassette was removed before diploid aggregation.</s><s>B: Whole embryo lysate of Fam181b-V5 knock-in embryos generated by diploid aggregation (V5-KI) and wildtype embryos (wt) were analyzed for V5-tagged FAM181B by immunoblot.</s><s>Laminin B1 served as loading control.</s><s>C-C″: NIH3T3 cells were transfected with an N-terminally V5-tagged Fam181b ORF expression construct, and analyzed by indirect immunofluorescence for V5.</s><s>Counterstaining was performed with DAPI and FITC-Phalloidin.</s><s>D-D‴: NIH3T3 cells were simultaneously transfected with C-terminally V5-tagged FAM181B and C-terminally EmGFP-tagged FAM181A expression constructs.</s><s>Analyses were performed by indirect immunofluorescence for EmGFP and V5, and cells were counterstained with DAPI.</s><s>Scale bar = 25 μm.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,95.07,52.21,396.36,344.69" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 3. Fam181b expression from E7.5-E12.5.</s><s>A-B′: Expression of Fam181b in E7.5 mouse embryos.</s><s>Staging (indicated in the top right corner) according to Downs and Davies (1993).</s><s>(A/B) lateral view, (A′/B′) view of anterior end, brackets mark emerging expression in neural plate (A) or head fold (B).</s><s>C-H‴: Expression of Fam181b in E8.5-E12.5 mouse embryos.</s><s>Staging according to Theiler (1989).</s><s>White dashed line indicates midbrain expression domain; black dashed line marks presomitic mesoderm expression.</s><s>C-D″: Red arrowheads highlight the rhombomeric expression domain anterior to the otic vesicle.</s><s>D: At E9.5 expression arises in the lateral plate mesoderm (white solid line).</s><s>E-F′: Black arrow heads mark striped expression domains in early limb anlagen; black star in E highlights expression in 1st branchial arch, white stars in F mark expression in spinal nerve precursors.</s><s>F-G″: From E10.5 (TS16) on, multiple, distinct expression domains in more advanced forelimb (red arrows) and hindlimb anlagen (black arrows) can be distinguished.</s><s>H-H‴: At E12.5 (TS21) expression domains in the developing phalanges (black bars) and the whisker pads (red arrow) become detectable.</s><s>White stars in H′ mark expression in spinal nerve precursors.</s><s>LB, late allantoic bud stage; a, anterior; p, posterior; l, left; r, right; EHF, early head fold stage; TS, Theiler stage; ht, heart tube; nt, neural tube; ov, otic vesicle; fb, forelimb bud; hb, hindlimb bud.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,53.29,52.21,497.48,319.81" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 4. Detailed expression of Fam181b.</s><s>A-E': Vibratome sections of TS15 (A-B''') and TS17 (C-E') mouse embryos.</s><s>A &amp; C: Representative embryos at each stage with indicated section planes (white dashed lines).</s><s>B, D, &amp; E: Overview of sectioned region.</s><s>B'-B''', D', &amp; E': Higher magnification of boxed regions in B, D, &amp; E. F-K: Detailed expression of Fam181b in E14.5 limb anlagen.</s><s>F/G: Representative E14.5 fore-(F) and hindlimbs (G) shown from dorsal and ventral sides.</s><s>H-K: Longitudinal vibratome sections of fore-(H-I) and hindlimbs (J-K).</s><s>L-L'''': In situ hybridization for Fam181b on midsagittal paraffin section of E14.5 wildtype embryo.</s><s>L: Overview image.</s><s>Black dashed line marks roof of neopallial cortex.</s><s>Asterisks highlight cartilage primordia of turbinate bones.</s><s>L'-L'''': Higher magnification of boxed regions in L. Arrowheads in L''' mark follicle primordia of the vibrissae.</s><s>Scale bars = 0.5 mm.</s><s>ba1, 1st branchial arch; cp, choroid plexus; d, dorsal; da, dorsal aorta; dm, dermomyotome; drg, dorsal root ganglia; fb, forelimb bud; h, hyoid bone cartilage primordium; hb, hindlimb bud; ht., heart; igIX/sgIX, inferior/superior ganglion of glossopharyngeal nerve; lg, lung; li, liver anlagen; mb, lateral wall of midbrain; nt, neural tube; ov, otic vesicle; s, somite; sm, submandibular gland; tgV, trigeminal ganglion; TS, Theiler stage; v, ventral; vcgVIII, vestibulocochlear ganglion.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,44.62,52.21,497.49,427.81" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 5. Fam181a expression from E7.5-E12.5.</s><s>A-B′: Expression of Fam181a in E7.5 mouse embryos.</s><s>Staging (indicated in the top right corner) according to Downs and Davies (1993).</s><s>(A/B) lateral view, (A′/B′) view of anterior end, bracket in B marks emerging expression in prospective midbrain region.</s><s>C-J: Expression of Fam181a in E8.5-E12.5 mouse embryos.</s><s>Staging according to Theiler (1989).</s><s>C/C′: Black arrowheads highlight a rhombomeric expression domain anterior to the otic vesicle.</s><s>D-H′: At E9.5 (TS14) expression arises in the eye anlagen and remains detectable up to E11.5 (TS20) (red arrowheads).</s><s>F-J: Around E10.5 (TS16) the midbrain expression domain becomes demarcated by increased staining intensity (white dashed line).</s><s>a, anterior; EHF, early head fold stage; fb, forelimb bud; hb, hindlimb bud; ht, heart tube; l, left; LHF, late head fold stage; nt, neural tube; ov, otic vesicle; p, posterior; r, right; TS, Theiler stage.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,53.29,52.22,497.48,304.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 6.</s><s>Fam181 expression in ES cells differentiated into the neural lineage and in adult tissues.</s><s>A: Neural differentiation of murine F1G4 ES cells according to Bibel et al. (2007).</s><s>During the differentiation procedure samples were taken following formation of the cellular aggregates and used for total RNA extraction and cDNA synthesis.</s><s>Fam181a/b expression levels were analyzed by quantitative real-time PCR.</s><s>Oct4 was used as a stem cell marker, Pax6 as a marker for neural differentiation, and TrkB for terminal neurons.</s><s>The expression of Fam181a is maximally upregulated in the D8 sample (230-fold), that of Fam181b in the neural progenitor (NP) cell sample (80-fold).</s><s>B: Fam181a and b expression in various tissues of an adult female mouse.</s><s>Total RNA was extracted from selected organs and reversetranscribed into cDNA.</s><s>A sample treated without reverse transcriptase was used as negative control.</s><s>The cDNA was either used for RT-PCR with Gapdh as loading control (inset), or for quantitative real-time PCR (graph).</s><s>qPCR was normalized to Pmm2 and analyzed by qGene.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,35.21,52.22,248.38,315.61" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 7. Oscillating Fam181b expression in-phase with Notch targets.</s><s>A-A″: Fam181b expression in individual E9.5 mouse caudal ends.</s><s>Brackets indicate differences in the PSM expression domain.</s><s>B/B′: E9.5 caudal end half culture.</s><s>The cultivated half shows changes in Fam181b expression compared to fixed (t = 0) half.</s><s>Cultivation time with respect to the fixed half (Δt) and number of samples with changes in expression (n) are indicated.</s><s>C/C′: Comparison of Fam181b and Dkk1 expression in individual E9.5 caudal end half pairs.</s><s>D/D′: Comparison of Fam181b and Lfng expression in individual E9.5 caudal end half pairs.</s><s>(White arrowheads in B-D′ mark anterior S0 somite boundary).</s><s>Scale bars = 0.5 mm.</s><s>E/E′: Representative E9.5 Dll1 control (E; wt and het) and Dll1 −/− (E′) embryos from their ventral sides.</s><s>Red dashed line highlights the psm.</s><s>Numbers of embryos are indicated in the bottom right corner.</s><s>ht, heart; ov, otic vesicle.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,53.12,52.21,497.84,249.11" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 8. Fam181b expression in C57BL/6J and 129S2SvHsd inbred strains.</s><s>A-C: CD1 (A), C57BL/6J (B), and 129S2SvHsd (C) E10.5 wild-type embryos were analyzed for Fam181b expression by WISH.</s><s>A′-C′: Magnification of boxed regions in A-C.</s><s>The number of embryos analyzed is indicated.</s><s>Dashed line and arrowhead in C′ indicate Fam181b lpm and psm expression respectively.</s><s>fb, forelimb bud; ov, otic vesicle.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="11,133.91,52.22,318.67,493.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig.9.</s><s>Fam181b knock-out mouse model.</s><s>A: Schematic representation of the Fam181b conditional allele.</s><s>The Fam181b-null allele resulted from excision of the loxP-flanked region following crossing F1 chimeric animals with the CMV-Cre general deletor strain.</s><s>An additional HindIII restriction site in the conditional allele (HindIII*) allowed for discrimination of the null allele from the wt allele.</s><s>B: Southern blot analysis with HindIII-digested genomic DNA and an external 5′ probe in order to detect the wildtype allele (8.5 kb) and the Fam181b-null allele (6.8 kb) in offspring from intercrosses of Fam181 +/− animals.</s><s>C-C′: No Fam181b transcript was detected at E9.5 by whole-mount in situ hybridization of homozygous mutants (C′) as compared to heterozygous littermates (C).</s><s>D-D′: At E17.5, heterozygotes (D) and homozygous-null fetuses (D′) were morphologically indistinguishable.</s><s>E: Heterozygous (+/−) and homozygous (−/−) adult offspring were viable, fertile, and indistinguishable by external morphology.</s><s>F: Analysis of Fam181a/b expression levels in head and neural tube samples (blue and purple, respectively) from Fam181b heterozygous and homozygous knock-out embryos at E9.5 by qPCR.</s><s>In both sample types, Fam181a levels were significantly reduced in homozygous-null embryos ( ⁎⁎: P ≤ 0.05, ⁎⁎⁎: P ≤ 0.01, n = 2).</s><s>The embryo schematic illustrates the dissected tissues.</s><s>G: Quantitative real-time PCR on cerebella from heterozygous (dark gray bars) and homozygous adult females (light gray) confirms the absence of detectable Fam181b transcripts in the homozygous-null animals.</s><s>While the levels of the Notch target gene Lfng and markers of neural differentiation (TrkB, Pax6) are unchanged, Fam181a expression is significantly reduced in the cerebellum (P ≤ 0.01, n = 2).</s><s>Normalization for qPCR was relative to Pmm2 and expression of the heterozygous samples set to 1.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p><s>We thank Dr. Heinrich Schrewe for discussions regarding this work, Manuela Scholze and Eun-ha Shin for providing reagents, Dijana Wrembel and Christin Franke for animal husbandry, and Karol Macura and Judith Fiedler for generating mouse lines and transgenic embryos.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic expression of lunatic fringe suggests a link between notch signaling and an autonomous cellular oscillator driving somite segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aulehla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0012160698991643" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">207</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Accessed September 12, 2014</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wnt3a plays a major role in the segmentation clock controlling somitogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aulehla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.cell.com/developmental-cell/fulltext/S1534-5807" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-01-19">2003. Accessed January 19. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient isolation of novel mouse genes differentially expressed in early postimplantation embryos</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bettenhausen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gossler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S088875438571172X" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="436" to="441" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-10-02">1995. Accessed October 2. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transient and restricted expression during mouse embryogenesis of Dll1, a murine gene closely related to Drosophila Delta</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bettenhausen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7671806" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2407" to="2418" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-10-02">1995. Accessed October 2. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generation of a defined and uniform population of CNS progenitors and neurons from mouse embryonic stem cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bibel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nprot.2007.147</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2007.147" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1034" to="1043" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-07-15">2007. Accessed July 15. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">YAP regulates neural progenitor cell number via the TEA domain transcription factor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Pfaff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://genesdev.cshlp.org/content/22/23/3320.short" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3320" to="3334" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Accessed May 7, 2014])</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural basis of YAP recognition by TEAD4 in the hippo pathway</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://genesdev.cshlp.org/content/24/3/290.short" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="290" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Accessed May 2, 2014</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular convergence of neurodevelopmental disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0002929714003966" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Hum. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-10-14">2014. Accessed October 14. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expression analysis of murine genes using in situ hybridization with radioactive and nonradioactively labeled RNA probes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chotteau-Lelièvre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dollé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gofflot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16780194" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">326</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Accessed May 12, 2014</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A clock and wavefront model for control of the number of repeated structures during animal morphogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cooke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Zeeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022519376801312" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Theor. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="455" to="476" />
			<date type="published" when="1976-03-23">1976. Accessed March 23. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Opposing FGF and retinoid pathways control ventral neural pattern, neuronal differentiation, and segmentation during body axis extension</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Del</forename><surname>Corral</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0896627303005658" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-03-23">2003. Accessed March 23. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A complex oscillating network of signaling genes underlies the mouse segmentation clock</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-L</forename><surname>Dequéant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/314/5805/1595.short" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">314</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5805</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1595" to="1598" />
			<date type="published" when="2006-03-23">2006. Accessed March 23. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Staging of gastrulating mouse embryos by morphological landmarks in the dissecting microscope</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Downs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://dev.biologists.org/content/118/4/1255.short" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1255" to="1266" />
			<date type="published" when="1993-07-16">1993. Accessed July 16. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FGF signaling controls somite boundary position and regulates segmentation clock control of spatiotemporal Hox gene activation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dubrulle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mcgrew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Pourquié</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.cell.com/fulltext/S0092-8674(01" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="438" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-03-23">2001. Accessed March 23. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Production of chimeras by aggregation of embryonic stem cells with diploid or tetraploid mouse embryos</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Eakin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A.-K</forename><surname>Hadjantonakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.nature.com/nprot/journal/v1/n3/pdf/nprot.2006.173.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1145" to="1153" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Accessed May 12, 2014</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Waves of mouse Lunatic fringe expression, in four-hour cycles at two-hour intervals, precede somite boundary formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Forsberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Crozet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0960982207004241" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1027" to="1030" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Accessed September 12, 2014</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential DNA methylation profiles of infants exposed to maternal asthma during pregnancy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gunawardhana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24166889" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatr. Pulmonol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="852" to="862" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-11-01">2014. Accessed November 1. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Maintenance of somite borders in mice requires the Delta homologue DII1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hrabe De Angelis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcintyre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gossler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/386717a0</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/386717a0" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">386</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6626</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="717" to="721" />
			<date type="published" when="1997-10-02">1997. Accessed October 2. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic Notch signaling in neural progenitor cells and a revised view of lateral inhibition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kageyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nn.2208</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nn.2208" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1247" to="1251" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-09-16">2008. Accessed September 16. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein structure prediction on the Web: a case study using the Phyre server</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J E</forename><surname>Sternberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nprot.2009.2</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2009.2" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="371" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-04-29">2009. Accessed April 29. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Divergent dysregulation of gene expression in murine models of fragile X syndrome and tuberous sclerosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=3940253&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;rendertype=abstract" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Autism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014-10-29">2014. Accessed October 29. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Available at</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clustal W and Clustal X version 2.0</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Larkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/content/23/21/2947.short" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2947" to="2948" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-03-19">2007. Accessed March 19. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A highly efficient recombineering-based method for generating conditional knockout mutations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jenkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Copeland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://genome.cshlp.org/content/13/3/476.short" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="476" to="484" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-04-28">2003. Accessed April 28. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lovatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The astrocyte transcriptome. Neuroglia (Available at: http:// books.google.de/books?hl=de&amp;lr=&amp;id=XPI6jCVk7BsC&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA347&amp; dq=fam181b&amp;ots=42dPvpFGDm&amp;sig=yOeled8NQ2ZOS8zzTwIFXGLc7f4</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-10-29">2012. Accessed October 29. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The lunatic fringe gene is a target of the molecular clock linked to somite segmentation in avian embryos</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mcgrew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0960982298704014" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="979" to="982" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Accessed September 12, 2014</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Periodic lunatic fringe expression is controlled during segmentation by a cyclic transcriptional enhancer responsive to Notch signaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Morales</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yasuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ish-Horowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1534580702002113" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Accessed September 12, 2014</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulation of segmental patterning by retinoic acid signaling during Xenopus somitogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Moreno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kintner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1534580704000267" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="218" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-03-23">2004. Accessed March 23. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Mesp2 transcription factor establishes segmental borders by suppressing Notch activity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Morimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nature03591</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature03591" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">435</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7040</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="354" to="359" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Accessed April 7, 2015])</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dickkopf1 is required for embryonic head induction and limb morphogenesis in the mouse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mukhopadhyay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1534580701000417" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="434" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-11-16">2001. Accessed November 16. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Short technical report processing of gene expression data generated by quantitative real-time RT-PCR</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Muller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.qpcrupdate.org/muller-2002-qgene.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechniques</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-11-14">2002. Accessed November 14. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DKK1, a negative regulator of Wnt signaling, is a target of the beta-catenin/TCF pathway</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Niida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/sj.onc.1207892</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/sj.onc.1207892" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncogene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8520" to="8526" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-08-12">2004. Accessed August 12. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The oscillation of Notch activation, but not its boundary, is required for somite border formation and rostral-caudal patterning within a somite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oginuma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://dev.biologists.org/content/137/9/1515.full" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1515" to="1522" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Accessed April 7, 2015])</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Avian hairy gene expression identifies a molecular clock linked to vertebrate segmentation and somitogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Palmeirim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0092867400804511" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="639" to="648" />
			<date type="published" when="1997-03-23">1997. Accessed March 23. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The hippo signaling pathway in development and cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.cell.com/article/S1534580710004296/fulltext" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="491" to="505" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Accessed May 8, 2014</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oscillations in notch signaling regulate maintenance of neural progenitors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Shimojo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ohtsuka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kageyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0896627308001669" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="52" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="2008-07-14">2008. Accessed July 14. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast, scalable generation of high-quality protein multiple sequence alignments using Clustal Omega</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sievers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=3261699&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;rendertype=abstract" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Syst. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011-03-19">2011. Accessed March 19. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>539 (Available at</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequencing three crocodilian genomes to illuminate the evolution of archosaurs and amniotes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>St John</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://genomebiology.com/2012/13/1/415" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">415</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012-03-23">2012. Accessed March 23. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Available at</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic validation of antibody binding and protein subcellular localization using siRNA and confocal microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Stadler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S187439191200070X" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Proteome</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2236" to="2251" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-03-23">2012. Accessed March 23. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequence of C. elegans lag-2 reveals a cell-signalling domain shared with Delta and Serrate of Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Tax</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Yeargers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/368150a0</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/368150a0" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">368</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6467</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="1994-10-02">1994. Accessed October 2. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The house mouse: atlas of embryonic development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Theiler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TEAD/TEF transcription factors utilize the activation domain of YAP65, a Src/Yes-associated protein localized in the cytoplasm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vassilev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://genesdev.cshlp.org/content/15/10/1229.full" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1229" to="1241" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-04-29">2001. Accessed April 29. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epigenome Variation in Severe Asthma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wysocki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Conley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wenzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://brn.sagepub.com/content/early/2014/10/03/1099800414553463.abstract" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Res. Nurs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109980041" to="104553463" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-10-31">2014. Accessed October 31. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
