<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Radiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Tyne and Wear</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">City Hospitals Sunderland NHS Foundation Trust AQ1</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kayll Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>SR4 7TP</postCode>
									<settlement>Sunderland</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Health Sciences and Wellbeing</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Sunderland, Sciences Complex</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Sunderland</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Tyne and Wear</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>SR1 3SD</postCode>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">857601A952785E0E0720370CB516DE9E</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 30 July 2018 / Accepted: 6 November 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Outsourcing Workload Clinical decision making</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Jon a t h a n , Si d dl e, Ka t h ry n a n d Cox, Julie (2 0 1 8) Cli nic a n s ' p e r c e p tio n s of t h e q u ality of o u t s o u r c e d r a diolo gy a n d a c tio n s t a k e n a r o u n d p e r c eiv e d i m a gi n g e r r o r s in p r a c tic e. E u r o p e a n R a diolo gy.</s><s>p p. 1-6.</s><s>IS S N 0 9 3 8-7 9 9 4 Do w nlo a d e d fro m: h t t</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>U s a g e g u i d e l i n e s</head><p><s>Pl e a s e r ef e r t o t h e u s a g e g ui d eli n e s a t h t t p://s u r e .</s><s>s u n d e rl a n d. a c. u k/ p olici e s. h t ml o r al t e r n a tiv ely c o n t a c t s u r e @ s u n d e rl a n d. a c. u k.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.</head><p><s>Please check if all the tables are presented correctly.</s><s>Also, the number of respondents and consultants in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref> totals to 51 and 46, respectively.</s><s>Please check.</s></p><p><s>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>: please amend as follows:</s></p><p><s>12.4 please amend from 'consultants' to '5 consultants' in Grade column 12.5 please amend from 'consultant' to '1 consultant' in Grade column 12.8 please amend from 'consultant' to '1 consultant' in Grade column 12.9 please amend from 'consultant' to ' 1 consultant' in grade column 12.11 please amend no of respondents to 7 from 8 and amend to '7 consultants' in grade column 12.12 please amend from 'consultants' to 3 consultants in grade column 12.13 please amend from 'consultants' to ' 2 consultants in grade column 12.14 please amend from 'consultants' to <ref type="bibr">'2</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>consultants' in grade column</head><p><s>The columns should add up to 50 now.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinicians' perceptions of the quality of outsourced radiology and actions taken around perceived imaging errors in practice</head><note type="other">Yitka</note></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>The increasing demand for radiological expertise in the UK has not been matched by workforce capacity.</s><s>This situation has led to chronic staff shortages, unfilled vacant consultant posts, often as a result of retirement, a need for longterm overtime and an increasing backlog of diagnostic imaging for interpretation.</s><s>Between 2010 and 2016, the radiology consultant workforce grew by an average of 3% per year; in England, from 2013 to 2016, the number of computerised tomography scans performed increased by 33% and the number of magnetic resonance imaging scans by 31% <ref type="bibr">[1]</ref>.</s><s>Within the practice of radiology, peer discussion and feedback are encouraged, with an established multidisciplinary team approach to review diagnostic imaging, auditing processes and discussion of issues of concern across clinical specialities.</s><s>This approach is commensurate with the UK published guidelines on standards of practice for radiologists <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s>It has been evidenced that a multi-disciplinary approach can lead to improved cancer outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, but despite the positive benefits of this approach, the additional time needed to participate in multi-disciplinary meetings places time and workload demands on radiologists <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>One approach to supporting the radiology workforce issues of workforce capacity and the unrelenting increase in the need for diagnostic imaging in the UK is to outsource radiology reporting to external providers, usually within the private sector <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s>This is becoming an increasingly common option.</s><s>In 2016, 78% of radiology departments in the UK reported outsourcing some reports to external providers compared to a rate of 33% in 2010 <ref type="bibr">[1]</ref>.</s><s>The interpretation of radiology reports is not an exact science as it is open to human interpretation; discrepancies between radiological interpretations are thought to occur at a rate of about 3-5% <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</s><s>There is no consensus on the definition of what constitutes a radiological error, and many discrepancies in error reporting may not overtly influence patient management.</s></p><p><s>Outsourcing of diagnostic imaging interpretations has altered the potential for effective communication between clinicians and reporting radiologists in clinical environments <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s><s>With in-house report authors, there are often encounters between radiology and other staff in informal settings outside multi-disciplinary meetings, e.g.</s><s>'corridor communications' which puts faces to names and builds rapport between radiologists and clinicans in other disciplines.</s><s>The practice of outsourcing has divided opinion within radiology, and other clinical specialities.</s><s>Currently, there is little published evidence about whether the author of radiology report, be it internal or outsourced, matters to the clinician.</s></p><p><s>The aim of this study was to understand clinicians' perspectives and experiences of outsourcing reports in clinical practice, if the author of imaging reports matters, and how clinicians handle what they perceive as errors in imaging reports.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials and methods</head><p><s>In order to capture a wide range of responses across the various clinical disciplines utilising the services of the Department of Radiology, surveys were chosen as the strategy for data collection.</s><s>A survey was a pragmatic approach to being able to access a relatively large sample of clinicians who depend and regularly use diagnostic radiology reporting services in their everyday practice.</s><s>The anonymous, ten-question written survey was then distributed to a purposive sample of 50 senior medical and surgical staff across a range of clinical specialties within a large NHS hospital, representing 20% of that workforce, in the North of England from May to October 2017.</s><s>These participants were identified as regularly engaging with the Department of Radiology, and would therefore be able to provide relevant information.</s><s>The survey questions included space for respondents to add additional comments to their responses which would give context to and allow a more comprehensive understanding of their perceptions to be gained.</s><s>To encourage open responses and maintain confidentiality, only basic demographic information was collected; therefore, it was not possible to send out a reminder to complete the survey.</s></p><p><s>The survey was designed to collect both quantitative and qualitative data, the latter owing to the subjective nature of the aim of the study.</s><s>Adopting a qualitative dimension allowed the investigators to explore and interpret the perspectives and experiences of the participants, extract meaning and gain knowledge of situation <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s><s>A constructivist approach was taken by the research team.</s><s>This is a philosophy which asserts there are multiple realities and interpretations of a situation, with meanings and actions constructed by the individual people experiencing or living with the phenomena <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, i.e. the management of errors in radiology reporting.</s><s>We applied this in order to gain a deep, rather a superficial insight by which to understand what the participants reported in the collected data <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and give context to the numerical data.</s></p><p><s>The questions were discussed and agreed with the research team and pilot tested with a representative sample to ensure that questions were understood and relevant to the aim of the study (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>).</s><s>The surveys were collated, and the research team analysed the initial responses.</s></p><p><s>Once basic descriptive statistics were collated, the participants' comments were further investigated using constant comparative analysis, which is a method of analysis which allows researchers to identify emergent concepts in the data <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, from which themes were constructed which provided context to the numerical data.</s><s>Each survey was read independently by the two qualitative researchers, who then compared and discussed and an initial set of concepts.</s><s>These concepts were then discussed with the rest of the research team, in order to reach consensus and agree on the final four themes generated from the analysis.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>A purposive sample of 50 senior clinicians across a broad range of clinical disciplines (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>) was obtained; this represents 20% of the 250 senior medical and surgical staff employed in our Trust.</s><s>All participants reported they looked at who had written the radiology report and that that the author was made a difference to them.</s><s>The actions taken when there is a perceived error on a report (internal or outsourced) varied, with all participants (n = 50) stating they would query the error.</s><s>However, action was taken depending on what the participant deemed to be important.</s><s>For participants who stated they would query a perceived error depending what the error was, 74% (n = 37) took action around a concern about the diagnosis, followed by a missed finding (72%, n = 36).</s><s>Queries around typographical errors were only reported by 18% (n = 9) of respondents (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">3</ref>).</s><s>There were noted differences in actions taken according to whether the report was done in-house or outsourced (see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">4</ref>).</s><s>When participants were asked how they felt about raising queries on reports, 52% (n = 26) were comfortable, 24% (n = 11) were very comfortable and 10% (n = 5) were slightly and well-received in nearly all cases.</s><s>The survey questions on feedback about report queries were positive, with 82% (n = 41) receiving feedback, 11% (n = 5) not receiving any and 7% (n = 3) sometimes.</s><s>Feedback was reported as helpful by 97% (n = 45), with 92% (n = 46) receiving this in a timely manner.</s><s>The perspectives of the participants are further explored through the four themes constructed from the data.</s><s>This was done to give context to the quantitative data and provide a greater understanding of the participants' experiences.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theme I having confidence in reporting process</head><p><s>Despite the acknowledged inevitable margin for error in interpretation, there was an overall feeling of confidence in communication with the in-house radiologists.</s><s>The processes for raising queries with both internal and external reports were largely the same, with varied methods of communication with the in-house radiologists preferred, such as email, telephone and face to face meetings, both in a multi-disciplinary team setting and individually.</s><s>With respect to clarification of findings on an outsourced report, only 4% (n = 2) stated they would contact the external provider in the event of a query; this was usually done with an in-house radiologist.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theme II trusting the in-house resources over external ones</head><p><s>There was an overarching theme of trust, both in the in-house staff and in-house reports, which was associated with a higher quality of provision.</s><s>The majority of participants who provided comments stated feelings of mistrust with outsourced reports, with clinicians feeling more confident in knowing that in-house clinical expertise is utilised for specific scans, e.g. head and neck, and that this an unknown entity with outsourced reports.</s><s>It was acknowledged that the quality of reports did vary whether internal or outsourced, but overall, the quality and confidence levels towards in-house reports were reported to be stronger.</s><s>The theme of trust was further articulated in the participant-reported value of the multi-disciplinary team, which facilitated communication, i.e. knowing who to contact in-house to discuss pathology and be supported by an in-house radiologist in planning an appropriate course of action to ensure optimum patient outcomes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theme III feeling comfortable raising queries</head><p><s>As patient safety is an overriding principle of good clinical governance, with accurate imaging reports crucial to appropriate pathways of care for patients, it is vital that clinicians feel comfortable in highlighting and querying discrepancy, potential error and lack of clarity in imaging reports.</s><s>The ability of clinicians to raise issues of concern regarding potential diagnostic error was important.</s><s>There were mixed levels of confidence in raising concerns, but overall, it was acknowledged that patient care should override feeling uncomfortable in seeking advice.</s><s>This appeared to be more challenging with outsourced reports, with participants stating the unknown author was the reason behind this.</s><s>The majority of participants who provided comments felt that the presence of a radiologist at multi-disciplinary team meetings assisted to reduce the discomfort and encouraged conversations.</s><s>The interrelationships between the radiologist and the clinician were fundamental to their perception of trust, knowing the person and the concept of 'challenging' alongside 'questioning' key diagnostic features.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theme IV negotiating ambiguous processes</head><p><s>The data showed that raising queries, reporting errors and receiving feedback, with internal and outsourced reports, were not a straightforward process, and there was a perceived element of ambiguity, despite regular multi-disciplinary meetings and reported pathways of communication:</s></p><p><s>Overall, these themes add a deeper insight into the findings.</s><s>These themes consolidate the evident ambiguity perceived by clinicians in relation to current radiological reporting processes.</s><s>This degree of ambiguity necessitates the use of greater skills of discernment, confidence and underpinning knowledge than a system without such degrees of ambiguity would warrant.</s><s>Communicative capacity between the clinicians and radiologists is perceived as imperative in this process, as seen here.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Overall, the findings show a high level of trust, interaction and communication between in-house radiologists and other clinicians.</s><s>The experiences and perspectives of the participants appeared to be consistent across the 13 clinical specialties.</s><s>Analysis of the comments showed that multi-disciplinary meetings provided a source of reassurance, debate and expertise, which was especially evident for queries on outsourced reports.</s><s>Generally, clinicians felt comfortable raising queries about report content and potential radiological error with an acknowledgement that patient safety was an overarching governance principle.</s><s>Direct contact with a radiologist in the context of a multi-disciplinary meeting helped many clinicians to deal with potentially difficult task of raising concerns about report accuracy and assisted clinical staff in negotiating ambiguous processes.</s></p><p><s>The addition of using multi-disciplinary meeting time to discuss queries with outsourced reports may add considerable burdens to an under-resourced workforce, making outsourcing a potentially less effective solution to this problem, with limited or no opportunity for effective communication between the clinician and the radiologist, leaving less time for other cases worthy of multi-disciplinary discussion.</s></p><p><s>There is an acknowledged margin for error within the interpretation of radiology reports, with many decisions made with a degree of uncertainty <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s><s>Regardless of clinical discipline or however advances in technology ensure efficiency in being able to obtain accurate diagnostic imaging, their radiology image interpretation and comparison with previous studies must still ensure professional accountability, clinical governance and effective inter-professional working and communication pathways.</s><s>The practice of outsourcing into the reporting system adds a layer of complexity to dealing with queries, which are often down to human factors, of which the primary source of the query is not always available for discussion.</s><s>Emphasis on the lack of available data on systems errors in radiology practice, despite much impetus being placed on the profession to create a culture of safety, was identified by Blumberg et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, and our findings show a lack of confidence by clinicians in the outsourced reports.</s><s>This has also been found in a previous census of clinical radiologists and oncologists, with 75% (n = 217) of the latter reporting that outsourced reports were of lesser quality than those produced in-house <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</s><s>The participantreported errors of diagnosis and missed findings with outsourced reports have been found in other literature and consistent with our findings, showing that this is an ambiguous process in need of further research <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The limitations of this study are acknowledged.</s><s>The findings are an interpretation of the perspectives and experiences of the participants working in a single hospital in a UK Trust, and policy and practice may differ elsewhere.</s></p><p><s>Although the survey was distributed to a wide range of clinical specialities within the hospital, the possibility of bias owing to more respondents in some clinical specialities than others cannot be excluded.</s><s>It is also acknowledged that the participants identified to take part in the survey were known to the study team, as they regularly engage with the radiology team, and this may have influenced the high response rate.</s><s>However, it was important to recruit participants who accessed radiology reporting in order to understand current practices.</s><s>The survey was limited to how queries were dealt with, and did not seek to find what actions were taken in the event of a query, i.e. repeated imaging, nor the impact of imaging queries on patients, which has been suggested to increase confidence in radiologists and services provided <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> which may have provided further insight.</s><s>It is acknowledged that the qualitative findings are the interpretation of the research team involved with the study and that not all participants chose to provide written comments.</s><s>Additionally, this study did not explore the common practice of performing scans in other centres, with findings reported by an external radiologist, as this is not generally performed in the hospital setting in which this study took place.</s></p><p><s>As reliance on outsourcing of imaging investigations looks set to further increase, hybrid solutions may become commonplace, with private sector radiologists who provide radiological reports for state hospitals remotely and/or physically participating in multi-disciplinary meetings and spending working time in those hospitals, particularly for error/governance meetings to enable the development of relationship building and communication with the referring clinicians.</s><s>This will further facilitate improvement in both the safety and efficacy of diagnostic imaging services.</s><s>Equally, the presence of radiologists at multi-disciplinary meetings by teleconferencing may be another method of establishing the inter-professional trust and relationships which are vital to excellent communication through the medium of radiology reports.</s><s>Finally, more reliance on regional specialist networks of local radiologists may supplement outsourcing in a regional 'chambers' model.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>There is a clear need to improve confidence in the accuracy of outsourced reports, as queries regarding these are taken up with core staff, adding to an existing overstretched workload.</s><s>Future research is recommended in the following areas.</s><s>Firstly, the implications for actions taken as a result of these queries on radiologist workloads in terms of measuring the financial and systems implications of outsourcing are a solution to an under-resourced workforce.</s></p><p><s>Secondly, to explore how to develop clear pathways for queries relating to outsourced reports to ensure timely responses, acknowledgement of the clinical expertise of the external reporting radiologist and a named contact provided in the event of a query.</s><s>Finally, the issues of trust and confidence amongst clinicians and with staff working within the outsourcing companies should be undertaken to improve communication, with potential solutions for communication identified by the workforce themselves.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p><s>The authors state that this work has not received any funding.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Compliance with ethical standards</head><p><s>Guarantor The scientific guarantor of this publication is Dr. Julie Cox.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p><s>The authors of this manuscript declare no relationships with any companies whose products or services may be related to the subject matter of the article.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Copy</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>a) Nothing____b) query</cell></row><row><cell>it____c) depends on the</cell></row><row><cell>error</cell></row><row><cell>If you answered c) would</cell></row><row><cell>you raise the query if it is:</cell></row><row><cell>Typographical error</cell></row><row><cell>Yes_____No____</cell></row><row><cell>Question regarding</cell></row><row><cell>diagnosis</cell></row><row><cell>Yes___No___</cell></row><row><cell>Question regarding a</cell></row><row><cell>missed finding</cell></row><row><cell>Yes___No____</cell></row></table><note><p><s>of survey Number Question Response 1 What job grade are you employed as? 2 Please state your clinical speciality 3 When reading a radiology report, do you look who has written it?(please</s><s>tick) Yes____ No_____ 4 Does the author of the report make a difference to you? Yes____ No If yes, why/how? 5 If you perceived there to be an error on the report, what do you do? 6For a scan that was reported within the hospital radiology department, how would you raise the query?</s><s>7 For a scan that was reported by an external company, how would you raise this?</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 Participant demographics Specialty AQ2 No. of respondents Grade Specialty AQ2 No. of respondents Grade</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>5 consultants</cell></row><row><cell>Rheumatology</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>1 specialty trainee level 3</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1 specialty trainee level 7</cell></row><row><cell>Haemotology</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>Consultants</cell></row><row><cell>Acute medicine</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>Consultant</cell></row><row><cell>Clinical oncology</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5 consultants 1 specialty trainee level 8</cell></row><row><cell>Gastroenterology</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4 consultants 1 specialty trainee level 5</cell></row><row><cell>Endocrinology</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>Consultant</cell></row><row><cell>Accident and emergency</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>Consultant</cell></row><row><cell>General surgery</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>10 consultants 1 specialty trainee level 8</cell></row><row><cell>Urology</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>Consultants</cell></row><row><cell>Ear, nose and throat</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>Consultants</cell></row><row><cell>Maxillo-facial</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>Consultants</cell></row><row><cell>Upper gastrointestinal surgery</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>Consultant</cell></row><row><cell>Total respondents</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>45 consultants 5 specialty trainees</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Reasons for raising queries on reports</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Reason</cell><cell>Raised</cell><cell>Not raised</cell><cell>Comments</cell></row><row><cell>Typographical error</cell><cell>18% (n = 9)</cell><cell>46% (n = 23)</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>10% (n = 5) would query if it was deemed to change the interpretation</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 4 Participant</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Discuss in radiology MDT</cell><cell cols="2">24% (n = 12) 24% (n = 12)</cell></row><row><cell>Response not clear</cell><cell>2% (n = 1)</cell><cell>2% (n = 1)</cell></row><row><cell>Contact external reporting company</cell><cell>n/a</cell><cell>4% (n = 2)</cell></row><row><cell>Contact radiology secretaries</cell><cell>4% (n = 2)</cell><cell>4% (n = 2)</cell></row><row><cell>Do not know</cell><cell>0% (n = 0)</cell><cell>4% (n = 2)</cell></row></table><note><p><s>-reported actions on raising queries with scans Action In-house scan Outsourced scan Email the specialist consultant 12% (n = 6) 8% (n = 4) Contact (email/telephone) radiologist linked to MDT 24% (n = 12) 32% (n = 8) Contact clinical director/lead radiologist 8% (n = 4) 14% (n = 7) Contact (email/telephone) with reporting radiologist 24% (n = 12) 12% (n = 6)</s></p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Statistics and biometry No complex statistical methods were necessary for this paper.</s></p><p><s>Informed consent Written informed consent was not required for this study because the participants were hospital staff, and written informed consent was waived by the Institutional Review Board.</s></p><p><s>Ethical approval Institutional Review Board approval was obtained.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methodology • retrospective</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Clinical radiology UK workforce census 2016 report</title>
				<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">References</forename><forename type="middle">1</forename><surname>Royal College Of Radiologists</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cancer multidisciplinary team meetings -standards for clinical radiologists</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Royal</forename><surname>College Of Radiologists</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Royal College of Radiolgists, London Contract No.: BFCR</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The proliferation of multidisciplinary team meetings (MDTMs): how can radiology departments continue to support them all</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Balasubramaniam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Subesinghe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Radiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3679" to="3684" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multidisciplinary team meetings and their impact on workflow in radiology and pathology departments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Luz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>O'briain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mcdermott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/1741-7015-5-15</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1186/1741-7015-5-15" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Outsourced radiology: will doctors be deskilled?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bmj.a785</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.a785" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">337</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008. 2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Error and discrepancy in radiology: inevitable or avoidable?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brady</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s13244-016-0534-1</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s13244-016-0534-1" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Insight Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="182" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Radiology demand and capacity: a stochastic analysis based on care pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sibanda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Engel-Hills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hering</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1080/23311975.2017.1334994</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1080/23311975.2017.1334994" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cog Bus Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1334994</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Basics of qualitative research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Corbin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Strauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<pubPlace>Sage, London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Social research methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bryman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Research design: qualitative, quantitative and mixedmethods approaches</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Creswell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<pubPlace>Sage, London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3rd edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Constructing grounded theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Charmaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<pubPlace>Sage, London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discrepancy and error in radiology: concepts, causes and consequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brady</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">Ó</forename><surname>Laoide</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mccarthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mcdermott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ulster Med J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Radiologic safety events within a pediatric emergency medicine network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Blumberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mahajan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Connell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatr Emerg Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="96" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Teleradiology and outsourcing census</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Royal College of Radiologists</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Royal College of Radiologists</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Medical errors arising from outsourcing laboratory and radiology services</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chasin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Elliott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Klotz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="819" to="e819" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direct communication between radiologists and patients following imaging examinations. Should radiologists rethink their patient care?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gutzeit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Heiland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sudarski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00330-018-5503-2</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00330-018-5503-2" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Radiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
