<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A new responder criterion (relative effect per patient (REPP) &gt; 0.2) externally validated in a large total hip replacement multicenter cohort (EUROHIP)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Orthopaedics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stadtspital Triemli</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Birmendsdorferstr. 497</addrLine>
									<postCode>CH-8063</postCode>
									<settlement>Zurich</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hüsler</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Mathematical Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bern</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Sidlerstr. 5</addrLine>
									<postCode>CH-3012</postCode>
									<settlement>Bern</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dieppe</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Peninsula College of Medicine and Dentistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Plymouth Campus</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>C420 Portland Square, Drake Circus</addrLine>
									<postCode>PL4 8 AA</postCode>
									<settlement>Plymouth</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Günther</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Orthopaedics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Gustav Carus University of Dresden</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Fetscherstr. 76</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-01307</postCode>
									<settlement>Dresden</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dreinh € Ofer ¶ #</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Judge</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Centre of Musculosceletal Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charit e, Charit eplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Orthopaedics, Traumatology and Sports Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>An der Mühle 2-9</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-13507</postCode>
									<settlement>Medical Park Berlin Humboldtmühle, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">yy Botnar Research Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Institute of Musculosceletal Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nuffield</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Orthopaedics, Rheumatology and Musculosceletal Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Windmill Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>OX3 7LD</postCode>
									<settlement>Headington</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Or-thopaedics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Birmensdorferstr. 497</addrLine>
									<postCode>8063</postCode>
									<settlement>Stadtspital Triemli, Postfach, Zurich</settlement>
									<region>CH</region>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A new responder criterion (relative effect per patient (REPP) &gt; 0.2) externally validated in a large total hip replacement multicenter cohort (EUROHIP)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">75D4158B4CD75C7167FA4364689AD3D7</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.joca.2015.10.012</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 15 April 2015 Accepted 21 October 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Responder OMERACT-OARSI REPP THR Outcome EUROHIP s u m m a r y</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Objective: To validate a new method to identify responders (relative effect per patient (REPP) &gt;0.2) using the OMERACT-OARSI criteria as gold standard in a large multicentre sample.</s><s>Method: The REPP ([score before e after treatment]/score before treatment) was calculated for 845 patients of a large multicenter European cohort study for THR.</s><s>The patients with a REPP &gt;0.2 were defined as responders.</s><s>The responder rate was compared to the gold standard (OMERACT-OARSI criteria) using receiver operator characteristic (ROC) curve analysis for sensitivity, specificity and percentage of appropriately classified patients.</s><s>Results: With the criterion REPP&gt;0.2</s><s>85.4% of the patients were classified as responders, applying the OARSI-OMERACT criteria 85.7%.</s><s>The new method had 98.8% sensitivity, 94.2% specificity and 98.1% of the patients were correctly classified compared to the gold standard.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion:</head><p><s>The external validation showed a high sensitivity and also specificity of a new criterion to identify a responder compared to the gold standard method.</s><s>It is simple and has no uncertainties due to a single classification criterion.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Total hip replacement (THR) is one of the most successful treatment procedures for patients with hip osteoarthritis; THR alleviates the symptoms (e.g., pain and stiffness) and degree of disability <ref type="bibr">1e4</ref> .</s><s>The success of THR can be measured as responder rate defined by Outcome Measures in Rheumatoid Arthritis Clinical Trials/Osteoarthritis Research Society International (OMERACT-OARSI) with patient reported outcome measurement tools (PROM's) 5e11 .</s><s>The responder rate for a surgical treatment (e.g., THR) contains valuable information and is easy to understand either for patients and general practitioners, surgeons and medical care providers 12e14 .</s><s>For example in the multicenter EUROHIP study the responder rate for THR was 85.4%, meaning that 6 out of 7 patients had a clinical improvement above the level of a minimally clinically important difference and one of 7 patients does not profit from THR (being a "non-responder") <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> .</s><s>This information may be helpful either for decision making for the patients and for process amelioration for surgeons analyzing possible factors to become a responder or possible factors to become a "non-responder".</s></p><p><s>But the method to calculate the responder rate is complex because one main criterion or two out of three subcriterias regarding pain or function needed to be fulfilled <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> .</s><s>An easier method simple to calculate would be helpful to overcome this limitation.</s><s>In the validation study of the relative effect per patient (REPP) [Fig.</s><s><ref type="figure">1</ref>] the threshold was defined with 0.2, representing a change equal or larger than the minimal clinically important difference (MCID) <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> .</s><s>Incidentally a high agreement was found between the patients with a REPP&gt;0.2</s><s>(91%) and the responder rate using the set of OMERACT-OARSI criteria (92%) <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> .</s></p><p><s>The aim of this study was to validate this finding externally in a highly generalizable sample of patients undergoing THR for primary OA in 12 European nations and to determine whether it identifies the same patients as responders using the OMERACT-OARSI method as the gold standard.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method</head><p><s>We included patients who were enrolled in the EUROHIP study and had complete PROMs from the Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC) follow-ups pre-THR and one year postoperatively for the patients with unilateral THR <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> .</s><s>The EUROHIP study included 1327 patients who underwent primary THR at 20 European orthopedic centers in 12 nations.</s><s>The study began by collecting data in January 2004 and concluded in December 2006.</s><s>The inclusion criteria were having a diagnosis of hip OA, undergoing primary THR, and providing signed informed consent.</s><s>The exclusion criteria were severe mental illness or dementia and patients who were unwilling/unable to participate.</s><s>Each center was responsible for obtaining local ethical approval.</s><s>The study protocol and data collection forms were designed in Bristol, UK and Ulm, Germany by the study principle investigators (Paul Dieppe, Klaus-Peter Günther and Karsten Dreinh€ ofer).</s><s>The patient questionnaire was reviewed for acceptability in Bristol and modified accordingly before it was sent to Ulm for translation and distribution.</s><s>Questionnaires were sent to each center for translation and were returned for editing before being printed and distributed with a set of instructions.</s></p><p><s>The WOMAC score was calculated including all 24 questions of three dimensions pain, stiffness and physical function on a scale 0 indicating no symptoms and 100 extreme symptoms.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outcome</head><p><s>We defined the patient outcome using the responder rate calculated with the REPP score (REPP&gt;0.2) as new criterion and compared it to the rate using the OMERACT-OARSI criteria as gold standard.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>REPP score and responder criterion</head><p><s>The REPP (pre treatment (tt) score e post tt score)/pre tt score) was calculated for each patient with the WOMAC score [Fig.</s><s><ref type="figure">1</ref>].</s><s>Every patient with a REPP &gt;0.2 was defined as responder <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>OMERACT-OARSI responder criteria</head><p><s>The OMERACT-OARSI responder criteria (Pham et al.) indicate a substantial improvement in pain or function of !50% and an absolute change of !20.</s><s>If the patient does not fulfill these criteria, improvement in !2 of the three following criteria is necessary: !20% improvement in pain and an absolute change of !10, !20% improvement in function and an absolute change of !10, !20% improvement in the patient's global assessment, and an absolute change of !10 5 .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical analysis</head><p><s>Descriptive statistics were used to determine the score variability before and after THR, as well as the number of responders.</s><s>Cross tabulation of both methods was conducted to assess the percentage of patients who were appropriately classified.</s><s>Receiver operator characteristic (ROC) curve analysis was used to assess the sensitivity, specificity, and percentage of patients who were appropriately classified compared to the newly proposed method, using the OARSI as the gold standard.</s><s>Stata 13.1 software (Stata Corp., College Station, TX, USA) was used for all statistical analyses.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>All patients with complete outcome data from the preoperative and 12-month postoperative assessments (n ¼ 845, comprising 63.7% of all included patients) were included.</s><s>The average patient age was 65.7 years (range, 26e92 years).</s></p><p><s>The median WOMAC score of the patients before and after THR decreased from 58.3 to 15.6 (P &lt; 0.001).</s><s>The REPP-scores ranged from 1 to À1.5, peaking at approximately 1 and slowly decreasing to zero; there were few results near or below zero, as well as an outlier.</s><s>For the EUROHIP cohort, the relative proportions of responders were 85.4% and 14.6% non-responders (12.7% unchanged, and 1.9% worse).</s><s>Using the OARSI-OMERACT criteria, we identified 85.7% of the patients as responders.</s></p><p><s>Both methods classified nearly the same patients as responders with 98.8% sensitivity, 94.2% specificity and 98.1% correctly classified, demonstrating good validation of the new REPP method to calculate the responders [Fig.</s><s><ref type="figure">2</ref>].</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Main findings</head><p><s>The criterion REPP&gt;0.2 to define a responder correlates with high sensitivity and also high specifity with the existing set of OARSI-OMERACT criteria.</s><s>The responder rate can be calculated simple and easier with REPP method.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Strengths/limitations</head><p><s>The strength of this study is the large number of participating patients in 12 nations with PROM's in 10 different languages at 20 centers allowing a reliable external validation of this new method.</s></p><p><s>Study limitations were the selection bias of patients and treatment.</s></p><p><s>The included patients (unilateral osteoarthritis of the hip, undergoing THR) were similar to those in the validation study.</s></p><p><s>A basic bias of the EUROHIP study group was that all participating surgeons and centers had a special interest in THR and in clinical science; therefore, the analyzed cohort may represent a positive patient selection and the responder rate may be higher than in general practice.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .Fig. 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1.</s><s>REPP formula and calculating REPP scores: three examples.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">J. Huber et al. / Osteoarthritis and Cartilage 24 (2016) 480e483</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>We wanted to thank all participants and all participating clinics of the EUROHIP study group: M. Krismer, B. Stoeckl, University Clinic Orthopaedic Surgery, Innsbruck, Austria; K. Knahr, O. Pinggera, Orthopedic Hospital Wien-Speising, Austria; P. Ylinen, Orton Orthopaedic Hospitala, Helsiniki, Finland; M. Hamadouche, Groupe Hospitalier Cochin, Paris, France; Ch.</s><s>Delaunay, Clinique De L'yette, Longjumeau, France; Ph.</s><s>Chiron, Centre Hospitalier Ranguell, Toulouse, France; W. Puhl, K. Dreinh€ ofer, M. Floeren, S. Baumann and D. Groeber-Graetz University of Ulm (RKU), Ulm, Germany; KP Günther, St. Fickert, Carl Gustav Carus University, Dresden, Germany; J. L€ ohr, A. Katzer and D.Klüber ENDO Clinic, Hamburg, Germany; V.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author contributions</head><p><s>All authors have contributed to each of the three activities:</s></p><p><s>1) The concept of the REPP and the application of the new responder criterion the EUROHIP study cohort and the data acquisition of the cohort especially for the clinical part measuring the outcome 2) Drafting the article or revising it critically for important intellectual content 3) Approval of the final version, and will take public responsibility for the content of the paper.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Role of the funding source</head><p><s>None.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Competing interests</head><p><s>None.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The operation of the century: total hip replacement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Learmonth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rorabeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">370</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1508" to="e1519" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Total hip replacement: a systematic review and meta-analysis on midterm quality of life</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Shan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Saxena</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Osteoarthritis Cartilage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="e406" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The association of patient characteristics and surgical variables on symptoms of pain and function over 5 years following primary hip-replacement surgery: a prospective cohort study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Judge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Arden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Batra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Beard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Javaid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patient-reported outcomes one year after primary hip replacement in a European collaborative cohort</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Judge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dreinhoefer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dieppe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Care Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="480" to="e488" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OMERACT-OARSI initiative: Osteoarthritis Research Society International set of responder criteria for oateoarthritis clinical trials revisited</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Pham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Van Der Heijde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Altman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bellamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hochberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Osteoarthritis Cartilage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="e99" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Validation study of WOMAC: a health status instrument for measuring clinically important patient relevant outcomes to antirheumatic drug therapy in patients with osteoarthritis of the hip or knee</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bellamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Buchanan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Goldsmith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Stitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1833" to="e1840" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hip disability and osteoarthritis outcome score (HOOS) e validity and responsiveness in total hip replacement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Nilsdotter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lohmander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kl€ Assbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Roos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Musculosceletal Disord</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simple orthopaedic patient questionnaire to measure symptoms and disabilities e validation experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Zuberbühler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Dabis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zumstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ruflin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Z Orthop Unf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">146</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="793" to="e798" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measurement of health status. Ascertaining the minimal clinically important difference (MCID)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jaeschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Singer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Guyatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Control Clin Trials</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="e415" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Smallest detectable and minimal clinically important differences of rehabilitation intervention with their implications for required sample sizes using WOMAC and SF.36 quality of life measurement instruments in patients with osteoarthritis of the lower extremities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Angst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aeschlimann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Stucki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Care Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="384" to="e91" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Responsiveness and clinically important differences for the WOMAC and SF-36 after hip joint replacement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Quintana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Escobar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bilbao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Arostegui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Lafuente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Vidaurreta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Osteoarthritis Cartilage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1076" to="1e83" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pre-operative expectation predicts 12-month postoperative outcome among patients undergoing primary total hip replacement in European orthopaedic centres</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Judge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Arden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hobbs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dixon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Osteoarthritis Cartilage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="659" to="e67" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patient acceptable symptom state and OMERACT-OARSI set of responder criteria in joint replacement. Identification of cut-off values</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Escobar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gonzalez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Quintana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Vrotsou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bilbao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Herrera-Espineira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Osteoarthritis Cartilage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="e92" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Social, educational, and occupational predictors of total hip replacement outcome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sch€ Afer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Krummenauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mettelsiefen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kirschner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Günther</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Osteoarthritis Cartilage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1036" to="e1042" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relative effect per patient (REPP) e outcome groups for total hip replacement and total knee replacement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Dabis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Zumstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huesler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Z Orthop Unf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">151</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="239" to="e243" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
