<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Piperacillin-induced mild haemolytic anaemia in a 44-year-old patient with cystic fibrosis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Carolin</forename><surname>Meinus</surname></persName>
							<email>carolin.meinus@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Cystic Fibrosis</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatric Pneumology and Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Carsten</forename><surname>Schwarz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Cystic Fibrosis</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatric Pneumology and Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Beate</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Transfusion Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Roehmel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Cystic Fibrosis</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatric Pneumology and Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Piperacillin-induced mild haemolytic anaemia in a 44-year-old patient with cystic fibrosis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">6706C4B7977C7ED9663962AFAE4EA7D4</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bcr-2016-216937</idno>
					<note type="submission">Accepted 7 October 2016 To cite: Meinus C, Schwarz C, Mayer B, et al. BMJ Case Rep</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:49+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Piperacillin-tazobactam is an antipseudomonal antibiotic frequently used in patients with cystic fibrosis (CF) to treat pulmonary exacerbations.</s><s>Drug-induced immune haemolytic anaemia is a rare complication during treatment with piperacillin.</s><s>So far, piperacillin-induced immune haemolytic anaemia (PIHA) is regarded as an acute and severe haemolytic anaemia resulting into lifethreatening events.</s><s>Here we report on a patient with mild PIHA, which did not result in any clinical symptoms or necessity for treatment.</s><s>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first case report of PIHA without an acute severe haemolytic anaemia.</s><s>Further research is needed to clarify if this case is a solitary clinical manifestation of PIHA or if mild clinical courses of PIHA might be underreported.</s><s>Cases of PIHA have been largely reported in patients with CF.</s><s>This unequal distribution maybe due to the frequent administration of piperacillin for pulmonary exacerbation in patients with CF or due to CF-related cofactors of yet unknown aetiology.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BACKGROUND</head><p><s>Piperacillin-tazobactam is an antipseudomonal antibiotic, frequently used in patients with cystic fibrosis (CF) to treat pulmonary exacerbations.</s><s>Drug-induced immune haemolytic anaemia (DIHA) is a complication during treatment with piperacillin.</s><s>In general, drug-induced haemolytic anaemia is a rare cause for anaemia. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> About 130 drugs have been identified until now, the most common being piperacillin, cefotetan and ceftriaxone. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref></s><s>iperacillin was first reported to cause drug-induced haemolytic anaemia in 1986. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> So far, piperacillin-induced immune haemolytic anaemia (PIHA) has been described as an acute and severe haemolytic anaemia resulting into lifethreatening events. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>Interestingly, the majority of the patients reported with PIHA in previous studies suffered from CF. <ref type="bibr">7 9</ref> This unequal distribution could be because patients with CF are recurrently exposed to piperacillin.</s><s>However, piperacillin also is a commonly used drug for the treatment of pulmonary and urinary tract infections in different patient groups where immune haemolytic anaemia has not been reported as frequently. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>In general, in patients with CF the prevalence of adverse reactions to antibiotics is high. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref></s><s>This hypersensitivity is of yet unclear aetiology and of variably reported prevalence, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> possibly due to unequal study cohorts.</s><s>Whether patients with CF have a specific vulnerability for PIHA remains unclear.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CASE PRESENTATION</head><p><s>A 44-year-old female patient with CF was hospitalised with increased sputum production, fatigue, fever and loss of body weight; symptoms characteristic of pulmonary exacerbation.</s><s>The physical examination revealed crepitation on the right lung with mild rhonchus.</s><s>Blood analysis showed increased inflammatory markers (C reactive protein (CrP) of 147.5 mg/L and leucocytes of 13.79/nL with neutrophils of 68.5%).</s><s>Haemoglobin (12.3 mg/dL), serum electrolytes and renal parameters were normal.</s></p><p><s>The patient had no immunohaematological diagnosis and no history of red blood cell, platelet or plasma transfusion.</s></p><p><s>Owing to chronic colonisation with Stenotrophomonas maltophilia, she was treated intravenously with piperacillin and tazobactam and tobramycin for this pulmonary exacerbation.</s></p><p><s>Owing to recurrent pulmonary exacerbation, the patient had previously received multiple courses of intravenous antibiotic treatment, including at least 15-20 courses of treatment with piperacillin and tazobactam, without documentation of any adverse effects.</s></p><p><s>During this clinical course, the patient received piperacillin 4 g+tazobactam 0.5 g thrice and tobramycin 340 mg once per day for 14 days intravenously.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INVESTIGATIONS</head><p><s>During the whole period of the treatment, the patient presented with stable cardiovascular signs.</s><s>Before discharge, a routine laboratory test was performed which revealed a significant decrease in the haemoglobin concentration from 12.3 mg/dL at admission to 8.6 mg/dL on day 14 of admission.</s><s>Further laboratory tests indicated a haemolytic process.</s><s>The reticulocyte count was 13.6%, serum lactate dehydrogenase was 276 U/L and haptoglobin was 0.18 g/L.</s><s>Urine examination was normal.</s></p><p><s>The direct antiglobulin test (DAT) was found to be strongly positive for IgG (4+) and for C3d (3+) and weakly positive for IgA (2+).</s><s>An eluate prepared from the patient's red blood cells failed to react in the absence of the drug but showed weakly positive reactions in the presence of piperacillin.</s><s>The antibody-screening test was negative with an initial sample in the absence of the drug but was positive with a second sample collected shortly after the administration of piperacillin.</s><s>Drug-dependent antibodies to piperacillin were detected in both samples, but not to tazobactam or tobramycin.</s></p><p><s>After the discontinuation of medication, the haemoglobin levels recovered spontaneously to 10.4 mg/dL with a reticulocyte count of 10.2% on the third day after discontinuing piperacillin.</s><s>The serum lactate dehydrogenase and haptoglobin returned to normal levels.</s><s>At this point, the DAT was still positive with a serological profile that showed anti-IgG (4+), anti-C3d (2+) and anti-IgA (2+), a negative eluate and a negative antibody-screening test in the absence of piperacillin, but with positive reactions after adding the drug.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>OUTCOME AND FOLLOW-UP</head><p><s>Three weeks after the discontinuation of piperacillin haemoglobin (11.3 mg/dL) had almost returned to normal with normal reticulocyte count (1.8%).</s></p><p><s>After this initial event, treatment with piperacillin was strictly avoided.</s><s>In the follow-up after 12 months, there was no evidence for anaemia or haemolysis in the monitored blood count.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>DIHA is a rare complication with an estimated incidence of about one to four cases per million individuals per year. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref></s><s>Cephalosporins and penicillins are the antibiotics most frequently associated with DIHA. <ref type="bibr">9 15</ref> Reports of DIHA attributed to piperacillin are increasing, especially in patients with CF. <ref type="bibr">4-12 16</ref> Whether this unequal distribution is due to the frequent usage of piperacillin for pulmonary exacerbation in patients with CF or due to CF-related promoting cofactors, such as hyperinflammation, still need to be clarified. <ref type="bibr">7 13 14 16</ref></s><s>iperacillin is assumed to cause hapten-induced intravascular haemolysis via complement activation, leading to potentially lifethreatening events.</s><s>To the best of our knowledge, 38 cases of piperacillin-induced anaemia have been published so far. <ref type="bibr">4-12 16</ref></s><s>iperacillin-induced haemolysis has been reported to result in acute profound anaemia with haemoglobin levels as low as 1.6 g/ dL, hypovolemic shock, renal failure and fatal outcome. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>n contrast to these cases, we report on a patient with a mild decrease in the haemoglobin level that did not result in any clinical symptoms or require any medical treatment.</s><s>After the discontinuation of the treatment with piperacillin, the haemoglobin concentration spontaneously returned to normal level.</s><s>To the best of our knowledge, this is the only reported case of PIHA without any acute severe clinical course.</s><s>Further investigation is needed to clarify if this case is a solitary clinical manifestation of PIHA or if mild courses of PIHA might be under-reported, especially in patients with CF.</s></p><p><s>Generally, due to the low incidence, clinical and serological data on PIHA are still scarce.</s><s>In addition, the clinical presentation and serological findings in PIHA are variable, which may lead to difficulties in diagnosis and possible misdiagnosis of for example, autoimmune haemolytic anaemia. <ref type="bibr">9 15</ref></s><s>n conclusion, awareness of this rare but severe adverse drug reaction is essential for prompt and adequate management.</s><s>Monitoring of the blood count should be conducted whenever piperacillin is administered.</s><s>Special consideration has to be given to patients with CF, since they seem to be at a higher risk for PIHA due to frequent and prolonged treatment with piperacillin and/or other still unknown factors.</s></p><p><s>Currently, the treatment options of patients with mild PIHA remain unclear.</s><s>Further research is needed to clarify if mild PIHA should result into a lifelong abstinence from piperacillin.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Learning points</head><p><s>▸ Drug-induced immune haemolytic anaemia is considered a rare and generally severe complication during treatment with piperacillin.</s><s>▸ To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report on a patient with mild piperacillin-induced immune haemolytic anaemia (PIHA), which did not result in any clinical symptoms or require any medical treatment.</s><s>▸ Further investigation is needed to clarify if this case report is a unique clinical manifestation of PIHA or if mild clinical courses of PIHA might be under-reported.</s><s>▸ Special consideration has to be given to patients with CF, since they seem to be at higher risk for PIHA due to frequent and prolonged treatment with piperacillin and/or other still unknown factors.</s></p><p><s>Contributors CM, CS and JR involved in the management of the patient.</s><s>BM performed and interpreted the immune-hematologic laboratory tests.</s><s>All authors contributed to drafting and revision of the manuscript.</s><s>All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</s></p><p><s>Competing interests None declared.</s></p><p><s>Patient consent Obtained.</s></p><p><s>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</s></p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Copyright 2016 BMJ Publishing Group.</s><s>All rights reserved.</s><s>For permission to reuse any of this content visit http://group.bmj.com/group/rights-licensing/permissions.</s><s>BMJ Case Report Fellows may re-use this article for personal use and teaching without any further permission.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drugs that have been shown to cause drug-induced immune hemolytic anemia or positive direct antiglobulin tests: some interesting findings since</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Garratty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Arndt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunohematology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="66" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drug-induced immune hemolytic anemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Garratty</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Adv Hematol Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="98" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Piperacillin-induced anemia and leukopenia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bressler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Huston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1097/00007611-198602000-00031</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">South Med J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">79</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="256" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transfusion medicine illustrated. Profound piperacillin-mediated drug-induced immune hemolysis in a patient with cystic fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gehrie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Neff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ciombor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1537-2995.2011.03407.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transfusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="5" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Piperacillin-induced immune hemolysis presenting with tachycardia and cardiac arrest</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lohiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tan-Figueroa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Krishna</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1155/2011/816497</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Case Rep Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">816497</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Life-threatening piperacillin-induced immune haemolysis in a patient with cystic fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Marik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Parekh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bcr-2012-007801</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ Case Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Piperacillin-induced immune hemolysis: new cases and a concise review of the literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yürek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Salama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1537-2995.2009.02544.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transfusion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1135" to="1138" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hemolytic anemia as a result of piperacillin/tazobactam administration: a case report and discussion of pathophysiology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Zanetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Biswas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7205/MILMED-D-12-00512</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mil Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">178</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="e1045" to="1047" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Variability of findings in drug-induced immune haemolytic anaemia: experience over 20 years in a single centre</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bartolmäs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yürek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1159/000440673</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transfus Med Hemother</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="339" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Piperacillin-induced immune hemolytic anemia in an adult with cystic fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bandara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Seder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Garratty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1155/2010/161454</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Case Rep Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">161454</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immune-mediated severe hemolytic crisis with a hemoglobin level of 1.6 g/dl caused by anti-piperacillin antibodies in a patient with cystic fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kunzmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s15010-009-9227-8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Infection</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Haemolytic anaemia following treatment with piperacillin in a patient with cystic fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Thickett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wildman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Fegan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/jac/43.3.435</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Antimicrob Chemother</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="435" to="436" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hypersensitivity to antibiotics in patients with cystic fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Roehmel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Schwarz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mehl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcf.2013.10.002</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cyst Fibros</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="211" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antibiotic hypersensitivity in patients with CF</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ramesh</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1385/CRIAI:23:1:123</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Rev Allergy Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="141" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immune hemolytic anemia caused by drugs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Garratty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1517/14740338.2012.678832</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Expert Opin Drug Saf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="635" to="642" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antibiotic hypersensitivity in CF: drug-induced life-threatening hemolytic anemia in a pediatric patient</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chavez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Scurlock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcf.2010.08.010</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cyst Fibros</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="433" to="438" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
