<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Salzburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Salzburg</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">the Red Cross Blood Transfusion Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Linz</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Research and Develop-ment</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Applied Sciences Upper Austria</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hagenberg</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">06AEB8961C13F2BA4A8B2594A194E1FE</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:36+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>produced increased levels of T H 2 cytokines, we found the pattern of proinflammatory or regulatory cytokines to be highly diverse, ranging from almost exclusive use of IFN-g and GM-CSF as compensatory cytokines to mixed responses comprised of up to 8 different cytokines (of 9 measured).</s><s>A dominant T R 1 response was rarely observed (3/19 donors) and always accompanied by proinflammatory cytokines (see Figs E4 and E5 in this article's Online Repository at www.jacionline.org).</s><s>As shown in Fig <ref type="figure">E6</ref> in this article's Online Repository at www.jacionline.org,</s><s>the compensatory secretion of proinflammatory and regulatory cytokines was reflected by a statistically significant correlation with T H 2 cytokines in both farmers and townspeople.</s><s>No such correlation was observed in allergic donors.</s><s>4]<ref type="bibr">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr">[6]</ref> Nevertheless, together with our data, it can be clearly ruled out that IL-10-secreting Treg cells represent the only players defining the non-allergic status.</s></p><p><s>Notably, we identified a small percentage of nonallergic subjects who mount allergen-specific T H 17/T H 22 responses against Phl p 5 (Fig 2 <ref type="figure">, F</ref>), which putatively contribute to regulation of immune responses.</s><s>Although T H 17 responses have been described mainly for their potential to exacerbate lung inflammation in allergic patients, recently, a high degree of instability and plasticity of T H 17 cells toward regulatory functions has been described. <ref type="bibr">9</ref></s><s>In summary, a picture emerges indicating that induction and maintenance of the nonallergic state is a dynamic and active immunologic process using multiple mechanisms in addition to Treg cell-based tolerance or T H 1-based immune deviation.</s></p><p><s>For the first time, the present study unequivocally demonstrates in a large cohort of healthy subjects that protection from type I allergic diseases is not exclusively mediated by IL-10-producing T R 1 cells.</s><s>Instead, a strikingly broad spectrum of T H response types counteracts allergic reactions.</s><s>As discussed in more detail in the Methods and Discussion sections in this article's Online Repository at www.jacionline.org,</s><s>our data are in principle agreement with the hygiene hypothesis <ref type="bibr">10</ref> and point to a variable and complex immune deviation (predominantly of the proinflammatory phenotype) as a natural protective response against allergens.</s><s>Moreover, in light of our results, it seems reasonable to rethink the numerous concepts that have been demonstrated to trigger antiallergic immune responses.</s><s>Some of them might carry a potential to develop protective and therapeutic antiallergic immunity similar to that evolved in nature.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Increased IgE levels are linked to faster relapse in patients with omalizumab-discontinued chronic spontaneous urticaria</head><p><s>To the Editor:</s></p><p><s>Omalizumab is effective in patients with chronic spontaneous urticaria (CSU), but little is known about what predicts the response. <ref type="bibr">1</ref></s><s>Recently, Palacios et al 2 and Gericke et al <ref type="bibr">3</ref> reported that patients with CSU with basophil-activating serum activity are less likely to have a complete and fast response to omalizumab, respectively.</s><s>Clinically, most patients with CSU who stop omalizumab treatment relapse within a few months after the last application, and retreatment with omalizumab generally results in rapid remission.</s><s>It is currently unclear which patient features, if any, are linked to relapse or the time to relapse after stopping omalizumab.</s></p><p><s>This prospective observational study assessed 93 patients with CSU during 2014-2016 for relapse and time to relapse after stopping omalizumab (300 mg/4 weeks).</s><s>Patients had an average disease duration of 48 months (range, 2-330 months) and a total serum IgE level of 81 IU/mL (range, 7-1540 IU/mL), and clinical findings were independent of the patient's atopic status.</s><s>Patients and physicians independently used a visual analog scale (VAS) to rate the overall severity of urticarial signs and symptoms during the previous month.</s><s>The VAS is a 10-cm scale, in which 0 and 10 correspond to no urticaria signs and symptoms of maximum severity, respectively.</s><s>At baseline, CSU activity was high, as assessed by using the Urticaria Activity Score (UAS) (median: 6, range: 3-6), physician VAS (median: 9, range: 4-10), and patient VAS (median: 9, range: 5-10).</s><s>Complete responders (CRs) showed complete remission (UAS score, 0; VAS score, 0) after 12 weeks of omalizumab treatment, and antihistamines and omalizumab were discontinued, as called for by Turkish reimbursement rules.</s><s>Most patients with CSU benefited from omalizumab treatment: 12 weeks after the start of treatment, 44 (47%) patients had a complete response, and 36 (39%) patients had a partial response.</s><s>Thirteen (14%) patients were nonresponders.</s><s>The female/male ratio was highest in nonresponders, lower in partial responders, and lowest in CRs (x 2 5 6.86, P 5 .032;</s><s>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">I</ref>).</s></p><p><s>After completion of the 12-week treatment phase, we discontinued omalizumab in the 44 CRs and monitored them for relapse for at least 52 weeks.</s><s>Relapse was defined as the reappearance of both hives and pruritus.</s><s>Only 15 patients showed sustained remission, whereas 29 showed relapse.</s><s>Total IgE serum levels before omalizumab treatment correlated negatively with the time to relapse after discontinuation of omalizumab in CRs (R s 5 20.456, P 5.019, n 5 26).</s><s>Kaplan-Meier estimates revealed that CRs with increased baseline total IgE levels showed shorter time to relapse after discontinuation of omalizumab than patients with normal IgE levels (log-rank test: x 2 5 5.78, P 5 .016;</s><s>Fig  1).</s><s>Total IgE levels of 100 IU/mL or greater were defined as increased levels based on the reference range of our laboratory.</s></p><p><s>In contrast, there was no correlation of pretreatment total IgE levels with time to response to omalizumab (R s 5 20.084, P 5 .612,</s><s>n 5 39) and no difference in time to response to omalizumab treatment between patients with increased and normal IgE levels.</s><s>Time to response and time to relapse after discontinuation of omalizumab therapy did not correlate with each other (r 5 20.239, P 5 .232).</s></p><p><s>In the current study most CRs show relapse after discontinuation of omalizumab within several weeks.</s><s>For the first time, we demonstrate that increased serum levels of total IgE are linked to faster relapse of CSU after discontinuation of omalizumab.</s></p><p><s>In this study nonresponders were more frequently female (18%) than male (7%).</s><s>The reasons for this difference are currently unknown.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Asero 4</ref> previously proposed that most female but not male patients have autoimmune CSU, as assessed by using autologous serum skin testing.</s><s>Serum levels of total IgE are held not to be relevant for the probability of patients with CSU to respond to omalizumab or the time it takes for them to do so. <ref type="bibr">3</ref></s><s>The present study confirms this.</s><s>Importantly, our study shows that serum levels of total IgE correlate with time to relapse of CSU after stopping omalizumab treatment.</s><s>The higher the IgE levels, the less time it takes for CSU symptoms to return after omalizumab is discontinued.</s><s>Specifically, the time to relapse was significantly shorter in patients with CSU with high IgE levels (&gt;100 IU/mL) compared with those with normal IgE levels.</s><s>Therefore measuring IgE levels before omalizumab therapy might help to predict and avoid quick relapse in patients who have to or want to check the need to continue their omalizumab treatment by stopping it.</s></p><p><s>Why are high IgE levels linked to faster CSU relapse after discontinuation of omalizumab?</s><s>The underlying mechanisms are currently unclear but probably involve factors that modulate the speed by which IgE levels recover and return to relevant levels, such as the production of IgE and the half-life of omalizumab. <ref type="bibr">5</ref></s><s>erum IgE levels are critically determined by the rate of IgE production and its clearance, <ref type="bibr">6</ref> and they have a greater dependence on the former than the latter. <ref type="bibr">7</ref></s><s>IgE clearance from the blood is short (up to a few days) and of low variability. <ref type="bibr">8</ref></s><s>Patients with high IgE levels and high rates of IgE production can be expected to reach relevant IgE levels more quickly after omalizumab discontinuation than those with normal IgE levels. <ref type="bibr">9</ref></s><s>ur study has several strengths and limitations.</s><s>With our recent observation that patients with CSU with basophil-activating serum activity respond slower to omalizumab, it would have been interesting to perform the autologous serum skin test and a basophil activation assay in all patients before, during, and after omalizumab treatment. <ref type="bibr">3</ref></s><s>ur study confirms that patients with CSU have different patterns of response to omalizumab: quick versus slow remission and complete versus partial versus no remission.</s><s>It also provides novel insights into what might be responsible for these different response patterns (patient sex) and what is probably not responsible (eg, duration of disease and age of patient).</s><s>Most importantly, our findings demonstrate that patients with CSU also show different patterns of response to stopping their omalizumab treatment (ie, fast relapse, slow relapse, or no relapse).</s><s>The fact that high IgE levels are linked to fast CSU relapse after cessation of omalizumab treatment supports the notion that the signs and symptoms, at least in patients with increased IgE levels, are driven by the activation of mast cells by IgE rather than by other mechanisms.</s><s>Further large-scale studies are needed to elucidate the role of IgE in patients with CSU. <ref type="bibr">10</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Food diversity during the first year of life and allergic diseases until 15 years</head><p><s>To the Editor:</s></p><p><s>Contrary to current recommendations, several clinical trials in high-risk children reported that early introduction of highly allergenic foods, especially peanut and egg, prevents food allergy later in life. <ref type="bibr">1,</ref><ref type="bibr">2</ref></s><s>This opened the debate about changing the recommendations about the timing of solid food introduction and the length of exclusive breast-feeding to prevent allergic diseases. <ref type="bibr">1,</ref><ref type="bibr">3</ref></s><s>xposure to food antigens and bacteria has been suggested to modulate immune tolerance, crucial for the later development of allergic diseases. <ref type="bibr">4</ref></s><s>Therefore, not only timing of solid food introduction but also solid food diversity has become of research interest.</s><s>6]<ref type="bibr">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr">[8]</ref> Two studies have concluded that higher food diversity during the first year of life might be protective against later development of allergic diseases in children. <ref type="bibr">5,</ref><ref type="bibr">6</ref></s><s>However, in the first study, <ref type="bibr">5</ref> stratified analyses indicated that associations with atopic asthma, allergic rhinitis, and wheeze were mainly present in a subgroup of children with atopic eczema.</s><s>In the second study, <ref type="bibr">6</ref> an association with asthma was no longer observed after the exclusion of children with extremely low food diversity.</s><s>Both studies are based on selected populations and were not able to sufficiently control for reverse causality.</s></p><p><s>In previous analyses of our own data from the population-based German birth cohort LISAplus (recruited from 1997 to 1999) we looked at food diversity within the first 6 months of life in</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIG 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIG 1. Relapse time in patients with normal (&lt;100 IU/mL) and increased (&gt;100 IU/mL) IgE levels (Kaplan-Meier plot).</s><s>Time to relapse after discontinuation of omalizumab was shorter in CRs with increased baseline total IgE levels compared with patients with normal IgE levels (log-rank test: x 2 5 5.78, P 5 .016,</s><s>n 5 26).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,47.00,313.63,227.25,193.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE I .</head><label>I</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Characteristics of study patients according to IgE levels of less than 100 IU/mL and greater than 100 IU/mL and baseline characteristics of patients according to treatment response</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>IgE &lt;100 IU/mL</cell><cell>IgE &gt;100 IU/mL</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(n 5 48)</cell><cell>(n 5 35)</cell><cell>P value</cell><cell>CR (n 5 44)</cell><cell>PR (n 5 36)</cell><cell>NR (n 5 13)</cell><cell>P value</cell></row><row><cell>Age (y), mean 6 SD</cell><cell>37.71 6 13.66</cell><cell>33.44 6 9.85</cell><cell>.198</cell><cell cols="3">35.20 6 11.76 40.94 6 11.60 37.31 6 8.98</cell><cell>.085à</cell></row><row><cell>Female sex, no. (%)</cell><cell>34 (70.8)</cell><cell>20 (57)</cell><cell>.196 §</cell><cell>24 (54.5)</cell><cell>28 (77.8)</cell><cell>11 (84.6)</cell><cell>.032 §</cell></row><row><cell>Male sex, no. (%)</cell><cell>14 (29.2)</cell><cell>15 (42.9)</cell><cell></cell><cell>20 (45.5)</cell><cell>8 (22.2)</cell><cell>2 (15.4)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Duration of disease (mo), median (IQR) 57.5 (13.5-120.0)</cell><cell>48.0 (18-96)</cell><cell>.545*</cell><cell>36 (12-72)</cell><cell cols="3">90 (15-132) 72.0 (30.5-180.0) .043k</cell></row><row><cell>Baseline UAS score, median (IQR)</cell><cell>6 (4.25-6)</cell><cell>5 (5-6)</cell><cell>.840*</cell><cell>5 (4.25-6)</cell><cell>5.5 (5.0-6.0)</cell><cell>6.0 (4.5-6.0)</cell><cell>.725</cell></row><row><cell>No. of responders in first, second,</cell><cell>First: 7 (33.3%)</cell><cell>First: 7 (38.9%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>and third months (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Second: 6 (28.6%) Second: 3 (16.7%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Third: 8 (38.1%)</cell><cell>Third: 8 (44.4%)</cell><cell>.679 §</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Relapse rate (%)</cell><cell>27.1</cell><cell>37.1</cell><cell>.329 §</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Time to relapse (wk), median (IQR)</cell><cell>10 (5-30.5)</cell><cell>4 (1.5-7.5)</cell><cell>.022*</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>The Dunn-Bonferroni posttest corrected for multiple comparisons was not significant for any of the pairs tested.IQR, Interquartile range; NR, nonresponder; PR, partial responder.</s><s>*Mann-Whitney U test.</s><s>Student t test.</s><s>àANOVA.</s><s>§x 2 Test.</s><s>kKruskal-Wallis test.</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">J ALLERGY CLIN IMMUNOL VOLUME 140, NUMBER 6 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR 1749</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">J ALLERGY CLIN IMMUNOLDECEMBER 2017</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>We thank Dr Sven Mostb€ ock for his contributions, suggestions, and critical discussion.</s></p><p><s>Almedina Kurtaj, MSc a Christoph Hillebrand, MSc a Gerda Fichtinger, BSc</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">It&apos;s a lot of work to be non-allergic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Schulten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="769" to="770" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preservation of epithelial cell barrier function and muted inflammation in resistance to allergic rhinoconjunctivitis from house dust mite challenge</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ahuja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Manoharan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Harper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Jimenez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hobson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Martinez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="844" to="854" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immune responses in healthy and allergic individuals are characterized by a fine balance between allergen-specific T regulatory 1 and T helper 2 cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Akdis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Verhagen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Karamloo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Karagiannidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Crameri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Exp Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">199</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1567" to="1575" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human CD41CD251 T cells derived from the majority of atopic donors are able to suppress TH1 and TH2 cytokine production</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Bellinghausen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Klostermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Knop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Saloga</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="862" to="868" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lack of allergy to timothy grass pollen is not a passive phenomenon but associated with the allergen-specific modulation of immune reactivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hinz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Seumois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gholami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Greenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Exp Allergy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="705" to="719" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Depletion of CD41CD251CD127lo regulatory T cells does not increase allergen-driven T cell activation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Skrindo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Farkas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Kvale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Johansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Jahnsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Exp Allergy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1752" to="1759" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Environmental biodiversity, human microbiota, and allergy are interrelated</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Von Hertzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fyhrquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Koskinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Torppa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Laatikainen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8334" to="8339" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IgE, IgG1, and IgG4 antibody responses to Blomia tropicalis in atopic patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pereira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Cunha-Junior</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Almeida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Alves</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Allergy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="406" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Th17 cells transdifferentiate into regulatory T cells during resolution of inflammation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Gagliani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amezcua</forename><surname>Vesely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Iseppon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brockmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Palm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">523</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="225" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coming back to a missing immune deviation as the main explanatory mechanism for the hygiene hypothesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Romagnani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1511" to="1513" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Available online</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jaci.2017.07.030</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jaci.2017.07.030" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-09-01">September 1, 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Omalizumab for the treatment of chronic spontaneous urticaria: a meta-analysis of randomized clinical trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hawro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1742" to="1750" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lack of basophil CD203c-upregulating activity as an immunological marker to predict response to treatment with omalizumab in patients with symptomatic chronic urticaria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Palacios</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Stillman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Borish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lawrence</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="530" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Serum autoreactivity predicts time to response to omalizumab therapy in chronic spontaneous urticaria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gericke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Metz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ohanyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Weller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Altrichter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Skov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1059" to="1061" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>e1</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sex differences in the pathogenesis of chronic urticaria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Asero</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="425" to="426" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asthma symptom re-emergence after omalizumab withdrawal correlates well with increasing IgE and decreasing pharmacokinetic concentrations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Slavin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ferioli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tannenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Blogg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="113" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>e3</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A mechanism-based binding model for the population pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of omalizumab</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Tsukamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sallas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Clin Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="548" to="561" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relationship between omalizumab pharmacokinetics, IgE pharmacodynamics and symptoms in patients with severe persistent allergic (IgE-mediated) asthma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tannenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gautier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jimenez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Clin Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immunotherapy approach to allergic disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Fick</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jardieu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunopharmacology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="307" to="310" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Allergen skin tests and free IgE levels during reduction and cessation of omalizumab therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Corren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Shapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Reimann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Deniz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Adelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="506" to="511" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Autoimmune chronic spontaneous urticaria: what we know and what we don&apos;t know</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kolkhir</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Church</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Weller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Metz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Schmetzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maurer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1772" to="1781" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Available online</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jaci.2017.08.007</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jaci.2017.08.007" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-09-01">September 1, 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
