<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">224th ENMC International Workshop</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-10-16">16 October 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yves</forename><surname>Allenbach</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Internal Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Pitie Salpetrière Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">AP-HP Sorbonne university</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mammen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">National Institutes of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bethesda</settlement>
									<region>MD</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Olivier</forename><surname>Benveniste</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Internal Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Pitie Salpetrière Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">AP-HP Sorbonne university</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Werner</forename><surname>Stenzel</surname></persName>
							<email>werner.stenzel@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neuropathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neuropathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">224th ENMC International Workshop</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-10-16">16 October 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F03A900C2BC154E0A7960F4FFB9EC7C4</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.nmd.2017.09.016</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 31 July 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:36+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p><s>Organizers of this 224th ENMC workshop welcomed 19 participants from 8 countries worldwide (Belgium, France, Germany, Japan, The Netherlands, Sweden, the United Kingdom, and the United States of America) to Zandvoort on 14-16 October 2016 for this workshop for clinicopathological classification of immune-mediated necrotizing myopathies.</s></p><p><s>Among the idiopathic inflammatory myopathies (IIMs), immune-mediated necrotizing myopathies (IMNMs) have been identified as important and separate entities during the past years.</s><s>A considerable wealth of studies detailing different sub-entities such as anti-signal recognition particle (SRP) and anti-HMG-CoA reductase (HMGCR)-associated myopathies has been published by different groups all over the world, and detailed knowledge about specific characteristics, pathophysiology and treatment options has accumulated.</s><s>Furthermore, characteristic morphological features separating IMNM from other idiopathic inflammatory myopathies have been studied.</s><s>In 2003, an expert team had defined clinicopathological criteria for IIMs during the 119th ENMC workshop, and these criteria have been widely used ever since.</s><s>Fourteen years on, it was time to revisit and expand these criteria for IMNM and a team of 18 experts has assembled to address the following goals:</s></p><p><s>-Consensus about identifying a valid definition of IMNM -Consensus about the definition of clinical diagnostic criteria -Consensus about the definition of pathological diagnostic criteria -Consensus on the role of serology in IMNMs -Proposition and discussion of possible/suitable treatment schemes for IMNM</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Definition of immune mediated necrotizing myopathy</head><p><s>Yves Allenbach opened the workshop with this first session, detailing the clinical characteristics of anti-SRP-associated myositis.</s><s>This included a presentation of French data in comparison to that of others.</s></p><p><s>He emphasized that anti-SRP myopathy was initially considered to be a form of polymyositis, and highlighted data showing that the pathological features of patients with this autoantibody are not restricted to pure 'necrotizing myopathy' without inflammation.</s><s>Rather, some patients have lymphocytic infiltrates on muscle biopsy.</s><s>The age of onset is usually after the fourth decade and mainly affects females <ref type="bibr">[1]</ref>.</s><s>Juvenile anti-SRP patients exist <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[2]</ref> and the presentation may mimic that of a muscular dystrophy in these children <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[3]</ref>.</s><s>Muscle weakness is the predominant clinical feature and affects the lower limbs most severely <ref type="bibr">[1]</ref>.</s><s>These patients usually have very high serum muscle enzyme levels with a mean peak CK of 6272 ± 1255 IU/L <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[6]</ref>.</s><s>In addition, dysphagia is frequently found in these patients (52.1 ± 30%) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[6]</ref>.</s><s>Of note, the titre of anti-SRP antibody correlates with serum CK levels <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[7]</ref>.</s><s>Anti-SRP myositis patients may also have cardiac involvement, including rhythm or conduction abnormalities as well as cardiac insufficiency in 15.8 ± 8.3% <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[6]</ref>.</s><s>Other extra-muscular manifestations may include interstitial lung disease (occurring in a third of patients in the French series) but is typically mild.</s><s>Allenbach highlighted that there is no increased risk of malignancy in anti-SRP patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[8]</ref>.</s><s>Importantly, the outcome of anti-SRP myopathy is poor since only half of patients recover normal strength after four years <ref type="bibr">[1]</ref>.</s><s>Finally, Yves Allenbach compared clinical phenotypes of both anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR patients, showing that anti-SRP myopathy is usually more severe <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[6]</ref> and with more intense muscle damage <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[9]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In summary, SRP myopathy is one of the most disabling auto-immune myopathies, characterized by an initially severe muscle weakness as well as often poor muscle recovery even with treatment.</s><s>The most concerning of the extra-muscular manifestations is the risk of cardiac involvement, which is rare but sometimes severe.</s><s>In contrast, lung involvement is frequent but usually without major clinical significance.</s></p><p><s>Anthony Amato outlined 'Clinical features of HMGCR myopathy' by discussing that Needham et al. reported statins may be associated with a distinct myopathy that persists after withdrawal of the statin and responds to immunosuppressive therapy <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[10]</ref>.</s><s>They described 8 patients ranging in age from 63 to 82 years who were on statins from 7 months to 9 years.</s><s>Four patients presented with symmetric proximal weakness, 1 with myalgia, 3 with combination of proximal weakness and myalgia.</s><s>Their CKs ranged from 958 to 45,000 U/L.</s><s>Muscle biopsies done 1 week to 6 months after discontinuation of the statin revealed findings suggestive of a necrotizing myopathy and increased expression of major MHC-1 was appreciated on the sarcolemma of non-necrotic muscle fibres.</s><s>Seven of 8 patients were treated with immunosuppressive therapy and improved.</s></p><p><s>A. Amato and colleagues subsequently reported 25 patients (12 men, 13 women) with an age of onset of 64.7 years (range 47-89 years) who developed a necrotizing myopathy in the setting of statin treatment <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[11]</ref>.</s><s>They manifested proximal muscle weakness and elevated CK levels (mean 8203 U/L, range 3000-17,280 U/L on statin) that persisted or worsened despite discontinuation of the drug (mean CK 6896 U/L, range 571-13,000 U/L off statin before treatment) and only improved following aggressive treatment with immunotherapy (mean CK 1052 U/L, range 20-3500 U/L).</s><s>Twenty-four patients required multiple immunotherapeutic agents.</s><s>Most patients relapsed after being tapered off immunotherapy.</s><s>Although patients improved, many had residual proximal weakness.</s><s>To support that statin use was associated with this immune-mediated necrotizing myopathy, they analysed their database of muscle patients with muscle biopsies.</s><s>They found that exposure to statins prior to onset was significantly higher in the necrotizing myopathies (82%) compared to patients with dermatomyositis (18%), polymyositis (24%), or inclusion body myositis IBM (38%).</s></p><p><s>The Johns Hopkins group supported this association and identified the antigenic target of the immune attack <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[12]</ref>.</s><s>They looked at sera from 38 patients diagnosed with a necrotizing myopathy on biopsy.</s><s>Twelve had a known autoantibody association or other aetiology for their myopathy (e.g., signal recognition particle antibodies).</s><s>Sixteen of the remaining 26 sera immunoprecipitated 200 and 100 kDa proteins.</s><s>Patients with anti-200/100 antibodies had proximal weakness, markedly elevated serum CK levels, and 63% had exposure to statins prior to the onset of weakness.</s><s>All patients responded to immunosuppressive therapy and many relapsed with medication tapering.</s></p><p><s>Mammen and colleagues subsequently determined that these anti-200/100 antibodies target HMGCR, the pharmacologic target of statin medications <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[13]</ref>.</s><s>They found anti-HMGCR autoantibodies in 45 of 750 patients presenting to the Johns Hopkins Myositis Center (6%).</s><s>Thirty of these 45 anti-HMGCR + individuals had prior statin exposure (66.6%) and among those, age 50 or older, 24 of 26 subjects had used statin medications (92.3%).</s><s>Patients manifested with proximal muscle weakness (95.6%), elevated CK levels (9718 ± 7383 IU/L), and myopathic EMG findings (97.3%).</s><s>All 40 of the available muscle biopsies demonstrated prominent necrotic and regenerating myofibres.</s><s>In addition, significant inflammatory infiltrates were noted in 8 of 40 (20%).</s><s>Those anti-HMGCR positive patients without statin exposure (one-third of patients) were clinically indistinguishable from those with prior statin use except for their younger age, higher CK levels, and race (46.7% vs. 86.7%</s><s>were white).</s></p><p><s>The Johns Hopkins group subsequently correlated anti-HMGCR levels, CK, levels and strength in 55 HMGCR+ individuals <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[14]</ref>.</s><s>They found that antibody levels correlated with CK levels, arm and leg strength at their baseline visit in statin-exposed patients only.</s><s>With immunotherapy, the autoantibody levels declined (but never disappeared) in statinexposed patients, but not in the statin-unexposed patients.</s></p><p><s>A European series found HMGCR antibodies in 45 of 206 patients with suspected immune-mediated necrotizing myopathy <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[15]</ref>.</s><s>The mean age of antibody-positive patients was approximately 49 years and over 70% were women.</s><s>They reported 8 cases that began in childhood or adolescence (ages 4-16 years).</s><s>Statin exposure was seen in only 44%.</s><s>As other series have appreciated, 39/45 were treated with immunotherapy and most required more than one immunotherapeutic agent.</s><s>No patient was able to discontinue immunotherapy for more than a year.</s><s>However, 2 were able to restart a statin and, interestingly, 3 individuals improved spontaneously without immunotherapy.</s></p><p><s>In a series of 405 Chinese patients with inflammatory myopathy, anti-HMGCR autoantibodies were present in 22 individuals (5.4%) and previous statin use was evident in only 4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[16]</ref>.</s><s>Anti-HMGCR+ patients had higher CKs and antibody levels correlated with CK levels and Myositis Disease Activity Assessment (MYOACT) scores at initial visit.</s><s>However, there was no correlation of antibody levels with CK or clinical assessments in long-term follow-up.</s></p><p><s>Researchers from Japan examined a cohort of 460 patients with idiopathic inflammatory myopathies (IIMs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[6]</ref>.</s><s>The frequencies of anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR antibodies were 18% and 12%, respectively (1 patient had both autoantibodies).</s><s>Severe limb muscle weakness, neck weakness, dysphagia, respiratory insufficiency and muscle atrophy were more frequently observed in patients with anti-SRP antibodies than in those with anti-HMGCR antibodies.</s><s>Chronic progression of muscle weakness over 12 months, which mimicked muscular dystrophy, was observed equally in both groups.</s><s>As with other reports, muscle biopsies were most often consistent with IMNM, and most patients needed multiple immunotherapies.</s><s>Most patients with anti-HMGCR autoantibodies were not previously taking statins.</s></p><p><s>An international, multi-centre study investigated the utility of anti-HMGCR antibodies in the diagnosis of IMNM (n = 69) in comparison to different forms of IIM (n = 1250) and controls (n = 656) <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[17]</ref>.</s><s>They confirmed that anti-HMGCR autoantibodies, when found in older patients and in conjunction with statin, were more frequently associated with markedly elevated CK and necrosis on muscle biopsy, that statins must be discontinued, and that treatment with immune modulators, including intravenous immunoglobulin, is often required.</s></p><p><s>Finally, some series have found that there may be an increased risk of cancer in HMGCR-positive patients, and thus cancer screening is necessary <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[20]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In summary, anti-HMGCR myopathy is associated with proximal muscle weakness, markedly elevated serum CKs, a myopathic EMG, and muscle biopsies that are usually suggestive of a necrotizing myopathy, but occasionally can be associated with inflammatory cell infiltrates.</s><s>The myopathy is often associated with prior statin use, particularly in patients older than 50 years of age.</s><s>However, in younger patients and Asians the myopathy is not typically associated with statin use.</s><s>The severity of the myopathy and CK levels may correlate with anti-HMGCR autoantibody titres, but more work needs to be done in this regard.</s><s>There may be an increased risk of cancer, so a malignancy work-up is recommended.</s><s>Patients with antimyopathy can be difficult to treat and often require multiple immunotherapies.</s><s>The slow progression in some individuals can mimic a limb-girdle dystrophy, so assessing for anti HMGCR (and -SRP) antibodies should be considered in patients with idiopathic limb-girdle syndromes so as to not miss a potentially treatable myopathy.</s></p><p><s>Yves Allenbach finished by focussing on the association between anti-HMGCR myopathy and cancer and presented their recent study on this topic <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[8]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Cancer associated myositis (CAM) is defined as malignancy occurring within the 3 years before or after the diagnosis of myositis <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[21]</ref>.</s><s>CAM mainly occurs in dermatomyositis patients (24% ).</s><s>Nevertheless it was also observed in patients suffering from polymyositis (10.2% [0-43]) <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[22]</ref>.</s><s>It was shown that the presence of arthritis and interstitial lung disease are less associated with cancer, suggesting that 'pure PM' may harbour an increased risk of malignancy <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[23]</ref>.</s><s>Of note, until recently, IMNM was considered to be a form of PM.</s><s>Initial reports in 1969 emphasized the association of cancer and necrotizing myopathies <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[24]</ref>, and the term of paraneoplastic necrotizing myopathies appeared at the end of the 1990s <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[25]</ref>.</s><s>Although anti-SRP was first reported in 1986 <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[26]</ref>, the concept of IMNM emerged only in 2004 <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[27]</ref> and anti-HMGCR antibodies were described only recently in 2011 <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[13]</ref>.</s><s>To clarify the risk of malignancy in IMNM according to the presence of myositis specific auto-antibodies, the incidence of cancer was compared between patients with IMNM and that observed in the general population (age and sex matched) <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[8]</ref>.</s><s>As in DM patients, it was shown that CAM occurred preferentially in IMNM patients who were 50 years of age or older.</s><s>Synchronous malignancy was diagnosed in 21.4% of seronegative IMNM (anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR antibody negative) and in 11.5% of anti-HMGCR patients; the incidence of cancer was higher compared to the general population in both groups.</s><s>No increased cancer prevalence was observed for anti-SRP myopathy patients.</s><s>No specific type of cancer was predominant and patients with a synchronous cancer had a decreased survival rate.</s><s>There is no other study comparing the incidence of cancer in anti-SRP IMNM and the general population.</s><s>Nonetheless, descriptive studies of anti-SRP IMNM do not report an increased incidence of malignancy.</s><s>For patients with anti-HMGCR myopathy, one other study confirmed an increased risk of malignancy <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[18]</ref> and another one did not <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[28]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In summary, the previous connection between malignancy and PM may be linked to IMNM rather than PM.</s><s>Among IMNM patients, seronegative individuals have the highest malignancy risk and may have the same risk as those with DM.</s><s>The cancer risk seems increased but less dramatic in anti-HMGCR patients, whereas anti-SRP INMN patients do not have an increased risk of developing cancer compared to the general population.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Pathological criteria of IMNM</head><p><s>This second session was opened by Werner Stenzel with a talk entitled 'Pathology of IMNM -the Berlin-Paris series'.</s><s>According to the 2003 ENMC criteria, the pathological definition of IMNM required prominent myofibre necrosis, the absence of significant inflammatory infiltrates, negative MHC class I expression, and variable complement deposition on capillaries.</s><s>Sarcolemmal deposition of complement was considered an exclusion criterion, evocative of a dystrophic process <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[27]</ref>.</s><s>Since 2003, this description has been revisited in a case series of anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR muscle biopsies and the following characteristics were found.</s><s>In both anti-HMGCR and anti-SRP patients' muscle biopsies, necrotic muscle fibres were distributed with a diffuse pattern and can be identified as being in different stages of necrosis.</s><s>Regenerating fibres are also diffusely distributed and can be abundant.</s><s>The most useful stains for characterizing the extent and distribution of regenerating fibres include NCAM, neonatal myosin, utrophin, and laminin alpha 5.</s><s>While the sequence of events leading to single myofibre necrosis is poorly defined and can sometimes be difficult to assess, regeneration is a longer process and can be identified by this series of immunohistochemical stains.</s><s>In some cases, necrosis can be rare and regeneration is more prominent.</s><s>Werner Stenzel pointed out that in their experience, sarcolemmal MHC class I is always detectable but sometimes the staining is faint.</s><s>In most cases, the distribution is diffuse and can be separated from perifascicular staining patterns as observed in most biopsies from patients with dermatomyositis and anti-synthetase syndrome (ASS)associated myopathies <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[29]</ref>.</s><s>Similarly, lymphocytic infiltrates (CD8 + ) are always present in the endomysium as well as in the perimysium and sometimes close to vessels.</s><s>While they may be sparse, we have not found a single case in which they were absent.</s><s>Granular complement (C5b-9) deposition is frequently present on the sarcolemma of myofibres, with a diffuse distribution and again not with a perifascicular pattern (as in ASS-associated myositis).</s><s>However, this feature can also be absent.</s><s>Werner Stenzel also highlighted the fact that in addition to the frequently discussed patients with anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR autoantibodies, necrotizing myopathy can also occur in various other contexts such as the NM with pipestem capillaries <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[30]</ref> and NM associated with connective tissue diseases, some of which may harbour myositis-associated autoantibodies (MAAs).</s><s>This latter aspect has not intensely been explored yet and may help to specify patients, which were formerly classified as non-specific myositis.</s></p><p><s>Ichizo Nishino (Tokyo, Japan) presented 'The Pathology of IMNM -The Japanese experience' At his institution, which harbours the major myopathology lab in Japan and includes a cohort of 460 patients for the period of 2010 to 2014, IMNM represented 39% of all inflammatory myopathies.</s><s>Among those with IMNM, 26% have anti-HMGCR myopathy, 39% have anti-SRP myopathy, and 35% were negative for these two autoantibodies.</s><s>He emphasized that among those with anti-HMGCR antibodies, but without exposure to statins, there were also children, even in the first decade of life; a similar age distribution was found in those patients, including children, with anti-SRP antibodies.</s><s>Children with anti-HMGCR myopathy were often first considered to have a muscular dystrophy rendering paediatric anti-HGMCR myopathy an important differential diagnosis to muscular dystrophy.</s><s>The clinical course was usually subacute or chronic, but occasionally presented acutely.</s><s>The myopathological patterns of biopsies from anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR patients corresponded to those reported by other groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[31]</ref>.</s><s>Importantly, this included sarcolemmal deposits of C5b9 in those with IMNM but not in muscular dystrophies (except for those patients with dysferlinopathies).</s><s>Sarcolemmal MHC class I was also expressed in childhood HMGCR myopathy.</s><s>In addition to anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR, autoantibodies recognizing the mitochondrial M2 protein, aminoacyl t-RNA synthetase (ARS), and few others were noted.</s><s>Among patients with anti-M2 antibodies, there were a high preponderance of females (7:29 M:F) and a peak presence at the sixth and seventh decades.</s><s>Anti-M2 patients' muscle tissues not only showed necrosis and regeneration, sarcolemmal MHC class I expression and sarcolemmal C5b9 deposits, but also rare (8%) granulomas.</s><s>The antisynthetase patients in this cohort, making up 11% of all patients, included those with autoantibodies against Jo-1 (30%), OJ (26%), PL-7 (24%), EJ (10%), PL-12 (8%), and KS (2%).</s><s>Muscle biopsies from the antisynthetase patients were notable for having perimysial fragmentation, enhanced perimysial histochemical activity of alkaline phosphatase, and perifascicular myofibre necrosis, which was present in 67% of those with anti-PL-7, 47% of those with anti-Jo-1, and 46% with anti-OJ autoantibodies.</s></p><p><s>Andrea Corse (Baltimore, USA) referred to 'Pathology of IMNM -The Hopkins experience'.</s></p><p><s>While necrotizing myopathies due to a variety of drugs and toxins and some genetic muscle diseases have long been recognized, remarkable discoveries of autoimmune-mediated necrotizing myopathies have emerged in the past two decades.</s><s>Historically, histopathologic features of necrotizing myopathies included myofibre degeneration, necrosis, and myophagocytosis with non-specific myopathic features.</s><s>Necrotizing myopathies were similarly distinguished by their lack of endomysial lymphocytic primary inflammation surrounding and invading non-necrotic myofibres, a histopathologic hallmark of many of the idiopathic inflammatory myopathies.</s><s>While this histopathologic distinction between necrotizing and inflammatory myopathies largely remains, diseases in the subcategory of immune-mediated necrotizing myopathies are increasingly recognized and better defined.</s><s>The previous narrower differential diagnosis of a necrotizing myopathy seems ever-expansive, including now an array of immune-mediated necrotizing myopathies, such as anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR associated myopathies, anti-synthetase syndrome associated myopathies, and cancer associated myopathies.</s><s>Progress in understanding histopathologic characteristics and clinical phenotypic correlations holds immense promise for improved targeted therapies.</s></p><p><s>In order to characterize the histopathology in anti-HMG-CoA reductase associated myopathy, we analysed muscle biopsies from 18 anti-HMGCR-associated myopathy patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[32]</ref>.</s><s>Statin exposure occurred in 88%, the mean maximum CK was 9551 IU/L, average patient age was 56 years, and 66% were women.</s><s>At the time of the biopsy, the median disease duration was 13 months and 33% were on immunosuppressive therapy.</s></p><p><s>In addition to myofibre degeneration, necrosis, and myophagocytosis, macrophages were the predominant infiltrating cell type present in 100% in the anti-HMGCR-associated myopathy biopsies.</s><s>All anti-HMGCR biopsies had a macrophage polarity favouring CD163 M2 macrophages indicating regeneration/repair, whereas few cases (18%) had CD11c M1 'phagocytic' macrophages.</s><s>While CD123 plasmacytoid dendritic cells were common in both anti-HMGCR myopathy biopsies (62%) and 100% of biopsies from 7 patients with dermatomyositis (DM) for comparison, the difference in the cellular distribution was striking.</s><s>In anti-HMGCR myopathy biopsies, plasmacytoid dendritic cells and M2 macrophages were preferentially located throughout the endomysium, while in DM they were primarily located in perimysial and perifascicular areas.</s></p><p><s>In each of the anti-HMGCR-associated myopathy biopsies, necrosis appeared out of proportion to the minimal lymphocytic infiltration, suggesting a lesser role of T and B cells in the pathogenesis of anti-HMGCR myopathy.</s><s>Yet MHC-I upregulation and MAC deposition both on intact myofibres throughout the endomysium were common features seen in 88% and 87%, respectively, in anti-HMGCR biopsies, supporting an immunopathogenesis, potentially complement-mediated.</s></p><p><s>Such distinct histopathology associated with anti-HMGCR related disease led us to investigate the prevalence of individual histopathologic features according to autoantibody status in 91 DM and 13 anti-Jo-1 associated myopathy biopsies <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[31]</ref>.</s><s>Autoantibodies screened included Jo-1, anti-TIF1-γ, NXP2, Mi-2, MDA5, PM-scl, and Ro52.</s><s>Histopathologic features assessed included perivascular inflammation, perifascicular atrophy, primary inflammation, mitochondrial dysfunction, and necrotizing myopathy.</s><s>At the time of the biopsy 56% of the patients were on immunosuppressive treatments.</s></p><p><s>Of the 91 biopsies of patients with a clinical DM diagnosis, one in six biopsies showed features indistinguishable from a necrotizing myopathy with myofibre degeneration, necrosis and myophagocytosis without perivascular inflammation, perifascicular atrophy, or primary inflammation.</s><s>Features such as classic clinical phenotype (dermatitis), antibody testing or immunostaining, would have been required to distinguish an immune-mediated necrotizing myopathy.</s><s>Alternatively, anti-TIF1-γ, and NXP2-associated myopathies often showed both perivascular inflammation and perifascicular atrophy with very rare primary endomysial inflammation.</s><s>Given the small number of patients with a given antibody and the considerable variability in biopsy features among patients with a given antibody, antibody status could not reliably infer histologic features in this study.</s><s>However, the prevalence of different histologic features did vary according to antibody status.</s><s>This may reflect, indeed, different pathologic pathways in patients with different autoantibodies in DM, anti-Jo-1-associated disease and the immune-mediated necrotizing myopathies.</s></p><p><s>Alan Pestronk (St. Louis, USA) addressed the 'Pathology of IMNM -The St. Louis experience':</s></p><p><s>Immune and inflammatory myopathies (IIM) can be classified according to patterns of tissue damage and inflammation in muscle <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[33]</ref>.</s><s>Myofasciopathies involve muscle fibres and connective tissue.</s><s>The most common of these syndromes, immune myopathies with perimysial pathology (IMPP), presents clinically as multisystem disorders with involvement of muscle, skin, lungs or joints.</s><s>Serum antibodies to tRNA synthetases and signal recognition particle (SRP) are associated with myofasciopathies.</s><s>Myovasculopathies are likely caused by vascular damage.</s><s>Muscle fibre, and other, pathology is often patchy, and related to the locations of intermediate-sized arteries and veins.</s><s>They often present clinically as dermatomyopathies, some of which are associated with risk of neoplasms.</s><s>Primary myopathies involve mainly muscle fibres, with little damage to other tissues in muscles.</s><s>Histiocytic inflammatory myopathies present with foci of histiocytic cells in muscle.</s></p><p><s>Some authors have proposed "necrotic myopathies" as a subtype of IIM.</s><s>However, if pathogenesis or pathology is a consideration, the presence of muscle fibre necrosis is, in itself, not a useful subclassification of IIM, or myopathies.</s><s>Myopathies with prominent muscle fibre necrosis include several very different disorders with varied patterns of necrosis.</s><s>Some myofasciopathies have prominent necrosis.</s><s>IMPP have necrotic fibres, most prominent near the perimysium <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[33]</ref>.</s><s>SRPantibody myopathy <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">34]</ref> and Brachio-cervical inflammatory myopathy (BCIM) <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[35]</ref> have randomly scattered necrotic fibres.</s><s>A myovasculopathy, Regional Ischemic Immune Myopathy (RIIM), has necrosis of muscle fibres in border zones between vessels <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[35]</ref>.</s><s>Hereditary, and other types of acquired myopathies, may have abundant scattered muscle fibre necrosis.</s><s>The presence of abundant muscle fibre necrosis may be clinically useful in generating a diagnostic differential diagnosis within IIM.</s><s>Myofibre necrosis and its serum correlate, very high CK levels, are most common in anti-HMGCR, anti-SRP, RIIM, and some anti-synthetase antibody (Jo-1 and OJ) associated IIM <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[36]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Serology of IMNMs</head><p><s>The last session of the first day addressed the relevance of Serology of IMNMs, and Andrew Mammen (NIH Bethesda, Maryland, USA) in his first presentation 'From identification to routine measurement of HMGCR' discussed the discovery of anti-HMG-CoA reductase autoantibodies and their association with statin exposure.</s><s>In the original description of anti-HMG-CoA reductase autoantibody-positive myopathy patients from the Johns Hopkins Myositis Center, 30 out of 45 (67%) had a prior prescription for statins <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[12]</ref>.</s><s>While even higher rates of statin exposure have been reported by some investigators <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[19]</ref>, other groups have reported significantly lower statin exposure rates ranging from 14% to 44% among anti-HMG-CoA reductase autoantibody-positive patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">16]</ref>.Although the reasons for differences in the reported overall prevalence of statin exposure are not clear, age-controlled comparisons have demonstrated an increased risk of statin exposure among patients over the age of 50 compared to patients with other forms of myositis <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[12]</ref>, even in cohorts with relatively low overall rates of statin exposure <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[6]</ref>.</s><s>Interestingly, a recent study suggested that atorvastatin may be most strongly associated with the development of anti-HMG-CoA reductase myopathy compared to simvastatin or rosuvastatin <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[37]</ref>.</s><s>The possibility that dietary sources of statins (e.g., oyster mushrooms) might confer risk of anti-HMG-CoA reductase myopathy was discussed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Clinical session</head><p><s>Marianne de Visser (Amsterdam) discussed the nomenclature of IMNM in the first presentation entitled 'Where to place IMNM in the spectrum of IIMs -the view of neurologists'.</s><s>Strictly speaking IMNM is a form of polymyositis since it is an inflammatory myopathy with strict involvement of the skeletal muscles albeit lymphocytic infiltration is sparse or absent.</s><s>The clinical picture, pathological features and MSA profile of IMNM differ markedly from those of antisynthetase syndrome and non-specific myositis.</s></p><p><s>With regard to trial readiness considerable hurdles have to be overcome.</s><s>First, there is no consensus on diagnostic criteria of IIMs; in particular the histology easily leads to different interpretations.</s><s>Currently there is an international project to establish diagnostic criteria based on consensus building including itemized discussions of myopathological methods and scoring.</s><s>Second, according to a 2015 Cochrane review, trials are of poor quality, and this holds for all myositis subtypes.</s><s>Third, there has to be a consensus whether patients with pure IMNM or with associated diseases (connective tissue disorders, cancer) are enrolled.</s><s>Fourth, stratification of IMNMsubtypes according to serological findings (SRP, HMGCR) has to be considered.</s><s>Fifth, there has to be consensus on outcome measures (NB: The IMACS outcome measures do not pertain to IMNM), and last there has to be collaboration across borders since the trials need to be adequately powered.</s></p><p><s>Ingrid Lundberg (Stockholm, Sweden) discussed 'Where to place IMNMs in the spectrum of IIMs, the view of the rheumatologist'.</s></p><p><s>During recent years, more than 15 myositis-specific autoantibodies (MSA) have been identified.</s><s>Interestingly, these MSAs are associated with distinct clinical phenotypes, such as antisynthetase autoantibodies with myositis and interstitial lung disease (ILD), anti-MDA5 with dermatomyositis and ILD (often rapidly progressive), and anti-TIF1-γ with DM and cancer.</s><s>Two MSAs, anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR autoantibodies, are mainly associated with muscle disease of necrotizing myopathy type.</s><s>These entities have together often been named IMNM.</s><s>The clinical and histopathological features associated with anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR have been well described, with muscle fibre necrosis as a characteristic feature of muscle biopsies.</s></p><p><s>However, there are some unanswered questions:</s></p><p><s>• What is the link between the immune system, anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR autoantibodies, and muscle fibre necrosis?</s><s>• Which is the mechanism behind the muscle fibre necrosis?</s><s>• Are the anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR autoantibodies pathogenic?</s><s>• Where does the primary immune reaction take place?</s><s>• Which are the antigens targeted by these autoantibodies?</s></p><p><s>Most of the studies on the IMNM have been performed in cross sectional cohorts and with a few longitudinal follow-up studies, and little information is available from time point of early disease or in the 'pre-disease phase'.</s></p><p><s>Learning from another disease: In another condition characterized by autoantibodies, rheumatoid arthritis (RA), a paradigm shift concerning understanding of disease pathogenesis and the onset of immune reaction has taken place after the discovery of anticitrullinated peptide autoantibodies (ACPA) up to 20 years before disease diagnosis with an increasing frequency of antibody positive individuals closer to time of diagnosis and an increased number of antigen specificities likewise close to time of diagnosis.</s><s>The latter suggests an epitope spreading <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[38]</ref>.</s><s>This observation has led to a shift in investigations from individuals with established diagnosis of RA towards individuals at risk of developing RA.</s><s>Risk factors for RA include both genetic and environment risk factors.</s><s>The strongest genetic risk factor is the so called shared epitope of HLA-DR4, and the most striking environmental risk factor in individuals with shared epitope is smoking <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[39]</ref>.</s><s>Another risk factor is high body mass index (BMI), as demonstrated in ACPA-positive individuals with arthralgias.</s><s>The combination of smoking and BMI was a strong risk factor to develop RA compared to non-smoking individuals with a normal BMI <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[40]</ref>.</s><s>The observation of autoantibodies before diagnosis and before clinical symptoms has introduced new phases of RA disease named localized and systemic autoimmunity, symptoms without RA, undifferentiated arthritis and RA <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[41]</ref>.</s><s>These observations have turned the focus of interest of research to understand the disease development from the joint to the lung, and accumulating data support the notion of lung as one important site of the initiation of immune reaction in ACPA-positive RA <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[42]</ref>.</s><s>In parallel, in patients with myositis, I Lundberg and colleagues have identified an association between smoking and anti-Jo-1 autoantibodies, and this was even stronger in myositis patients with HLA-DRB1*03 genotype <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[43]</ref>.</s><s>This information together with previous published data on the higher expression of the histidyl-tRNA antigen, the target of the anti-Jo-1 autoantibodies, in epithelial cells of the lungs, and where granzyme-cleaved neoepitopes of the histidyl-tRNA antigen have been recorded, has made us postulate a hypothesis that anti-Jo-1-associated myositis may be initiated in the lungs, and we have focussed our studies on immune reactions for this subset of myositis to the lungs.</s></p><p><s>For patients with anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR antibodies, a similar approach may be of value.</s><s>To understand the development of disease a possibility would be to focus investigations on early organ involvement and extra-muscular organ involvement.</s><s>In anti-SRP-positive patients, extra muscular organ involvement includes the heart, joints and lungs with interstitial lung disease <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[6]</ref>, whereas in HMGCR-positive patients mainly the skeletal muscles are clinically affected.</s><s>Another approach could be to focus on known risk factors, such as statin exposure in the anti-HMGCR-positive patients and how statins could lead to modifications of self-antigens to become immunogenic, and if there are other risk factors not yet identified.</s></p><p><s>In summary, in patients with anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR antibodies the clinical major target organ is skeletal muscle leading to muscle weakness.</s><s>Patients often have muscle damage at time of diagnosis.</s><s>How can we intervene earlier?</s><s>Where does the initial immune response take place?</s><s>How can we study early phases of disease?</s><s>A future research approach would be identification of early "non-specific cases".</s></p><p><s>Werner Stenzel delivered a second talk entitled ' IMNMs and dystrophy mimics'.</s><s>Some monogenetic diseases are of particular differential diagnostic interest, when it comes to morphological features that define immune mechanisms, versus those that accompany a degenerative process based on a genetic defect.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Of the</head><p><s>LGMDs, Anoctaminopathy (LGMD2L), Dysferlinopathy (LGMD2B), and the Sarcoglycanopathies can show numerous necrotic myofibres and also CD8 + lymphocytic infiltrates.</s><s>As a rule of thumb, most dystrophies are characterized by fibre-size variation, which is more prominent/ large as compared to IMNMs, and small regenerating fibres are mostly clustering in contrast to IMNM.</s><s>MHC class I in LGMDs is present only on regenerating fibres and the latter are frequently clustering in small groups and/or are particularly small, which differentiates these entities from immunemediated counterparts with myofibre necrosis.</s><s>However, complement (C5b-9) can be prominent on the sarcolemma especially in Dysferlinopathies.</s><s>Similarly, in FKRP mutations (LGMD2I), T cells and macrophages in clusters, mostly situated around regenerating fibres, can be identified.</s><s>In FSHD inflammation may be prominent and in Laminopathies, inflammation may even mimic juvenile Dermatomyositis (Nishino).</s><s>Numerous other inherited myopathies can occasionally harbour inflammatory cells, but do not constitute a realistic differential diagnosis of immune mediated necrotizing myopathy.</s><s>Werner Stenzel pointed out that consideration of the clinical context, thorough analysis of muscle biopsies with a panel identifying inflammatory features as well as a panel identifying protein defects characteristic of certain myopathies or dystrophies, are useful for differentiation of sporadic vs. inherited conditions.</s><s>When in doubt, a genetic analysis may be necessary.</s><s>He also stressed that consideration of single items such as e.g.</s><s>'CD8 + T-cells surrounding or invading myofibres' or complement deposition or MHC upregulation may be misleading, and that it is important to consider a combination of different items in any case.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Pathophysiology of IMNMs</head><p><s>Audrey Aussey, speaking also on behalf of Olivier Boyer (both Rouen, France), discussed the 'Pathophysiology of immune-mediated necrotizing myopathies (IMNMs) using new animal models.'</s></p><p><s>Anti-HMGCR and anti-SRP auto-antibodies (aAbs) are strongly specific for IMNMs, but their role in the onset and/or persistence of disease is unknown.</s><s>Recent development of quantitative immuno-assays (ALBIA/Luminex technology) allowed a fine analysis of these aAbs.</s><s>In 2011, Benveniste et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[7]</ref> found a strong correlation between anti-SRP aAb levels and disease activity (creatine kinase levels and muscle strength) in adults.</s><s>Momomura et al. confirmed this result in 2014 in a paediatric patient.</s><s>Furthermore, Werner et al. and Allenbach et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">15]</ref> also found a correlation between anti-HMGCR aAb levels, muscle strength and CK levels in 2012 and 2014, respectively.</s></p><p><s>These results suggest a possible pathogenic role for anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR aAbs in IMNMs.</s><s>To investigate this issue, animal models are strongly required.</s><s>Two strategies could be considered: active immunization using human recombinant SRP or HMGCR proteins, or passive immunization by transfer of IgG or purified aAbs obtained from patients.</s><s>Collaborative results from Boyer and Benveniste labs were presented by Aussey, which strongly support this hypothesis since immunization and transfer experiments provoke an acquired myopathy in mice.</s><s>Such models should be useful for elucidating pathophysiological mechanisms and evaluating new therapeutic approaches <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[12]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Andrew Mammen in his presentation 'Statins and HMGCRassociated IMNM' discussed the development of diagnostic tools to detect anti-HMGCR autoantibodies.</s></p><p><s>Identification of anti-HMGCR autoantibodies was originally achieved by immunoprecipitation (IP) of the protein from 35 Smethionine-labeled HeLa cell lysates (Christopher-Stine et al. 2010).</s><s>Subsequently, an IP assay using radioactively labeled HMG-CoA reductase protein produced by in vitro transcription and translation (IVTT) was utilized <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[13]</ref>.</s><s>As IP assays are labour intensive, a rapid ELISA was developed to detect anti-HMGCR autoantibodies.</s><s>Compared to the "gold standard" IP, the ELISA has a sensitivity and specificity of 94.4% and 99.3%, respectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[13]</ref>.</s><s>The ELISA was used to screen for anti-HMGCR autoantibodies in 1966 healthy control subjects, none of whom had known myopathy and more than half of whom had a prior statin exposure.</s><s>While 14 (0.7%) of the subjects were positive by ELISA, none of these were positive by IP <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">[44]</ref>.</s><s>These findings underscore the utility of using an IP test to confirm ELISA positive results.</s><s>Moreover, they show that anti-HMGCR autoantibodies are rarely, if ever, found in patients without myopathy.</s><s>Subsequent studies have shown that anti-HMGCR autoantibodies are uncommon, if present at all, in patients with mild self-limited statin-related myopathy, severe statin-related rhabdomyolysis, or genetic muscle diseases.</s></p><p><s>Olivier Benveniste (Paris, France) spoke on 'In-vitro work on IMNMs'.</s></p><p><s>Anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR autoantibodies are associated with IMNM and the titres of these autoantibodies are correlated with disease activity.</s><s>O. Benveniste and colleagues investigated if anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR Abs could be involved in pathogenicity, specifically their role in causing muscle atrophy and impairing muscle regeneration.</s></p><p><s>They analysed muscle biopsies of 40 patients for atrophy and regeneration by measuring the fibres sizes and quantifying muscle regeneration by performing immunostaining of neonatal myosin heavy chain.</s><s>To further understand the role of the autoantibodies in the pathology, they performed in vitro primary muscle cells co-cultures with the autoantibodies.</s><s>Atrophy and regeneration were studied based on the myotube surface area, gene expression analysis, and cytokines profiles.</s></p><p><s>Ex vivo in muscle biopsies, they observed an important proportion of small fibres corresponding to both atrophic and regenerating fibres.</s></p><p><s>In vitro, anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR autoantibodies induced muscle fibre atrophy and increased the transcription of MAFbx and Trim63.</s><s>In addition, muscle fibre atrophy was associated with high levels of the inflammatory cytokines TNF and IL-6 as well as reactive oxygen species.</s><s>In the presence of anti-SRP or anti-HMGCR autoantibodies, muscle regeneration was also impaired due to a defect of myoblast fusion.</s><s>This defect was associated with a decreased production of IL-4 and IL-13.</s><s>The addition of IL-4 and/or IL-13 totally rescued fusion capacity <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[45]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Together, these data show that molecular mechanisms of atrophy and regeneration are affected and contribute to muscle damage occurring in IMNM.</s><s>This emphasizes the potential interest of targeted therapies addressing these mechanisms and/or these myositis-specific autoantibodies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Toxins, genes and epigenetics in IMNMs</head><p><s>Janine Lamb (Manchester, UK) reported on genetics of IMNM.</s><s>The idiopathic inflammatory myopathies (IIM) are a spectrum of rare autoimmune diseases, thought to be caused by immune activation following specific environmental events in genetically predisposed individuals.</s><s>Autoantibodies are detected in up to 80% of IIM patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[46]</ref>.</s><s>Traditional classification criteria for IIM result in heterogeneous subgroups, suggesting that stratifying patients according to autoantibody status may be more useful, as patients with certain autoantibodies have specific clinical features and respond differently to treatment.</s></p><p><s>Within the Myositis Genetics Consortium (MYOGEN), the aim of J Lamb and colleagues is to investigate the genetic architecture of IIM, including the different clinical and serological subgroups.</s><s>They carried out a primary analysis of &gt;2500 Caucasian individuals with myositis, using the Illumina Immunochip array.</s><s>This array contains dense coverage of genetic variation across 186 regions implicated in 12 autoimmune and inflammatory diseases, allowing accurate high resolution imputation <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[47]</ref> across eight human leukocyte antigen (HLA) alleles to investigate whether amino acids may be more significantly associated than classical HLA alleles.</s></p><p><s>They confirmed a strong association of the 8.1 ancestral haplotype, including several independent associations, in IIM and clinical subgroups of adult and juvenile dermatomyositis, polymyositis <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[48]</ref>.</s><s>This large common haplotype confers susceptibility to many autoimmune or immune-mediated diseases <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">[49]</ref>.</s><s>They showed that key amino acid positions within HLA genes are differentially associated in the IIM subgroups, suggesting that these amino acids may confer risk in these genes by affecting the structure of the peptide binding pocket, subsequent binding of antigenic peptides and presentation to the T cell receptor.</s><s>Beyond the HLA region, they identified overlap with risk variants reported in other seropositive autoimmune diseases; these genes are involved in activation of the adaptive immune response.</s><s>There is evidence also of different genetic architectures in clinical subgroups of IIM, suggesting different underlying predominating pathophysiology.</s></p><p><s>Currently, they are using the imputed data to characterize HLA associations within IIM serology subgroups.</s><s>For Immune-Mediated Necrotizing Myopathy (IMNM), our analysis focusses on individuals who are positive for autoantibodies against SRP or HMGCR.</s><s>In individuals who are HMGCR autoantibody-positive (n = 41), they identified association to HLA-DRB1*11 (p = 1.58 × 10 −5 , OR = 5.60, 95% CI = 2.62-12.63),</s><s>where 57.1% of HMGCR autoantibody-positive individuals had at least one copy of HLA-DRB1*11, compared to 20.7% of healthy controls.</s><s>These results confirm the previously reported HLA-DRB1*11 association in HMGCR autoantibody-positive individuals <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">[50]</ref>.</s><s>The presence of a glutamic acid at position 58 was the most strongly associated amino acid, although at a comparable level of significance to the classical HLA association (p = 4.90 × 10 −5 , OR = 4.20, 95% CI = 2.12-8.55).</s><s>All DRB1*11 alleles have glutamic acid at position 58; therefore it is not clear whether risk is due to this amino acid, or whether it is a proxy for the HLA allele.</s><s>In individuals with SRP autoantibodies (n = 45), they identified associations to HLA-C*07:01 and HLA-B*08:01, although these associations did not meet a Bonferroni corrected significance level of p &lt; 6.6 × 10 −5 for all HLA variants tested.</s></p><p><s>They propose to continue this 'splitting' approach in future analyses to stratify HMGCR autoantibody-positive individuals into those who are statin-exposed vs. not statin-exposed.</s><s>Their Immunochip data also will enable them to carry out genomewide or targeted association analysis, for example, of the SLCO1B1 gene, reported as associated in statin-induced myopathy <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">[51]</ref>.</s><s>Further proposed analyses include analysis in larger cohorts of SRP and HMGCR autoantibody positive individuals, extension to non-Caucasian samples, and use of structural modelling of HMGCR peptide binding to DRB1*11:01.</s></p><p><s>Jan De Bleecker (Ghent, Belgium) gave a talk entitled 'Exclusion of toxic and other non-autoimmune causes of necrotizing myopathy'.</s></p><p><s>Besides IMNM and forms of muscular dystrophy, necrotizing myopathy is commonly diagnosed on muscle biopsy in toxic, infectious and metabolic myopathies.</s><s>The list of drugs causing muscle necrosis is long, but cholesterol-lowering agents, the immunophilins cyclosporine and tacrolimus, and nucleoside analogues such as telbivudine and entecavir used in hepatitis treatment are among the more common ones.</s><s>Statins cause muscle pain and mild weakness in about 1/8000 persons, starting weeks to a few months after initiation of therapy, more rarely after years.</s><s>In those late cases, other drugs, mainly those competing for the CYP3A4 liver isoenzyme, sometimes elicit the myopathy.</s><s>Fibrates, although used less commonly, carry at least as high a risk of developing a myopathy.</s><s>Among leisure drugs, alcohol intoxication in binge drinking and the use of cocaine and heroin are associated with muscle necrosis.</s><s>Snake venoms, including the rattlesnake venom containing crotamine that affects sodium channel function in the tubular system, and cobra venom having phospholipase A2 activity on the muscle fibre membrane, are encountered in distinct regions of the world.</s><s>Biopsies usually show isolated muscle fibre necrosis and regeneration, without lymphocytic inflammation or MHC class I upregulation.</s></p><p><s>Infectious causes of muscle necrosis include hepatitis B, C and E. In some cases, biopsies also showed MHCI upregulation and scattered lymphocytic infiltrates, not invading non-necrotic muscle fibres.</s><s>These biopsies cannot be reliably separated from IMNM, and the clinical context must be taken into account to reach a correct diagnosis.</s><s>In some published cases, the individual roles of the viral infection and the treatment with nucleoside analogues or interferon alpha cannot be distinguished.</s><s>Viral particles or RNA have never been demonstrated in muscle tissue.</s><s>Influenza A or B infection is probably the most common viral cause of muscle necrosis, with adenovirus, Epstein Barr virus, Coxsackie virus and HIV being less common causes.</s><s>Bacterial and parasitic infections may also cause muscle necrosis.</s></p><p><s>Metabolic causes of necrotizing myopathy include genetic disorders of glycogenolysis and glycolysis, disorders of lipid metabolism and more rarely mitochondrial myopathies.</s><s>Rhabdomyolysis is often the clinical reason for biopsy taking, and the clinical history is usually helpful.</s><s>Systemic metabolic derangements such as hypokalaemia, hypocalcaemia, hypophosphatemia, nonketotic hyperosmotic disorders and diabetic ketoacidosis can provoke muscle necrosis.</s><s>Endocrine disorders, most notably hypo-and hyperthyroidism and adrenal insufficiency are also common causes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Treatment in IMNM</head><p><s>In the last session, Tahseen Mozaffar (Irvine, USA) addressed 'Conventional immunosuppressants in IMNM'.</s><s>There is very little literature detailing the experience with conventional immunosuppressants in IMNM.</s><s>IMNM is a relatively new disease, described for the first time in 2004.</s><s>There have been no randomized trials and except for a few anecdotal reports, there are no large enough case series available to make definite conclusions or formal recommendations <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">52,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">53]</ref> necrotizing myopathy and there is a fair amount of heterogeneity in the different cases.</s><s>So, decisions regarding addition of conventional immunosuppressive agents may affect other co-morbidities related to age, diabetes, pregnancy, interstitial lung disease, malignancy, osteoporosis, etc.</s><s>First line treatment remains corticosteroids, either oral high dose prednisone/prednisolone or pulsed intravenous methylprednisolone.</s><s>However, some experts are recommending intravenous immunoglobulin as a first line, especially in HMGCR antibody associated necrotizing myopathies and in pregnant patients and young patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[54]</ref>.</s><s>If a prolonged course of corticosteroids is anticipated, or the patients' therapy cannot be lowered to less than 10 mg/day, or if they have concomitant medical issues such as interstitial lung disease, osteoporosis, or diabetes, it is recommended to add a second agent.</s><s>Azathioprine is the preferred agent with a dose of 3 mg/kg/actual body weight.</s><s>Methotrexate can also be used at 20-25 mg per week orally or subcutaneously.</s><s>Both azathioprine and methotrexate require monitoring of hepatic function and blood count, and folic acid/ folinic acid supplementation may be required in some cases.</s><s>If there is concern of hepatic dysfunction, mycophenolate mofetil can be used at a dose of 2-3 grams a day in two divided doses.</s><s>Third line drugs would include rituximab.</s><s>There has been considerable experience with rituximab in SRP autoantibody associated myositis and anti-synthetase syndrome, but the use of rituximab is becoming more common in HMGCR-antibody associated myopathy <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">[55]</ref>.</s><s>Other options include cyclosporine, cyclophosphamide and etanercept.</s><s>The emerging consensus is that in some patients, a 3-drug regimen may be needed, with the third drug being intravenous immunoglobulins.</s></p><p><s>Baptiste Hervier (Paris, France) described 'Treatment of IMNM: from steroids to IVIg through Rituximab -The Paris experience.'</s></p><p><s>In the absence of evidence provided by rigorous trials dedicated to the treatment of IMNM, it is difficult to give recommendations.</s><s>However, sharing experiences is still an essential exercise in the aim of building international prospective trials.</s><s>The "Paris experience" is based on a retrospective cohort of 107 IMNM patients: 14 seronegative, 48 anti-SRP, and 45 anti-HMGCR.</s><s>Complete remission was defined as normal strength and normal CK whereas partial remission was an improvement of MMT-8 &gt;110% and/or CK, which however remains &gt;2 times the normal range.</s><s>Three situations are discussed: induction and maintenance therapies as well as treatment of refractory/relapsing patients.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.1.">Induction therapy</head><p><s>-According to Mammen et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[54]</ref>, corticoid-free induction has been proposed only few times.</s><s>Although complete remissions have been obtained after 1 year of follow-up in 2 anti-HMGCR patients, most patients finally required steroids due to slowness of improvement at three months of therapy.</s><s>However, strategies similar to what has been proposed in lupus nephritis <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[56]</ref> be evaluated in the future (IV Steroids + oral immunosuppressive drugs (ISD) and rituximab as a first line therapy).</s></p><p><s>-47% and 67% of anti-HMGCR and anti-SRP patients, respectively, received an immunosuppressant in addition to corticosteroids from the onset of their disease, respectively.</s><s>At the end of the follow-up, these proportions reached 78% and 100%, suggesting that an immunosuppressant should probably be first given more systematically.</s><s>Among the immunosuppressants, methotrexate was most often given (&gt;2/3 of the cases).</s><s>When comparing 23 anti-SRP patients with and without immunosuppressant administration, this strategy seemed more efficient in terms of partial or complete response.</s><s>An exception might be in cases with an associated cancer.</s><s>-The use of IVIg is common in our cohort, with half of the patients using this medication as a first line therapy and 76% and 92% at the end of the follow-up for anti-HMGCR and anti-SRP patients, respectively.</s><s>When comparing 24 anti-SRP patients with or without IVIg, we observed partial and complete remissions more frequently in patients receiving IVIg.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.2.">Maintenance therapy</head><p><s>Our aim is to find the minimal efficient steroid dosage associated with improvement.</s><s>The optimal duration of this treatment remains unknown.</s><s>The place of IVIg is quite unclear: in remission phase, IVIg could be tapered and/or withdrawn progressively.</s><s>The median number of injections is 10, ranging from 2 to 60.</s><s>In the absence of clear predictors of long-term response to treatment, IVIg is discussed case by case.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.3.">Refractory/relapsing patients</head><p><s>This situation should first raise the question of adherence to treatments.</s></p><p><s>In case of relapse, we may either restart an induction therapy or propose rituximab.</s><s>In our centre, 18 IMNM patients received this targeted therapy (mainly as a 3rd line, ranging from 2 to 6), using the 'rheumatology plan': 1 g D1 and D14 followed by a median of 4 infusions (1 g each, ranging from 1 to 10), every 6 months.</s><s>No or only partial response were observed in half of the cases, while remission was obtained in the remaining cases.</s><s>This remission proportion is relatively low and may be related to the delay of Rituximab use.</s><s>Thus, earlier rituximab infusions could perhaps be evaluated in the future.</s></p><p><s>In conclusion, IMNM is a severe and difficult to treat condition.</s><s>Treatments are to date mostly based on steroids, immunosuppressants and IVIg.</s><s>In our experience, rituximab is still a 2nd line therapy.</s><s>Although retrospective, the data from our cohort could suggest modulations of the strategies in the future: limiting the use of oral steroids, by using only IV steroids at onset? starting rituximab infusions earlier: at six months of therapy in case of only partial remission?</s></p><p><s>Marianne de Visser, also on behalf of Jan De Bleecker presented 'Differences in therapeutic approach between IMNM and other subgroups of myositis -the data from Amsterdam and Ghent'.</s><s>Thirty-three patients were included with a median age of 53 years (range 20-83 years).</s><s>All had limb-girdle distribution of muscle weakness, 15 also had dysphagia, 5 dropped head and one had to be artificially ventilated.</s><s>Six patients also had a well-defined connective tissue disorder, mostly systemic sclerosis, 3 had interstitial lung disease.</s><s>Four patients had or had had cancer (bladder, breast, larynx or ovarium cancer).</s><s>In half of the 17 Dutch patients muscle imaging (MRI) was performed, which in occasional patients showed hyperintensity of the skeletal muscle and the fascia.</s></p><p><s>By far the majority of patients had a very high serum creatine kinase (CK) activity up to 20 times the upper limit of normal.</s><s>Four patients had an elevated CK but below 1000 IU/L.</s><s>Myositis-specific antibodies were available from patients: 7 had positive anti-SRP antibodies, 7 anti-HMGCR (4 of those had used statins), 1 anti-MDA-5.</s></p><p><s>In six patients, solo treatment with corticosteroids sufficed, 23 patients needed additional immunosuppressants (azathioprine, methotrexate, mycophenolate mofetil or rituximab) and 11 patients required intravenous immunoglobulins (IVIg) of whom 4 received IVIg as initial and only treatment.</s><s>For comparison, one out of 31 Dutch dermatomyositis patients and none out of 15 with non-specific myositis needed IVIg.</s></p><p><s>In 13 out of 30 patients (from 3 no data were available) outcome was good to excellent, 8 patients had a moderate response, 6 were poor responders and 3 had died (one from peritonitis, one from metastases of a bladder carcinoma, 1 disease-related).</s></p><p><s>Finally, Andrew Mammen discussed his presentation, 'The Baltimore/NIH experience in the treatment of IMNM, from prednisone to IVIg, through rituximab', focussing on the clinical course and treatment of patients with anti-SRP and anti-HMG-CoA reductase myopathies in the Johns Hopkins Cohort.</s><s>An analysis of 37 anti-SRP-positive patients followed up for an average of nearly 3 years revealed that younger age at disease onset was associated with a more severe disease course [1].</s><s>Among the 21 anti-SRP-positive patients followed up for at least 2 years, only 10 (48%) returned to at least near-full strength; among these, 6 of 10 had evidence of persistently active disease with CK levels remaining greater than 500 IU/L despite aggressive immunosuppressive treatment.</s><s>Although responses to different medications could not be rigorously assessed in this retrospective study, out of 21 patients who received rituximab, 13 had improved strength or at least a 10-fold decline in CK levels within 6 months of administration.</s><s>A separate study of 104 anti-HMGCR-positive patients followed up for an average of more than 3 years revealed that younger age of onset predicted a less favourable response to treatment in these patients as well <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">[57]</ref>.</s><s>For example, among patients over the age of 60, 50% returned to normal strength within 4 years of diagnosis.</s><s>In contrast, only 25% of those under the age 50 returned to normal strength within the same time frame.</s><s>In this study too, it was not possible to assess the relative efficacy of different treatment regimens.</s><s>However, it was noted that IVIg is often included in successful treatment regimens and that 3 patients responded well to treatment with IVIg as monotherapy <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[54]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.">Reaching consensus</head><p><s>The group reached consensus that IMNM is not a homogeneous entity.</s><s>Rather, three different IMNM subgroups can currently be defined.</s><s>First, patients with (a) elevated serum CK levels, (b) proximal muscle weakness, and (c) anti-HMGCR autoantibodies can be defined as having "anti-HMGCR myopathy".</s><s>Second, patients with (a) elevated serum CK levels, (b) proximal muscle weakness, and (c) anti-SRP autoantibodies can be defined as having "anti-SRP myopathy".</s><s>While muscle biopsy features, EMG findings, and muscle MRI may be useful in further characterizing patients with anti-HMGCR and anti-SRP myopathies, they are not required for subtyping.</s><s>Third, "antibody negative IMNM" can be defined in patients with (a) elevated CK levels, (b) proximal muscle weakness, (c) no myositis-specific autoantibodies, and (d) a muscle biopsy revealing features as described below.</s><s>Drug/toxin-induced myopathy should be excluded.</s></p><p><s>Consensus was reached on the utility and relevance of measuring MSAs including anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR; however it was pointed out that currently commercial line-blots do not cover all MSAs and that different techniques to identify these autoantibodies may yield different results.</s><s>Certain MAAs may also be present in IMNM, and characterize a heterogeneous subgroup in addition to the ones mentioned above.</s></p><p><s>The group also reached consensus regarding treatment recommendations for patients with anti-HMGCR and anti-SRP myopathies (see Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>).</s><s>In brief, initial treatment for both conditions usually includes intravenous and/or oral steroids, along with the addition of another agent at the same time or within one month (depending on severity and response to treatment).</s><s>For both conditions, methotrexate would be a reasonable option.</s><s>For anti-SRP myopathy, rituximab could either be added instead of or, in severe cases, along with methotrexate; rituximab should always be added within 6 months if other strategies are failing.</s><s>For anti-HMGCR myopathy, IVIg could be added instead of, or in severe cases, along with methotrexate; IVIg should always be added within 6 months if other strategies are not effective.</s><s>Some members of the panel felt that IVIG could be considered as monotherapy in anti-HMGCR myopathy patients with contraindications to or intolerance of high dose steroids.</s><s>In patients requiring intensive care as well as in refractory patients, plasma exchange, cyclophosphamide and/or cyclosporine may be considered.</s><s>After achieving maximum benefit from treatment of either anti-SRP or anti-HMGCR myopathy, steroids should be tapered as tolerated.</s><s>Only after at least two years of well-controlled disease with minimal or no steroids, should other agents be stopped or tapered as tolerated.</s><s>In anti-HMGCR myopathy, however, many patients may require chronic IVIG.</s></p><p><s>Initial treatment of seronegative IMNM is similar to anti-HMGCR myopathy, with respect to severity.</s><s>In case of cancerassociated IMNM, beside the oncology treatment, at least steroids and/or IVIG might be given.</s></p><p><s>Individualized physiotherapy is important for every patient.</s></p><p><s>The group reached consensus on pathological features required to diagnose IMNM and summarized them as follows:</s></p><p><s>-The presence of necrotic fibres with scattered distribution (necrotic fibres may sometimes be rare).</s><s>-Different stages of necrosis and myophagocytosis and regeneration (scattered ongoing necrosis and regeneration).</s></p><p><s>(Ideally, all these aspects should be identified in characteristically affected muscle biopsies, but sometimes may be difficult to ascertain.)</s><s>-Macrophage predominant, paucilymphocytic infiltrates.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional consistent features are:</head><p><s>-Sarcolemmal MHC class I expression may be seen on nonnecrotic/non-regenerating fibres.</s><s>-Sarcolemmal complement deposition (patchy) may be seen.</s></p><p><s>-Endomysial fibrosis and proliferation is often prominent.</s></p><p><s>-Enlarged capillaries may be prominent (pipestem capillaries with complement are rare).</s></p><p><s>Some participants pointed out that occasionally, there may be subtle differences between anti-HMGCR and anti-SRP myopathies: Anti-HMGCR myopathies in contrast to anti SRP-myopathies may harbour perifascicular pathology and nuclear abnormalities (however, clearly different from pathology in anti-synthetase-syndrome-associated myopathy).</s><s>Then pathological criteria of the 119th ENMC workshop <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[27]</ref> have to be revised accordingly.</s></p><p><s>A lively discussion on the term 'IMNM' took place, which even extended to post-congress debates by e-mail.</s><s>Nevertheless, the consensus was to keep this terminology.</s><s>Several aspects should be highlighted:</s></p><p><s>-We do not know at this stage whether the diseases are autoimmune by nature and hence 'immune' should be retained.</s><s>-'Necrotizing' may be misleading and imply that the (whole) muscle is necrotic.</s><s>The term 'with myofibre necrosis' may be more suitable, indicating that single myofibres are undergoing necrosis.</s><s>Pestronk pointed out that the pattern and distribution of necrosis is of outmost importance.</s><s>He also discussed the relevance of an unambiguous definition of a necrotic myofibre.</s><s>-There was no doubt about the immune-inflammatory nature of the process, although the exact pathomechanisms are not yet fully understood.</s><s>-There was also no doubt about the relevance of the autoantibodies directed against SRP and HMGCR for both disease entities.</s><s>Myopathies (France), Deutsche Gesellschaft für Muskelkranke (Germany), Muscular Dystrophy Campaign (UK), Muskelsvindfonden (Denmark), Prinses Beatrix Fonds (The Netherlands), Schweizerische Stiftung für die Erforschung der Muskelkrankheiten (Switzerland),Telethon Foundation (Italy), Spierziekten Nederland (The Netherlands), and Associated member: Finnish Neuromuscular Association (Finland).</s><s>We thank Sanquin (The Netherlands) for their generous support of this workshop.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. Consensus for the initial treatment of IMNM.</s><s>(A) Anti-SRP-myopathy.</s><s>(B) Anti-HMGCR myopathy.</s><s>IV: intravenous, IVIG: intravenous immunoglobulins, d: day, m: month, sc: sub-cutaneous,*: walking difficulties and/or dysphagia, °: Azathioprine or Mycophenolate mofetil in case of Methotrexate intolerance, £: rigorous data from the literature are however missing, §: along with Methotrexate, especially in severe cases.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="11,42.44,72.20,252.07,365.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>. The literature also suffers from not having a uniform definition of what constitutes a</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>94</cell><cell>Workshop report / Neuromuscular Disorders 28 (2018) 87-99</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Workshop report / Neuromuscular Disorders 28 (2018) 87-99</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>The workshop was made possible, thanks to the financial support of the European Neuromuscular Centre (ENMC) and ENMC main sponsors:Association Francaise contre les</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yves</forename><surname>Allenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Olivier Benveniste</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Paris, France) Antony Amato; Boston, USA) Audrey Aussy; Rouen, France; Paris, France</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><forename type="middle">De</forename><surname>Bleecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Marianne de Visser</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Ghent, Belgium; Rouen, France; Amsterdam, The Netherlands</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><surname>Corse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">(</forename><surname>Baltimore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Usa) Norina</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Hans-Hilmar Goebel</editor>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Berlin, Germany; Berlin, Germany; Amsterdam, The Netherlands</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Ingrid de Groot</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Baptiste</forename><surname>Hervier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>Paris, France</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Hilton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">-Jones (</forename><surname>Oxford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Uk) Ingrid</forename><surname>Lundberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Tahseen Mozaffar</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Stockholm, Sweden) Janine Lamb (Manchester, UK) Andrew Mammen (Bethesda, USA; California, USA; Tokyo, Japan</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Ichizo Nishino</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alan</forename><surname>Pestronk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<pubPlace>St. Louis, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spectrum of immune-mediated necrotizing myopathies and their treatments</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Pinal-Fernandez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mammen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="619" to="624" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Ulrike Schara (Essen, Germany) Werner Stenzel</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inflammatory myopathy with anti-signal recognition particle antibodies: case series of 100 patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nishikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kuwana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Nishimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Watanabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nakahara</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Orphanet J Rare Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">61</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical utility of anti-signal recognition particle antibody in the differential diagnosis of myopathies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Satoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Otomo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hirayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Sato</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rheumatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1539" to="1542" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Myopathy associated with antibodies to signal recognition particle: disease progression and neurological outcome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kuwana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tsuburaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Nishino</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="728" to="732" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antibody to signal recognition particle in polymyositis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Targoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1361" to="1370" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical features and prognosis in anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR necrotising myopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Watanabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Uruha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nakahara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hamanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Takayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1038" to="1044" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation of anti-signal recognition particle autoantibody levels with creatine kinase activity in patients with necrotizing myopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Benveniste</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Drouot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Jouen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Charuel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bloch-Queyrat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Behin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1961" to="1971" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High risk of cancer in autoimmune necrotizing myopathies: usefulness of myositis specific antibody</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Allenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Keraen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bouvier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Jooste</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Champtiaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hervier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2131" to="2135" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thigh muscle MRI in immune-mediated necrotising myopathy: extensive oedema, early muscle damage and role of anti-SRP autoantibodies as a marker of severity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Pinal-Fernandez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Casal-Dominguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Carrino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lahouti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Basharat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Albayda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Rheum Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="681" to="687" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Progressive myopathy with up-regulation of MHC-I associated with statin therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Needham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Fabian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Knezevic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Panegyres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zilko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mastaglia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuromuscul Disord</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="194" to="200" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immune-mediated necrotizing myopathy associated with statins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Grable-Esposito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Katzberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Greenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Srinivasan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Amato</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Muscle Nerve</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="190" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel autoantibody recognizing 200-kd and 100-kd proteins is associated with an immune-mediated necrotizing myopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Christopher-Stine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Casciola-Rosen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Corse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mammen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2757" to="2766" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Autoantibodies against 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase in patients with statin-associated autoimmune myopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mammen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Christopher-Stine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rosen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rosen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Doering</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="713" to="721" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antibody levels correlate with creatine kinase levels and strength in anti-3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase-associated autoimmune myopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Werner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Christopher-Stine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ghazarian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Pak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Daya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4087" to="4093" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anti-HMGCR autoantibodies in European patients with autoimmune necrotizing myopathies: inconstant exposure to statin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Allenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Drouot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rigolet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Charuel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Jouen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Romero</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medicine (Baltimore)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical characteristics of anti-3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl coenzyme A reductase antibodies in Chinese patients with idiopathic inflammatory myopathies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Shu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e0141616</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anti-HMGCR antibodies as a biomarker for immune-mediated necrotizing myopathies: a history of statins and experience from a large international multi-center study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Musset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Allenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Benveniste</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Boyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Bossuyt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bentow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Autoimmun Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="983" to="993" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cancer association as a risk factor for anti-HMGCR antibody-positive myopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kadoya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hashimoto Maeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Taira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ikenaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Uchio</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurol Neuroimmunol Neuroinflamm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e290</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical and genetic associations of autoantibodies to 3-hydroxy-3-methyl-glutaryl-coenzyme A reductase in patients with immune-mediated myositis and necrotizing myopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Limaye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bundell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hollingsworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rojana-Udomsart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mastaglia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Blumbergs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Muscle Nerve</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="196" to="203" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HMGCR antibody-associated myopathy as a paraneoplastic manifestation of esophageal carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tsujikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Muro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Nakanishi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Niwa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Koike</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="841" to="843" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Novel classification of idiopathic inflammatory myopathies based on overlap syndrome features and autoantibodies: analysis of 100 French Canadian patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Troyanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Targoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Tremblay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Goulet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Raymond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Senecal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medicine (Baltimore)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="249" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Malignancy in myositis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Zahr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Baer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Rheumatol Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="208" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Myopathy with anti-signal recognition particle antibodies: clinical and histopathological features in Chinese patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuromuscul Disord</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="335" to="341" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Skeletal muscle necrosis associated with carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="1969">1969</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Paraneoplastic necrotizing myopathy: clinical and pathological features</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Levin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mozaffar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Al-Lozi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pestronk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="764" to="767" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human autoantibodies reactive with the signal-recognition particle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Reeves</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Nigam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Blobel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9507" to="9511" />
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">119th ENMC international workshop: trial design in adult idiopathic inflammatory myopathies, with the exception of inclusion body myositis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hoogendijk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Amato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Lecky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Choy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lundberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuromuscul Disord</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="345" />
			<date type="published" when="2003-10-12">10-12 October 2003. 2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Idiopathic inflammatory myopathies and malignancy: a comprehensive review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tiniakou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mammen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Rev Allergy Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrated classification of inflammatory myopathies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Allenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Benveniste</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Goebel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Stenzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuropathol Appl Neurobiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="62" to="81" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Necrotizing myopathy with pipestem capillaries, microvascular deposition of the complement membrane attack complex (MAC), and minimal cellular infiltration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Emslie-Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Engel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="936" to="939" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The prevalence of individual histopathologic features varies according to autoantibody status in muscle biopsies from patients with dermatomyositis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Pinal-Fernandez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Casciola-Rosen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Christopher-Stine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Corse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mammen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1448" to="1454" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The composition of cellular infiltrates in anti-HMG-CoA reductase-associated myopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Christopher-Stine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Paik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Corse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mammen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Muscle Nerve</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="195" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acquired immune and inflammatory myopathies: pathologic classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pestronk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="595" to="604" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Myopathy with antibodies to the signal recognition particle: clinical and pathological features</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Al-Lozi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lopate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pestronk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="420" to="428" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brachio-cervical inflammatory myopathies: clinical, immune, and myopathologic features</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pestronk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lopate</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Al-Lozi</forename><surname>Mt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1687" to="1696" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Skeletal muscle involvement in antisynthetase syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Noguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Uruha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hamanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ohnuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tsugawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JAMA Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="992" to="999" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statin-induced anti-HMGCR-associated myopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Basharat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lahouti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Paik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Albayda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Pinal-Fernandez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bichile</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="234" to="235" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiplex analyses of antibodies against citrullinated peptides in individuals prior to development of rheumatoid arthritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hansson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mathsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Jakobsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Holmdahl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hallmans</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="899" to="910" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new model for an etiology of rheumatoid arthritis: smoking may trigger HLA-DR (shared epitope)-restricted immune reactions to autoantigens modified by citrullination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Klareskog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stolt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lundberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kallberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bengtsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Grunewald</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Smoking and overweight determine the likelihood of developing rheumatoid arthritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>De Hair</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Landewe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Van De Sande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Van Schaardenburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Van Baarsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gerlag</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Rheum Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1654" to="1658" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preclinical rheumatoid arthritis: progress toward prevention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mankia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Emery</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="779" to="788" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Klareskog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Catrina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Paget</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">373</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="659" to="672" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Rheumatoid arthritis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interaction of HLA-DRB1*03 and smoking for the development of anti-Jo-1 antibodies in adult idiopathic inflammatory myopathies: a European-wide case study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chinoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Adimulam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Marriage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>New</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vincze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Zilahi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Rheum Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="961" to="965" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rarity of anti-3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase antibodies in statin users, including those with self-limited musculoskeletal side effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mammen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Pak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Brisson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Coresh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Selvin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Care Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="269" to="272" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathogenic role of anti-SRP and anti-HMGCR antibodies in necrotizing myopathies: myofiber atrophy and impairment of muscle regeneration in necrotizing autoimmune myopathies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Arouche-Delaperche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Allenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Amelin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Preusse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Mouly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Mauhin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="538" to="548" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Myositis-specific autoantibodies: an important tool to support diagnosis of myositis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Betteridge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mchugh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Intern Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">280</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imputing amino acid polymorphisms in human leukocyte antigens</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Jia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Han</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Onengut-Gumuscu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Concannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e64683</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dense genotyping of immune-related loci in idiopathic inflammatory myopathies confirms HLA alleles as the strongest genetic risk factor and suggests different genetic background for major clinical subgroups</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rothwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lundberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Gregersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bowes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Rheum Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1558" to="1566" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathogenesis of autoimmune diseases associated with 8.1 ancestral haplotype: effect of multiple gene interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Candore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Colonna</forename><surname>Romano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Caruso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Autoimmun Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increased frequency of DRB1*11:01 in antihydroxymethylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase-associated autoimmune myopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mammen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gaudet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Brisson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Christopher-Stine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Leffell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Care Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1233" to="1237" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SLCO1B1 variants and statin-induced myopathy-a genomewide study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Group</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Link</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Parish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Armitage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bowman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Heath</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">359</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="789" to="799" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical features and treatment outcomes of necrotizing autoimmune myopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Kassardjian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lennon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Alfugham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mahler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Milone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JAMA Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="996" to="1003" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical course and treatment of anti-HMGCR antibody-associated necrotizing autoimmune myopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ramanathan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Langguth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hardy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Garg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bundell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Rojana-Udomsart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurol Neuroimmunol Neuroinflamm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e96</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intravenous immune globulin for statintriggered autoimmune myopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mammen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tiniakou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">373</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1680" to="1682" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rituximab therapy for myopathy associated with anti-signal recognition particle antibodies: a case series</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Valiyil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Casciola-Rosen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mammen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Christopher-Stine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1328" to="1334" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prospective observational single-centre cohort study to evaluate the effectiveness of treating lupus nephritis with rituximab and mycophenolate mofetil but no oral steroids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Condon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ashby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pepper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Cook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Levy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Griffith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Rheum Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1280" to="1286" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">More severe disease and slower recovery in younger patients with anti-3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase-associated autoimmune myopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tiniakou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Pinal-Fernandez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Albayda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Paik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Werner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rheumatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="787" to="794" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
