<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Articles You May Have Missed</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-01-24">24 January 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Goodnough</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of California San Francisco</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>San Francisco</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Charles</forename><forename type="middle">Edward</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of California San Francisco</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>San Francisco</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Craig</forename><surname>Smollin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of California San Francisco</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>San Francisco</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Repplinger</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of California San Francisco</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>San Francisco</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Articles You May Have Missed</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-01-24">24 January 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">DCBD19328E52843631E870736405B8BA</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s13181-017-0647-z</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 30 August 2017 / Revised: 10 September 2017 / Accepted: 11 September 2017 /</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:36+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Chironex fleckeri (box jellyfish)</term>
					<term>Salicylate</term>
					<term>Hemodialysis</term>
					<term>Carbon monoxide</term>
					<term>Hyperbaric oxygen</term>
					<term>Envenomation</term>
					<term>Varespladib</term>
					<term>Phospholipase A2 inhibitor</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Single-center, open-label, randomized controlled trial comparing hot water immersion at 45 °C with icepack application for treatment of pain due to C. fleckeri stings.</s><s>Patients age ≥ 8 years presenting to the emergency department (ED) within 4 h of suspected C. fleckeri stings and without evidence of severe systemic or ocular effects were enrolled.</s><s>All patients had vinegar applied to their wounds prior to initiation of hot water immersion or icepack therapy.</s><s>The primary outcome measure was pain severity at 30 min post-treatment, as assessed by a visual analog scale.</s><s>The primary outcome was assessed by intention-to-treat analysis.</s><s>Secondary outcomes included ED length of stay (LOS), need for opioid analgesia, crossover to alternative treatment, and delayed urticaria.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Forty-two patients were randomized to icepack (n = 25) or hot water immersion (n = 17) therapy.</s><s>Demographics and severity of envenomation were similar between groups.</s><s>All were discharged from the ED; 95% of patients were pain free at discharge.</s><s>Clinically meaningful pain improvement at 30 min was achieved in 56% of patients treated with ice and in 65% treated with hot water (absolute difference 9%; 95% CI − 22 to 39%; p = 0.75).</s><s>The LOS was 1.6 h for icepack treatment (IQR 1-1.8 h) and 2.1 h for hot water treatment (IQR 1.6-1.8</s><s>h; p = 0.07).</s><s>One patient from the icepack group crossed over to hot water immersion and two patients from each group required intravenous opioids.</s><s>No patients re-presented with recurrent pain.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p><s>The current standard of care for Chironex fleckeri in northern Australia involves application of vinegar, management of life-threatening effects, and icepacks for pain.</s><s>If icepacks fail to adequately relieve pain, oral or parenteral analgesias are recommended.</s><s>Heat immersion therapy has not been previously investigated for management of pain due to C. fleckeri stings.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Question</head><p><s>Is hot water immersion at 45 °C superior to icepack application for reducing pain due to C. fleckeri stings?</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>Hot water immersion at 45 °C was no more effective than icepacks for treating pain due to C. fleckeri stings but is more labor intensive and may increase LOS.</s><s>After application of vinegar to the sting site, icepacks remain the recommended ED treatment for pain due to significant box jellyfish stings.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Critique</head><p><s>The study was underpowered and groups were unequally allocated due to a smaller than expected treatment effect and due to the block size used in the blocked randomization.</s><s>Although the authors concluded that LOS was longer for heat immersion, the difference was not statistically significant (p &gt; 0.05).</s><s>Though heat immersion was not found to be superior to icepack, it was as effective for pain control.</s><s>The treatment effect of hot water immersion may have been limited due to a delay between envenomation and initiation of therapy.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Implication for Toxicologists</head><p><s>The data do not support changing current protocols recommending icepacks for pain reduction of box jellyfish stings.</s><s>Future research should investigate the initiation of hot water immersion in the prehospital setting.</s><s>Hot water immersion as a second-line therapy, prior to initiation of opioid analgesia, should be investigated.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Article Title</head><p><s>McCabe DJ, Lu JJ: The association of hemodialysis and survival in intubated salicylate-poisoned patients.</s><s>American Journal of Emergency Medicine 2017; https://doi.org/10.</s><s>1016/j.ajem.2017.04.017.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p><s>Salicylate (ASA) poisonings are common but varied presentation and severity lead to inconsistent treatment.</s><s>In severe poisoning, mental status changes or fatigue of respiratory compensation may require endotracheal intubation.</s><s>Mechanically ventilated patients risk inadequate respiratory compensation for acidosis and worsening ASA poisoning.</s><s>Hemodialysis (HD) is inconsistently applied to these patients.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Question</head><p><s>Is there an association between survival and HD in ASApoisoned patients who require endotracheal intubation?</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p><s>Retrospective, observational review of ASA poisonings called to the Illinois Poison Center between 1/1/2003 and 12/31/ 2014.</s><s>All intubated patients with serum ASA levels &gt; 50 mg/dl were included.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>A total of 56 cases were identified.</s><s>Overall survival was 73.2%, and 73.5% (11/15) of fatal cases did not receive HD.</s><s>For cases that did not receive HD, an ASA level of &gt; 50 mg/dl had a survival rate of 56% (14/25), compared to 0% (0/9) with levels &gt; 80 mg/dl.</s><s>In patients who received HD, an ASA level &gt; 50 mg/dl had a survival rate of 83.9% (26/31), compared to 83.3% (15/18) of those with a level &gt; 80 mg/dl.</s><s>All 31 cases that received HD were previously intubated.</s><s>Among the 9 cases with an initial ASA level &lt; 50 mg/dl but subsequent level &gt; 50 mg/dl, HD did not affect survival.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>In patients with ASA levels &gt; 50 mg/dl (particularly those with levels &gt; 80 mg/dl) who required endotracheal intubation, HD was associated with increased survival.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Critique</head><p><s>The authors did not include 6 patients who received incomplete HD (due to cardiac arrest) in the HD group, which likely skewed results.</s><s>Retrospective data was limited; it is possible that patients not receiving HD were too unstable for this intervention.</s><s>As a poison center-based study, limited patient information (e.g., pre-existing conditions, co-ingestions, relevant laboratory data [e.g., serum pH]) were not available, therefore introducing numerous confounders.</s><s>Lastly, the small sample size underpowered the ability to detect a survival difference.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Implication for Toxicologists</head><p><s>These data do not support lowering the threshold for HD in intubated patients with ASA toxicity.</s><s>However, the apparent higher mortality among non-dialyzed, intubated patients indicates that further investigation is warranted.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Article Title</head><p><s>Huang CC, Ho CH, Chen YC, Lin HJ, Hsu CC, Wang JJ, Su SB, Guo HR: Hyperbaric oxygen therapy is associated with lower short-and long-term mortality in patients with carbon monoxide poisoning.</s><s>Chest 2017;doi: 10.1016/j.chest.2017.03.049.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p><s>The effect of hyperbaric oxygen therapy (HBOT) on mortality in patients with acute carbon monoxide (CO) poisoning is controversial, and which patients may benefit from HBOT remains unknown.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Question</head><p><s>Does HBOT reduce mortality in patients with CO poisoning?</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p><s>Retrospective cohort study of 25,737 patients diagnosed with CO poisoning in Taiwan between 1999 and 2013.</s><s>The mortality risk of patients who received HBOT was compared with those who did not receive HBOT.</s><s>Multiple stratified subgroup analyses were performed based on age, gender, comorbidities, acute organ failure, suicide attempt, and income.</s><s>Data were obtained via ICD-9 code searching of the Nationwide Poisoning Database, which is a sub-database of the Taiwan National Health Insurance Database.</s><s>Mortality risks of the cohorts were compared with Cox proportional hazard regression adjusted for age, sex, and numerous medical and socioeconomic comorbidities.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Patients who received HBOT had lower mortality risk, with an adjusted hazard ratio (AHR) of 0.74 (95% CI 0.67-0.81).</s><s>Stratified analysis showed this was true for all age groups (particularly age &lt; 20 years; AHR 0.45; 95% CI 0.26-0.80),</s><s>gender, suicide attempts, drug poisoning, and comorbidities (hypertension, hyperlipidemia, liver disease, and mental health disorder).</s><s>HBOT reduced mortality in patients with and without acute respiratory failure (AHR 0.43; 95% CI 0.35-0.53</s><s>and AHR 0.84; 95% CI 0.76-0.93,</s><s>respectively).</s><s>HBOT was associated with reduced mortality at all follow-up points (2 weeks to 4 years).</s><s>A subgroup analysis demonstrated reduced mortality for patients receiving ≥ 2 HBOTs, compared to only one session.</s><s>However, &gt; 5 sessions were associated with intermediate long-term survival benefit, suggesting against a dose response.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>HBOT was associated with reduced mortality risk in patients with CO poisoning, particularly among younger (&lt; 20 years) patients and those with acute respiratory failure.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Critique</head><p><s>There were numerous limitations that hinder clinically useful conclusions.</s><s>It was a retrospective review of limited data involving patients without randomization of treatment.</s><s>No clinically relevant data (CO levels, physical examinations, vital signs, evidence of end-organ dysfunction, co-ingestions) were provided or controlled for.</s><s>Compared with the non-treatment group, patients receiving HBOT were younger (including fewer &gt; 65 years) and had fewer comorbidities.</s><s>Patients with acute respiratory failure were identified based on diagnosis codes and need for intubation/mechanical ventilation; thus, it is unknown if the etiology of respiratory failure was similar between groups.</s><s>The cause of death for these patients was not reported and may not have been sequelae of CO poisoning.</s><s>The treatment protocols for HBOT were not standardized, and all HBOT initiated within 1 month of CO poisoning was included.</s><s>The authors' definition of mortality included patients who left against medical advice or left the national healthcare system.</s><s>Why such patients were counted as dead was not explained.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Implication for Toxicologists</head><p><s>The results of this study should be interpreted with caution due to the possibility of selection bias, which may lead to an overestimation of the treatment effect.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Article Title</head><p><s>Lewin M, Samuel S, Merkel J, Bickler P: Varespladib (LY315920) appears to be a potent, broad-spectrum, inhibitor of snake venom phospholipase A2 and a possible pre-referral treatment for envenomation.</s><s>Toxins 2016;8(248);doi:10.3390/</s><s>toxins8090248.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p><s>Snake envenomation results in 125,000 annual deaths worldwide, with an estimated 75% of these deaths occurring prehospital.</s><s>Broad-spectrum inhibitors of snake venom have the theoretical promise of providing point of care treatment.</s><s>Two such potential drugs are varespladib and its prodrug methyl-varespladib, which are secretory phospholipase A2 (PLA2) inhibitors.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Questions</head><p><s>Do varespladib and methyl-varespladib provide PLA2 inhibition in snake venom across multiple species in vitro; and does intravenous (IV) varespladib provide survival benefit in rodents inoculated with lethal doses of snake venom?</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p><s>Part 1</s></p><p><s>Descriptive study of in vitro chromogenic assays to plot doseresponse curves for varespladib and methyl-varespladib inhibition of PLA2 from bee venom (control) and from venoms of 28 snake species.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Part 2</head><p><s>Prospective proof of concept in vivo survival studies involving envenomated rodents treated with varespladib.</s><s>Model one compared 24-h survival of five mice, pre-treated with varespladib, compared to controls.</s><s>Both groups were injected with lethal doses of elapid venom.</s><s>Model two compared survival of concurrent or post-venom varespladib treatment, versus control, in mice injected with lethal doses of Vipera berus venom.</s><s>Model three compared survival, PLA2 activity, and hemolysis in three groups of rats treated with 4 or 8 mg/kg doses of M.fulvius venom: group 1 was controls, group 2 received varespladib at 30 s after venom injection, and group 3 received varespladib 5 min after injection of venom.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Varespladib and methyl-varespladib had high-potency in vitro inhibition of PLA2 activity in venom from 28 species of snakes.</s><s>Mouse model one showed 100% death in control mice at 63 min, compared with varespladib-treated mice surviving between 8 and 30 h.</s><s>Model two showed survival benefit of varespladib (IV more so than subcutaneous [SQ]), compared to controls, at 24 h for animals receiving varespladib with or after (unknown time interval) V. berus venom injection.</s><s>Model three showed greater survival (100%) at 24 h in rats injected with IV varespladib (5 min after lethal doses of venom administration) compared to controls.</s><s>Model three also showed inhibition of PLA2 activity and hemolysis in varespladib-treated rats compared to controls.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>Varespladib and methyl-varespladib showed highly potent in vitro activity against PLA2 in 28 snake venoms.</s><s>In rodents, pre-treatment, concurrent treatment, and rescue treatment with IVor SQ varespladib provided survival benefit up to 24 h after lethal dose envenomation from three different snake species.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Critique</head><p><s>Extracting human relevance from animal data is difficult, and the benefit appears limited to parenteral administration of varespladib prior to, concurrent with, or within 5 min of envenomation.</s><s>And these effects are limited to ~30 h.</s><s>The authors readily acknowledged these limitations.</s><s>A potential conflict exists due to the primary investigator owning a company (Ophirex® Inc.) which markets snakebite antidotes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Implication for Toxicologists</head><p><s>These data suggest that broad-spectrum inhibitor therapy (in the prehospital setting) for snakebite may be a bridge to antivenom and comprehensive care.</s><s>More extensive in vivo testing, across venom types, and the development of an oral formulation are needed.</s><s>The benefit of these therapies requires optimized timing and dosing of administration for greatest benefit.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sources of Funding None</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Compliance with Ethical Standards</head><p><s>Conflicts of Interest The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</s></p></div>			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">J.Med. Toxicol. (2018) 14:104-107  </note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
