<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Antagonistic Activities of Sox2 and Brachyury Control the Fate Choice of Neuro-Mesodermal Progenitors</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-08-17">August 17, 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Frederic</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Developmental Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63-73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Manuela</forename><surname>Scholze</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Developmental Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63-73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>, ...,</roleName><forename type="first">Lars</forename><surname>Wittler</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Developmental Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63-73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bernd</forename><surname>Timmermann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Sequencing Core Facility</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63-73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Karol</forename><surname>Macura</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Developmental Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63-73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Bernhard</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
							<email>herrmann@molgen.mpg.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Developmental Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63-73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Medical Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´-University Medicine Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Benjamin Franklin, Hindenburgdamm 30</addrLine>
									<postCode>12203</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Lead Contact</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Dennis</forename><surname>Schifferl</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Developmental Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63-73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Smita</forename><surname>Sudheer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Developmental Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63-73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Phillip</forename><surname>Grote</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Developmental Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Ihnestr. 63-73</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Periye. P.O</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Central University of Kerala</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Tejaswini Hills</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>671316</postCode>
									<settlement>Kasaragod District, Kerala</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Cardiovascular Regeneration</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Goethe University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Theodor-Stern-Kai 7</addrLine>
									<postCode>60590</postCode>
									<settlement>Frankfurt am Main</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Antagonistic Activities of Sox2 and Brachyury Control the Fate Choice of Neuro-Mesodermal Progenitors</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2017-08-17">August 17, 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3CE1A51E77537ABCAC5AA5B83FF86E32</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.devcel.2017.07.021</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: January 26, 2017 Revised: June 7, 2017 Accepted: July 24, 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Highlights d Brachyury is essential for the maintenance of neuromesodermal progenitors d Sox2 and Brachyury antagonistically control the neural versus mesodermal fate choice d Brachyury is essential for chromatin remodeling promoting the mesodermal lineage d Tbx6 sustains the mesodermal lineage choice and commits cells to the paraxial fate</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>In Brief</head><p><s>The mammalian trunk arises from neuromesodermal progenitors (NMPs) giving rise to two fundamentally different cell lineages, one forming the spinal cord and the other mesodermal tissues.</s><s>Analyzing the lineages derived from NMPs, Koch et al. find antagonistic roles for Sox2 and Brachyury in the specification of neural and mesodermal fates.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p><s>The trunk of murine embryos forms by continuous recruitment of cells generated in the primitive streak (PS), node-streak border (NSB), and caudal lateral ectoderm (CLE), located at the caudal end of the embryo, into the neural or mesodermal lineage thereby elongating the body anlage <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(Wilson et al., 2009)</ref>.</s><s>The source of cells giving rise to the spinal cord and mesodermal tissues, comprising the vertebral column, skeletal musculature, ventral body wall, kidneys, gonads, limbs, and others, is a resident progenitor cell type with self-renewing capability, the neuro-mesodermal progenitor (NMP) <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Garriock et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Gouti et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Henrique et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">Rodrigo Albors and Storey, 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">Tzouanacou et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Wymeersch et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>NMPs are characterized by co-expression of the stem cell factor and key neural progenitor cell (NPC) regulator Sox2, and of the pan-mesodermal control factor Brachyury (T) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Bergsland et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Boyer et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Herrmann et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Kispert et al., 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">Wilkinson et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Wymeersch et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>Recent grafting experiments carried out in embryonic day 8.5 (E8.5) embryos showed that the fate of NMP descendants correlates with the relative levels of Sox2 or T protein expression and with their position in the PS/CLE <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(Wymeersch et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>This study also confirmed previous reports demonstrating the dependence of mesoderm formation in the trunk on WNT signaling <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Jurberg et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Martin and Kimelman, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Takada et al., 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">Tsakiridis et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>T was the first regulator shown to play an essential role in trunk development: T knockout embryos show a bulky PS, lack posterior mesoderm, arrest axis elongation, and therefore lack the trunk and tail <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Chesley and Dunn, 1936;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Herrmann, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">Yanagisawa et al., 1981)</ref>.</s><s>T acts together with Wnt3a, Fgfr1, and Fgf4/Fgf8 in trunk mesoderm development and is a target of WNT and fibroblast growth factor (FGF) signaling <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Chapman and Papaioannou, 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Ciruna and Rossant, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Naiche et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Yamaguchi et al., 1999)</ref>.</s><s>Studies in zebrafish have shown that T, by controlling Wnt3a and the retinoic acid inhibitor Cyp26a1, establishes the mesodermal progenitor niche <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Martin and Kimelman, 2010)</ref>.</s><s>Work in Xenopus demonstrated the importance of the T ortholog Xbra in neuromesodermal stem cell maintenance and in mesoderm formation <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Gentsch et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Thus, the combined genetic and fate mapping data would suggest that T is involved in the maintenance and mesodermal fate choice of NMPs.</s><s>Recent reports, however, claimed that Tbx6 in mouse and its functional homolog in zebrafish Tbx16 suppress Sox2 and the neural fate, and recruit progenitors into the mesodermal lineage <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Bouldin et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Takemoto et al., 2011)</ref>.</s><s>To resolve these partly conflictive conclusions, we have carried out a broad investigation of the role and interaction of T, Sox2, and Tbx6 in NMPs and in fate decisions of NMP descendants during trunk development, based on genome-wide datasets derived from purified embryonic cell populations.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head><p><s>Transcriptome Analysis Reveals Five Distinct Gene Groups Characterizing NMPs and Their Descending Lineages To characterize NMPs in vivo and to investigate the fate choice of their descendants toward mesodermal or neural differentiation, we established a double reporter (T:mCherry, hereafter T mCh ; Sox2:Venus, hereafter Sox2 Ve ) embryonic stem cell (ESC) line for the generation of embryos via tetraploid complementation <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Eakin and Hadjantonakis, 2006)</ref>.</s><s>To this end, BAC clones containing the T gene or the Sox2 gene were modified by replacing their respective start codons with fluorescent reporter cassettes via recombineering <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Muyrers et al., 1999)</ref>.</s><s>Tetraploid complementation assays showed that the expression of the fluorescent reporters in E8.5 embryos reflects the endogenous pattern of T or Sox2 expression and mark the mesodermal or the neural lineage, respectively (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Wymeersch et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>We detected the T reporter in the caudal epiblast, PS, nascent and early differentiating mesoderm, as well as the node and notochord, while the Sox2 reporter is expressed in the epiblast, primitive streak, neuroectoderm, and brain, as well as in endoderm.</s><s>T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ cells with low reporter activity are prominent in the caudal epiblast, recently identified as the major site where NMPs reside, while high activity of both reporters was detected in the anterior streak near the node.</s><s>We isolated caudal ends (up to pre-somite À2) of Theiler stage 13 (TS13; E8.5) embryos and subjected the single-cell suspension to fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) analysis <ref type="bibr">(Figures 1B and S1A)</ref>.</s><s>The majority ($50%) of labeled cells expressed the T reporter (T mCh+ ), a substantial fraction ($25%) was double positive (T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ ), and a minor fraction ($10%) expressed the Sox2 reporter (Sox2 Ve+ ), representing early mesodermal, putative NMP, and neuroectodermal cells, respectively.</s></p><p><s>We subjected the three cell pools to transcriptome analysis by RNA sequencing (RNA-seq).</s><s>We filtered the data for genes, which are differentially expressed across the three samples.</s><s>Clustering of the RNA-seq data using per gene normalized FPKM values (fragments per kilobase of transcript per million mapped reads) revealed five distinct gene groups (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref> and Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>; see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1B</ref> for examples).</s><s>Group I comprises 154 genes, which are most highly expressed in T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ cells and downregulated in T mCh+ and Sox2 Ve+ cells.</s><s>This group contains genes known to be expressed in nascent mesoderm <ref type="bibr">(Fgf3,</ref><ref type="bibr">Fgf4,</ref><ref type="bibr">Fgf8,</ref><ref type="bibr">Fgf15,</ref><ref type="bibr">Rspo3,</ref><ref type="bibr">Dkk1</ref>; see http://mamep.</s><s>molgen.mpg.de for expression patterns), and genes essential for axial elongation and trunk development (Wnt3a, T, Msgn1).</s><s>Group II genes (250) are already significantly expressed in T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ cells, mostly further upregulated in T mCh+ but downregulated in Sox2 Ve+ cells.</s><s>This group contains early mesodermal control genes <ref type="bibr">(e.g.,</ref><ref type="bibr">Tbx6,</ref><ref type="bibr">Snai1,</ref><ref type="bibr">Lef1,</ref><ref type="bibr">Meox1,</ref><ref type="bibr">Mesp1,</ref><ref type="bibr">Foxc1)</ref>.</s><s>A different set of mesodermal control genes is collected in group III (375 genes).</s><s>Their expression is low in T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ cells and high in T mCh+ cells, suggesting later activation in the mesodermal lineage.</s><s>This group contains several regulators of the lateral and intermediate mesoderm <ref type="bibr">(e.g.,</ref><ref type="bibr">Foxf1,</ref><ref type="bibr">Tbx3,</ref><ref type="bibr">Gata1,</ref><ref type="bibr">Gata3,</ref><ref type="bibr">Gata6,</ref><ref type="bibr">Hand1,</ref><ref type="bibr">Hand2,</ref><ref type="bibr">and Osr1,</ref><ref type="bibr">respectively)</ref>.</s><s>A mirror image of groups II and III is provided by groups IV (261 genes) and V (362 genes) containing regulators of the neural lineage.</s><s>Early neural lineage genes expressed in T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ and mostly further upregulated in Sox2 Ve+ cells (group IV) but downregulated in T mCh+ cells, comprise the control factors Sp8, Nkx1-2, and Pax3.</s><s>Later neural regulators, which are strongly expressed in Sox2 Ve+ cells (group V) but not in T mCh+ cells, comprise Sox1, Sox3, Sox21, Olig3, Irx1, and Zic5.</s><s>Due to its strong upregulation in the neural lineage Sox2 also clustered in this group.</s><s>To verify our clustering approach, we generated box plots representing the distribution of expression values within each group (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1D</ref>).</s><s>The graphs confirm the visual interpretation of gene clustering shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Thus, the expression profiles of control genes, which are essential for axial elongation, mesoderm formation, or neurogenesis during trunk development, confirmed that the neural and mesodermal lineage derive from T/Sox2 double-positive cells.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Single-Cell Transcriptome Analyses Distinguish NMPs from Cells Undergoing the Lineage Choice</head><p><s>The distinct expression profiles of group I genes (downregulated in both lineages) and group II/group IV genes (upregulated in one and downregulated in the other lineage) suggested that T mCh+ / Sox2 Ve+ cells might represent a heterogeneous cell population comprising NMPs and cells undergoing lineage choice.</s><s>In addition, Msgn1 is a mesoderm control gene and not supposed to be expressed in NMPs <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Chalamalasetty et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b68">Yoon and Wold, 2000)</ref>.</s><s>To analyze the cellular composition of the T mCh+ / Sox2 Ve+ cells, we performed single-cell transcriptome analysis.</s><s>T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ cells were isolated from TS13 embryos, FACS sorted, and subjected to single-cell capture on a Fluidigm C1 IFC.</s><s>We obtained quality-controlled transcriptome data for 45 single cells by RNA-seq.</s><s>Principal component analysis identified four distinguishable cell groups representing NMPs, prospective (E) PCA plot of cell types identified using a semi-supervised clustering and cell type imputation approach, displaying levels of marker gene expression.</s><s>(F) PCA plot showing the cell trajectories based on differential gene expression between cell types identified in (E).</s><s>See also Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1</ref> and Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>.</s></p><p><s>neural or mesodermal cells, and cells, which could not be assigned to any group (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1E</ref>).</s><s>All except three cells expressed the NMP markers T, Sox2, Wnt3a, Rspo3, and Fgf8.</s><s>The NMPs were identified by high-level expression of the NMP marker genes, but no expression of Tbx6 or other lineage-specific control genes from groups II-V.</s><s>The prospective mesodermal cells were characterized by the mesoderm markers Tbx6 and Msgn1, and the prospective neural cell group by co-expression of Sox2 (14/15), Pax3 (6/15), and Nkx1-2 (3/15).</s><s>The set of 17 cells, which could not be assigned to any cell group, showed expression of the NMP marker genes plus Tbx6, as well as Pax3 or Nkx1-2 in some of them.</s><s>The latter cells and the prospective mesodermal and neural cells showed overlapping expression of lineage-specific regulators at variable intensity.</s></p><p><s>The cell trajectory, based on differential gene expression between the four cell groups, illustrates the distinct nature but close relationship of NMPs with the undefined cells (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1F and  S1C</ref>).</s><s>Some of the latter are distributed along the trajectory toward the branch point between the prospective mesodermal and neural cells.</s><s>Thus, we conclude that this undefined cell group represents a transient cell state consisting of NMP descendants undergoing lineage choice.</s></p><p><s>Overall, the single-cell analysis demonstrated the heterogeneous nature of T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ cells consisting of NMPs, a distinct transient cell type expressing lineage control genes, and cells already determined for neural or mesodermal differentiation.</s></p><p><s>T and Sox2 Co-occupy Genes of Both Lineages Next we investigated the involvement of T and Sox2 in the control of the NMP and lineage-specific gene expression profiles.</s><s>To address this point we analyzed the genomic binding sites of T protein and Sox2 protein in NMPs by chromatin immunoprecipitation sequencing (ChIP-seq).</s><s>Due to limited embryonic material we used an in vitro differentiation model to obtain sufficient numbers of progenitor cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Gouti et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>We differentiated the same reporter ESC line in vitro that we had utilized for the generation of embryos.</s><s>FACS profiling of single-cell suspensions revealed that at day 3 of differentiation more than 80% of the cells are T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ double positive <ref type="bibr">(Figures S2A and S2B)</ref>.</s><s>Western blotting confirmed that T protein and Sox2 protein are co-expressed in reporter as well as in wild-type ESCs at this stage (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2C</ref>).</s><s>We therefore differentiated wild-type ESCs for 3 days and performed T and Sox2 ChIP-seq experiments on bulk cultures.</s><s>Initial ChIP-peak analyses revealed 15,259 binding sites for T and 17,759 sites for Sox2, mostly (around 85% for T, 72% for Sox2) in genic and intergenic regions, at putative regulatory elements (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>).</s><s>The motif analysis of binding regions revealed a palindromic T-box motif and the canonical Sox2 motif as enriched at their respective peaks (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Kispert and Herrmann, 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Luna-Zurita et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Marson et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">Shen et al., 2011)</ref>.</s><s>We defined potential target genes by associating the ChIP-peaks of either factor with genes located in their immediate neighborhood (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2C</ref>).</s><s>13,674 genes were associated with either factor, about half of them with binding sites of both.</s><s>Among the 1,402 differentially expressed genes identified by cluster analysis of RNA-seq data from FACS-purified embryonic cells (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref>), 193 genes (13.8%) were found to be associated with binding sites for T and 238 (17%) with binding sites for Sox2.</s><s>For 397 genes (28.3%) an association with Sox2 or T peaks was not detected by our method.</s><s>Strikingly, 574 (40.9%) of the differentially expressed genes are associated with binding sites of both factors, many of them located within  <ref type="table">S2</ref>.</s></p><p><s>1 kb (Figures 2C [see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2D</ref> for examples] and S2E; Table <ref type="table">S2</ref>).</s><s>Thus, in total 71.7% of the differentially expressed genes are associated with either T or Sox2 binding.</s><s>Moreover, even among all 10,773 genes expressed in at least one of the three embryonic RNA samples we found 7,277 (67.5%) genes associated with peaks of either factor, 3,348 (46%) of the latter with peaks of both (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>).</s><s>In addition, we found that all five differentially expressed gene groups (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref>) show a similar distribution of binding sites of T (16%-23%), Sox2 (19%-27%), or both factors (51%-63%), and thus no enrichment of either factor in any of the five groups is evident (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2E</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Together, these data show that the vast majority of genes that are differentially expressed in NMPs and their neural or mesodermal descendants are occupied by T or Sox2, and mostly by both transcription factors, irrespective of the cell type or lineage.</s><s>This suggests that T and Sox2 together control the lineage choice of NMP descendants.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>T Activates NMP and Mesodermal Control Genes, in Cooperation with WNT Signaling, and Represses Neural Control Genes Including Sox2</head><p><s>We further investigated the role of T in the mesodermal fate choice of NMP descendants.</s><s>Previous reports had shown that T is essential for mesoderm formation in the trunk and expressed in NMPs <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Gouti et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Herrmann, 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Wymeersch et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>However, whether T controls the lineage choice of NMPs toward mesoderm, and if so by what molecular mechanism this is achieved, has not been addressed.</s><s>We generated embryos from wild-type and T 2J/2J mutant ESCs expressing the T reporter (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S3A</ref>) and isolated T mCh+ cells from stage-matched embryos (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S3B</ref>).</s><s>We dissected the caudal ends of TS13 embryos at the onset of a visible mutant phenotype.</s><s>We sorted T mCh+ cells by FACS and subjected the cell preparations to RNA-seq analysis.</s><s>The data revealed 689 dysregulated genes, 333 downregulated and 356 upregulated, in the T 2J mutant (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A</ref>).</s><s>We found NMP markers, such as Wnt3a, Fgf8, Rspo3, and control genes of all mesodermal sublineages, such as Tbx6 and Msgn1 (paraxial mesoderm), Foxf1 (lateral plate mesoderm), and Osr1 (intermediate mesoderm) among the downregulated genes.</s><s>We found important neural lineage regulators for early and later neural differentiation, including Sox2, Sox3, and Sox1, among the upregulated genes <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Bergsland et al., 2011)</ref>.</s><s>We identified direct T targets by overlapping the sets of dysregulated genes and of genes associated with T peaks (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3B</ref>).</s><s>Among 335 direct T targets, we found the NMP markers Sox2, Wnt3a, Rspo3, and Fgf8, the mesodermal control genes Tbx6, Osr1, and Msgn1, and the neural regulators Nkx1-2, Sox1, and Sox3 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3B</ref>).</s><s>We then divided the direct targets into activated genes and repressed genes and analyzed their relationship with the five groups in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref> (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C</ref>).</s><s>This analysis revealed that most direct target genes activated by T belong to group I comprising NMP genes, and to the mesodermal groups (II and III).</s><s>In contrast, genes directly repressed by T are found in the neural groups (IV and particularly group V), including Sox2, Sox1, and Sox3.</s></p><p><s>In summary, these data show that key NMP, mesodermal, and neural regulators are directly targeted and controlled by T, and demonstrate a dual role of T as activator of NMP and mesodermal control genes, and as repressor of neural control genes.</s></p><p><s>Next we asked how T might distinguish activated and repressed targets.</s><s>A de novo motif analysis within a 400-bp window around T peaks revealed the palindromic T motif as most enriched at activated (248/509 peaks) as well as at repressed target genes (311/444 peaks; data not shown) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>).</s><s>Since co-factor binding might be involved in differential target control, we scrutinized T peak regions for co-occurring motifs.</s><s>Among the most prominent motif co-occurring with the T site at T-activated genes is the LEF/TCF site (at 157/509 peaks) mediating the WNT signaling response in the nucleus.</s><s>To further underpin this finding, we performed a ChIP-seq experiment to identify the genomic binding sites of Ctnnb1 (b-catenin) protein in NMP cells differentiated in vitro.</s><s>We identified 4,411 binding sites, the vast majority (89%) located in intergenic or genic regions (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S3C</ref>).</s><s>The motif analysis of binding regions revealed the consensus Lef1 site at 65% of the peaks.</s><s>To check for co-location of T bound and b-catenin bound sites at T-activated genes, we clustered the latter sites identified in the vicinity of the former (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>).</s><s>We found that b-catenin bound near 254/509 T sites, including 36/93 sites associated with NMP group genes.</s><s>Thus, WNT signaling indeed cooperates with T in controlling a large fraction of T-activated genes.</s></p><p><s>However, when we clustered Sox2 bound sites detected by ChIP-seq in the vicinity of T bound sites in NMPs, we found a substantial co-occurrence of both sites at both the T-repressed and the T-activated targets (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>; example shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S3D</ref>).</s><s>b-Catenin binding also co-occurred together with Sox2 binding near 72/444 T sites associated with T-repressed genes, suggesting cooperation of T and b-catenin also in repressing at least some of the neural lineage genes.</s></p><p><s>The combined data suggest a mutual interaction of both T and Sox2 in NMPs on target control regions of genes promoting the neural or mesodermal lineage.</s><s>Since our data show that T is required for activating mesodermal and for suppressing neural control genes, and Sox2 is a known neural control factor binding to both neural and mesodermal control genes in NMPs, we conclude that T and Sox2 antagonize each other in cells undergoing the lineage choice toward either the neural or mesodermal fate.</s><s>However, the molecular mechanism underlying the antagonism between T and Sox2 remains unclear and needs to be addressed in future work.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>T Controls Chromatin Remodeling Promoting Mesodermal Lineage Development</head><p><s>Since we found several thousand T binding sites in intergenic regions, while only a few hundred genes were affected by T loss of function, we wondered whether T might be involved in shaping the chromatin for mesodermal development.</s><s>Therefore we asked whether T is able to control the chromatin state.</s><s>We introduced the Sox2:Venus reporter into T 2J/2J mutant ESCs expressing the T:mCherry reporter and generated embryos (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S4A</ref>).</s><s>We isolated the T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ , T mCh+ , and Sox2 Ve+ subpopulations from TS12 and TS13 embryos by FACS (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S4B</ref>) and performed ATAC-seq (assay for transposase-accessible chromatin with high-throughput sequencing) analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Buenrostro et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>After verifying comparable fragment length distributions (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S4C</ref>), the analysis was performed using 50-kb bins of normalized ATAC-seq data to investigate global changes in chromatin accessibility (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S4D</ref>).</s><s>We computed log 2 ratios using T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ cell data from TS12 and TS13 wild-type embryos as a reference.</s><s>At both developmental stages, mesodermal (T mCh+ ) and neuroectodermal (Sox2 Ve+ ) cells display distinct global chromatin conformation patterns indicating extensive differential chromatin remodeling between the NMP state and either cell lineage (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4A and S5A</ref>).</s><s>While we observe wider regions of chromatin accessibility changes in Sox2 Ve+ cells, the changes revealed in the T mCh+ population are mostly more local.</s><s>Strikingly, the T mCh+ cell population of T 2J/2J mutants displayed the neuroectodermal (Sox2 Ve+ cell) chromatin signature, suggesting that T is required for generating the distinct chromatin signature of the mesodermal lineage <ref type="bibr">(Figure 4A)</ref>.</s><s>Moreover, T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ cells derived from T 2J/2J mutants also displayed the chromatin signature of the neural lineage, suggesting that in T mutants NMPs and their descendants undergo chromatin remodeling for neural differentiation.</s><s>Calculating global correlations across the whole genome showed a strong correlation of T mCh+ or T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ cells from mutant with Sox2 Ve+ cells from wild-type embryos, both at TS13 (r = 0.8 or r = 0.83, respectively) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B</ref>) and TS12 (r = 0.71) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S5B</ref>).</s><s>These correlations are also apparent upon plotting of the ATAC-seq data for TS13 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4C</ref>) and TS12 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S5C</ref>) across the genomes using Hilbert curves.</s></p><p><s>In summary, the chromatin accessibility data reveal genomewide chromatin remodeling from NMPs to the neural or mesodermal lineage, which display distinct chromatin patterns.</s><s>T is essential for remodeling the chromatin for mesodermal development.</s></p><p><s>Tbx6 Represses Progenitor Genes and Promotes Mesoderm Formation Downstream of T It has been proposed that the lineage decision for mesodermal development is determined by Tbx6-dependent regulation of Sox2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Takemoto et al., 2011)</ref>.</s><s>However, in Tbx6 mutants mesoderm formation is initiated, whereas the paraxial tissue formed in the trunk eventually switches to the neural fate <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Chapman and Papaioannou, 1998)</ref>.</s><s>The latter suggests that Tbx6 is not essential for the fate decision as such, but is sustaining the paraxial fate.</s><s>To investigate the different roles of T and Tbx6 in the lineage choice and in mesoderm development in more detail, we compared the sets of direct target genes of either factor.</s><s>For this purpose we introduced a Tbx6:mCherry reporter BAC into wild-type and Tbx6 À/À ESCs and generated embryos (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6A</ref>).</s><s>We isolated Tbx6 mCh+ cells from caudal ends of dissected TS14 embryos (up to pre-somite À2 in wild-type embryos) by FACS (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6B</ref>) and performed transcriptome analyses.</s><s>Genes dysregulated in either Tbx6 or T mutant embryos were compared (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5A</ref>).</s><s>We found a large overlap of genes commonly regulated by T and Tbx6, in particular mesodermal control genes of the paraxial (Msgn1), intermediate (Osr1), and lateral (Foxf1) sublineages, which are downregulated in either mutant (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6C</ref> for examples).</s><s>However, two gene groups showed opposite behavior.</s><s>Many genes showing highest expression in NMPs (group I, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref>) are downregulated in the T mutant, but upregulated in Tbx6 À/À embryos, indicating positive regulation by T and repression by Tbx6 (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6D</ref> for examples).</s><s>In contrast, many neural transcription factor genes, among them Sox1 and Sox3, are upregulated in  (legend continued on next page)</s></p><p><s>T mutants and thus are repressed by T, but unchanged in Tbx6 À/À embryos (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6E</ref> for examples).</s><s>An important exception is Sox2, which is upregulated in either mutant, indicating repression by both T and Tbx6.</s></p><p><s>To identify Tbx6 binding sites and direct targets (dysregulated genes in Tbx6 À/À embryos associated with Tbx6 sites), we performed ChIP-seq on ESCs differentiated to pre-somitic mesoderm in vitro <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Sudheer et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>In comparison with T, a larger proportion of Tbx6 binding sites was found at promoters rather than in genic or intergenic regions (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5B</ref>), and the exclusive Tbx6 binding motif is not a palindrome but a single T-box motif (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5C</ref>).</s><s>Thus Tbx6 and T differ in their genomic binding site distribution patterns and DNA binding characteristics.</s><s>To compare T and Tbx6 targets in more detail, we first divided Tbx6 targets into activated and repressed genes and also assigned them to the five groups derived in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref> (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5D</ref>).</s><s>Like T (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C</ref>), Tbx6 activates many mesodermal genes (groups II and III).</s><s>Unlike T, however, only four NMP genes (group I) are activated by Tbx6.</s><s>Instead NMP genes including T are mostly repressed by Tbx6.</s><s>Also, several neural lineage genes (group IV and a few from group V) are repressed by Tbx6.</s><s>However, most key neural transcription factors such as Sox1, Sox3, Zic2, Zic5, Irx5, Pax3, or Nkx1-2 are not repressed by Tbx6 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5E</ref> and data not shown).</s><s>Exceptions are Sp8, and Sox2, which acts as both key NMP and neural control gene.</s></p><p><s>The comparison of direct targets of T and Tbx6 revealed 62 genes regulated by both factors (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5F</ref>; see Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S6F-S6H</ref> for examples); 42 are either activated or repressed by both regulators (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5G</ref>).</s><s>Among 26 genes activated by T and Tbx6 are the paraxial control genes Msgn1, Foxc1, Meox1, and Lef1, and components of the Notch pathway.</s><s>Eighteen genes were found to be activated by T but to be repressed by Tbx6 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5G</ref>), and those comprised the key genes acting in NMPs and early mesoderm development (T, Wnt3a, Cyp26a1, and Fgf8, Fgf4) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Gouti et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Henrique et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Martin and Kimelman, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Naiche et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Wymeersch et al., 2016)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Clustering of T, Sox2, and Tbx6 ChIP-seq signals around T peaks associated with direct targets shows a strong overlap of T and Tbx6 bound sites at genes activated by T, while there is less overlap at T-repressed genes (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5H</ref>).</s></p><p><s>The combined data demonstrate that Tbx6 acts downstream of T in the mesodermal lineage.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>Our study addresses the molecular mechanism of NMP maintenance and lineage choice in mouse based on global analyses of purified embryonic cell populations.</s><s>This approach allowed a more refined analysis of NMPs and of the molecular changes occurring from the progenitor state to the neural or mesodermal lineage than previously possible, and thus establishes principal mechanisms controlling early mammalian trunk development.</s></p><p><s>We provide convincing evidence that the fate choice of NMP descendants is determined by antagonistic interaction between T and Sox2.</s><s>Both neural and mesodermal lineage-specific control genes are co-occupied by both transcription factors.</s><s>We show that T activates mesodermal and represses neural lineage genes.</s><s>Conversely, Sox2 is a well-known regulator of neural progenitors <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Bergsland et al., 2011)</ref> and might (directly or at least indirectly) act as repressor of mesodermal genes.</s><s>The latter is based on the finding that mesodermal genes occupied by Sox2 are downregulated in the neural lineage and that in T mutants, cells induced to form mesoderm (T mCh+ cells in T 2J/2J embryos) switch to the neural fate.</s></p><p><s>Using ATAC-seq data we show that the chromatin accessibility signatures change between the NMP state and the neural or mesodermal lineage, indicating that remodeling of the chromatin is involved in the formation of these distinct lineages.</s><s>Strikingly, in the absence of T the chromatin landscape of T mCh+ / Sox2 Ve+ cells changes to the neural pattern.</s><s>Mutant cells induced to form the mesodermal lineage (T mCh+ cells in T 2J/2J embryos) fail to undergo proper chromatin remodeling; they also show the neural chromatin signature.</s><s>These data suggest that T is essential for global chromatin remodeling accompanying or required for mesodermal lineage development.</s></p><p><s>Several reports have provided evidence for an essential requirement of Wnt3a in the maintenance of NMPs and in mesoderm formation <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Garriock et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Jurberg et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Martin and Kimelman, 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Takada et al., 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Wymeersch et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>Studies in zebrafish have revealed an autoregulatory loop between Wnt3a and T establishing the progenitor niche <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Martin and Kimelman, 2010)</ref>.</s><s>Wnt3a, the extracellular WNT activator Rspo3, Fgf8, and other factors of the WNT and FGF pathways are direct targets of T in NMPs (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1E and 3B</ref>), and T is a target of WNT and FGF signaling <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Arnold et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Ciruna and Rossant, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">de Lau et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Martin and Kimelman, 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b65">Yamaguchi et al., 1999)</ref>.</s><s>However, the lack of T, Wnt3a, or FGF signaling disrupts trunk formation <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Chesley and Dunn, 1936;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Ciruna and Rossant, 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">Takada et al., 1994)</ref>.</s><s>Thus T, WNT, and FGF signaling together form a positive feedback (autoregulatory loop) mechanism required for NMP maintenance (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref>).</s></p><p><s>However, each of these factors/pathways is also essential for mesoderm formation, which requires exit from the progenitor state.</s><s>How can these opposite roles co-exist, and how can NMP maintenance work despite the antagonism between Sox2 and T? Sox2 is essential for the ''stemness'' of ESCs <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Boyer et al., 2005)</ref>.</s><s>It is conceivable that Sox2 is required for maintaining the progenitor state of NMPs and for preventing differentiation.</s><s>In NMPs (in CLE) Sox2 is activated by the N1 enhancer, which is controlled by WNT and FGF signaling <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Takemoto et al., 2011)</ref>.</s><s>Thus, NMP maintenance might directly depend on the activation of Sox2 by the T/WNT/FGF autoregulatory loop.</s><s>Both activities might be necessary to generate a balanced state (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref>).</s><s>When T, WNT, or FGF signaling are impaired by loss of function the progenitor state is exited, and cells undergo differentiation and take the neural fate.</s><s>The latter implies that Sox2 is not sufficient to maintain the progenitor state without the T/WNT/FGF autoregulatory loop.</s></p><p><s>During lineage choice, however, Sox2 and T oppose each other.</s><s>In this process, high Wnt3a/Fgf8/Fgf4/Rspo3 levels in the cellular environment activating the WNT/FGF signaling cascades and T promote the mesodermal fate choice of NMP descendants.</s><s>WNT activity is highest close to the node, node/ streak border, and anterior PS <ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(Ukita et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b64">Wymeersch et al., 2016)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The lineage choice apparently is not taking place in the NMPs themselves but in their immediate descendants (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">1E, 1F,  and 6</ref>).</s><s>We infer this because it is hardly conceivable that selfrenewal and differentiation can happen concurrently in the same cell.</s><s>A switch between the two states is required.</s><s>Experimental evidence for a distinct nature of NMPs and of cells commencing differentiation comes from our single-cell transcriptome data on T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ cells.</s><s>We identified a separate group of cells expressing NMP control genes without Tbx6 or other lineage-specific regulators, which therefore most likely represent NMPs.</s><s>The lineage trajectory analysis identified cells of an intermediate state between NMPs and prospective mesodermal or neural cells, which express NMP genes together with Tbx6 and neural lineage genes.</s><s>The latter cells most likely represent NMP descendants undergoing lineage choice.</s><s>The singlecell data therefore confirm that T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ cells comprise self-renewing NMPs and distinct cells undergoing lineage choice followed by differentiation.</s></p><p><s>Our data show that Rspo3 is expressed together with T, Sox2, Wnt3a, and Fgf8 in NMPs and in cells undergoing lineage choice, and thus suggest that Rspo3, an activator of WNT signaling, might be an important NMP regulator.</s><s>Since Rspo3, just as Wnt3a and Fgf4/Fgf8, is secreted and thus can act in an autocrine as well as a paracrine fashion, it might be able to promote self-renewal of NMPs as well as promote the mesodermal fate in NMP descendants undergoing lineage choice <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Chal et al., 2015)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In previous reports, Tbx6 (in mouse) and its functional equivalent in zebrafish, Tbx16, have been suggested to play a major role in mesodermal fate choice and neural suppression <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Bouldin et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">Takemoto et al., 2011)</ref>.</s><s>Tbx6 has been shown to be involved in the repression of Sox2 in the mesodermal lineage via (indirect) inactivation of the Sox2 N1 enhancer <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Takemoto et al., 2011)</ref>.</s><s>However, an earlier report had shown that Tbx6 mutants initiate mesoderm formation but fail to maintain the paraxial mesoderm fate <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Chapman and Papaioannou, 1998)</ref>.</s><s>Thus the combined data suggested the action of another factor involved in mesoderm formation.</s><s>Tbx16 has been shown to lock cells into the mesodermal state and to repress progenitor genes including Sox2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Bouldin et al., 2015)</ref>.</s><s>This conclusion was based  on data derived by ectopic overexpression of Tbx16 in the progenitors.</s><s>This ectopic activity might have forced NMPs to prematurely exit the progenitor state and take the mesodermal fate.</s><s>However, Tbx16 was not sufficient for initiating the epithelialto-mesenchymal transition required for mesoderm formation, suggesting an additional factor(s) involved in the exit from the progenitor state.</s></p><p><s>Thus both reports demand an additional (upstream?)</s><s>factor besides Tbx6 to be involved in mesoderm formation.</s><s>We argue that this factor is T, but also come to different conclusions with respect to the role of Tbx6.</s><s>We show that Tbx6 is a direct target of T, and both T and Tbx6 activate mesoderm control genes.</s><s>We also provide strong arguments that T is the major antagonist of Sox2 during lineage choice and is a repressor of the neural fate.</s><s>This is based on the fact that T represses most key neural transcription factors and that T and Sox2 co-occupy sites at a large fraction of T-repressed genes.</s><s>In contrast, Tbx6 represses only Sox2 and Sp8 among many neural transcription factors, and several neural lineage genes of various functions.</s><s>In addition, Tbx6 represses progenitor genes including T and Sox2.</s><s>Moreover, whereas all trunk mesoderm formation is arrested in T mutants, Tbx6 mutants do produce paraxial tissue and lateral mesoderm <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Chapman and Papaioannou, 1998)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The combined data strongly suggest that Tbx6 is upregulated by T during lineage choice and supports T in sustaining the mesodermal fate choice of NMP descendants, but is not essential for the latter.</s><s>Our single-cell transcriptome data showing Tbx6 expression in cells undergoing lineage choice, but not in NMPs, support this conclusion.</s></p><p><s>Interestingly, the single-cell analysis showed that Msgn1 expression is first detected in prospective mesodermal cells, whereas Tbx6 is already expressed in NMP descendants undergoing lineage choice.</s><s>These data confirm previous reports demonstrating that Msgn1 is a T target and is synergistically controlled by WNT signaling and Tbx6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Chalamalasetty et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b63">Wittler et al., 2007)</ref>.</s><s>Thus, Msgn1 clearly acts downstream of Wnt3a, T, and Tbx6.</s><s>Msgn1 knockout embryos show loss of paraxial mesoderm in the trunk, while lateral mesoderm appears unaffected <ref type="bibr" target="#b68">(Yoon and Wold, 2000)</ref>.</s><s>The combined genetic and single-cell transcriptome data therefore suggest that Msgn1 is required to assign paraxial mesoderm identity to prospective mesoderm cells, which are exposed to sufficiently high WNT activity.</s></p><p><s>T is only transiently active in nascent mesoderm and, at least in the paraxial lineage, not sufficient to maintain mesoderm differentiation.</s><s>The latter requires Tbx6, since in the absence of Tbx6 paraxial tissue eventually switches to the neural fate <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Chapman and Papaioannou, 1998)</ref>.</s><s>This suggests that T and WNT/FGF signaling act as lineage selectors rather than as differentiation factors for the mesodermal lineage.</s><s>The lineage decision, however, needs to be locked in, which is termed commitment, and at least in the paraxial mesoderm this requires Tbx6 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref>).</s><s>However, lateral mesoderm apparently is not affected in the Tbx6 mutant <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Chapman and Papaioannou, 1998)</ref>, and therefore may require other commitment factors.</s><s>To our knowledge these have not been reported.</s></p><p><s>In summary, the combined data suggest that T together with WNT and FGF signaling maintain the NMPs via a positive feedback mechanism, repress the neural fate choice by antagonizing Sox2, and promote the mesodermal fate (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6B</ref>).</s><s>The upregulation of Tbx6 by these factors reinforces the latter, and together they control Msgn1 expression, which is required to confer paraxial mesoderm identity.</s><s>Paraxial mesoderm again needs Tbx6 for sublineage commitment.</s></p><p><s>While this article was under review, a similar work addressing the gene regulatory network controlling neural and mesodermal lineage specification from NMPs was published <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Gouti et al., 2017)</ref>.</s><s>In contrast to our study, this work is mainly based on data derived from NMPs differentiated in vitro, in combination with single-cell transcriptome data.</s><s>In this work the authors establish a core NMP signature comprising T and Sox2, as well as Cdx2, Nkx1-2, and Sp8, and suggest an important role for retinoic acid (RA) signaling in the induction and differentiation of NMPs.</s><s>In their model, opposing activities of WNT and RA signaling, which control mutually inhibiting T and Sox2, respectively, generate a switch resolving either into mesoderm or neural differentiation, depending on the relative level of each inducer.</s><s>They conclude that mesoderm precursor cells produce RA, which promotes Sox2 expression and differentiation of NMPs located adjacent to the NSB to pre-neural tube and NPC identity.</s><s>To our knowledge, currently there is no evidence that RA signaling plays a role in NMP induction, maintenance, or lineage choice in vivo.</s><s>However, RA is a well-known inducer of neural differentiation, and it will be interesting to dissect the exact role of RA in spinal cord formation during trunk development in the embryo.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>STAR+METHODS</head><p><s>Detailed methods are provided in the online version of this paper and include the following: for at least one to several days.</s><s>Embryos were embedded in low-melting point agarose (1.5% in PBS) in a glass capillary of 1.5 mm diameter.</s><s>The sample chamber of the Z.1 (Zeiss) was filled with RIMS and embryos were incubated in the chamber overnight.</s><s>Imaging was performed using a 20x clearing objective.</s><s>The image was processed using the Vision 4D software (Arivis).</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">d KEY RESOURCES</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>In Vitro Differentiation</head><p><s>For NMP differentiation, we used a previously described protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Gouti et al., 2014)</ref> with slight modifications.</s><s>ESCs were removed from feeders by dissociation using 0.05% trypsin and then plated onto tissue culture plates for four short successive periods <ref type="bibr">(25', 20', 15', 10')</ref> to remove feeders.</s><s>We then cultivated the cells for at least two passages in 2i + Lif medium (1:1 DMEM/F12:Neurobasal medium, 1x Pen/Strep, 1x Glutamax, 1x non-essential amino-acids, 1x Na-Pyruvate, 0,11mM b-mercaptoethanol, 1x N2, 1x B-27 without vitamin A, 1mM PD0325901 (Stemgent), 3mM CHIR99021 (Stemgent), 1x Lif).</s><s>Cells were then counted and plated on CellBINDSurface dishes (Corning) precoated with Synthemax II-SC (Corning) at a density of 1x10 4 cells per cm 2 in a medium consisting of 'N2B27' medium <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Gouti et al., 2014)</ref>, supplemented with 10ng/ml bFGF (Peprotech) for 3 days (d1-d3).</s><s>From d2-d3 5mM CHIR99021 (CHI, Calbiochem) was added to the medium.</s><s>Presomitic mesoderm differentiation was carried out as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(Sudheer et al., 2016)</ref> using CHIR99021 and high levels of FGF2 (250ng/ml for 2 days), following the conversion to EpiSCs.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Western Blot</head><p><s>For Western blot analysis, cells were differentiated as described, harvested at the indicated time points and counted.</s><s>After centrifugations, 1x NuPAGE LDS Sample Buffer (Life Technologies) was added to a final concentration of 2000 cells/ml.</s><s>Samples were sonicated for 20 cycles (30s on/30s off) in a Bioruptor Pico (Diagenode) to fragment the DNA.</s><s>For each sample, 5ml were mixed with 5ml of 1x Nupage LDS Sample Buffer containing 25ml/ml b-mercaptoethanol and boiled for 5 minutes at 95 C. The resulting 10ml were loaded onto a 12-well NuPAGE 4-12% Bis-Tris gradient gel (Life Technologies) according to the manufacturer's protocol.</s><s>The wet transfer was performed using transfer buffer (25mM Tris, 192mM glycine, 400ml MeOH) for 1 hour at 4 C and constant 100V onto a PVDF membrane (Bio-Rad).</s><s>The membrane was subsequently blocked for 1h in 5% milk (Sigma Aldrich) in TBS-T (10mM Tris pH8, 150mM NaCl, 0.05% Tween-20) at room temperature.</s><s>The blot was cut into appropriate pieces, washed quickly twice with TBS-T and incubated with the appropriate antibodies in 2% milk overnight at 4 C under agitation.</s><s>The antibodies used were rabbit anti-T (1:2000; <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Kispert et al., 1995)</ref>, goat anti-Sox2 (1:2000; AF2018, R&amp;D), rabbit anti-Tbx6 (1:500; see below) and rabbit anti-H3 (1:2000; ab1791, Abcam).</s><s>The blots were washed 3x10 minutes with TBS-T and incubated with the appropriate antibodies in 2% milk for 1 hour at room temperature.</s><s>The secondary antibodies used were a goat anti-rabbit-HRP (1:5000; #7074, Cell Signaling Technology) and a donkey anti-goat-HRP (1:5000, 705-035-003, Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories).</s><s>The blots were washed 3x10 minutes with TBS-T.</s><s>Detection was performed using the Amersham ECL reagents (GE Healthcare) and scanned using a Fusion SL chemiluminescence system (Vilber).</s><s>The detection of T and Sox2 was performed on the same membrane, by first probing for T and subsequent stripping using Restore PLUS Western Blot Stripping buffer (Thermo Scientific) for 45 minutes at room temperature.</s><s>The Tbx6 blot was performed using a separate gel and membrane.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cell Sorting</head><p><s>For Tbx6::mCherry embryos, the PSM up to the -2 somite was dissected from TS14 embryos.</s><s>For the T::mCherry and T::mCherry/ Sox2::Venus embryos, we used the caudal end containing the node-streak border and surrounding caudal lateral epiblast.</s><s>In order to obtain single cell suspensions from embryo tissue for FACS sorting, 10ml of 5% BSA in PBS was added to the pooled samples and 100ml of ice-cold 0.05% trypsin was added.</s><s>A homogenous suspension was achieved by slow pipetting and the reaction was stopped with the addition of 200ml of 5% BSA in PBS.</s><s>Before cell sorting on a FACS Aria II (Becton Dickinson), the cell suspension was filtered through a 35mm mesh.</s><s>For downstream RNA-seq experiments cells were sorted directly into Eppendorf tubes containing 350ml RLT buffer (Qiagen) and 3.5ml b-mercaptoethanol.</s><s>For ATAC-seq, cells were sorted into FACS-tubes containing 5% BSA in PBS, which had previously been rotating for several hours to pre-coat the tube walls with BSA.</s><s>Sorted cells were centrifuged at 1000rpm and 4 C for 10 minutes, transferred to Eppendorf tubes containing PBS with 0.05% Triton X-100 and centrifuged at 1000rpm and 4 C for 10 minutes.</s><s>The supernatant was removed and cells were directly processed for ATAC-seq.</s><s>For single-cell RNA-seq, T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ cells were sorted from caudal ends of TS13 embryos and collected in Eppendorf tubes containing filtered 5% BSA in PBS at 4 C.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RNA-Seq</head><p><s>For the T/Sox2 subpopulations, total RNA from approximately 2,500 cells was isolated using the RNeasy Micro kit (Qiagen) and genomic DNA was digested on column with the addition of an extra 1ml of RNase-free DNase I (Roche) to ensure complete digestion.</s></p><p><s>The RNA was eluted from the columns using RNase-free water.</s><s>RNA-seq libraries with the RNA equivalent of approximately 1,000 cells were generated using the TotalScript RNA-seq Kit (Epicentre) with random hexamers according to manufacturer's instructions with slight modifications.</s><s>Briefly, all reagents during the cDNA synthesis steps were scaled down in order to achieve a total volume of 39ml, allowing all of the material to be used in the subsequent tagmentation procedure.</s><s>To further improve strand-specificity of the libraries, Actinomycin D was added to the first strand cDNA synthesis reaction at a 5ng/ml final concentration and the libraries were finally amplified using 14 cycles.</s></p><p><s>For T and Tbx6 wild-type vs.</s><s>knock-out comparisons, total RNA was isolated from approximately 20,000 cells using the RNeasy Micro kit (Qiagen) as described above.</s><s>The RNA was quantified using the Qubit RNA HS Assay and the integrity was verified using Bioanalyzer RNA Pico chips.</s><s>Approximately 80-100ng of total RNA was used for the generation of strand-specific RNA-seq libraries using the ScriptSeq v2 (Epicentre) low input libarary preparation kit according to manufacturer's instructions.</s><s>During library preparation, the purification after rRNA-depletion was performed using RNeasy Micro columns and the cDNA was purified using the MinElute PCR Purification Kit (Qiagen).</s><s>The library was finally amplified with 15 PCR cycles.</s></p><p><s>Quantification of all RNA-seq libraries was performed using the Qubit high sensitivity DNA assay (Life Technologies) and the size distribution was verified using the DNA HS Bioanalyzer chips (Agilent).</s><s>Libraries were pooled and paired-end sequenced on a HiSeq 2500 with 2x50bp read lengths.</s></p><p><s>Single-Cell RNA-Seq Sorted cells were pelleted by centrifugation and subsequently resuspended in 10ul PBS.</s><s>The density and viability (&gt;90%) were checked on a Luna cell counter (Logos Biosystems).</s><s>The suspension was adjusted to a cell density of 250 cells/ml, resuspension buffer added (4.5:1 ratio of cells:buffer) and approximately 5ml were loaded onto a 5-10mm C1 IFC (Fluidigm).</s><s>The IFC was processed according to the Fluidigm mRNA-seq protocol.</s><s>A 1:4000 dilution of ERCC spike-ins (Ambion) was added to the lysis buffer.</s><s>Upon visual inspection, 55 capture sites were called to contain cells.</s><s>The amplified cDNA was measured using the Qubit DNA HS assay and a selection of samples was verified on a Bioanalyzer DNA HS chip (Agilent).</s><s>The final libraries for those 55 capture sites were prepared with the Nextera XT (Illumina) kit according to the protocol, pooled and sequenced on a NextSeq (Illumina) sequencer using 2x75bp read lengths.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Antibody Generation Against TBX6</head><p><s>A cDNA fragment of Tbx6, lacking the coding region for amino acid #103 to 347, was cloned in frame downstream of a maltose binding protein (MBP) sequence, controlled by an Arabinose inducible promoter in an E. coli expression vector.</s><s>Recombinant, soluble MBP-TBX6(D103-347) was produced in E. coli DH5a, purified over an amylose column and two rabbits immunized (Pineda Antiko ¨rper-Service, Berlin, Germany).</s><s>Specificity of the anti-TBX6 antibody was verified on western blot and immunohistochemistry.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chromatin Immunoprecipitation (ChIP)</head><p><s>ChIP experiments were carried out essentially as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Koch et al., 2011)</ref>.</s><s>Crosslinking was performed directly on differentiating cells in growth medium with the addition of 1/10th volume of crosslinking solution (11% formaldehyde, 100mM NaCl, 1mM EDTA pH8, 0.5mM EGTA pH8, 50mM Hepes pH7.8) for 10 minutes at room temperature, with the dishes placed on a shaker.</s><s>The crosslinking reaction was quenched with the addition of 1/10th volume of 2.5M glycine and 5 minutes incubation.</s><s>Dishes were placed on ice or in a 4 C cold room and washed twice with cold PBS.</s><s>Cells were scraped and washed off using cold PBS, containing 0.05% Triton X-100 to break the surface tension.</s><s>Cells were pooled in aliquots of $3-5x10 7 in Eppendorf tubes, snap frozen and stored at -80 C until sonication.</s><s>For sonication, complete protease inhibitors without EDTA (Roche) at 1x final concentration was added to all lysis buffers (LB) prior to use.</s><s>Each pellet was resuspended in LB1 (50mM Hepes pH7.5, 140mM NaCl, 1mM EDTA pH8, 10% glycerol, 0.75% NP-40, 0.25% triton X-100) and rotated at 4 C for 20 minutes.</s><s>The cell suspension was homogenized using a douncer with a tight pestle with 3x 15 strokes, with short resting times on ice in between.</s><s>The chromatin was pelleted by centrifugation at 1400g and 4 C for 5 minutes and resuspended in 2.5ml LB2 (200mM NaCl, 1mM EDTA pH8, 0.5mM EGTA pH8, 10mM Tris pH 8) per cell pellet.</s><s>After 10 minutes rotation at 4 C, the centrifugation step was repeated and each pellet was resuspended in 1.5ml LB3 (1mM EDTA pH8, 0.5mM EGTA, 10mM Tris pH8, 100mM NaCl, 0.1% Na-deoxycholate, 0.5% N-lauroylsarcosine), transferred to 15ml Falcon tubes and sonicated using a W-450D Digital Sonifier (Branson) sonicator for 14 cycles of 10s on/50s off in a 4 C coldroom with tubes chilled in ice water.</s><s>After sonication, 150ml of triton X-100 was added per tube, transferred to two 1.5ml Eppendorf tubes and debris was pelleted by centrifugation at 20,000g and 4 C for 10 minutes.</s><s>The solubilized chromatin was then pooled and mixed thoroughly.</s><s>After taking 50ml as an input control, the chromatin was distributed into 1.5ml aliquots, snap frozen and stored at -80 C until use.</s></p><p><s>The input was reverse-crosslinked with the addition of 50ml 2x elution buffer (100mM Tris pH8, 20mM EDTA pH8, 2% SDS) and overnight (13h-15h) incubation at 65 C. The next day, 100ml of TE buffer were added to dilute the SDS of the elution buffer and RNA was digested using RNase A at a 0.2mg/ml final concentration at 37 C for 2 hours.</s><s>Proteins were digested with the addition of 0.2mg/ml proteinase K and incubation at 55 C for 2 hours.</s><s>The DNA was purified with two subsequent phenol:chloroform:isoamylalcohol (25:24:1, pH8) isolations and a subsequent MinElute (Qiagen) purification.</s><s>Purification was performed according to manufacturer's recommendations, except that the columns were washed twice with PE and air dried for at least 10 minutes before elution with EB.</s><s>The input DNA was quantified using a NanoPhotometer (Implen) and the shearing was verified by running 600ng of DNA on a 1.5% agarose gel.</s><s>For sonication to be considered successful and sonicated chromatin to be usable for ChIP, the bulk DNA of the input had to be located between 100bp-500bp.</s></p><p><s>For ChIP, 50ml or 100ul (for b-catenin) of protein-coated Dynal beads (Life Technologies) were washed 3x using 1ml of blocking solution (PBS containing 0.5% BSA), resuspended in 500ml of blocking solution together with approximately 5mg or 10mg (for b-catenin) antibody and rotated overnight at 4 C.</s><s>The antibodies used were a goat polyclonal anti-T (Santa Cruz, sc-17743), a goat polyclonal anti-Sox2 (R&amp;D Systems, AF2018), a rabbit polyclonal anti-b-catenin (Invitrogen, 71-2700) and a rabbit polyclonal anti-Tbx6 (this paper).</s><s>The next day, three further washes using 1ml blocking buffer were performed and the beads were resuspended in 100ml blocking buffer.</s><s>Chromatin equivalent to approximately 25x10 6 or 50x10 6 (for b-catenin) cells was added and rotated overnight at 4 C.</s><s>The following day, washing steps (6, 8 and 9 washes for Tbx6, Sox2 / b-catenin and T respectively) were performed using 1ml RIPA buffer (50mM Hepes pH7.6, 500mM LiCl, 1mM EDTA pH8, 1% NP-40, 0.7% Na-Deoxycholate) containing 1x complete protease inhibitors without EDTA and finally with 1ml of TEN (10mM Tris pH8, 1mM EDTA pH8, 50mM NaCl).</s><s>The immunoprecipates were eluted in two subsequent steps using 100ml of 1x elution buffer (50mM Tris pH8, 10mM EDTA pH8, 1% SDS) and incubation at 65 C while shaking for 10 minutes each.</s><s>The eluates were combined and incubated overnight (13h-15h) at 65 C under agitation.</s><s>The next day, 200ml of TE were added to dilute the SDS of the elution buffer and the ChIPs were purified as described for the input above.</s><s>ChIP DNA was quantified using the Qubit (Life Technologies) DNA HS assay.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ChIP-Seq Library Preparation and Sequencing</head><p><s>The ChIP-seq libraries were generated using the TruSeq ChIP library kit (Illumina) with the following modifications.</s><s>After adapter ligation, 0.95x of AMPure XP beads (Beckman Coulter) were used for a single purification and the DNA was eluted using 15ml of resuspension buffer (RSB, Illumina).</s><s>In the case of Tbx6, 14ml of the eluate were used for PCR pre-amplification in order to convert adapters into double-stranded DNA.</s><s>After the addition of 1ml primer mix (25mM each, Primer 1: 5'-AATGATACGGCGACCACCGA*G-3'; Primer2: 5'-CAAGCAGAAGACGGCATACGA*G-3') and 15ml 2x Kapa HiFi HotStart Ready Mix (Kapa Biosystems), amplification was performed for 45 seconds at 98 C, 5 cycles of [15 seconds at 98 C, 30 seconds at 63 C and 30 seconds at 72 C] and a final 1 minute incubation at 72 C. The PCR products were purified using 0.95x of beads and eluted using 21ml of RSB.</s><s>After transfer of 20ml of eluate, 6ml of 5x loading buffer was added and the ligation products were separated using a 1.5% agarose gel.</s><s>Post-run staining was performed using Sybr Gold (Life Technologies) under agitation for 30 minutes.</s><s>Gel slices according to $250-400bp fragment size were cut out using a Dark Reader (Clare Chemical Research) transilluminator.</s><s>The gel extraction was performed using 5 gel volumes of QG buffer (Qiagen) with the addition of one gel volume of isopropanol, with each flow through added to the column a second time.</s><s>The MinElute (Qiagen) columns were washed once with QG buffer and twice with PE buffer, air-dried for at least 10 minutes and eluted using 21ml of EB buffer.</s><s>Of the eluate, 19ml was used in the final amplification, with the addition of 1ml primer mix and 20ml 2x Kapa HiFi Hotstart premix.</s><s>The same protocol as for the pre-amplification was used, with the exception of using 13 amplification cycles.</s><s>In the case of NMP ChIPs and input, the gel purification step was omitted and libraries were directly amplified for 18 cycles.</s><s>The libraries were quantified using the Qubit DNA HS assay and the library size was validated using DNA HS bioanalyzer chips.</s></p><p><s>Sequencing was performed on either the HiSeq 2000 or NextSeq 500 (Illumina) using 2x 50bp or 2x75bp read lengths respectively.</s><s>In the case of 75bp read lengths, sequences and quality strings were trimmed to 50bp prior to alignment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ATAC-Seq</head><p><s>ATAC-seq was performed essentially as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Buenrostro et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>In total, 1,000-5,000 cells were used per ATAC-seq experiment.</s><s>After spinning down the FACS sorted cells, the pellets were resuspended in 50ml of lysis buffer (10mM Tris pH7.4,</s><s>10mM NaCl, 3mM MgCl2, 0.1% NP-40) and immediately spun down at 500g and 4 C for 10 min.</s><s>The supernatant was discarded and each pellet was resuspended in the transposition reaction mix (25ml 2x TD buffer, 2.5ml Tn5 transposase, 22ml H2O) and incubated at 37 C for 30 minutes.</s><s>After incubation, the reaction was stopped with the addition of PB buffer (Qiagen) and the tagmented DNA was purified using the MinElute kit (Qiagen).</s><s>The DNA was combined with the ATAC index PCR primers and 2x Kapa HiFi Hotstart Readymix and pre-amplified (98 C 30 seconds, 8x [98 C 10 seconds, 63 C 30 seconds, 72 C 1 minute] in a 50ml volume.</s><s>To determine the remaining cycles to avoid potential overamplification, 5ml of the preamplification mix was combined with the primers, 1x Evagreen Sybr green (Jena Biosciences) and 2x Kapa HiFi Hotstart Readymix in a 15ml total volume and run for 30 cycles on a StepOne Plus.</s><s>The remaining 45ml pre-amplified samples were amplified for a further 9 cycles, resulting in a total of 17 cycles.</s><s>The libraries were purified using MiElute column (Qiagen) and the concentration was measured using the DNA HS Qubit assay (Life Technologies).</s><s>Approximately 4ng of each library were run on a DNA HS Bioanalyzer ChIP (Agilent) to verify library size and calculate molarities.</s><s>Samples were pooled and paired-end sequenced on an Illumina NextSeq 500 at 2x75bp read length.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>QUANTIFICATION AND STATISTICAL ANALYSIS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Genome Assembly</head><p><s>All datasets were mapped to the mouse mm10 genome containing chromosomes 1-19, X, Y and M using bowtie version 1.1.2</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Langmead et al., 2009)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RNA-Seq</head><p><s>For RNA-seq, reads were mapped with TopHat2 (version 2.1.0)</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Kim et al., 2013)</ref> using bowtie <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Langmead et al., 2009)</ref>, providing refSeq annotations in gtf format (UCSC) and the options -no-coverage-search -no-mixed -no-discordant -g1 -library-type (''fr-firststrand'' or ''fr-secondstrand'' for libraries generated using the TotalScript and Scriptseq kits respectively).</s><s>Reads that were called to be spliced and containing ambiguous strand information (e.g. containing both XS:A:+ and XS:A:-tags) were removed together with their respective mates.</s></p><p><s>For visualization, wiggle tracks were generated with BEDTools (version 2.23.0) <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(Quinlan and Hall, 2010)</ref>, normalized towards the sample with the lowest read count, converted into bigwig format and loaded into the Integrated Genome Browser <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Freese et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>For calculation of FPKM's, we used Cuffdiff, part of Cufflinks (version 2.2.1) <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Trapnell et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Trapnell et al., 2010)</ref>, with the options -u -no-effective-length-correction -b.</s></p><p><s>For initial clustering of the T/Sox2 subpopulations into 5 expression groups, we first performed two filtering steps.</s><s>Firstly, we selected only those genes displaying FPKM greater 2 in at least one of the samples, and secondly, those genes with a fold-change greater than 2 between any two samples -resulting in a gene list of 1402 genes.</s><s>We then employed a per gene normalization, such that the sum of the squared FPKM values in each row equal 1.0, and k-means clustering into 5 groups using Cluster 3.0 <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(de Hoon et al., 2004)</ref> which was visualized using Java TreeView <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Saldanha, 2004)</ref>.</s><s>The boxplots of selected groups was performed using the same per gene normalized values and BoxPlotR (http://boxplot.tyerslab.com).</s></p><p><s>In order to compare the WT vs. T 2J/2J transcriptomes, we selected only those genes displaying FPKM greater 2 in at least one of the samples and with a fold-change greater than 2. We then sorted the genes from most highly repressed to most highly activated and plotted the FPKM values using Java TreeView <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Saldanha, 2004)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>For clustering of the T KO against the Tbx6 KO transcriptomes, we first selected the most highly expressed genes with an FPKM &gt; 10 in at least one of the samples.</s><s>We then selected highly dysregulated genes with a fold-change of at least 3 in any pair-wise comparison.</s><s>We then exported the log2 fold-changes between WT and KO and performed hierarchical clustering using Cluster 3.0 <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(de Hoon et al., 2004)</ref> and visualized the heatmap using Java TreeView <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Saldanha, 2004)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Single Cell RNA-Seq Those libraries with very few reads (2 samples with less than 1x10 6 reads) were excluded from further processing.</s><s>Reads were mapped to the mm10 genome as previously described for the bulk RNA-seq analysis with TopHat2 (version 2.1.0)</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Kim et al., 2013)</ref> using bowtie <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Langmead et al., 2009)</ref>, providing refSeq annotations in gtf format (UCSC) and the options -no-mixed -no-discordant -g1 -mate-inner-dist 200 -mate-std-dev 100, without initial trimming of reads.</s><s>We then calculated FPKM values using Cuffquant and Cuffnorm from the Cufflinks (version 2.2.1) <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Trapnell et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b55">Trapnell et al., 2010)</ref> package.</s><s>Downstream analysis was carried out using the R Monocle package (version 2.4.0)</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Qiu et al., 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b57">Trapnell et al., 2014)</ref>, by reading in the FPKM, sample and gene attributes tables from the Cufflinks output.</s></p><p><s>The FPKM values were converted into RPC values <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Qiu et al., 2017)</ref> and initial quality control was performed.</s><s>We filtered out genes displaying a low RPC value (&lt; 0.1) in all the cells analyzed.</s><s>In order to identify outliers, we calculated the mean and SD of RPC values across all the cells.</s><s>Those with an RPC count greater than the mean + 1.5xSD (6 cells) or less than the mean -1.5xSD (2 cells) were excluded from the analysis since they are likely to represent doublets or dead cells respectively.</s><s>This resulted in a final amount of 45 cells used for downstream analysis.</s><s>We then re-ran the quantifications using Cuffquant and Cuffnorm without the excluded cells.</s></p><p><s>We loaded the resulting files into Monocle, converted the FPKM values to RPC and repeated the quality control steps for verification.</s><s>As expected, no cells were detected as outliers anymore.</s><s>We then removed genes from the analysis with an RPC value less than 0.1 less than two cells.</s><s>We then created a cell type hierarchy based on marker expression (RPC &gt; 0.1) for neuroectoderm (co-expression of Sox1 and Sox3 or co-expression or Nkx1-2 and Pax3), mesoderm (co-expression of Tbx6 and Msgn1) and putative NMP's (no expression of neuroectoderm and mesoderm markers, but co-expression of T and Sox2).</s><s>Using these settings, we performed the initial cell type imputation, resulting in 4 neuroectodermal cells, 9 mesodermal cells, 3 NMP's and 29 cells of an unknown cell type.</s><s>The dimensions were reduced using the tSNE method and cells were clustered into four groups.</s><s>We then performed differential gene expression analysis between the 4 groups (p-value &lt; 0.05) and selected the 500 most cell type-specific genes from this analysis.</s><s>We checked for the variance explained by each component in the analysis and reduced the data to 2 dimensions accordingly using tSNE.</s><s>We then repeated the cell type imputation using the selected marker genes and clustered the cells into 4 groups.</s><s>This resulted in a final distribution of 15 neuroectodermal, 10 mesodermal, 3 NMP and 17 unclassified cells.</s><s>These final cell groups are shown according to the PCA1 and PCA2 distance, displaying the expression levels of genes.</s><s>In order to calculate a cell trajectory, we performed differential gene expression analysis between these final 4 groups and selected genes with a p-value &lt; 0.04.</s><s>The cell trajectory is shown based on PCA1 and PCA2 with expression values of marker genes or pseudotime.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ChIP-Seq</head><p><s>ChIP-seq data was using bowtie.</s><s>For Tbx6, we estimated the fragment size distribution of the library and determined the maximum length cutoff by performing an initial mapping of a limited number of reads using the options -y -m 1 -S -I 100 -X 500.</s><s>The final mapping was performed using the same options and the determined maximum length parameter (-X).</s><s>For the NMP ChIP's and input, we used -X 1000 for the maximum length parameter.</s></p><p><s>Paired-end reads from the .sam</s><s>file were combined in a bed file by generating the original fragment using a custom perl script, duplicates were removed and .wig</s><s>files were generated using BEDtools.</s><s>For peak detection, 10bp step .gff</s><s>files were generated and loaded into CoCAS <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Benoukraf et al., 2009)</ref>.</s><s>For NMP's, we made use of the input file and removed all reads overlapping with regions displaying enrichment in the input from downstream analysis.</s></p><p><s>In order to assign ChIP-seq peaks to genomic locations and putative target genes, we first overlapped the peaks with -5kb/+2kb of the transcription start sites of refseq annotated genes and assigned them as promoter associated.</s><s>The remaining peaks were overlapped with +2kb from the transcription start site to +5kb after the end of refseq annotated genes and assigned them to be genic.</s><s>The remaining peaks were called to be intergenic binding events.</s><s>In order to associate intergenic peaks to putative targets, we isolated both the closest up-and down-stream gene.</s><s>These peak/gene associations were also used for performing overlaps with WT vs. mutant transcriptomes and to assign peaks to the five groups obtained from the T/Sox2 subpopulations.</s></p><p><s>For de novo motif analysis, were isolated the 10bp bin with the highest binding-value from the peak detection and extracted genomic sequences +/-85bp from their location using bedtools.</s><s>The resulting fasta files were used for motif discovery in Meme</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Transcriptome Analysis of NMPs, Nascent Mesoderm, and Neuroectoderm Isolated from Mouse Embryos Reveals Five Differentially Expressed Gene Groups (A) TS12 (E8.25) embryo expressing T:mCherry and Sox2:Venus reporters imaged by lightsheet microscopy.</s><s>Left: 3D model; an optical section through the node region (right) is indicated by a dashed bar.</s><s>(B) FACS profile of single cells derived from caudal ends of TS13 (E8.5) embryos, used for transcriptome analysis of T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ , T mCh+ /Sox2 VeÀ , and T mChÀ / Sox2 Ve+ subpopulations.</s><s>(C) Heatmap of k-means clustered differentially expressed genes, using per gene normalized FPKM values; groups (I-V) are indicated to the left, with important regulators within each group to the right.</s><s>(D) Box plots representing the distribution of FPKM values within each group, validating the clustering approach.(E)</s><s>PCA plot of cell types identified using a semi-supervised clustering and cell type imputation approach, displaying levels of marker gene expression.</s><s>(F) PCA plot showing the cell trajectories based on differential gene expression between cell types identified in (E).</s><s>See also FigureS1and TableS1.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. T and Sox2 Co-occupy a Large Fraction of NMP and Lineage Control Genes (A) Genomic distribution of T (top) and Sox2 (bottom) peaks from NMPs derived by in vitro differentiation of ESCs.</s><s>(B) Most significant de novo motifs detected at T (top) or Sox2 (bottom) peaks, and corresponding frequency distribution plots ±90 bp around peak summits.</s><s>(C) Venn diagram overlapping genes differentially expressed between NMPs and descending lineages (as in Figure 1C) (orange), and genes associated with T and/or Sox2 peaks.</s><s>(D) Same analysis as in (C), but for all genes expressed across the three cell types irrespective of differential expression.</s><s>(E) Bar plots showing the percentage of 1,005 genes associated with T and/or Sox2 sites, split into the five gene groups.</s><s>See also Figure S2 and TableS2.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,53.86,101.59,237.60,436.42" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. T Activates Mesodermal and Represses Neural Lineage Genes (A) Ranked heatmap showing log 2 fold changes of genes dysregulated in T 2J/2J embryos.</s><s>Examples of important regulators are indicated to the right.</s><s>WT, wild-type.</s><s>(B) Venn diagram showing the overlap between genes associated with T peaks and genes dysregulated in T 2J/2J embryos; examples of direct T targets are shown.</s><s>(C) Bar plots showing the number of T peaks (blue, left axis) and associated genes (red, right axis) in groups I-V separately for activated (top) and repressed (bottom) T targets.</s><s>(D) T binding sites and heatmaps of clustered ChIP-seq signals for T, Sox2, and b-catenin at T peaks associated with genes activated (left) or repressed (right) by T. For T-activated genes, the motif analysis and a heatmap illustrating the overlap between T and b-catenin binding sites at group I genes are shown.</s><s>See also Figure S3.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,89.18,101.59,418.05,441.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. T Controls the Chromatin State of NMPs (A) Genome browser snapshot of chromosome 2 showing ATAC-seq data profiles derived from FACS-purified cells of wild-type (WT) or T 2J/2J embryos relative to stage-matched wild-type NMP cells.</s><s>(B) Genome-wide correlation matrix of all ATAC-seq datasets derived from indicated cell types and genotypes at TS13 relative to their respective stage-matched wild-type NMP dataset.</s><s>(C) Heatmap of the genome-wide Hilbert curve of global ATAC-seq data (relative to the NMP dataset) derived from FACS-purified T mCh+ , T mCh+ /Sox2 Ve+ , or Sox2 Ve+ cells from TS13 wild-type (WT) or mutant (T 2J/2J ) embryos.</s><s>The map of the underlying Hilbert curves shows the location of each chromosome.</s><s>See also Figures S4 and S5.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,96.49,101.59,416.84,308.58" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. Direct Target Comparisons Reveal Different Roles of T and Tbx6 in NMPs, Lineage Choice, and Mesoderm Formation (A) Heatmap showing hierarchical clustering of log 2 fold-change expression values of genes dysregulated in T 2J/2J and Tbx6 À/À embryos compared with wildtype.</s><s>Major clusters and examples of important regulators are shown to the right; arrows indicate up-or downregulation.</s><s>(B) Peak analysis of Tbx6 ChIP-seq data from in vitro differentiated paraxial (pre-somitic) mesoderm shows a similar prevalence of Tbx6 binding sites in promoters, genic, and intergenic regions.(legend</s><s>continued on next page)</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,88.61,101.59,419.23,584.16" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>(C) De novo peak analysis identifies the (single) T-box motif as most significant and enriched below Tbx6 peaks.</s><s>(D) Bar plots showing the distribution of peaks (blue, left axis) and associated genes (red, right axis) among groups I-V separately for target genes activated (left) or repressed (right) by Tbx6.</s><s>(E) Venn diagram showing the overlap between genes associated with T or Tbx6 peaks and genes dysregulated in the respective mutant embryos.</s><s>Important neural lineage regulators are indicated.</s><s>(F) Venn diagram showing overlap between direct T and Tbx6 target genes.</s><s>(G) A 4-way Venn diagram displaying the overlaps between activated and/or repressed direct T and Tbx6 target genes.</s><s>(H) Heatmap representing k-means clustered ChIP-seq signals of T, Sox2, and Tbx6 binding around T peaks associated with genes activated (left) or repressed (right) by T. See also Figure S6.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6.</s><s>Model: Basic Mechanisms of Trunk Development Comprising Progenitor Maintenance, Lineage Choice, and Commitment</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="11,54.77,101.59,235.86,417.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>A) NMPs (green/red circles) are maintained by an autoregulatory loop involving T and WNT/FGF signaling, which also control Sox2, together generating a ''balanced'' state.</s><s>NMP descendants undergo the lineage choice involving antagonistic activities of T/WNT/FGF and Sox2, generating a ''determined'' state; lineage control genes, e.g., Tbx6, are upregulated and reinforce the lineage choice, Pre-neural cells (green) remain in the epiblast (straight green arrow), while nascent mesodermal cells (red) detach and migrate through the primitive streak (PS, indicated by red curved arrows).(B)</s><s>Paraxial (pre-somitic) mesoderm (PSM) formation is a multi-step process controlled by the WNT targets T, Tbx6, and Msgn1.</s><s>Tbx6 supports T in the mesodermal fate choice; their target Msgn1 confers PSM identity and Tbx6 PSM commitment.</s><s>For details see text.</s><s>Black arrows indicate activation; black bars indicate inhibition; Wnt3a, Fgf4/8, Rspo3 (red color) indicate extracellular growth factors; gene symbols are shown in black.</s><s>NMP, neuro-mesodermal progenitor; MPC, mesoderm progenitor cell; LPM, lateral plate mesoderm; NC, notochord; NPC, neural progenitor cell; NT, neural tube.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>STAR+METHODS</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>KEY RESOURCES TABLE</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>REAGENT or RESOURCE</cell><cell>SOURCE</cell><cell></cell><cell>IDENTIFIER</cell></row><row><cell>Antibodies</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Goat polyclonal anti-Brachyury (N-19)</cell><cell>Santa Cruz Biotechnology</cell><cell></cell><cell>sc-17743x; RRID: AB_634980</cell></row><row><cell>Goat polyclonal anti-Sox2</cell><cell>R&amp;D Systems</cell><cell></cell><cell>AF2018; RRID: AB_355110</cell></row><row><cell>Rabbit polyclonal anti-Tbx6</cell><cell>This paper</cell><cell></cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Rabbit polyclonal anti-b-catenin</cell><cell>Invitrogen</cell><cell></cell><cell>71-2700; RRID: AB_2533982</cell></row><row><cell>Rabbit polyclonal anti-Brachyury</cell><cell>Kispert et al., 1995</cell><cell></cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Rabbit polyclonal anti-H3</cell><cell>Abcam</cell><cell></cell><cell>ab1791; RRID: AB_302613</cell></row><row><cell>Chemicals, Peptides, and Recombinant Proteins</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>LIF</cell><cell>Chemicon</cell><cell></cell><cell>ESG1107</cell></row><row><cell>bFGF</cell><cell>Peprotech</cell><cell></cell><cell>100-18B</cell></row><row><cell>CHIR99021</cell><cell>Merck</cell><cell></cell><cell>361571</cell></row><row><cell>PD0325901</cell><cell>Stemgent</cell><cell></cell><cell>04-0006-02</cell></row><row><cell>CHIR99021</cell><cell>Stemgent</cell><cell></cell><cell>04-0004-02</cell></row><row><cell>Critical Commercial Assays</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>TotalScript RNA-Seq Kit</cell><cell>Epicentre</cell><cell></cell><cell>TSRNA12924</cell></row><row><cell>ScriptSeq Complete (Human/Mouse/Rat) low</cell><cell>Epicentre</cell><cell></cell><cell>SCL24H</cell></row><row><cell>input RNA-Seq Kit</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>TruSeq ChIP Library Preparation Kit</cell><cell>Illumina</cell><cell></cell><cell>IP-202-1012</cell></row><row><cell>Nextera DNA Library Preparation Kit</cell><cell>Illumina</cell><cell></cell><cell>FC-121-1030</cell></row><row><cell>C1 Reagent Kit for mRNA Seq</cell><cell>Fluidigm</cell><cell></cell><cell>100-6201</cell></row><row><cell>SMARTer Ultra Low RNA Kit for the Fluidigm</cell><cell>Clontech</cell><cell></cell><cell>634833</cell></row><row><cell>C1 System</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Deposited Data</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Raw and analyzed data</cell><cell>This paper</cell><cell></cell><cell>GEO: GSE93524</cell></row><row><cell>Mouse reference genome GRCm38/mm10</cell><cell>Genome Reference Consortium</cell><cell></cell><cell>http://hgdownload.soe.ucsc.edu/</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>goldenPath/mm10/</cell></row><row><cell>Mouse mm10 RefSeq annotation</cell><cell>NCBI RefSeq project</cell><cell></cell><cell>http://hgdownload.soe.ucsc.edu/</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>goldenPath/mm10/</cell></row><row><cell>Experimental Models: Cell Lines</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mouse JM8A1.N3 (C57BL/6N) ESCs</cell><cell>Pettitt et al., 2009</cell><cell cols="2">Tetraploid Complementation Assay and Embryo N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Mouse C57BL/6J ESCs</cell><cell>This paper</cell><cell>Dissection</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Mouse C57BL/6J T 2j /T 2j ESCs</cell><cell>This paper</cell><cell cols="2">B Microscopy and Clearing N/A</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">B In Vitro Differentiation</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">B Western Blot</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">B Cell Sorting</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>B RNA-Seq</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">B Single-Cell RNA-Seq</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">B Antibody Generation Against TBX6</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">B Chromatin Immunoprecipitation (ChIP)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">B ChIP-Seq Library Preparation and Sequencing</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>B ATAC-Seq</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>d CONTACT FOR REAGENT AND RESOURCE SHARING d EXPERIMENTAL MODEL AND SUBJECT DETAILS d METHOD DETAILS B ESC Derivation B Embryonic Stem Cell Cultivation B Reporter ESC Generation B d QUANTIFICATION AND STATISTICAL ANALYSIS B Genome Assembly B RNA-Seq B Single Cell RNA-Seq B ChIP-Seq B ATAC-Seq B Venn Diagrams d DATA AVAILABILITY</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="514">Developmental Cell 42, 514-526, September 11, 2017 ª 2017 Elsevier Inc. (legend on next page) Developmental Cell 42, 514-526, September 11, 2017 515</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">DevelopmentalCell 42, 514-526, September 11, 2017 517</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">DevelopmentalCell 42, 514-526, September 11, 2017 519</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">DevelopmentalCell 42, 514-526, September 11, 2017 523</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Developmental Cell 42, 514-526.e1-e7, September 11, 2017 e3</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">e4 Developmental Cell 42, 514-526.e1-e7, September 11, 2017</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Developmental Cell 42, 514-526.e1-e7, September 11, 2017 e5</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">e6 Developmental Cell 42, 514-526.e1-e7, September 11, 2017</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Developmental Cell 514-526.e1-e7, September 11, 2017 e7</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>We thank Virginia E. Papaioannou for providing the Tbx6 mutant.</s><s>We thank members of the Department of Developmental Genetics, in particular Anna D. Senft for generating the Tbx6::mCherry reporter BAC, ESC lines, and microscopy of derived embryos; Anna Anurin for support in NMP differentiation and ChIP-seq experiments; Lisette Lange, Sandra Piehl, and Gaby Bl€ ass for support in cell culture and embryo preparation; Judith Fiedler from the Transgenic Unit for generating chimeric embryos; Ludger Hartmann, Mirjam Peetz, Christin Franke, Dijana Micic, and Heike Schlenger from the animal facility for support in generating chimeric embryos and for animal husbandry; Uta Marchfelder for FACS support; Norbert Mages for technical support with single-cell sequencing; and all members of the Sequencing Core Facility.</s><s>This work was supported by an EMBO Long-Term Fellowship to F.K. (co-funded by the European Commission EMBOCOFUND2010, GA-2010-267146) and funded by the Max Planck Society.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION</head><p><s>Supplemental Information includes six figures and two tables and can be found with this article online at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2017.</s><s>07.021.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</head><p><s>B.G.H. conceived and supervised the project; F.K. and B.G.H. designed experiments and evaluated data; F.K., M.S., L.W., D.S., P.G., B.T., and K.M. performed experiments; F.K. performed bioinformatics analyses; S.S. carried out pre-somitic mesoderm differentiation in vitro; B.G.H. and F.K. wrote the manuscript.</s></p><p><s>Mouse C57BL/6J Tbx6</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONTACT FOR REAGENT AND RESOURCE SHARING</head><p><s>Further information and requests for resources and reagents should be directed to and will be fulfilled by the Lead Contact, Bernhard G. Herrmann (herrmann@molgen.mpg.de).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPERIMENTAL MODEL AND SUBJECT DETAILS</head><p><s>All animal procedures were conducted as approved by the local authorities (LAGeSo Berlin) under the license numbers G0368/08 and G0247/13.</s><s>All mouse ESC lines used in this study were male and either from a JM8A1.N3 (C57BL/6N) or C57BL/6J genetic background and were cultured according to standard conditions.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHOD DETAILS ESC Derivation</head><p><s>The T 2J/2J , Tbx6 -/and C57BL/6J WT ESC lines were established from C57BL/6J homozygous blastocysts using N2B27 Medium supplemented with FGF/Erk and Gsk3 pathway inhibitors (2i) and LIF according to Nagy and Nichols <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Pease et al., 2011)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Embryonic Stem Cell Cultivation</head><p><s>All mouse ESC lines used in this study were male and either from a JM8A1.N3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Pettitt et al., 2009)</ref> (C57BL/6N) or C57BL/6J genetic background.</s><s>Cells were maintained on gelatinized plates and mitotically inactive primary mouse embryo fibroblasts with standard ESC medium containing 15% FCS and 1000 U/ml leukemia inhibitory factor (LIF, Chemicon ESG1107).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reporter ESC Generation</head><p><s>To generate the fluorescent reporter constructs, we genome-engineered the mouse BACs RP24-530D23 (T), RP23-249O15 (Sox2) and RP23-421P23 (Tbx6), containing $180 -230kb of the C57BL/6 mouse genome surrounding the respective loci, via Red/ET recombineering <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Muyrers et al., 1999)</ref>.</s><s>Briefly, we replaced the starting codon (ATG) of the genes with a reporter gene containing mCherry (H2B-mCherry in the case of T 2J/2J T::mCherry / Sox2::Venus ESCs) or H2B-Venus, followed by the rabbit b-globin polyadenlylation signal and an FRT-flanked selection cassette (hygromycin or neomycin), driven by the Pgk promotor.</s><s>For random integration, 5mg of the modified BACs were linearized with PI-SceI (NEB) and electroporated into 3x10 6 ESCs.</s><s>Selection was performed using ESC medium containing 250mg/ml neomycin or 150mg/ml hygromycin.</s><s>After selection, single clones were picked, expanded and checked for BAC integration by PCR.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tetraploid Complementation Assay and Embryo Dissection</head><p><s>All animal procedures were conducted as approved by the local authorities (LAGeSo Berlin) under the license numbers G0368/08 and G0247/13.</s><s>The modified ESCs were used to generate embryos via the tetraploid complementation assay <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Eakin and Hadjantonakis, 2006)</ref>.</s><s>For embryo isolation, mice were sacrificed by cervical dislocation and uteri were dissected in PBS.</s><s>Isolated embryos were transferred to M2 medium (Sigma) for staging and microdissection.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Microscopy and Clearing</head><p><s>Embryos containing the T, Sox2 or Tbx6 fluorescent reporters were either imaged using a Leica MZ 16FA or Zeiss Axiozoom microscope with appropriate filters for mCherry and Venus.</s><s>For imaging of cleared T::mCherry/Sox2::Venus reporter positive embryos on a Zeiss Z.1 lightsheet microscope, embryos were fixed for 30 minutes in 4% PFA in PBS at 4 C under rotation.</s><s>All samples were kept in the dark as much as possible.</s><s>After stopping the fixation by washing with PBS, embryos were rinsed 3x  <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Bailey and Elkan, 1994)</ref> and to plot the distribution of discovered motifs.</s><s>For the detection of associated motifs, we enlarged the flanking regions to +/-195 bp and submitted the resulting fasta files to MemeChIP <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Machanick and Bailey, 2011)</ref> using default parameters.</s></p><p><s>Clustering of ChIP-seq data was performed using SeqMiner <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">(Ye et al., 2011)</ref>, using bed files containing the 10bp summits of T peak coordinates associated to either up or downregulated genes.</s><s>The original bed files obtained after mapping, containing the elongated fragments, were loaded and clustered into either 2 or 4 groups when using either only the T/Sox2 or T/Sox2/Tbx6 datasets using the KMeans linear method.</s><s>Clustering was performed at +/-2500bp around the peaks, disabling the read extension setting.</s><s>Due to the lower signal/noise ration of the b-catenin ChIP, we used a percentile threshold of 90% for the T/Sox2/b-catenin cluster.</s><s>For the T/Sox2/Tbx6 cluster, we used a percentile threshold of 75%.</s><s>The remaining settings were the same in both clusters: wiggle step of 10, percentile threshold of 90%, 400 runs and a T threshold of 5.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ATAC-Seq</head><p><s>ATAC-seq, data was reads were trimmed to 50bp length and adapters were detected and removed using fastq-mcf of ea-utils (https://expressionanalysis.github.io/ea-utils,</s><s>version 1.04.738).</s><s>Those reads in which the adapter sequences were not found, were further trimmed by 5bp (to account for potentially undetected but present short adapter sequences) and paired-end mapped using bowtie <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Langmead et al., 2009)</ref>, allowing a maximum fragment size of 2000bp.</s><s>Possible PCR duplicates were removed using Picard (https://broadinstitute.github.io/picard,</s><s>version 1.103).</s><s>Reads for which the adapter sequences were found and removed were independently mapped from their mates to the mm10 genome (containing chromosomes 1-19, X, Y and M) using bowtie and supplying the options -y -m 1 -S..</s><s>After merging the resulting output files, the samtools ( <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Li et al., 2009)</ref>, version 1.2) fixmate function was used to combine corresponding reads into mates.</s><s>Only those properly mapped mates with a maximum fragment length of 2000bp were filtered and potential PCR duplicates were removed using Picard.</s><s>The resulting pairs were combined with the previously mapped reads, resulting in the final alignment file.</s><s>Inspection of the data revealed 35 regions in the genome, mostly repetitive and on average 18kb in size, displaying mapping artefacts <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Buenrostro et al., 2015)</ref>.</s><s>We used samtools to remove reads, together with their corresponding mates, falling into these regions.</s><s>Due to the repetitive nature of the Y chromosome and non-informative mitochondrial genome, reads mapped to either of them were filtered out.</s></p><p><s>For global analysis of the ATAC-seq data, we first generated wig files representing the genomic read density binned into 50kb windows.</s><s>We then calculated the total coverage across each chromosome in every sample and normalized the datasets toward the sample with the lower genome coverage.</s><s>To verify the normalization, the coverage scores across each chromosome was calculated again and the pre-and post-normalized data was visualized using boxplots generated with BoxPlotR (http://boxplot.tyerslab.</s><s>com).</s><s>We then calculated a log2 ratio of each dataset compared to the stage-matched NMP sample, smoothened the data using a sliding window of 3 bins and calculated the Pearson correlation matrices using the ''corrplot'' function in R. Hilbert curves were generated using the ''HilbertCurve'' <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Gu et al., 2016</ref>) R package for chromosomes 1-19 and X.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Venn Diagrams</head><p><s>Proportional 2-way and 3-way Venn diagrams were generated using BioVenn <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Hulsen et al., 2008)</ref>.</s><s>The 4-way Venn diagram for comparing the T and Tbx6 direct targets were generated using Venny version 2.1 (http://bioinfogp.cnb.csic.es/tools/venny/</s><s>index.html).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DATA AVAILABILITY</head><p><s>The accession number for the sequencing data reported in this paper is GEO: GSE93524.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brachyury is a target gene of the Wnt/beta-catenin signaling pathway</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stappert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kispert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kemler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mech. Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="249" to="258" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fitting a mixture model by expectation maximization to discover motifs in biopolymers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bailey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Elkan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Int. Conf. Intell. Syst. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CoCAS: a ChIP-on-chip analysis suite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Benoukraf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cauchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fenouil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jeanniard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jaeger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Thieffry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Imbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Andrau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Spicuglia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="954" to="955" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequentially acting Sox transcription factors in neural lineage development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bergsland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ramskold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zaouter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Klum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sandberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Muhr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2453" to="2464" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wnt signaling and tbx16 form a bistable switch to commit bipotential progenitors to mesoderm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bouldin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Manning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Farr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kimelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2499" to="2507" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Core transcriptional regulatory circuitry in human embryonic stem cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Boyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Johnstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Zucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Guenther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Jenner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="947" to="956" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transposition of native chromatin for fast and sensitive epigenomic profiling of open chromatin, DNA-binding proteins and nucleosome position</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Buenrostro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Giresi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Zaba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Greenleaf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1213" to="1218" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single-cell chromatin accessibility reveals principles of regulatory variation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Buenrostro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Litzenburger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ruff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gonzales</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Snyder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Greenleaf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">523</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="486" to="490" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differentiation of pluripotent stem cells to muscle fiber to model Duchenne muscular dystrophy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oginuma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Al Tanoury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gobert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Sumara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bousson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zidouni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mursch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Moncuquet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="962" to="969" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Wnt3a/beta-catenin target gene Mesogenin1 controls the segmentation clock by activating a Notch signalling program</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Chalamalasetty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Dunty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Biris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ajima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Iacovino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Beisaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Feigenbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Yoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kyba</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">390</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mesogenin 1 is a master regulator of paraxial presomitic mesoderm differentiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Chalamalasetty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Garriock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Dunty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jailwala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Si</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Yamaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4285" to="4297" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three neural tubes in mouse embryos with mutations in the T-box gene Tbx6</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Papaioannou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">391</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="695" to="697" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The inheritance of taillessness (anury) in the house mouse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Chesley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Dunn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="525" to="536" />
			<date type="published" when="1936">1936</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FGF signaling regulates mesoderm cell fate specification and morphogenetic movement at the primitive streak</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ciruna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rossant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Open source clustering software</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>De Hoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Imoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nolan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Miyano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1453" to="1454" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lgr5 homologues associate with Wnt receptors and mediate R-spondin signalling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>De Lau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Barker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Low</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Koo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Teunissen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kujala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Haegebarth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Van De Wetering</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">476</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="297" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Production of chimeras by aggregation of embryonic stem cells with diploid or tetraploid mouse embryos</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Eakin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hadjantonakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1145" to="1153" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrated genome browser: visual analytics platform for genomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Freese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Norris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Loraine</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2089" to="2095" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lineage tracing of neuromesodermal progenitors reveals novel Wnt-dependent roles in trunk progenitor cell maintenance and differentiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Garriock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Chalamalasetty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Canizales</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lewandoski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Yamaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1628" to="1638" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vivo T-box transcription factor profiling reveals joint regulation of embryonic neuromesodermal bipotency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gentsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Owens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Piccinelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Faial</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Trotter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gilchrist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1185" to="1196" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vitro generation of neuromesodermal progenitors reveals distinct roles for wnt signalling in the specification of spinal cord and paraxial mesoderm identity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gouti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tsakiridis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wymeersch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kleinjung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Briscoe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1001937</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A gene regulatory network balances neural and mesoderm specification during vertebrate trunk development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gouti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Delile</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stamataki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wymeersch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kleinjung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Briscoe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="243" to="261" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>e7</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HilbertCurve: an R/Bioconductor package for high-resolution visualization of genomic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Eils</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schlesner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2372" to="2374" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Henrique</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Abranches</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Verrier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Storey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neuromesodermal progenitors and the making of the spinal cord</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2864" to="2875" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expression pattern of the Brachyury gene in wholemount TWis/TWis mutant embryos</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="913" to="917" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloning of the T gene required in mesoderm formation in the mouse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Labeit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Poustka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lehrach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">343</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="617" to="622" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BioVenn-a web application for the comparison and visualization of biological lists using area-proportional Venn diagrams</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hulsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>De Vlieg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alkema</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Genomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">488</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Jurberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Aires</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Novoa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rowland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mallo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compartment-dependent activities of Wnt3a/beta-catenin signaling during vertebrate axial extension</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">394</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="263" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Developmental Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">525</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017-09-11">September 11. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TopHat2: accurate alignment of transcriptomes in the presence of insertions, deletions and gene fusions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pertea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Trapnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Pimentel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Salzberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">R36</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Brachyury gene encodes a novel DNA binding protein</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kispert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3211" to="3220" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The T protein encoded by Brachyury is a tissue-specific transcription factor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kispert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Koschorz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4763" to="4772" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcription initiation platforms and GTF recruitment at tissue-specific enhancers and promoters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fenouil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cauchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Albert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zacarias-Cabeza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Spicuglia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>De La Chapelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Heidemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hintermair</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="956" to="963" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Langmead</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Trapnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Salzberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">R25</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The sequence alignment/map format and SAMtools</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Handsaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wysoker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fennell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ruan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Homer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Marth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Abecasis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Durbin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Genome Project Data Processing Subgroup</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1000">1000. 2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2078" to="2079" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Complex interdependence regulates heterotypic transcription factor distribution and coordinates cardiogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Luna-Zurita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Stirnimann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Glatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kaynak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Baudin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Samee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Small</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mileikovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">164</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="999" to="1014" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">MEME-ChIP: motif analysis of large DNA datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Machanick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Bailey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1696" to="1697" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Connecting microRNA genes to the core transcriptional regulatory circuitry of embryonic stem cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Marson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Frampton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Brambrink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Johnstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Guenther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Johnston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wernig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Newman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">134</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="521" to="533" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brachyury establishes the embryonic mesodermal progenitor niche</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kimelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2778" to="2783" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Canonical Wnt signaling dynamically controls multiple stem cell fate decisions during vertebrate body formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kimelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="232" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid modification of bacterial artificial chromosomes by ET-recombination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Muyrers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Testa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stewart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1555" to="1557" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FGF4 and FGF8 comprise the wavefront activity that controls somitogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Naiche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Holder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lewandoski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4018" to="4023" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">and International society for transgenic technologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pease</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Saunders</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advanced Protocols for Animal Transgenesis: An ISTT Manual</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Agouti C57BL/6N embryonic stem cells for mouse genetic resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pettitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Rairdan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Moran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Prosser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Beier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lloyd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bradley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Skarnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="493" to="495" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single-cell mRNA quantification and differential analysis with Census</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Qiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Packer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Trapnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="315" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Quinlan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="841" to="842" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mapping body-building potential</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rodrigo</forename><surname>Albors</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Storey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e14830</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Java Treeview-extensible visualization of microarray data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Saldanha</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3246" to="3248" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tbx20 regulates a genetic program essential to adult mouse cardiomyocyte function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Aneas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sakabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dirschinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Smemo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Westlund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Dalton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clin. Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4640" to="4654" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Different concentrations of FGF ligands, FGF2 or FGF8 determine distinct states of WNT-induced presomitic mesoderm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sudheer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Anurin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Scholze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Senft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wittler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Macura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Grote</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stem Cells</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1790" to="1800" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wnt-3a regulates somite and tailbud formation in the mouse embryo</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Takada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Stark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Shea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Vassileva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mcmahon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mcmahon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="174" to="189" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tbx6-dependent Sox2 regulation determines neural or mesodermal fate in axial stem cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Takemoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Uchikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yoshida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lovell-Badge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Papaioannou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kondoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">470</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="394" to="398" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcript assembly and quantification by RNA-Seq reveals unannotated transcripts and isoform switching during cell differentiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Trapnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pertea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mortazavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kwan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Baren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Salzberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pachter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="515" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential analysis of gene regulation at transcript resolution with RNA-seq</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Trapnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hendrickson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sauvageau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Goff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pachter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="53" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The dynamics and regulators of cell fate decisions are revealed by pseudotemporal ordering of single cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Trapnell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cacchiarelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Grimsby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pokharel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Morse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lennon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Livak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mikkelsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rinn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="381" to="386" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinct Wnt-driven primitive streak-like populations reflect in vivo lineage precursors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tsakiridis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Blin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Skylaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wymeersch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Osorno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Economou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Karagianni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lowell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1209" to="1221" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Redefining the progression of lineage segregations during mammalian embryogenesis by clonal analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tzouanacou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wegener</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wymeersch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nicolas</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="365" to="376" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wnt signaling maintains the notochord fate for progenitor cells and supports the posterior extension of the notochord</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ukita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hirahara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Oshima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Imuta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Yoshimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Jang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oginuma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Saga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Behringer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kondoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mech. Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="791" to="803" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expression pattern of the mouse T gene and its role in mesoderm formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Wilkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bhatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">343</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="657" to="659" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stem cells, signals and vertebrate body axis extension</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Olivera-Martinez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Storey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">136</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1591" to="1604" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expression of Msgn1 in the presomitic mesoderm is controlled by synergism of WNT signalling and Tbx6</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wittler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Grote</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kispert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Beckers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gossler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Werber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Herrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="784" to="789" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Position-dependent plasticity of distinct progenitor types in the primitive streak</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wymeersch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Blin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Cambray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wilkie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wilson</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e10042</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">T (Brachyury) is a direct target of Wnt3a during paraxial mesoderm specification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Yamaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Takada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yoshikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mcmahon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3185" to="3190" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of the brachyury (T) mutation on morphogenetic movement in the mouse embryo</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Yanagisawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Fujimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Urushihara</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="242" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">seqMINER: an integrated ChIP-seq data interpretation platform</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Krebs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Choukrallah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Keime</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Plewniak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Davidson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tora</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e35</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The bHLH regulator pMesogenin1 is required for maturation and segmentation of paraxial mesoderm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Yoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genes Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3204" to="3214" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
