<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Near-infrared spectroscopy monitoring during immediate transition after birth: time to obtain cerebral tissue oxygenation</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-08-19">19 August 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Evelyn</forename><surname>Ziehenberger</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">•</forename><surname>Berndt Urlesberger</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Corinna</forename><surname>Binder-Heschl</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0003-2405-7143</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bernhard</forename><surname>Schwaberger</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nariae</forename><surname>Baik-Schneditz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Gerhard</forename><surname>Pichler</surname></persName>
							<email>gerhard.pichler@medunigraz.at</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0003-2405-7143</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation>
								<orgName>1 Research Unit of Neonatal Micro-and Macrocirculation, Department of Paediatrics, Medical University of Graz, </orgName>
								<address><addrLine>Graz, Austria Auenbruggerplatz 34, 8036 Graz, Austria</addrLine></address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation>
								<orgName> 2 Division of Neonatology, Department of Paediatrics, Medical University of Graz,</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Near-infrared spectroscopy monitoring during immediate transition after birth: time to obtain cerebral tissue oxygenation</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2017-08-19">19 August 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">8BA77200184B481AF962C0ADBF7226F1</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10877-017-0052-9</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 2 June 2017 / Accepted: 7 August 2017 /</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Near-infrared-spectroscopy</term>
					<term>Neonate</term>
					<term>Immediate transition</term>
					<term>Time periods</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>values displayed.</s><s>Cerebral tissue oxygenation can be measured within 1 min after arriving at the resuscitation table in term and preterm neonates after birth without difference between devices.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p><s>During immediate transition after birth beside the clinical assessment of newly born infants, routine monitoring with pulse oximetry/ECG is recommended.</s><s>These two noninvasive continuous monitoring methods enable measurement of the arterial oxygen saturation (SpO 2 ) and heart rate.</s><s>Unfortunately, these methods do not provide information about potentially compromised oxygen delivery to the brain.</s><s>Therefore, there is a growing interest, to monitor the cerebral regional tissue oxygenation by using near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) during immediate postnatal transition <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s>There are different NIRS devices available, but two most widely used devices in neonates are the NIRO 200 NX (Hamamatsu Photonics, Japan) providing "tissue oxygenation index" (TOI) and the INVOS 5100C (Covidien, USA) providing "regional tissue oxygen saturation" (rSO 2 ).</s><s>With both NIRS devices centiles of cerebral tissue oxygenation immediately after birth starting with first values 2 min after birth have been already published <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>.</s><s>For an efficient medical monitoring during crucial situations, such as the immediate transition period of newborn infants after birth, monitoring devices should be easily applicable and the first values have to be provided quickly.</s><s>Several studies already reported on time periods to obtain first SpO 2 values with pulse oximetry immediately after Abstract Feasibility of cerebral tissue oxygenation measurements immediately after birth has been published starting with first values 2 min after birth.</s><s>Aim of this study was to evaluate, the time periods from birth and from arrival at the resuscitation table to obtain the first cerebral tissue oxygenation values with two different near infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) devices.</s><s>The present study is an analysis of exploratory parameters of two prospective observational studies.</s><s>Cerebral tissue oxygen saturation was measured by the NIRO 200NX measuring "cerebral-tissue-oxygenationindex" (cTOI) or the INVOS5100C measuring "cerebralregional-oxygen-saturation" (crSO 2 ).</s><s>Four time periods (T) were defined: T1 birth to arrival at resuscitation table, T2 arrival to application of NIRS sensor, T3 application to first displayed cTOI or crSO 2 value, and T4 from arrival at resuscitation table to first displayed values.</s><s>Additionally, we compared first displayed values of cTOI and crSO 2 .</s><s>Thirty neonates were included.</s><s>Twenty-four were term and six latepreterm neonates.</s><s>Fifteen neonates measured with NIRO were compared to 15 measured with INVOS.</s><s>T1 was 49 (6-163) s with NIRO versus 59 (15-87) s with INVOS, T2 14 (4-20) s versus 12 (15-18) s, T3 33 (13-138) s versus 17 (6-290) s and T4 46 (20-153) s and 34 (14-300) s.</s><s>The first displayed value tended to be higher for cTOI [54% (18-80)] compared to crSO 2 [35% (15-87)].</s><s>There were no significant differences between devices in time periods and first birth <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s><s>These studies showed that it is possible to obtain first SpO 2 values in less than 1 min <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</s><s>However, there is no study which has investigated the time needed to apply a NIRS sensor and to obtain first TOI/rSO 2 values after the arrival of a newborn infant at the resuscitation table.</s><s>Therefore, the aim of this study was to evaluate, the time periods from birth and from arrival at the resuscitation table to obtain the first cerebral tissue oxygenation values with two different devices.</s><s>We hypothesized that there is no difference between these two devices.</s><s>Excluded: n=31</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Methods</head><p><s>The present study was a post-hoc analysis of exploratory parameters of different prospective observational studies performed at the Medical University of Graz (Regional Committee on Biomedical Research Ethics approval No. 23-403 ex 10/11, 25-342 ex 12/13).</s><s>Parental informed consent was obtained from all individual participants included in the study.</s><s>Videos of term and preterm infants during immediate transition after birth were analysed, which were recorded during these prospective studies.</s><s>The video started when the whole body was delivered.</s><s>Immediately after birth, the neonates were brought by the midwife from the operating theatre and placed on the resuscitation table under an overhead heater.</s><s>The forehead skin area was cleaned and dried.</s></p><p><s>In neonates either the NIRS sensor of the NIRO 200 NX (Hamamatsu Photonics, Japan) was positioned on the right forehead to evaluate the "cerebral tissue oxygenation index" (cTOI) or the neonatal sensor of INVOS 5100C (Covidien, USA) on the left forehead for evaluating the "cerebral regional oxygen saturation" (crSO 2 ).</s><s>Neonates were excluded when the arrival-time or application of sensor was not clearly visible on video recordings or if both NIRS sensors were applied simultaneously in one neonate.</s><s>For analyses neonates, in whom INVOS 5100C was applied, were matched for gestational age (±1 week) to neonates in whom NIRO 200 NX was applied.</s><s>Neonates with application of both sensors simultaneously were excluded.</s><s>The sensor was fixed in both groups on the forehead with a double adhesive plaster and/or gauze bandage by a research team member, who was not involved into resuscitation.</s><s>Four time periods (T) were defined: T1 from birth to arrival of the neonate on the resuscitation table, T2 from arrival to application of the NIRS sensor, T3 from application to first cTOI or crSO 2 values on the monitor, and T4 from arrival to first displayed NIRS values.</s><s>Additionally, we analysed first displayed values of cTOI and crSO 2 .</s></p><p><s>The data are presented as mean ± standard-deviation (±SD) for normally distributed continuous data and median (range) when the distribution was skewed.</s><s>Data of NIRO group and INVOS group were compared using paired t-test and Wilcoxon-rank-sum-test for parametric and non-parametric continuous variables, respectively, and chi square or Fisher's exact test for categorical variables.</s><s>A p value of 0.05 was considered significant.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results</head><p><s>Out of the 150 neonates with NIRS measurements during the first 15 min after birth, 15 neonates measured with INVOS 5100C were included, in whom time of arrival and application of the sensors were clearly visible.</s><s>Main exclusion criterion was hindered visibility caused by attending staff (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>).</s><s>These neonates were matched for gestational age to 15 neonates in whom the NIRO 200 NX sensor was applied (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>).</s><s>Of the 15 neonates from the NIRO 200 NX cohort 7 were male and four were preterm neonates.</s><s>Out of the 15 neonates from the INVOS 5100C cohort six were male and two were preterm neonates.</s><s>The demographic data of the study population is presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>.</s><s>The results of the four defined time periods are presented in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">2</ref>.</s><s>The median time periods from arrival of the neonate on the resuscitation table and first value displayed tended to be shorter with INVOS 5100C compared to NIRO NX 200 without reaching significance.</s><s>Shortest time periods were within 20 s with NIRO 200 as well as with INVOS 5100C.</s><s>First displayed values of cTOI tended to be higher compared to crSO 2 , also without reaching significance.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Discussion</head><p><s>The present study demonstrates that after the arrival of the neonate on the resuscitation table non-invasive cerebral NIRS monitoring is feasible within 1 min.</s><s>The application of the NIRS sensor on the neonate's forehead can be performed quickly independently of which device was used enabling first values even within 20 s after arrival of the neonate at the resuscitation table.</s><s>However, most studies present data of cerebral regional tissue oxygenation starting 2 min after birth <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s>The main reason for this delay, as in the present study, is the delay in arrival of the neonate at the resuscitation table after birth.</s><s>Present time periods of application to first NIRS signal after The signal quality of NIRS can especially be improved with careful application, since it is influenced by vernix, moisture, bruise, oedema or dense growth of hair <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s>In the present study time periods to obtain the first displayed signal was similar with both devices.</s><s>However, the first displayed value tended to be lower with the INVOS 5100C device using the neonatal sensor compared to the NIRO 200 NX.</s><s>This difference is well known especially in the lower regions of tissue oxygenation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> and published centiles with both devices <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusion</head><p><s>Cerebral tissue oxygenation can be measured within 1 min after arriving at the resuscitation table in term and preterm neonates after birth without difference between devices.</s></p><p><s>Therefore, NIRS has the potential to become an additional routinely used tool for cerebral monitoring during immediate transition and resuscitation after birth.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig.</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1 Flow chart of included and excluded term and preterm neonates with NIRS monitoring during immediate transition</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>1</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Flow chart of included and excluded term and preterm neonates with NIRS monitoring during immediate transition</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Eligible preterm and term neonates</cell></row><row><cell>n= 150</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Excluded:</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>both sensor applied</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>n=22</cell></row><row><cell>crSO 2 measured</cell><cell>cTOI measured</cell></row><row><cell>n=47</cell><cell>n=81</cell></row><row><cell>Excluded:</cell><cell>Excluded:</cell></row><row><cell>arrival or</cell><cell>arrival or</cell></row><row><cell>application not</cell><cell>application not</cell></row><row><cell>visible</cell><cell>visible</cell></row><row><cell>crSO 2 n= 32</cell><cell>cTOI n=35</cell></row><row><cell>crSO 2</cell><cell>cTOI</cell></row><row><cell>n=15</cell><cell>n=46</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Matched for</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>gestational age</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(±1 week)</cell></row><row><cell>crSO 2</cell><cell>cTOI</cell></row><row><cell>n=15</cell><cell>n=15</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Demographic data of 30 term and preterm neonates</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">NIRO, n = 15 INVOS, n = 15 p value</cell></row><row><cell>Gestational age (weeks)</cell><cell>38 ± 2</cell><cell>38 ± 3</cell><cell>0.51</cell></row><row><cell>Birth weight (g)</cell><cell>3125 ± 645</cell><cell>3198 ± 434</cell><cell>0.74</cell></row><row><cell>Apgar 1 min</cell><cell>9 (6-10)</cell><cell>9 (5-9)</cell><cell>0.87</cell></row><row><cell>Apgar 5 min</cell><cell>10 (9-10)</cell><cell>10 (8-10)</cell><cell>0.77</cell></row><row><cell>Apgar 5 min</cell><cell>10 (9-10)</cell><cell>10 (9-10)</cell><cell>0.58</cell></row><row><cell>Female (n)</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0.60</cell></row><row><cell>Term neonates &gt;37 (n)</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>0.65</cell></row><row><cell>Gestational age (weeks)</cell><cell>39 ± 1</cell><cell>39 ± 1</cell><cell>0.59</cell></row><row><cell>Birth weight (g)</cell><cell>3212 ± 507</cell><cell>3314 ± 328</cell><cell>0.25</cell></row><row><cell>Late preterm neonates &lt;37</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0.65</cell></row><row><cell>(n)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Gestational age (weeks)</cell><cell>36 ± 1</cell><cell>35 ± 1</cell><cell>0.85</cell></row><row><cell>Birth weight (g)</cell><cell>2888 ± 992</cell><cell>2440 ± 170</cell><cell>0.91</cell></row><row><cell>p value &lt;0.05</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Time periods of the</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>NIRO 200NX and INVOS</cell><cell></cell><cell>NIRO n = 15</cell><cell>INVOS n = 15</cell><cell>p value</cell></row><row><cell>5100C</cell><cell>Birth to arrival at the resuscitation table (s)</cell><cell>49 (6-163)</cell><cell>59 (15-87)</cell><cell>0.96</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Arrival to application of NIRS transducer (s)</cell><cell>14 (4-30)</cell><cell>12 (5-18)</cell><cell>0.30</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Application to first value (s)</cell><cell>33 (13-138)</cell><cell>17 (6-290)</cell><cell>0.58</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Arrival to first displayed value (s)</cell><cell>46 (20-153)</cell><cell>34 (14-300)</cell><cell>0.64</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Initial cTOI or crSO 2 value (%)</cell><cell>54 (18-80)</cell><cell>35 (15-87)</cell><cell>0.19</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>p value &lt;0.05</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Acknowledgements Open access funding provided by Medical University of Graz.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Compliance with ethical standards</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p><s>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethical approval</head><p><s>All procedures performed in the study were in accordance with the ethical standards of the institutional and/or national research committee and with the 1964 Helsinki declaration and its later amendments or comparable ethical standards.</s></p><p><s>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/),</s><s>which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A phase II randomized clinical trial on cerebral near-infrared spectroscopy plus a treatment guideline versus treatment as usual for extremely preterm infants during the first three days of life (SafeBoosC): study protocol for a randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hyttel-Sorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Austin</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Van Bel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Benders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Claris</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Dempsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fumagalli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Greisen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Grevstad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hagmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hellström-Westas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lemmers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lindschou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Naulaers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Van Oeveren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Pellicer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pichler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Roll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Skoog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Winkel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gluud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/1745-6215-14-120</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trials</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How to monitor the brain during immediate neonatal transition and resuscitation? A systematic qualitative review of the literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pichler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Cheung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Aziz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Urlesberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Schmölzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1159/000357162</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neonatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regional oxygen saturation of the brain and peripheral tissue during birth transition of term infants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Urlesberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Grossauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pocivalnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Avian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pichler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jpeds.2010.05.013</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pediatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="740" to="744" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reference ranges for cerebral tissue oxygen saturation index in term neonates during immediate neonatal transition after birth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Baik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Urlesberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schwaberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Schmölzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mileder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Avian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pichler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1159/000438450</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neonatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="283" to="286" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reference ranges for regional cerebral tissue oxygen saturation and fractional oxygen extraction in neonates during immediatetransition after birth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pichler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Binder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Avian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Beckenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Schmölzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Urlesberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jpeds.2013.07.007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pediatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">163</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1558" to="1563" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determining the best method of Nellcor pulse oximeter sensor application in neonates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Saraswat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Simionato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Thio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cof</forename><surname>Kamlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Owen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Schmölzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Davis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1651-2227.2011.02571</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Paediatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="484" to="487" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Time to achieve stable pulse oximetry values in VLBW infants in the delivery room</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gandhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Rich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Finer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.resuscitation.2012.12.007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Resuscitation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">84</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">970</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pulse oximeter sensor application during neonatal resuscitation: a randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Louis D 1</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Sundaram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1542/peds.2013-2175</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="476" to="482" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Monitoring oxygen Saturation and heart rate in the early neonatal period</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Morley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.siny.2010.03.004</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semin Fetal Neonatal Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="203" to="207" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of four near-infrared spectroscopy devices shows that they are only suitable for monitoring cerebral oxygenation trends in preterm infants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Minnich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hofstätter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Weisser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hattinger-Jürgenssen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wald</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/apa.12698</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Paediatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="934" to="938" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calibration of a prototype NIRS oximeter against two commercial devices on a blood-lipid phantom 2013</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hyttel-Sorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kleiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Greisen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1364/BOE.4.001662</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biomed Optics Express</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
