<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Use of a Patient-Activated Event Recording System in Patients with Tachycardic Palpitations: How Long to Follow Up?</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Philipp</forename><surname>Attanasio</surname></persName>
							<email>philipp.attanasio@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitaetsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Klinikum</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitaetsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Klinikum</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Huemer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitaetsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Klinikum</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Lena</forename><surname>Loehr</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitaetsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Klinikum</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Abdul</forename><forename type="middle">Shokor</forename><surname>Parwani</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitaetsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Klinikum</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Leif-Hendrik</forename><surname>Boldt</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitaetsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Klinikum</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Wilhelm</forename><surname>Haverkamp</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitaetsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Klinikum</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Alexander</forename><surname>Wutzler</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitaetsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Klinikum</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Use of a Patient-Activated Event Recording System in Patients with Tachycardic Palpitations: How Long to Follow Up?</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5FC16EE7B563449C9D1CF0576B0D0397</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/anec.12301</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Introduction: Palpitations are a common symptom causing patients to consult a cardiologist, yet diagnosing a potential cardiac origin can be difficult.</s><s>In patients with a nondiagnostic Holter-ECG, external loop-recorders are an additional tool to diagnose the clinical arrhythmia in these patients.</s><s>The aim of our study was to evaluate the additional value of an external, patient-activated loop recorder and to determine the optimal time of follow up needed to achieve a symptom-rhythm correlation with the device.</s></p><p><s>Methods and Results: A total of 1404 patients presented to our outpatient clinic between November 2011 and November 2014 for first time evaluation of symptomatic arrhythmias.</s><s>Of a total of 91 patients were included (age 43.6±18.1;</s><s>69.2% female) in the study.</s><s>All patients presented with tachycardic palpitations and a 48-hour Holter-ECG that did not detect relevant arrhythmias.</s><s>All patients were given a "leadless" patient-activated event-recording system and regular follow-up visits were scheduled after 3, 6, and 12 months.</s><s>Within a maximum follow-up time of 1 year, 72 patients (79.1%) recorded at least one ECG with the device.</s><s>Of the recorded ECGs, 51% were recorded within the first week after the device was handed out.</s><s>This figure rises to 80% and 93% after 1 and 2 months.</s><s>The last recording was after 174 days.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion:</head><p><s>For patients with tachycardic palpitations, the external "leadess" event recorders are effective in achieving a symptom-rhythm correlation.</s><s>A follow up of 2 months will suffice to establish a diagnosis in a large majority of this patient group.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Palpitations are a common symptom causing patients to seek help of a cardiologist.</s><s>To determine whether the cause is benign or further specific treatment is needed, the initial diagnostic evaluation should always include a detailed history, physical examination, and 12-lead electrocardiography. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Yet, in most of the cases, the initial evaluation will be completely unremarkable and a diagnosis can only be presumed. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref></s><s>o exclude or determine an arrhythmic cause, the cardiac rhythm has to be recorded during an episode of palpitations.</s><s>Holter-ECG monitoring is commonly used as a first-line diagnostic tool.</s><s>As the preferred monitoring interval is 24-48 hours. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s>he diagnostic yield can be very low, especially if symptoms do not occur daily.</s><s>So other ambulatory monitoring devices that allow a longer follow-up must be used if the diagnosis is still unclear.</s></p><p><s>According to a position paper by the European Heart Rhythm Association, 2 external patientactivated event recorders are recommended in patients with nondiagnostic Holter-ECG with palpitations not accompanied by hemodynamic impairment.</s><s>For this study, such patients presenting to our outpatient clinic were included.</s><s>The aim of this analysis was to determine the optimal time of follow-up needed to achieve a symptom-rhythm correlation with the device.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head><p><s>A total of 1404 patients presented to our outpatient clinic between November 2011 and November 2014 for first time evaluation of symptomatic arrhythmias.</s><s>Ninety-one patients presenting with palpitations were included in this study.</s><s>Included patients described tachycardic palpitations, had no known structural heart disease and normal transthoracic echocardiography.</s><s>A 12lead electrocardiography as well as 48-hour Holter could not establish a diagnosis.</s><s>Exclusion criteria were a history of syncope as well as the presence of a pacemaker or an implantable defibrillator.</s><s>Patients who were incapable of using the device adequately were also excluded (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s></p><p><s>All patients were given a "leadless" patientactivated event-recording system (Omron HeartScan 801, Port Melbourne, Australia) and instructed on how to use it.</s><s>Patients were advised to use the recorder only once or twice during symptoms and once again when symptoms had passed or significantly changed.</s><s>The function of the device was described before by Kaleschke et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> Follow up was scheduled after 3 months.</s><s>If no episode was recorded in this period of time, follow up was prolonged for up to 1 year with visits after 6 and 12 months.</s><s>All recorded tracings were downloaded and analyzed by a trained cardiologist.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Analysis</head><p><s>Data are expressed as mean ± standard deviation or as absolute values and percentages as appropriate.</s><s>Statistical analyses were conducted using SPSS software (SPSS v22, IBM, Armonk, NY, USA).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head><p><s>A total of 91 patients were included.</s><s>Baseline patient characteristics are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Seventy-two patients (79.1%) recorded at least one ECG with the device.</s><s>Patient on average recorded 22 ± 19 ECGs.</s><s>The quality of the recorded ECG was sufficient in all patients to establish a diagnosis.</s><s>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref> summarizes the recorded episodes.</s><s>The average time of follow-up until a rhythmsymptom correlation was achieved with the event recorder was 20.6 ± 30.4 days (median 7 days, IQR 23.5).</s><s>Of the recorded ECGs, 51% were recorded within the first week after the device was handed out.</s><s>This figure rises to 80% and 93% after 1 and 2 months.</s><s>The last recording was after 174 days (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</s><s>The maximum follow-up was 1 year.</s><s>Patients with "true" arrhythmias recorded an ECG after a median of 21 (IQR 38) days, compared to a median of 4 (IQR 17) days for those that registered sinus rhythm or sinus tachycardia.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>Event recorders do not register ECG signals continuously, but during shorter, programmable time periods.</s><s>The patient is able to trigger the registration himself, which helps to diagnose infrequent episodes of palpitations.</s></p><p><s>External, patient-activated event recorders can be divided in two groups.</s><s>The first group of recorders are continuously connected to the patient skin with sticky electrode patches.</s><s>The second group has to be placed in contact with the chest during symptoms (so-called "leadless" event recorders).</s><s>When used to establish a diagnosis in patients presenting with palpitations, external patient-activated event recorders showed a diagnostic yield of 66%. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> In another study by Brown et al., <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> ECG signals during symptoms were obtained in 68% of patients presenting with palpitation, dizziness, or syncope.</s><s>One randomized clinical trial was conducted to evaluate the use of an external, patient-activated event recorder for patients who consulted their general practitioner for a new episode of palpitations and/or light headedness. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>A cardiac diagnosis explaining the symptoms was found in 67% of the participants.</s><s>Another recently performed analysis even found a 86% diagnostic yield for palpitations when an external loop recorder was used. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref></s><s>ll these studies were performed using a "standard" loop recorder with electrode patches.</s><s>The "leadless" event recorder used in our study was previously compared by Scherr et al. to the standard event recorder in the diagnosis of patients with palpitations. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref></s><s>In this prospective comparative study, 18 patients received both a standard and a "leadless" patient-activated event recorder.</s><s>Both devices showed comparable results.</s></p><p><s>Asmundis et al. performed a larger study comparing a leadless patient activated event recorder with traditional 24-hour Holter in patients with palpitations or dizziness. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref></s><s>Although Holter monitor recording was able to detect the clinical cardiac arrhythmia only in 1.8% of patients, the leadless patient activated event recorder detected symptoms-related arrhythmias in 89% of the patients.</s></p><p><s>In our study, a rhythm-symptom correlation was achieved in 79% of the patients, which again confirms the high diagnostic yield of the device.</s><s>In addition, our goal was to determine the optimal time of follow-up.</s></p><p><s>In our collective of 91 patients, 72 (79.1%) recorded at least one ECG during symptoms within a maximum follow-up of 1 year.</s><s>A total of 51% of the ECGs were recorded within the first week, 80% within 1 month, and 93% within 2 months.</s><s>These results suggest that within a follow-up of two months, the overall majority of patients that will eventually record ECG signals during symptoms is included.</s><s>Follow-up may be prolonged for another 1 or 2 months for individual cases.</s><s>Interestingly, patients with "true" arrhythmias recorded an ECG later than those that registered sinus rhythm or sinus tachycardia.</s></p><p><s>In conclusion, external "leadess" event recorders are effective in achieving a symptom-rhythm correlation in this patient collective within a follow up of 2 months.</s><s>Unfortunately, these devices are still quite costly and their number is limited.</s><s>Cheaper, smartphone-based external event recorders are under development, which may provide a solution to this problem.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LIMITATIONS</head><p><s>The limited number of patients should be considered when interpreting our study.</s><s>Nonetheless, the arrhythmias that were recorded (premature beats 13%, atrial fibrillation 9%, supraventricular tachycardia 7%) reflect the spectrum and incidence of arrhythmias that are expected in this age group.</s><s>In our opinion, it is unlikely that the distribution and type of arrhythmias (including sinus tachycardia) would be very different if the study was conducted in another center or if more patients were included.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Flow chart demonstrating how patients were included in the study.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,99.03,112.77,435.17,184.51" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Percentage of registered ECGs with successful rhythmsymptom correlations at different time points of follow-up.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,132.96,540.36,288.00,158.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Baseline Patient Characteristics</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Beta adrenergic blocker</cell><cell>14 (15.4)</cell></row><row><cell>ACE/ARB</cell><cell>6 (6.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Symptoms</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Palpitations (%)</cell><cell>91 (100)</cell></row><row><cell>Dizziness (%)</cell><cell>12 (13.2)</cell></row><row><cell>Sudden onset (%)</cell><cell>16 (17.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Vagal maneuvers successful (%)</cell><cell>6 (6.6)</cell></row></table><note><p><s>(n = 91) Age (SD) (years) 43.6±18.1 Female (%) 63 (69.2) Structural heart disease (%) 0 (0) Hypertension (%) 12 (13.2) Diabetes (%) 2 (2.2%) SD = standard deviation; ACE = angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitor; ARB = angiotensin receptor blocker.</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 . Results (n = 91)</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Number of patients that recorded an</cell><cell>72 patients</cell></row><row><cell>ECG during symptoms (%)</cell><cell>(79.1)</cell></row><row><cell>Episodes recorded</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sinus tachycardia (%)</cell><cell>25 (27.5)</cell></row><row><cell>Sinus rhythm (%)</cell><cell>19 (20.9)</cell></row><row><cell>Ventricular or supraventricular</cell><cell>12 (13.2)</cell></row><row><cell>premature beats (%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Atrial fibrillation/atrial flutter (%)</cell><cell>9 (9.9)</cell></row><row><cell>AVNRT/AVRT (%)</cell><cell>7 (7.7)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">AVNRT = atrioventricular nodal reentrant tachycardia; AVRT</cell></row><row><cell>= atrioventricular reentrant tachycardia.</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of patients with palpitations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zimetbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Josephson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">New Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">338</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1369" to="1373" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">European Heart Rhythm Association. Management of patients with palpitations: A position paper from the European Heart Rhythm Association</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Raviele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Giada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bergfeldt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Europace</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="920" to="934" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use of event recorders and loop recorders in clinical practice: Results of the European Heart Rhythm Association Survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sciaraffia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hocini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Europace</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1384" to="1386" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prospective, multicentre validation of a simple, patient-operated electrocardiographic system for the detection of arrhythmias and electrocardiographic changes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kaleschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hoffmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Drewitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Europace</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1362" to="1368" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Utility of patientactivated cardiac event recorders in the detection of cardiac arrhythmias</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hsieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Tai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Interv Card Electrophysiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Detection of arrhythmias: use of a patient-activated ambulatory electrocardiogram device with a solid-state memory loop</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Dawkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="253" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diagnostic yield of patient-activated loop recorders for detecting heart rhythm abnormalities in general practice: A randomised clinical trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hoefman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Reitsma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Fam Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="478" to="484" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of extended external loop recorders for the diagnosis of unexplained syncope, pre-syncope, and sustained palpitations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Locati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Vecchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vargiu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/europace/eut337</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Europace</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="914" to="922" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prospective comparison of the diagnostic utility of a standard event monitor versus a &quot;leadless&quot; portable ECG monitor in the evaluation of patients with palpitations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Scherr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dalal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Henrikson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10840-008-9251-0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Interv Card Electrophysiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of the patient-activated event recording system vs. traditional 24 h Holter electrocardiography in individuals with paroxysmal palpitations or dizziness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Deasmundis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Conte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sieira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Europace</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1231" to="1235" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
