<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laires</forename><surname>Pa</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Oeiras</settlement>
									<country key="PT">Portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Laíns</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Centro de Medicina e Reabilitação da Região Centro</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Coimbra</settlement>
									<country key="PT">Portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Miranda</forename><surname>Lc</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Instituto Português de Reumatologia</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lisbon</settlement>
									<country key="PT">Portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">ARS Norte</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Oporto</settlement>
									<country key="PT">Portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Eurotrials</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Scientific Consultants</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lisbon</settlement>
									<country key="PT">Portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Silva</forename><surname>Jc</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Med Data Analytics, Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>7 Merck Co</addrLine>
									<settlement>East Brunswick, Rahway</settlement>
									<region>NJ, NJ</region>
									<country>USA, USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="institution">Garcia de Orta Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Almada</settlement>
									<country key="PT">Portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">1D1D2F2D3A5F10FE8BEDD8117B1BE305</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Objectives: The prospective multinational Survey of Osteoarthritis Real World Therapies (SORT) was designed to investigate treatment patterns, adequacy of pain relief and quality of life in knee osteoarthritis (OA).</s><s>This analysis describes the demographic and clinical characteristics most associated with inadequate pain relief (IPR) in knee OA in Portugal.</s><s>MethOds: Male or female subjects aged ≥ 50 years with primary knee OA and who were receiving oral or topical analgesics were enrolled between January and December 2011 at seven primary care centers.</s><s>Pain was assessed using the Brief Pain Inventory (BPI).</s><s>IPR was defined as a score &gt; 4/10 on the BPI item "What is your pain on average?" reflecting moderate to severe disease.</s><s>Multivariable logistic regression model was employed to identify the subject characteristics most associated with IPR.</s><s>Results: Overall, 197 consecutive patients were analyzed.</s><s>The mean age was 67.0 ± 8.6 years and 78.2% were female.</s><s>The mean duration of knee OA was 6.2 ± 6.3 years.</s><s>The most common comorbidities were hypertension (64.0%), hyperlipidemia (58.4%), disability (41.6%) and depression (37.6%).</s><s>Nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs were the most frequently used analgesics.</s><s>IPR was reported by 51.3% of patients (95%CI 44.1%, 58.4%).</s><s>Disability, depression and diabetes were more frequent among patients with IPR than in patients with Non-IPR (p&lt; 0.05).</s><s>No statistically significant differences were observed in the type and mean number of different classes of medication used by IPR and Non-IPR patients.</s><s>Female gender (adjusted odds ratio -OR 2.15 [95%CI 1.1, 4.5]), diabetes <ref type="bibr">(adjusted OR 3.1 [95%CI 1.3,</ref><ref type="bibr">7.7]</ref>)</s><s>and depression (adjusted OR 2.24 [95%CI 1.2, 4.3]) were associated with higher risk of IPR.</s><s>cOnclusiOns: Our findings indicate that improvements are needed in the management of pain in knee OA in order to achieve better outcomes and highlight the requisite for further interventions targeting frequent comorbid conditions in knee OA in Portugal.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PMS105 Patient RePoRted outcoMe in HealtH SeRviceS ReSeaRcH: a PRoSPective Study of oRtHoPedic SuRgeRy in Routine caRe in SwitzeRland</head><p><s>Eichler K 1 , Hess S 1 , Twerenbold C 1 , Grobet C 2 , Flury M 2 , Wieser S 1 , Audigé L 2 1 Winterthur Institute of Health Economics, Zurich University of Applied Sciences, Winterthur, Switzerland, 2 Schulthess Clinic, Zurich, Switzerland Objectives: Rotator cuff tear of the shoulder is a common musculoskeletal disorder, may have a substantial impact on patients' quality of life (QOL) and implies a significant cost burden.</s><s>Arthroscopic rotator cuff repair (aRCR) is one established standard therapy, however, health services research has generated little information about the impact of aRCR on QOL and on costs in real world settings.</s><s>We aimed to assess the impact of aRCR in routine care in Switzerland.</s><s>MethOds: In a prospective before-after study, consecutive patients with aRCR in a single tertiary orthopaedic centre were assessed for QOL using EQ-5D-5L to gain health states/ utilities (range: 0.00-1.00;</s><s>multiple measurements from pre-operative enrolment until 2 years after surgery).</s><s>Direct medical costs in Swiss Francs (CHF) were assessed from a third party payer perspective using health insurance claims data for 3 time intervals (1 year before surgery; year 1 and 2 after surgery).</s><s>Results: 152 patients (mean age 57 years [range: 31-73]; male: 61%) were operated, of which 67 were evaluated for QOL up to 12 months.</s><s>QOL showed a stepwise improvement: 0.75 (mean utility at enrollment), 0.71 (pre-op), 0.61 (2 weeks), 0.85 (3 months), 0.91 (6 months), 0.93 (12 months).</s><s>Direct medical costs (mean, SD) of the first patients with cost data were CHF 7,540 (6,684) in the year before surgery (n= 47: mean inpatient: 882; outpatient: 6,658) and <ref type="bibr">CHF 9,</ref><ref type="bibr">759 (3,</ref><ref type="bibr">675)</ref> in the first year after surgery (n= 40: mean inpatient: 4,964 [including operation]; outpatient: 4,795).</s><s>cOnclusiOns: Patients with aRCR in routine care show a significant and clinically relevant improvement of QOL until 12 months after surgery.</s><s>This is important information for decision makers in Switzerland.</s><s>Completion of follow up of our patient cohort will allow a better understanding of the relationship between gain in QOL and involved direct medical costs.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PMS106 validation of tHe engliSH veRSion of tHe foRgotten Joint ScoRe -12 in PatientS undeRgoing total Knee oR HiP aRtHRoPlaSty</head><p><s>Giesinger JM 1 , Loth FL 1 , Howie C 2 , Giesinger K 3 , Hamilton DF 2 1 Medical University of Innsbruck, Innsbruck, Austria, 2 University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK, 3 Kantonsspital Sankt Gallen, Sankt Gallen, Switzerland Objectives: The recently developed Forgotten Joint Score -12 (FJS-12) is increasingly being used in patients with hip or knee pathologies to assess joint awareness following surgical or conservative treatment.</s><s>Joint awareness is a construct considered to be especially relevant in patients with good to excellent outcome.</s><s>In our study we aimed at investigating reliability, validity and sensitivity to change over time of the English version of the FJS-12 in patients with total knee arthroplasty (TKA) or total hip arthroplasty (THA).</s><s>MethOds: Patients undergoing THA or TKA at the Royal Infirmary of Edinburgh were consecutively included in the study and assessed with the FJS-12 at pre-surgery, 6 months and 12 months.</s><s>To determine convergent validity we administered the Oxford Hip Score (OHS) and the Oxford Knee Score (OKS).</s><s>We calculated Cronbach's Alpha as a measure of internal consistency of the FJS-12.</s><s>Sensitivity to change is given as effect size (Cohen's d).</s><s>Results: At present we have recruited 219 TKA patients and 193 THA patients (recruitment ongoing).</s><s>Mean age of the TKA patients was 68.3 (SD 9.3) and 54.1% were female.</s><s>Mean age in the THA group was 67.6 years (SD 10.5) and 116 (60.1%) were female.</s><s>Cronbach's alpha was very high in both groups (0.95 in TKA patients and 0.96 in THA patients).</s><s>Correlations with the OHS (r= 0.76) and the OKS (r= 0.72) indicated good convergent validity of the FJS-12.</s><s>Effect sizes for change between 6 months and 12 months in FJS-12 scores were 0.40 in TKA patients and d= 0.17 in THA patients.</s><s>cOnclusiOns: The English version of the FJS-12 showed high internal consistency in THA and TKA patients and good convergent validity with the OHS and OKS.</s><s>Our findings suggest that the FJS-12 is a reliable and valid instrument for the assessment of outcome after THA and TKA.</s><s>patient organizations wasn't perceived significant.</s><s>Areas that have improved compared to the period of patients starting their treatment: communication with healthcare personnel (80%), more effective therapies available (65%).</s><s>cOnclusiOns: This study showed significant impact of the rheumatic diseases on work capabilities and socio-economic status.</s><s>The results of the research were presented and discussed with the patient community and rheumatologists and on their respective conferences.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PMS102 Patient BeliefS and PRefeRenceS in tReatMent witH diSeaSe Modifying anti-RHeuMatic dRugS</head><p><s>Schiffner-Rohe J 1 , Alten R 2 , Krueger K 3 , Behmer OS 4 , Schiffhorst G 5 , Rellecke J 5 , Nolting H 5 1 Pfizer Deutschland GmbH, Berlin, Germany, 2 Schlosspark-Klinik Akademisches Lehrkrankenhaus der Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany, 3 Praxiszentrum St. Bonifatius,  München, Germany, 4 Pfizer Pharma, Berlin, Germany, 5 iges Institute, Berlin, Germany Objectives: Chronic autoimmune diseases such as rheumatoid arthritis (RA) require continuous disease modifying medication to influence disease progression.</s><s>Real-life efficacy of treatments rests on adherence.</s><s>Since patients' beliefs impact on adherence, adherence could be supported by treatments better respecting these beliefs.</s><s>Thus, using an RA sample, the present study establishes in how far patients' beliefs are reflected by their preferences for treatment characteristics of disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drugs (DMARDs).</s><s>MethOds: Preferences were assessed in a choice experiment (Best-Worst Scaling).</s><s>1588 RA patients were asked to choose most and least preferred DMARDs among treatment options with varying levels of the following key attributes: mode of administration, frequency of administration, time till onset of drug effect, necessity of combination therapy, and side effects.</s><s>Patients were classified into groups of "accepting", "ambivalent", "sceptical", and "indifferent" patients <ref type="bibr">(Clifford et al., 2008)</ref> according to a modified "beliefs about medicines"-questionnaire.</s><s>Utilities of attribute levels were assessed by paired model regression analysis <ref type="bibr">(Flynn et al., 2007)</ref> and compared between groups.</s><s>Regression analysis was conducted to control for confounding patientrelated variables.</s><s>Results: Majority of patients were female (74%), 50 to 64 years of age (45%), with &lt; 10 years of disease duration (54%), and were receiving DMARDs (95%).</s><s>Mode of administration appeared the most important attribute, with "oral application" being most desired.</s><s>Second most relevant attribute was "necessity of combination therapy with MTX", followed by frequency of administration, side effects and time to onset of effect.</s><s>Preferences concerning "mode of administration" and "tolerance of side effects" were significantly different between subjects classified by their beliefs about medicines", according to regression analysis adjusting for confounding patient-related variables.</s><s>cOnclusiOns: Results indicate beliefs about medicines to be meaningfully associated with patient preferences regarding DMARD characteristics.</s><s>This offers important leads to improving adherence by designing more consumer-friendly pharmaceutical products for chronic diseases.</s><s>Objectives: To synthesize the available information on patients' preferences for rheumatoid arthritis (RA) treatment and their participation in the treatment decision-making process.</s><s>MethOds: Electronic databases [PubMed, ISI-WOK, Cochrane Library, MEDES, IBECS, CSIC] and grey literature, were searched.</s><s>Studies written in English or Spanish, published in Europe and North America between January 2005 and February 2015 were selected.</s><s>Editorials, letters, opinion papers and studies performed on specific populations were excluded.</s><s>Results: The search resulted in 1,156 citations; 15 studies accomplished the selection criteria.</s><s>Nine studies explored patients' preferences for RA treatments characteristics (administration methods= 7; frequency= 2).</s><s>Auto-injected devices that facilitated self-administration at home and improved comfort, and less frequent doses were preferred.</s><s>Convenience (home administration and non-interference with everyday life) was the main reason for choosing subcutaneous routes, while safety, rapidity of action, reassurance and confidence were the reasons for choosing intravenous routes.</s><s>Two publications examined the influence of patients' characteristics on treatment status-quo.</s><s>Patients who were moderately affected by RA were more open to consider new treatment alternatives.</s><s>One study explored patients' priorities regarding treatment outcomes.</s><s>Less pain, joint damage or fatigue, daily life activities and more mobility were the prioritized outcomes.</s><s>Three studies elicited preferences regarding patients' participation in treatment decision-making, showing that they were negatively associated with age but positively associated with RA knowledge.</s><s>Although patients preferred shared treatment decision-making, they reported that most of the physician-patients communication was centered on symptoms and impact of RA.</s><s>Most patients valued treatment recommendations given by their physicians considering their expert knowledge and clinical experience.</s><s>Unawareness of having a choice was the main barrier for patients' participation in decision-making.</s><s>cOnclusiOns: Patients' preferences are influenced by patients' characteristics, clinical status and impact of RA in their daily life.</s><s>Including patients' preference and involving patients in treatment decision-making may contribute to better clinical outcomes.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Rentero ML 1 , Comellas M 2 , Lizan L 2 , Sacristán JA 1 1 Lilly, Alcobendas (Madrid), Spain, 2 Outcomes 10, Castellon, Spain</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>PMS104 factoRS aSSociated witH inadequate Pain Relief in PatientS witH PRiMaRy Knee oSteoaRtHRitiS in PoRtugal: an analySiS fRoM tHe SuRvey of oSteoaRtHRitiS Real woRld tHeRaPieS (SoRt)</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
