<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Diagnostic and prognostic potential of circulating cell-free genomic and mitochondrial DNA fragments in clear cell renal cell carcinoma patients</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Klinik für Urologie</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Medizinischen Fakultät</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin DISSERTATION</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">vorgelegt der Medizinischen Fakultät</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin von Hongbiao Lu aus China</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Jiangsu</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Diagnostic and prognostic potential of circulating cell-free genomic and mitochondrial DNA fragments in clear cell renal cell carcinoma patients</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">E31384C61088BB51ED47F524173FE16A</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Background: There is inconsistent information about the clinical usefulness of circulating cell-freeDNA (cfDNA) in plasma from clear cell renal cell cancer (RCC) patients.</s><s>This is attributed to preanalytical, analytical, and clinical factors that were considered as far as possible in this study.</s></p><p><s>Methods: cfDNA was extracted from EDTA plasma of healthy people (n = 40), nonmetastatic (n = 145) and metastatic (n = 84) RCC patients using the QIAamp Circulating Nucleic Acid Kit.</s><s>Genomic and mitochondrial cfDNA concentrations were determined using qPCR of different cfDNA fragments (67-306 bp).</s><s>Their diagnostic and prognostic potential was estimated using receiver operating characteristics (ROC) and Cox regression analyses.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results:</head><p><s>The 67 bp and 180 bp genomic cfDNA fragments did not differ between the three study groups while the 306 bp fragment was lower in RCC patients than in controls.</s><s>The mitochondrial cfDNA was higher in metastatic than in non-metastatic patients and controls.</s><s>The cfDNA integrity indices decreased from controls to metastatic patients.</s><s>Models built by logistic regression and Cox regression resulted in area under the ROC curves &gt; 0.75 and concordance indices of &gt;0.800 in predicting recurrence-free survival and overall survival.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion:</head><p><s>The study suggests that combinations of cfDNA markers have promising diagnostic and prognostic potential in RCC patients and are worth for further validation in future prospective multicenter studies.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Affidavit</head><p><s>I, <ref type="bibr">[Hongbiao, Lu]</ref> certify under penalty of perjury by my own signature that I have submitted the thesis on the topic [Diagnostic and prognostic potential of circulating cell-free genomic and mitochondrial DNA fragments in clear cell renal cell carcinoma patients] I wrote this thesis independently and without assistance from third parties, I used no other aids than the listed sources and resources.</s></p><p><s>All points based literally or in spirit on publications or presentations of other authors are, as such, in proper citations (see "uniform requirements for manuscripts (URM)" the ICMJE www.icmje.org)</s><s>indicated.</s><s>The sections on methodology (in particular practical work, laboratory requirements, statistical processing) and results (in particular images, graphics and tables) correspond to the URM (s.o) and are answered by me.</s><s>My contributions in the selected publications for this dissertation correspond to those that are specified in the following joint declaration with the responsible person and supervisor.</s><s>All publications resulting from this thesis and which I am author of correspond to the URM (see above) and I am solely responsible.</s></p><p><s>The importance of this affidavit and the criminal consequences of a false affidavit (section 156,161 of the Criminal Code) are known to me and I understand the rights and responsibilities stated therein.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>____________________________ ____________________________ Date Signature</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Declaration of any eventual publications</head><p><s>Hongbiao Lu had the following share in the following publications:</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>AbstraktHintergrund:</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Die Informationen von zellfreier, zirkulierender DNA (cfDNA) als potenzieller diagnostischer und/oder prognostischer Marker bei Patienten mit einem Nierenzellkarzinom sind widersprüchlich.</s><s>Dies ist offensichtlich bedingt durch eine bisher unzureichende Berücksichtigung von präanalytischen, analytischen und klinische Einflussgrößen.</s><s>Das Konzept der vorliegenden Studie mit einer entsprechenden Fallzahlberechnung resultiert auf diesen und neuen Erkenntnissen aus cfDNA-Studien bei anderen Tumoren.</s><s>Hierbei sollte insbesondere der Einfluss untersucht werden, den unterschiedlich lange cfDNA-Fragmente auf die klinische Aussage haben.</s><s>Methoden: cfDNA wurde aus EDTA-Plasma einer gesunden Kontrollgruppe (n = 40), von Patienten mit einem klarzelligen Nierenzellkarzinom vor der Tumorentfernung durch Nephrektomie, bei denen keine Metastasierung vorlag (n=145), und bei metastasierten Patienten vor und während einer Systemtherapie mit Thyrosinkinaseinhibitoren (n=84) unter Verwendung der QIAamp Circulating Nukleinsäure-Testkombination extrahiert.</s><s>Genomische und mitochondriale cfDNA-Konzentrationen wurden durch quantitative Polymeraseketten-Reaktion mit sieben unterschiedlich langen Fragmenten (67 bis 306 Basenpaare [bp]) bestimmt.</s><s>Das diagnostische und prognostische Potential der Marker wurde mit der "Receiver operating characteristics" (ROC) und Cox-Regression eingeschätzt.</s><s>Ergebnisse: Die Konzentrationen der genomischen Fragmente mit 67 bp und 180 bp unterschieden sich nicht in den drei Studiengruppen, während das 306 bp-Fragment in den Patienten niedrige Konzentrationen aufwies als in den Kontrollen.</s><s>Die mitochondriale cfDNA war in den metastasierten Patienten höher als in nichtmetastasierten Patienten vor Nephrektomie und Kontrollen.</s><s>Die Integritätindizes als Quotienten der längeren zu kurzen Fragmenten fielen von den Kontrollen zu der metastasierten Patienten ab.</s><s>Modelle, die mit Hilfe der logistischen Regression aus den Einzelparametern und Integritätsindizes zur Differenzierung zwischen den Patientengruppen errechnet wurden, ergaben unter Flächen von &gt;0,75 unter den ROC-Kurven.</s><s>Die mit der multivariaten CoxRegression errechneten cfDNA-Prädiktionsmodelle wiesen Konkordanz-Indizes von &gt;0,80 für das rezidiv-freie Überleben und das Gesamtüberleben auf und übertrafen damit die Ergebnisse, die anhand der klinisch-pathologischen Daten erzielt wurden.</s><s>Fazit: Die Studie lässt die Schlussfolgerung zu, dass Kombinationen von cfDNA-Marker aussagekräftige diagnostische und prognostische Informationen für Patienten mit einem Nierenzellkarzinom liefern können.</s><s>Die hier empfohlenen Parameter sind es wert, in künftigen prospektiven multizentrische Studien eingeschlossen und validiert zu werden.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>"</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>the paper will not be published for Copyright of the journal in the electronic version of my work."</s><s>Hongbiao Lu, Jonas Busch, Monika Jung, Silke Rabenhorst, Bernhard Ralla, Ergin Kilic, Steffen Mergemeier, Nils Budach, Annika Fendler, Klaus Jung: Diagnostic and prognostic potential of circulating cell-free genomic and mitochondrial DNA fragments in clear cell renal cell carcinoma patients, Clin.Chim.</s><s>Acta 452 (2016) 109-119 http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cca.2015.11.009 8 Curriculum vitae " My curriculum vitae does not appear in the electronic version of my paper for reasons of data protection "</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Publication 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>HongbiaoLu, Jonas Busch, Monika Jung, Silke Rabenhorst, Bernhard Ralla, Ergin Kilic, Steffen Mergemeier, Nils Budach, Annika Fendler, Klaus Jung, Diagnostic and prognostic potential of circulating cell-free genomic and mitochondrial DNA fragments in clear cell renal cell carcinoma patients, Clin.Chim.Acta 452 (2016) 109-119.Contribution in detail: Hongbiao Lu participated part of the sample collections, implemented all the DNA extraction and quantitative real-time PCR analysis, did the statistics of the characteristics of patients, carried out mainly the analysis and interpretation of data, and was the main author in drafting the manuscript.</s><s>Hongbiao Lu is the first author of the publication.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Printed Copy of Publication</cell></row><row><cell>Diagnostic and prognostic potential of circulating cell-free genomic and</cell></row><row><cell>mitochondrial DNA fragments in clear cell renal cell carcinoma</cell></row><row><cell>patients</cell></row><row><cell>Hongbiao Lu*, Jonas Busch , Monika Jung , Silke Rabenhorst , Bernhard Ralla , Ergin</cell></row><row><cell>Kilic ,</cell></row><row><cell>Steffen Mergemeier , Nils Budach , Annika Fendler , Klaus Jung</cell></row><row><cell>Signature, date and stamp of the supervising University teacher</cell></row><row><cell>____________________________</cell></row><row><cell>Signature of the doctoral candidate</cell></row><row><cell>_________________________</cell></row></table><note><p><s>*</s></p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>First of all, I would like to thank my advisors, PD.</s><s>Dr. med.</s><s>Jonas Busch and Prof. Dr. Klaus Jung, for gladly welcoming me as a member of the research group and equally for their committed and excellent supervision.</s></p><p><s>I also thank Prof. Dr. med.</s><s>Carsten Stephan, for her constructive criticism and numerous good suggestions that helped to improve this thesis.</s><s>Special thanks to Dr. Monika Jung, Dr. Bernhard Ralla, Silke Rabenhorst, and other colleagues for their great support during the course of the study.</s></p><p><s>Finally, I would like to extend special thanks to my hospital and family, for their great support and always company.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>18</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary data</head><p><s>Supplementary data to this article with a list of Supplemental Figures and Tables can be found online at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cca.2015.11.009.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diagnostic and prognostic potential of circulating cell-free genomic and mitochondrial DNA fragments in clear cell renal cell carcinoma patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hongbiao</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonas</forename><surname>Busch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Monika</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Silke</forename><surname>Rabenhorst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bernhard</forename><surname>Ralla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ergin</forename><surname>Kilic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Steffen</forename><surname>Mergemeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nils</forename><surname>Budach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Annika</forename><surname>Fendler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Klaus</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Chim. Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">452</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="119" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Risk prediction models for biochemical recurrence after radical prostatectomy using prostatespecific antigen and Gleason score</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cammann</forename><surname>Hu Xin-Hai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Meyer</forename><surname>Henning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">-A</forename><surname>Hellmuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jung</forename><surname>Klaus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lu</forename><surname>Hong-Biao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Leva</forename><surname>Natalia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Magheli</forename><surname>Ahmed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stephan</forename><surname>Carsten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jonas</forename><surname>Busch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Asian journal of andrology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="897" to="901" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-11">2014 Nov-Dec</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential expression of vimentin in hypospadiac male rats induced by Di -n -butyl Phthalate</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wei</forename><surname>Gaijie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lu</forename><surname>Hongbiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Shi</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Urology and Nephrology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="3" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Association between IL13 gene polymorphisms and susceptibility to cancer: a meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Su</forename><surname>Tong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lu</forename><surname>Hongbiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">515</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-02-15">2013 Feb 15</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Prevention and Treatment of Percutaneous Nephrolithotripsy Complications. HEALTH RESEARCH</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lu</forename><surname>Hongbiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">He</forename><surname>Xiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="220" to="224" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Case analysis True hermaphroditism. The journal of practical medicine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lu</forename><surname>Hongbiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">He</forename><surname>Xiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>26; 12. 2264</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxygen free radicals regulate energy metabolism via AMPK pathway following cerebral ischemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lu</forename><surname>Hongbiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurological Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="779" to="784" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-09">2010 Sep</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
