<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A novel pretherapeutic gene expression-based risk score for treatment guidance in gastric cancer</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-10-23">23 October 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bauer</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hapfelmeier</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Medical Statistics and Epidemiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Technical University of Munich</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Munich</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Blank</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Heidelberg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Heidelberg</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Reiche</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Slotta-Huspenina</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jesinghaus</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Novotny</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Technical University of Munich</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Munich</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Schmidt</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Heidelberg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Heidelberg</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Grosser</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kohlruss</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Weichert</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">German Cancer Consortium (DKTK)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Partner Site Munich</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Technical University Munich</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Munich</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ott</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Klinikum Rosenheim</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Rosenheim</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Keller</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Prof</roleName><forename type="middle">Gisela</forename><surname>Keller</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Departments of 1 Pathology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Technical University of Munich</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Trogerstr. 18</addrLine>
									<postCode>81675</postCode>
									<settlement>Munich</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A novel pretherapeutic gene expression-based risk score for treatment guidance in gastric cancer</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2017-10-23">23 October 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">877303994C1E94254E7545FAF79DF813</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/annonc/mdx685</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:42+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>gastric carcinoma</term>
					<term>prognosis</term>
					<term>risk score</term>
					<term>perioperative chemotherapy</term>
					<term>gene expression</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Background: Perioperative chemotherapy is an established treatment of advanced gastric cancer patients.</s><s>Treatment selection is based on clinical staging (cT).</s><s>We aimed to establish and validate a prognostic score including clinical and molecular factors, to optimize treatment decisions for these patients.</s></p><p><s>Patients and methods: We analyzed 626 carcinomas of the stomach and of the gastro-esophageal junction from two academic centers including primarily resected and pre-/perioperatively treated patients.</s><s>Patients were divided into a training (N ¼ 269) and validation (N ¼ 357) set.</s><s>Expression of 11 target genes was measured by quantitative PCR in resected tumors.</s><s>A risk score to predict overall survival (OS) was generated and validated.</s><s>Intra-tumoral heterogeneity was assessed by analyzing 50 tumor areas from 10 patients.</s></p><p><s>Results: A risk score including the expression of CCL5, CTNNB1, EXOSC3 and LZTR1 and the clinical parameters cT, tumor localization and histopathologic type suggested two groups with a significant difference in OS [hazard ratio (HR) 0.30; 95% confidence interval (CI) 0.17-0.52].</s><s>The risk score was successfully validated in an independent cohort (HR 0.32; 95% CI 0.21-0.51;</s><s>P &lt; 0.001) as well as in subgroups of primarily resected (HR 0.30; 95% CI 0.17-0.54;</s><s>P &lt; 0.001) and pre-/perioperatively treated patients (HR 0.37; 95% CI 0.17-0.81;</s><s>P ¼ 0.009).</s><s>A significant difference in OS of high-and low-risk patients was also found in primarily resected patients with intestinal (HR 0.45; 95% CI 0.23-0.90;</s><s>P ¼ 0.020) and nonintestinal-type carcinomas (HR 0.1; 95% CI 0.02-0.42;</s><s>P &lt; 0.001).</s><s>Intra-tumor heterogeneity analysis indicated a classification reliability of 95% for a supposed analysis of three biopsies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion:</head><p><s>The identified risk score could substantially contribute to an improved management of gastric cancer patients in the context of perioperative chemotherapy.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Gastric carcinoma (GC) is characterized by a high mortality rate due to a frequent diagnosis at advanced stages.</s><s>Pre-/perioperative chemotherapy mainly based on platinum and 5-fluorouracil (5FU) has been shown to prolong patients' survival and is now the standard of care in Europe for patients staged cT2-cT4 with any N <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>German guidelines recommend additionally that patients with cT2 tumors can be treated in a neoadjuvant or perioperative setting <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s>This can recommendation reflects an uncertainty about the choice of the optimal therapeutic approach in particular for patients with cT2 tumors.</s><s>Clinical staging, which forms the sole basis for patient selection for this treatment is generally known to be imprecise.</s><s>In particular, the accuracy of clinical staging for patients with cT2 adenocarcinomas of the gastro-esophageal junction (AEG) was demonstrated to be poor <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</s><s>Undertreatment of patients with exceptionally aggressive prognostically bad cT1/cT2 tumors and overtreatment of patients with less aggressive and prognostically favorable cT3/cT4 tumors cannot be excluded.</s><s>Thus, reliable molecular prognostic markers complementing clinical information for therapeutic decisions with respect to the initiation of a pre-or perioperative chemotherapy are needed.</s></p><p><s>The goal of our study was to establish a prognostic score, which could include clinical and molecular prognostic factors to support or guide this decision on the initiation of a pre-or perioperative chemotherapy.</s><s>To achieve this objective, we analyzed the tumors for the expression of genes, which were selected based on their prognostic significance reported in previous studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref>.</s><s>Regarding the role of the selected genes in the context of the recent published molecular subtypes of GC, a significant differential expression in one of the subtypes was found for some of them.</s><s>In particular, the expression of the cytokine CCL5 was higher in the group with microsatellite instability (MSI) and in EBV positive tumors and lower in the chromosomal unstable group <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>We carried out the analysis of GC and AEG carcinoma patients including tumors from primarily resected and of patients treated with pre-/perioperative chemotherapy, who were in addition recruited from two different medical centers to maximize the robustness and prognostic relevance of the score.</s><s>Gene expression data and clinical characteristics available before the start of chemotherapy were offered for statistical modelling to produce a final optimal risk score.</s></p><p><s>As only pretherapeutic biopsies would be available for a potential application in daily clinical practice related to the start of a pre-or perioperative chemotherapy, we investigated the deviation of the risk score in relation to intra-tumor heterogeneity.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patients and methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patients</head><p><s>In total, 705 patients with GC, including tumors of the gastro-esophageal junction (AEG II and AEG III as defined by Siewert and Stein <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref>), that were treated at the Department of Surgery at the Technical University Munich between 2001 and 2013 and at the Department of Surgery at the University of Heidelberg between 2001 and 2012 were included.</s><s>Among them, 337 primarily resected tumors were from patients with clinically staged cT2 and cT3/cT4 tumors, that were potentially eligible for pre-/ perioperative chemotherapy (CTx) and 368 tumors were from CTxtreated patients.</s></p><p><s>Tumors from CTx-treated patients were included only if they exhibited partial or minimal/no tumor regression [tumor regression grades (TRG) 2 and 3 with 10%-50% or &gt;50% residual tumor cells/tumor bed, respectively] <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref>.</s><s>TRG1 tumors with &lt;10% residual tumor cells were not included either due to the absence of residual tumor or due to the technical difficulties adherent to low tumor cell content.</s></p><p><s>Primarily resected cT3/cT4 tumors of four patients and resected specimen after CTx of six patients with TRG3 were used in the analysis for molecular tumor heterogeneity.</s><s>Five tumor areas from each patient were analyzed.</s></p><p><s>Pretherapeutic biopsies of five patients with cT3 tumors were used to demonstrate exemplarily the feasibility to measure the expression of the relevant genes using bioptic samples.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chemotherapy</head><p><s>Patients were treated with cisplatinum or oxaliplatinum-based chemotherapeutic regimens in combination with 5-fluorouracil or capecitabine, optionally combined with taxanes, epirubicin or other agents.</s><s>A subset of these patients was treated with adjuvant chemotherapy or adjuvant radio-chemotherapy after surgery.</s><s>Details are listed in supplementary Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>, available at Annals of Oncology online.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Follow-up and overall survival</head><p><s>Follow-up was carried out as described and median follow-up was calculated by the inverse Kaplan-Meier method <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">15]</ref>.</s><s>The primary end point of the study was overall survival (OS), which was defined as the time between the date of operation and death by any cause.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethics statement</head><p><s>The study was approved by the local Institutional Review Boards at the Technical University Munich (reference: 5861/13) and at the University of Heidelberg (reference: 301/2001).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RNA extraction and gene expression analysis</head><p><s>Total RNA was extracted from formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tissues from resection specimen after manual microdissection of tumor areas composed of at least 50% tumor cells in the majority of cases.</s></p><p><s>Eleven target genes were selected for analysis based on their reported prognostic role in GC (CCL5, CTNNB1, EXOSC3, FGFR2, GSK3B, LZTR1, NOTCH2, PLA2G2A, TOP2A, TRANK1 and TRIM44) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref>.</s><s>B2M, IPO8 and PPIA were used as reference genes.</s><s>Methods for RNA extraction, reverse transcription, reference gene selection and gene expression analysis are included in supplementary File S1, Tables <ref type="table">S2 and S3</ref>, available at Annals of Oncology online.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis of MSI</head><p><s>Overall 290 of the 626 tumors had been analyzed for MSI as described in supplementary File S1, available at Annals of Oncology online.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Development of the risk score and statistical analysis</head><p><s>Development of the risk score based on multivariable Cox regression analysis and further statistical analysis are described in detail in supple mentary File S1, available at Annals of Oncology online.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study enrollment and patients characteristics</head><p><s>Of the 705 patients initially evaluated for the study, 79 were excluded and the final dataset comprised 626 patients.</s><s>The training and validation cohort encompassed 269 and 357 tumors, respectively, and the proportion of the patients treated with pre-/ perioperative chemotherapy was balanced in both cohorts (47% versus 50%).</s><s>An overview of the study enrollment and reasons for exclusion are given in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</s><s>Patients' characteristics of the training and validation cohorts are shown in supplementary Table <ref type="table">S4</ref>, available at Annals of Oncology online.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Establishing the prognostic score</head><p><s>Relative expression values of the 11 genes from the 269 tumors of the training cohort and the pretherapeutically available clinical factors were offered for selection into the statistical model.</s><s>The best risk score modeled on these data encompassed the gene Original article expression of CCL5, CTNNB1, EXOSC3 and LZTR1 and the clinical factors cT, tumor localization and histopathologic tumor type (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2A</ref>).</s><s>The c-index of the model was 0.670, and gene expression and clinical variables contributed significantly to the model's goodness of fit (each P &lt; 0.001).</s><s>The model summary including hazard ratios (HR) and P-values is shown in supple mentary Table <ref type="table">S5</ref>, available at Annals of Oncology online.</s><s>A cutoff value was determined with emphasis on a high sensitivity of 90% to detect high-risk patients and two patient groups with a highly significant difference in OS were identified (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2B</ref>).</s><s>Median OS of the low-risk group was not reached and median OS of the high-risk group was 24.9 months (95% CI 17.07-32.79)</s><s>(HR 0.30; 95% CI 0.17-0.52).</s></p><p><s>The risk score can be computed by applying the individual patient's characteristics in the following formula or by using the nomogram shown in supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1</ref>, available at Annals of Oncology online.</s><s>The cut-off value for high/low risk is set at À0.58.</s><s>Analysis of the risk score separately in the subgroups of CTxtreated (N ¼ 177) and primarily resected tumors (N ¼ 178) also showed significant survival differences in both groups (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2D</ref> and E; supplementary Table <ref type="table">S6</ref>, available at Annals of Oncology online).</s><s>In the subgroup of CTx-treated patients the median OS was not reached in the low-risk group and was 29.1 months (95% CI 23.3-34.9) in the high-risk group (HR 0.37; 95% CI 0.17-0.81;</s><s>P ¼ 0.009).</s><s>The c-index of the model was 0.621.</s><s>In the subgroup of primarily resected patients, OS was 122.8 months (95% CI 76.0-169.5) in the low risk and 29.3 months (95% CI 10.9-47.8) in the high-risk group (HR 0.30; 95% CI 0.17-0.54;</s><s>P &lt; 0.001).</s><s>The c-index of the model in this group was 0.647.</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Risk score ¼ À2:397 þ 0:000; if cT2 0:807; if cT3 1:330; if cT4 8 &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &lt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; : 9 &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; = &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; ; þ 0:000; if</formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">8 &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &lt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; : 9 &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; = &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; ; þ 0:000; if</formula><p><s>Further subgroup analysis within the primarily resected cohort, considering only patients with cT2 tumors or only patients with cT3/cT4 tumors, demonstrated separation of survival curves of high-and low-risk patients in the cT3/cT4 group and in the cT2 group with borderline significance (P ¼ 0.058 and P ¼ 0.105, respectively) (supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2A and B</ref>, available at Annals of Oncology online).</s><s>The HR of the low-risk group in the cT2 group was 0.50 (95% CI 0.21-0.1.18)</s><s>and 0.28 (95% CI 0.07-1.15) in the cT3/cT4 group (supplementary Table <ref type="table">S6</ref>, available at Annals of Oncology online).</s></p><p><s>Validation of the score in the group of patients with primarily resected tumors, stratified according to the histopathologic tumor type, showed significant survival differences for the prespecified cut-off value within the intestinal and nonintestinal group (P ¼ 0.02 and P &lt; 0.001, respectively) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2F</ref> and G; supplementary Table S6, available at Annals of Oncology online).</s><s>Of note, in the nonintestinal group the low-risk group encompassed 31 of 89 patients, who demonstrated a particularly good survival with an HR of 0.10 (95% CI 0.02-0.42).</s><s>Only 2 of the 31 patients (6%) in this group had died.</s><s>The c-index of the model in   this group was 0.733.</s><s>Among the 89 nonintestinal-type carcinomas, 35 were of mixed and 54 were of the diffuse type according the Laure ´n classification.</s><s>Comparing the frequency of high-and low-risk patients in these particular subgroups revealed no significant differences.</s></p><p><s>Validation of the score in the patients stratified according to tumor localization showed significant survival differences for patients with GEJ tumors and for patients with other tumor localizations (P ¼ 0.006 and P ¼ 0.009, respectively).</s><s>The corresponding hazard ratios were 0.09 (95% CI 0.01-0.71)</s><s>and 0.43 (95% CI 0.22-0.83),</s><s>respectively (supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2C</ref> and D and Table <ref type="table">S6</ref>, available at Annals of Oncology online).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Intra-tumor heterogeneity</head><p><s>As a potential application of the risk score lays in the determination of high-and low-risk patients before the start of chemotherapy, which necessitates an analysis of gene expression from pretherapeutic tumor biopsies, we analyzed the performance and robustness of the score in relation to intra-tumor heterogeneity.</s></p><p><s>Overall 50 tumor areas from 10 patients were analyzed of which 49 samples passed quality control.</s><s>The probability that patients would be allocated to a different risk group due to intratumor variability of gene expression was calculated.</s><s>The crossing probability was 7% in the training and 8.6% in the validation cohort for a single measurement.</s><s>Assuming an increased number of analyzed tumor regions per patient (i.e.</s><s>number of biopsies) and calculation of the resulting crossing probability showed that an average score from two or three biopsies would reduce the crossing probability to 5% and 4.1% in the training cohort and to 6.1% and 5.0% in the validation cohort.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pretherapeutic biopsies</head><p><s>Gene expression analysis was successfully carried out for five bioptic samples and the corresponding risk scores were within the 5%-95% quantile range of the normal distribution of the risk scores as defined by the training and validation cohorts of the primarily resected tumors (supplementary Figure <ref type="figure">S3</ref>, available at Annals of Oncology online).</s></p><p><s>The prognostic score and MSI MSI was found in 23 of 290 (8%) analyzed cases.</s><s>A higher frequency of low-risk patients was found in the MSI group compared with the microsatellite stable (MSS) group (48% versus 21%, P ¼ 0.003).</s><s>However, difference in OS of high-and low-risk patients in the MSS group was comparable to the differences in the training and validation set (each P &lt; 0.001).</s><s>The number of 23 MSI tumors was considered too small for further evaluation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Despite the improved survival among patients with gastric or gastro-esophageal junction carcinomas treated by multimodal treatment regimens, a substantial number of patients do not benefit from this therapy <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">15]</ref>.</s><s>Thus, the selection of the patients to treat or not to treat before surgery is crucial to prevent underand overtreatments and to optimize the benefit of the patients.</s></p><p><s>Criteria for the initiation of a pre-/perioperative chemotherapy are mainly based on clinical tumor stage.</s><s>Clinical staging is investigator dependent and shows a relatively high variability depending on the methods used.</s><s>In experienced hands clinical staging is of some prognostic impact, however, additional investigator-independent factors are strongly warranted <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref>.</s><s>In this study, we addressed this issue and we report for the first time to our knowledge the successful establishment and validation of a prognostic scoring system including gene expression data and clinical characteristics of the patients, which are available before the start of a pre-/perioperative chemotherapy.</s><s>This makes our scoring system potentially useful to guide or support therapeutic decisions in this context and represents a risk classification system, which could contribute to a more reliable patient selection for pre-/perioperative chemotherapy than based on clinical staging alone.</s></p><p><s>For establishing this scoring system we used a rather diverse sample pool including GC and AEG II/III patients, with and without pre-/perioperative chemotherapy.</s><s>We demonstrate that validation was successful, not only in a nonoverlapping, comparably heterogeneous patient cohort, but also in the subgroups of patients who were treated or not treated by CTx.</s><s>The most impressive separation was seen in the subgroup of patients not treated by CTx and stratified according to the histopathologic tumor type.</s><s>Of note, in the group with nonintestinal GC, 94% of the low-risk patients were still alive delineating these patients as prime candidates for immediate surgical resection and not for aggressive multimodal therapy regimens.</s><s>Taken together the establishment of the scoring system in a heterogeneous group of patients from two medical centers and the successful validation in an independent second cohort as well as in more homogeneous subgroups of patients underlines the robustness and prognostic significance of the risk score.</s><s>Furthermore, patients risk profiles are determined by the analysis of only four genes and by readily available clinical factors.</s><s>This together with an easy to handle nomogram distinguishes the scoring system as a convenient and economic tool appropriate for translation into clinical practice.</s></p><p><s>Our study also has some limitations.</s><s>First, it is a retrospective study and the results should be confirmed prospectively.</s><s>Second, we used resected tumor specimens to measure gene expression to build a prognostic model with pretherapeutic clinical characteristics of the patients.</s><s>However, for an application in daily clinical practice only pretherapeutic biopsies would be available and had to be used.</s><s>This raises the question about the representability of gene expression in the tissues given the known problem of intratumor heterogeneity.</s><s>To address this issue, we analyzed 50 different tumor areas from 10 patients as surrogates for biopsies.</s><s>The resulting reliability of classification was calculated at 93%, which could be potentially increased to 95% by using an average score derived from three biopsies.</s><s>This is essentially in line with the recommendation to analyze at least three biopsy fragments to precisely predict HER2 or cMET status in GC with a false negative risk in the range of 5% <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In our study, gene expressions of CTNNB1, CCL5, EXOSC3 and LZTR1 contribute to the scoring system and a prognostic relevance of these genes has been demonstrated for GC previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">18]</ref>.</s><s>CTNNB1 (b-catenin) is a key molecule in the Wnt signaling pathway and Wnt pathway activation has been shown to be associated with decreased patients' survival <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref>.</s><s>Chemokine ligand 5 (CCL5) is part of a complex inflammatory network and seems to be involved in GC progression and metastasis <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref>.</s><s>EXOSC3 is a component of the exosome and is important for RNA processing and degradation and LZTR1 is a probable transcriptional regulator.</s><s>The functional role of both of these genes in gastric carcinogenesis is largely unclear.</s></p><p><s>Regarding MSI, OS of the high-and low-risk patients in the MSS group was similar compared with OS of both groups in the training and validation set, which indicates, that risk stratification is independent of the MSI status.</s><s>The higher frequency of low-risk patients among the MSI group, points to an overlap between these groups, which may be due to some functional relationship.</s></p><p><s>Gene expression-based predictive or prognostic scoring systems have been described for various tumors entities including GC <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21]</ref>.</s><s>For example, a particular gene expression signature has been shown to be relevant to predict clinical outcome for GC patients treated with chemotherapy and a six-gene expression signature was developed for the classification of GC patients with a high or low risk for relapse <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>.</s><s>Gene expression-based models to predict the recently described subgroups of GC have been demonstrated to successfully stratify the patients by survival and outcome to adjuvant chemotherapy <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>However, none of them addressed the question to select patients in the context of pre-/perioperative CTx or combined gene expression with clinically relevant patients' characteristics.</s></p><p><s>Taken together, our study demonstrates the establishment and validation of a prognostic scoring system using gene expression and pretherapeutically available clinical parameters of the patients.</s><s>Thus, prospective validation assumed, these findings could substantially contribute to an improved selection and management of GC patients eligible for perioperative chemotherapy.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>NFigure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Overview of study enrollment.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Discrimination of patients' survival by the risk score.</s><s>(A) ROC curves of the risk score in the training cohort at different time points.</s><s>Kaplan-Meier curves of the high-and low-risk patients of the different cohorts and subgroups; (B) training cohort; (C) validation cohort; (D) pre-/perioperative CTx validation cohort; (E) primarily resected validation cohort; (F) intestinal-type subgroup of the primary resected validation cohort only; (G) nonintestinal-type subgroup of the primarily resected validation cohort only.</s><s>All P-values: log-rank test.</s><s>Kaplan-Meier curves are cut at 60 months for better visibility; full follow-up data were used for all calculations.</s><s>Dotted lines represent 95% confidence intervals.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,182.87,504.77,109.88,109.46" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="130">| Bauer et al. Volume 29 | Issue 1 | 2018</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="132">| Bauer et al. Volume 29 | Issue 1 | 2018</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p><s>Federal Ministry of Education and Research, BMBF, Germany (Grant no.</s><s>FKZ 03V0850 for the Technical University Munich, Germany and FKZ 03V0851 for the University Heidelberg, Germany).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disclosure</head><p><s>WW has a consulting role for Novartis/Pfizer, BMS, MSD, Roche, Boehringer Ingelheim and has research funding from Roche, AZ and Novartis.</s><s>All remaining authors have declared no conflicts of interest.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perioperative chemotherapy versus surgery alone for resectable gastroesophageal cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cunningham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Allum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Stenning</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">355</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perioperative chemotherapy compared with surgery alone for resectable gastroesophageal adenocarcinoma: an FNCLCC and FFCD multicenter phase III trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ychou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Boige</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Pignon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1715" to="1721" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gastric cancer: ESMO Clinical Practice Guidelines for diagnosis, treatment and follow-up</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Smyth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Verheij</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Allum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perioperative chemotherapy with docetaxel, oxaliplatin, and fluorouracil/leucovorin (FLOT) versus epirubicin, cisplatin, and fluorouracil or capecitabine (ECF/ECX) for resectable gastric or gastroesophageal junction (GEJ) adenocarcinoma (FLOT4-AIO): A multicenter, randomized phase 3 trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Al-Batran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Homann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schmalenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4004</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">German S3-guideline &quot;Diagnosis and treatment of esophagogastric cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moehler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Al-Batran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Andus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Z Gastroenterol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">04</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="461" to="531" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinically staged cT2 adenocarcinomas of the gastroesophageal junction: accuracy of staging and therapeutic consequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Vallbohmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sisic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Blank</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncol Res Treat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expression profiling of stem cellrelated genes in neoadjuvant-treated gastric cancer: a NOTCH2, GSK3B and beta-catenin gene signature predicts survival</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Langer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e44566</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gene expression signature-based prognostic risk score in gastric cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cheong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1850" to="1857" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Three-gene predictor of clinical outcome for gastric cancer patients treated with chemotherapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacogenomics J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="127" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fibroblast growth factor receptor 2 gene amplification status and its clinicopathologic significance in gastric carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Min</forename><surname>Sy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum Pathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1559" to="1566" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expression of group IIA phospholipase A2 is an independent predictor of favorable outcome for patients with gastric cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum Pathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2020" to="2027" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A 4-gene signature predicts survival of patients with resected adenocarcinoma of the esophagus, junction, and gastric cardia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rees</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hardwick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gastroenterology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1995" to="2004" />
			<date type="published" when="1915">2010. e1915</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cancer Genome Atlas Research Network. Comprehensive molecular characterization of gastric adenocarcinoma</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">513</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="202" to="209" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Classification of adenocarcinoma of the oesophagogastric junction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Siewert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Stein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1457" to="1459" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Significance of histopathological tumor regression after neoadjuvant chemotherapy in gastric adenocarcinomas: a summary of 480 cases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Langer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Reim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">253</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="934" to="939" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of pretherapeutic routine clinical staging for the individualization of treatment in gastric cancer patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Blank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Blaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schaible</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Langenbecks Arch Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">397</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ideal number of biopsy tumor fragments for predicting HER2 status in gastric carcinoma resection specimens</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Van Vrancken</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncotarget</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38372" to="38380" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The inflammatory chemokine CCL5 and cancer progression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Aldinucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Colombatti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mediators Inflamm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">292376</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oncogenic pathway combinations predict clinical prognosis in gastric cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ooi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ivanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1000676</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nanostring-based multigene assay to predict recurrence for gastric cancer patients after surgery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Do</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e90133</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intrinsic subtypes of gastric cancer, based on gene expression pattern, predict survival and respond differently to chemotherapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ivanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gastroenterology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="476" to="485" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical significance of four molecular subtypes of gastric cancer identified by the Cancer Genome Atlas Project</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Sohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Jang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4441" to="4444" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
