<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sip1 Downstream Effector ninein Controls Neocortical Axonal Growth, Ipsilateral Branching, and Microtubule Growth and Stability</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Swathi</forename><surname>Srivatsa</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute for Cell and Neurobiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Anatomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´-Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Virchowweg 6</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Experimental Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Hermann-Rein-Strasse 3, 37075 Go ¨ttingen</addrLine>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Srinivas</forename><surname>Parthasarathy</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute for Cell and Neurobiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Anatomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´-Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Virchowweg 6</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Experimental Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Hermann-Rein-Strasse 3, 37075 Go ¨ttingen</addrLine>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zolta</forename><surname>´n Molna</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Physiology, Anatomy, and Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Le Gros Clark Building</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Oxford</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>OX1 3OX</postCode>
									<settlement>Oxford</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Victor</forename><surname>Tarabykin</surname></persName>
							<email>victor.tarabykin@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute for Cell and Neurobiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Anatomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´-Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Virchowweg 6</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sip1 Downstream Effector ninein Controls Neocortical Axonal Growth, Ipsilateral Branching, and Microtubule Growth and Stability</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">028260748C15D6B640E0A61FFE66B8C9</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.neuron.2015.01.018</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:42+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Highlights d Sip1 controls the formation of long-and short-range neocortical projections d Sip1 exerts cell-autonomous control over axon elongation and branch formation d It acts through its direct downstream target ninein, a microtubule binding protein d Ninein in turn influences microtubule stability and dynamics in neocortical axons</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p><s>Sip1 (Zfhx1b, Zeb2) is a zinc-finger transcription factor whose heterozygous mutations cause the Mowat-Wilson syndrome (MWS) in humans.</s><s>MWS patients are characterized by multiple congenital abnormalities, intellectual disability, and epilepsy, frequently accompanied by agenesis of the corpus callosum (CC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Garavelli and Mainardi, 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">Wilson et al., 2003)</ref>.</s><s>Within the mouse neocortex, onset of Sip1 expression corresponds to the appearance of the first set of postmitotic cells at E12.5 and expands with the expansion of the cortical plate (CP) <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Seuntjens et al., 2009)</ref>.</s><s>Sip1 deletion in the mouse CNS during development was shown to cause multiple developmental disturbances including hippocampal degeneration <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Miquelajauregui et al., 2007)</ref>, abnormal specification of cortical pyramidal neurons and interneurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(McKinsey et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Seuntjens et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">van den Berghe et al., 2013)</ref>, and abnormal myelination <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Weng et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>Although it has been reported that both MWS pa-tients and Sip1-deficient mice show agenesis of the CC <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Miquelajauregui et al., 2007)</ref>, the role of Sip1 in axonal growth and navigation has not been dissected.</s><s>Based on their origin and projection site, neocortical axons can be broadly classified as intercortical and corticofugal projections <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Molyneaux et al., 2007)</ref>.</s><s>Intercortical connections include the CC and the anterior commissure (AC).</s><s>The corticofugal connections include the corticothalamic tract (CT) and the corticospinal tract (CST) <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Fame et al., 2011)</ref>.</s><s>Apart from these long-range projections, ipsilateral intracortical connections are also present that help in coordinating information within the cortical hemisphere.</s><s>Understanding the cellular and molecular mechanisms governing the establishment of these connections is important for understanding brain function <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Courchet et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Wang et al., 2007)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In this study we have examined the role of the transcription factor Sip1 in establishing cortical connections.</s><s>We show that Sip1 is not only required for CC formation but also contributes to the establishment of other cortical axonal tracts like AC and CST.</s><s>Sip1 acts cell-autonomously to control CC and CST formation by regulating axonal growth rate.</s><s>Sip1 also controls ipsilateral axonal collateral formation in vivo.</s><s>Furthermore, we identified ninein, a microtubule (MT) minus-end binding protein, to be a direct target of Sip1 transcriptional regulation.</s><s>Through ninein gain-and loss-of-function experiments we have shown that ninein controls axonal growth rate in cortical projection neurons.</s><s>We further show that ninein in turn can stabilize MTs and facilitate MT growth rate in cortical neurons.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cortical Axonal Tracts Are Severely Affected in the Sip1</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conditional Mutant</head><p><s>In order to address the role of Sip1 in the development of cortical axonal tracts, we deleted Sip1 conditionally in pyramidal neurons using a Nex Cre mouse line <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Goebbels et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Higashi et al., 2002)</ref>.</s><s>We examined Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre/wt mutants for alterations in axonal tracts at E18.5 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>) and P2 (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1A</ref> available online).</s><s>Commissural connections, namely the CC and AC, were absent in the Sip1 mutant.</s><s>The callosal fibers formed Probst bundles instead.</s><s>Interestingly, the hippocampal commissure (HC) was present in the Sip1 mutant.</s><s>Sip1 mutants also showed defects in dorsal midline closure at the region of CC, while ventral to the region of callosal crossing, the midline closure was complete and was comparable to the controls (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>).</s><s>To further characterize the neocortical connectivity defects in the Sip1 mutant, we performed carbocyanine dye tracing by placing DiI crystals in the somatosensory, motor, and visual cortex of control and Sip1 mutant brains harvested (A) Nissl staining at E18.5 reveals that the CC (arrows) and the AC (double arrowhead) are absent in the Sip1 mutant, while the HC (arrowhead) is unaffected.</s><s>The CC axons in the Sip1 mutant instead form Probst bundles (arrows).</s><s>Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre brains show defects in dorsal midline closure.</s><s>Higher-magnification images correspond to the boxed regions.</s><s>Dotted and solid lines indicate unfused and fused regions of the midline, respectively.</s><s>In the Sip1 fl/wt Nex Cre brains, while the midline dorsal to the CC remains unfused (red dotted line), midline fusion has taken place in the region of the CC crossing (blue line) and further ventrally (green line).</s><s>In the Sip1 mutant brains the entire dorsal midline remains unfused (red and blue dotted line, arrows).</s><s>Ventral fusion is complete (green line).</s><s>Scale bars, 1 mm (lowermagnification images), 0.5 mm (higher-magnification images).</s><s>(B) Anterograde DiI labeling from the putative somatosensory and motor cortex at P5 confirms the absence of the CC in the Sip1 mutant.</s><s>The corticothalamic tract (CT) is unaffected.</s><s>The CST is almost absent in the Sip1 mutant brains, with almost no fibers passing through the CP.</s><s>(C) Retrograde DiI labeling from the thalamus and CP reconfirms the presence of CT and absence of CST axons, respectively, in the Sip1 mutants.</s><s>Inset boxes show crystal placement.</s><s>Scale bars, 1 mm (lower magnification images), 0.5 mm (high-magnification images) (see also Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1</ref>).</s><s>NCx, neocortex; Th, thalamus.</s><s>at P5. Tracing confirmed the absence of the CC in the mutants (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>).</s><s>Examining the corticofugal connections in the Sip1 mutant revealed that CT was unaltered, as axons could be traced passing through the internal capsule into the thalamus.</s><s>Back-labeled thalamic neurons could also be visualized indicating the presence of intact thalamo-cortical fibers (TC) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>).</s><s>CST, on the other hand, was completely absent in the Sip1 mutants, where almost no axons could be seen passing through the cerebral peduncle (CP) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>).</s><s>The presence of the CT and absence of the CST in the Sip1 mutant was also confirmed by retrograde DiI tracing from the ventrobasal complex of the thalamus and the CP, respectively, at P5.</s><s>In the control brains, layer VI, VIb, and V neurons were back-labeled from the thalamus, and layer V neurons were exclusively back-labeled from the CP.</s><s>On the other hand, in the Sip1 mutant brains, while layer VI, VIb, and V neurons were back-labeled from the thalamus, hardly any layer V neurons could be back-labeled from the CP (legend continued on next page) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref>).</s><s>Previous work from our laboratory showed that due to non-cell-autonomous effects of Sip1 deletion, deep-layer neurons are reduced in the Sip1 mutants when compared to controls <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Seuntjens et al., 2009)</ref>.</s><s>To verify whether the loss of the CST was due to the reduction in layer V population, we immunostained the back-labeled sections against Ctip2.</s><s>Colocalizing Ctip2-positive and DiI-positive cells showed that, although reduced, a significant number of Ctip2-positive layer V neurons were present in the Sip1 mutant but failed to project through the CST.</s><s>This indicated that the lack of formation of the CST was not due to the absence of layer V neurons but rather to projection defects (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1B</ref>).</s><s>Additionally, staining Sip1 fl/wt Nex Cre/wt and Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre/wt sections for cleaved caspase-3, a marker of apoptotic cell death, at E18.5 showed that there was no apparent cell death in the Sip1 mutant cortex compared to the control (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1C</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mosaic Deletion of Sip1 Affects CC and CST Formation</head><p><s>While the lack of dorsal midline closure in the Sip1 mutants might be involved in causing the absence of CC, we wanted to determine if Sip1 also played a cell-autonomous role in the formation of cortical projections.</s><s>We electroporated a GFP-IRES-Cre plasmid expressed under the ubiquitin promoter in Sip1 fl/wt and Sip1 fl/fl embryos at E12.5 and harvested the embryos at E18.5.</s><s>We confirmed the mosaic deletion of Sip1 in the Creexpressing cells in the Sip1 fl/fl cortex (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2</ref>).</s><s>This approach made it possible to study the in vivo behavior of mutant axons within a wild-type environment.</s><s>While the GFP-positive axons in the Sip1 fl/wt embryos could be traced passing through the CC into the contralateral hemisphere, the Cre/GFP-positive and hence Sip1-negative axons in the Sip1 fl/fl embryos could not form the CC, and almost no GFP-positive fibers could be detected at the midline (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>).</s><s>It is noteworthy that Sip1negative/GFP-positive fibers in the Sip1 fl/fl brain were unable to project across the midline even though GFP negative; wildtype axons (stained with anti-L1 antibody) formed an intact CC.</s><s>Since neurons from layer V as well as UL neurons contribute to the formation of the CC <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Fame et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Srivatsa et al., 2014)</ref>, electroporation of GFP-IRES-Cre at E12.5 would target a subset of both these populations.</s><s>Thus, the cell-autonomous requirement of Sip1 for the formation of the CC applies to callosally projecting neurons of all layers.</s><s>Quantifying the relative fluorescence area of the callosal axons crossing the midline with respect to the fluorescence area of the electroporated region showed a 99% decrease in Sip1 fl/fl embryos when compared to Sip1 fl/wt embryos (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To determine if the corticospinal projection neurons were similarly affected on Sip1 deletion, we electroporated Sip1 fl/wt and Sip1 fl/fl embryos at E12.5 and studied the CST at E17.5, a stage where a majority of wild-type CST projections have passed through the CP.</s><s>GFP-positive projections could be traced at the level of the CP in the Sip1 fl/wt but not in the Sip1 fl/fl brain, indicating that in the absence of Sip1 the CST was also not formed (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>).</s><s>In order to determine if the lack of CC and CST at E18.5 and E17.5, respectively, in the Sip1 fl/fl mice was due to a delay in the axonal growth of Sip1-deficient neocortical neurons, we electroporated Sip1 fl/fl and Sip1 fl/wt brains with GFP-IRES-Cre at E12.5 and harvested the brains at P7.</s><s>In these experiments Sip1-deficient callosal fibers formed both the CC and the CST (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>).</s><s>Therefore, Sip1 cell-autonomously controls axonal growth rate but not axonal navigation, as the defects in CC and CST formation were not observed at later developmental stages.</s></p><p><s>Sip1-Deficient UL Neurons Show Defects in the Formation of Intracortical Axon Collaterals UL neurons, apart from projecting to the contralateral cortex through the CC and making synaptic contacts with contralateral neurons, also form axonal branches and hence synaptic connections with ipsilateral layer V neurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Burkhalter, 1989;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Kritzer and Goldman-Rakic, 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Thomson and Lamy, 2007)</ref>.</s><s>Since the lack of Sip1 affected axonal growth through the CC and CST, we wanted to test whether Sip1 deficiency also affects the formation of ipsilateral axonal collaterals.</s><s>First, in order to investigate the normal course of collateral formation of UL neurons on layer V, we electroporated an eGFP expressing plasmid at E15.5 in wild-type neocortex and harvested the embryos subsequently at postnatal stages ranging from P0 to P7.</s><s>We observed that between P0 and P3 as the UL neurons migrate into the CP and take up their final position in the cortex, they project axons to the white matter (WM) with no visible axonal collaterals.</s><s>By P4, the first branches of ipsilateral axonal collaterals could be seen at the level of layer V, demarcated by Ctip2-positive cells (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A</ref>).</s><s>Between P4 and P7, there was a steady increase in the density of these axonal branches.</s><s>Hence, ipsilateral branching of UL axons commences at P4 and is very prominent at P7 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A</ref>).</s></p><p><s>We then electroporated a GFP-IRES-Cre plasmid into Sip1 fl/fl and Sip1 fl/wt embryos at E15.5 and harvested the pups at P7, a stage when the ipsilateral axonal collaterals are normally well established.</s><s>We observed that while the axons in the Sip1 fl/wt cortex branched to form a dense network at layer V, Sip1 lacking UL neurons in the Sip1 fl/fl brains were seen sending axons to the WM without forming collaterals at layer V (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3B</ref>).</s><s>We quantified the fluorescent area of the axonal collateral at layer V within a radial unit relative to the number of electroporated neurons and observed a 5.8-fold decrease in the relative fluorescence area in Sip1 fl/fl embryos when compared to Sip1 fl/wt embryos (B) IUE of GFP-IRES-Cre in Sip1 fl/wt and Sip1 fl/fl embryos at E12.5 and analysis at E17.5.</s><s>Rostral images depict the electroporation site.</s><s>Scale bar, 800 mm.</s><s>Highermagnification images correspond to the CP.</s><s>Scale bar, 200 mm.</s><s>GFP-positive axons of the Sip1 fl/wt brains pass through the CP, while GFP-positive axons of the Sip1 fl/fl brains do not.</s><s>(C) Analysis of P7 Sip1 fl/wt and Sip1 fl/fl brains electroporated with GFP-IRES-Cre at E12.5.</s><s>The GFP-positive axons cross the midline in both Sip1 fl/wt and Sip1 fl/fl brains.</s><s>Scale bar, 1 mm.</s><s>Quantification of the CC fluorescence area at the midline relative to the electroporated fluorescence area at P7, mean ± SD: Sip1 fl/wt = 0.0569 ± 0.0141, Sip1 fl/fl = 0.0356 ± 0.0085, p value = 0.1039, Student's t test, n = 3. (D) GFP and L1 staining on caudal sections of P7 Sip1 fl/wt and Sip1 fl/fl brains electroporated with GFP-IRES-Cre at E12.5.</s><s>GFP-positive axons of wild-type and Sip1-deficient neurons project through the CP (see also Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2</ref>).</s></p><p><s>(Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C</ref>).</s><s>In order to determine if the lack of formation of the axonal branches at P7 was due to a delay in branch formation similar to the axonal growth delay, we electroporated GFP-IRES-Cre at E15.5 in Sip1 fl/fl and Sip1 fl/wt embryos and analyzed the brains at P14.</s><s>We observed that at this stage the Sip1-deficient UL neurons formed ipsilateral axon collaterals at layer V, comparable to corresponding Sip1 fl/wt brains (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S3</ref>).</s><s>Therefore, these experiments indicate that Sip1 cell-autonomously controls the timing of intracortical axonal branch formation.</s></p><p><s>Sip1 Controls the Expression of the Microtubule-Associated Protein ninein through Direct Binding to the ninein Enhancer In order to identify Sip1 targets that control axonal growth and collateral formation, we studied previously performed and pub- (A) IUE of eGFP at E15.5 in wild-type embryos and subsequent immunohistochemistry on harvested tissue at P0, P2, P3, P4, P5, and P7 with anti-GFP and anti-Ctip2 antibody.</s><s>Axons of UL neurons do not branch until P3 at layer V. Collateral branches start to form at P4 at the level of layer V neurons and continue to increase at later stages (boxed region).</s><s>Scale bar, 200 mm.</s><s>The higher-magnification images correspond to a region in Layer V. Scale bar, 50 mm.</s><s>(B) IUE of GFP-IRES-Cre at E15.5 in Sip1 fl/wt and Sip1 fl/fl embryos and analysis at P7 shows that Sip1-negative neurons do not form ipsilateral axon collaterals while control neurons branch robustly.</s><s>Higher-magnification images correspond to a region in Layer V. Scale bar, 200 mm.</s><s>(C) Quantification of the extent of branching at the level of layer V neurons between Sip1 fl/wt and Sip1 fl/fl sections relative to the number of cells electroporated, mean ± SD: Sip1 fl/wt = 850.78</s><s>± 78.598, Sip1 fl/fl = 147.05</s><s>± 57.909, p value = 0.0003, Student's t test, n = 3 (see also Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S3</ref>).</s><s>lished microarray analysis conducted at E14.5 to identify genes with altered expression in the Sip1 deficient cortex (GEO accession number GSE16699; <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Seuntjens et al., 2009)</ref>.</s><s>Since Sip1 deletion had effects on both DL neurons (CC and CST forming) and UL neurons (CC and ipsilateral collateral forming), we presumed that analyzing differential expression of genes at E14.5 could reveal a potential target.</s><s>We initially restricted our search to candidates that belong to axon guidance molecules or cytoskeletal proteins, as these groups of molecules have previously been shown to affect axon growth, guidance, and branching.</s><s>The microarray analysis revealed that ninein, a centrosome and MT minus-end binding protein, was downregulated in the absence of Sip1.</s><s>We verified this finding by performing an immunohistological staining with an anti-ninein antibody on E16.5 control and Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre/wt embryos.</s><s>Within the wild-type neocortex, ninein was strongly expressed in the CP with no laminar restriction and in the ventricular zone (VZ) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4A</ref>).</s><s>Expression of ninein was also detected within the WM in the control brains.</s><s>In the Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre/wt mutant, a severe downregulation of ninein expression in the CP as well as in the WM of the cortex could be observed.</s><s>The expression of ninein in the VZ, where neither Sip1 nor Nex is expressed, was unaltered (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4A</ref>).</s><s>To test the expression of ninein at postnatal stages relevant to layer V axon collateral formation, we performed western blot analysis on cortical lysates from P0, P3, P4, and P7 brains.</s><s>Ninein was expressed in all the stages tested (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S4A</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To test whether Sip1 activates ninein expression directly or indirectly, we performed chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) assay with an anti-Sip1 antibody on wild-type and Sip1 mutant cortices.</s><s>The immunoprecipitated chromatin was analyzed through qRT-PCR for the presence of six different genomic regions, denoted as Nin-P1 to Nin-P6 within 25 Kb upstream of the ninein transcription start site (TSS).</s><s>These regions contained the Sip1 consensus binding sequence CACCT(G) <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Verschueren et al., 1999)</ref>.</s><s>The ChIP assay showed 7-to 10-fold enrichment in all six regions tested with wild-type tissue (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B</ref>).</s><s>Sip1 mutant cortex showed no enrichment.</s><s>We also tested for Sip1 enrichment in the Fgf9 enhancer region.</s><s>Fgf9 was previously shown to be upregulated in the Sip1 mutant but not to be a direct target (Seuntjens et al.,</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>and Activates Its Expression</head><p><s>(A) Immunohistochemistry using anti-ninein antibody shows that ninein is expressed in the cortical plate (CP), white matter (WM), and the ventricular zone (VZ) in the control brains at E16.5, but is downregulated in the CP as well as WM of Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre embryos.</s><s>The expression of ninein at the VZ is unaffected in the Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre embryos.</s><s>Scale bar, 100 mm.</s><s>MZ, marginal zone; IZ, intermediate zone.</s><s>(B) Six regions with Sip1 consensus-binding sequence within 25 Kb upstream of the ninein transcription start site (TSS) were selected: Nin-P1 (Distal) to Nin-P6 (proximal).</s><s>ChIP data shows significant enrichment in all six regions tested in wild-type tissue when compared to Sip1 mutant tissue.</s><s>Sip1 did not show any enrichment at the Fgf9 locus used as a negative control.</s><s>Mean ± SD; wild-type, n = 4: Nin-P1 = 9.73 ± 4.35, Nin-P2 = 7.45 ± 3.56, Nin-P3 = 7.69 ± 0.89, Nin-P4 = 7.47 ± 3.49, Nin-P5 = 7.24 ± 3.25, Nin-P6 = 8.97 ± 3.25; Fgf9 = 1.83 ± 1.27; Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre , n = 3: Nin-P1 = 0.80 ± 0.28, Nin-P2 = 0.76 ± 0.42, Nin-P3 = 0.92 ± 0.29, Nin-P4 = 0.93 ± 0.32, Nin-P5 = 0.76 ± 0.20, Nin-P6 = 1.04 ± 0.61, Fgf9 = 0.92 ± 0.07; p values (Student's t test), Nin-P1 = 0.0259, Nin-P2 = 0.0316, Nin-P3 = 0.0001, Nin-P4 = 0.0323, Nin-P5 = 0.0278, Nin-P6 = 0.009, Fgf9 = 0.342.</s><s>(C) The most proximal enhancer element was cloned upstream of gaussia luciferase called GL-Nin-P6.</s><s>A 2.6-fold increase in relative luminescence on Sip1 binding was observed.</s><s>Mean ± SD; GLuc = 0.039 ± 0.006, GLuc + Sip1 = 0.012 ± 0.001, n = 3; GL-Nin-P6 = 5.96 ± 0.990, GL-Nin-P6 + Sip1 = 15.72 ± 0.242; p value = 0.002, n = 3 (Student's t test) (see also Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S4</ref>).</s><s>2009).</s><s>We did not observe any enrichment at this locus (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To test the functionality of this binding, we performed luciferase assay in HEK293T cells with the ninein enhancer region most proximal to the TSS that was positive for Sip1 binding, i.e., Nin-P6.</s><s>In the presence of Sip1, Nin-P6 showed a significant upregulation of luciferase activity (2.6fold), thus confirming the functionality of Sip1 binding to the ninein locus (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4C</ref>).</s><s>Since distal genomic regions also showed Sip1 binding, we further tested the functional relevance of Sip1 binding to Nin-P1 and Nin-P4.</s><s>In the presence of Sip1, Nin-P1 showed a significant downregulation ($5.6-fold) of luciferase activity, while Nin-P4 did not show any significant change (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S4B</ref>).</s><s>These experiments together showed that Sip1 activates ninein expression through direct binding and that binding to a specific site close to the TSS is essential for Sip1 to function as a transcriptional activator.</s><s>It is also probable that the distal elements might not even belong to the active enhancer region, owing to their distance from the TSS or that the coactivator complex required for Sip1 to activate the transcription of ninein binds specifically to the proximal region.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ninein Is Present in All Cytoskeletal Compartments of Cortical Neurons and Influences Axonal Elongation In Vitro</head><p><s>It has been previously shown through expression of GFP-tagged ninein or using an anti-ninein antibody that ninein localizes to the somatodendritic compartment of neurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Baird et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Ohama and Hayashi, 2009)</ref>.</s><s>Since apart from the CP and VZ we also detected expression of ninein in the WM of the wildtype cortex at E16.5 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4A</ref>), we wanted to test if ninein also localizes to the axon and the axonal growth cone.</s><s>Hence, a plasmid expressing eGFP tagged ninein was cotransfected with a plasmid expressing dsRed into dissociated cortical neurons at DIV 1 (first day in vitro) and analyzed at DIV 2 or DIV 7. We observed that at DIV 2 eGFP-Ninein puncta were localized to the soma, dendrites, axon, and axonal growth cone (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5A</ref>).</s><s>Examining DIV 7 neurons also revealed a similar distribution of ninein (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5B</ref>).</s><s>Thus in addition to localizing to the dendrites and the soma, ninein also localizes to axons and axonal branches.</s></p><p><s>We wanted to test if ninein, being an MT binding protein that localizes to the axon and is downregulated in the Sip1 mutant, could influence axonal elongation.</s><s>First we tested if Sip1 deletion from neocortical neurons would affect axonal length in vitro.</s><s>Sip1 fl/wt and Sip1 fl/fl embryos were electroporated with a GFP-IRES-Cre plasmid at E14.5 and the brains were isolated at E17.5.</s><s>The electroporated region of the cortex was isolated and dissociated, and neurons were cultured for 2 days in vitro.</s><s>In utero electroporation (IUE) was used instead of plasmid transfection in order to delete Sip1 as early as possible.</s><s>The neurons were immunostained with antibodies against GFP and tau-1 to demarcate the axon.</s><s>We observed that the average length of the axon of Sip1-deficient neurons was significantly shorter when compared to wild-type neurons, thus reconfirming the cell-autonomous requirement of Sip1 for axon growth (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5C</ref>).</s><s>We also performed a similar experiment with hippocampal neurons from Sip1 fl/wt Nex Cre/wt and Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre/wt E17.5 brains and measured the axon length of these neurons at DIV 3. Similar to neocortical neurons, we observed that Sip1-deficient hippocampal neurons also showed a significant decrease in the average axonal length (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S5A</ref>).</s><s>To address whether ninein acts downstream of Sip1 to control axonal length, we restored ninein expression in Sip1-deficient cortical neurons by expressing a plasmid encoding eGFP-Ninein preceded by a floxed mCherry-polyA cassette, designated as pCAG-FMF-eGFPNinein, together with the GFP-IRES-Cre plasmid.</s><s>The expression of ninein only upon Cre activation was confirmed (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S5B</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Parthasarathy et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>Expressing ninein in Sip1-deficient cells significantly increased the average length of the axon when compared to Sip1-negative neurons, although it was not restored to wild-type levels (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5C</ref>).</s><s>We additionally performed ninein gain-of-function experiments by expressing ninein in wild-type neurons and measuring their axon length at DIV2.</s><s>We observed that overexpression of ninein marginally increases the average length of the axons (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S5C</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Restoration of ninein Expression in Sip1-Deficient</head><p><s>Neurons Rescues CC, CST, and Ipsilateral Axonal Collaterals Since re-expression of ninein could increase the axonal length of Sip1-deficient neurons in vitro, we wanted to test if ninein could also be the major effector of axonal growth and branching in vivo, downstream of Sip1.</s><s>We hence electroporated pCAG-FMF-eGFPNinein and GFP-IRES-Cre plasmid into Sip1 fl/wt and Sip1 fl/fl embryos at E12.5.</s><s>The brains were analyzed for CC formation at E18.5 and were compared with Sip1 fl/fl and Sip1 fl/wt brains examined previously, electroporated with only the GFP-IRES-Cre plasmid.</s><s>The deletion of Sip1 in Cre + ninein-expressing cells in the Sip1 fl/fl cortex was confirmed (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S6A</ref>).</s><s>Expressing ninein in the Sip1-deficient cells could rescue the CC, as the electroporated neurons were able to project their axons, across the midline into the contralateral hemisphere.</s><s>Similar to the in vitro rescue of axonal length, the in vivo rescue of the CC was partial, as both the proportion of GFP-positive axons crossing the midline and maximal axonal length at E18.5 were not restored to wild-type levels.</s><s>Unlike the in vitro experiments, there was no significant difference in CC thickness between control and ninein overexpressing wild-type brains <ref type="bibr">(Figures 6A and 6C)</ref>.</s><s>To ascertain if restoring ninein expression in Sip1-deficient corticofugal neurons could rescue the defects in the formation of the CST, we electroporated pCAG-FMF-eGFPNinein and GFP-IRES-Cre plasmids in Sip1 fl/fl and Sip1 fl/wt embryos at E12.5 and analyzed the GFP-positive corticofugal projections at E17.5.</s><s>Unlike in the case of Cre electroporation in the Sip1 fl/fl brains, where almost no axons could be seen passing through the CP at E17.5 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>), Cre + ninein electroporation in Sip1 fl/fl partially restored the CST (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S6B</ref>).</s><s>We further confirmed the cell-intrinsic role of ninein in CC formation by electroporating pCAG-FMF-eGFPNinein in control and Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre/wt mutant brains at E12.5.</s><s>We hypothesized that, since Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre/wt mutant brains show defects in midline closure, re-expression of ninein in a subset of neocortical neurons would not be able to rescue the CC, provided ninein specifically plays a cell-autonomous role in cortical neurons.</s><s>Sip1-negative but ninein-positive axons in the Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre/wt brains examined at E18.5 were unable to form the CC, stopping short of the midline crossing, thus confirming that ninein acts cell autonomously in cortical projection neurons to control axon elongation (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S6C</ref>).</s></p><p><s>In order to evaluate if ninein also influences the formation of UL neuron axonal collaterals at the level of layer V neurons, pCAG-FMF-eGFPNinein and GFP-IRES-Cre were electroporated into Sip1 fl/wt and Sip1 fl/fl embryos at E15.5, to specifically target UL neurons, and analyzed at P7. Previously examined Sip1 fl/fl and Sip1 fl/wt brains electroporated with only GFP-IRES-Cre plasmid were used as controls.</s><s>We observed that Sip1-deficient UL neurons, on expression of ninein, were able to form ipsilateral axonal collaterals at the level of layer V neurons, similar to the Sip1 fl/wt controls.</s><s>Ninein + GFP-IRES-Cre-expressing Sip1 fl/wt neurons did not show a significant difference in the extent of branching when compared to only GFP-IRES-Creexpressing Sip1 fl/wt neurons (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6B and 6D</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Downregulation of ninein Expression Phenocopies the Effects of Sip1 Loss, Both In Vitro and In Vivo</head><p><s>To address the role of ninein in axon growth and branching directly, we performed in vitro and in vivo loss-of-function experiments using an shRNA against ninein.</s><s>The efficiency of ninein downregulation by the shRNA used has been previously validated <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Wang et al., 2009)</ref>.</s><s>Cortical neurons expressing plasmids encoding shNinein and eGFP were dissociated and the lengths of the axons were measured at DIV 2. An shRNA against luciferase (shLuc + eGFP) was used as a control.</s><s>Similar to Sip1-negative neurons, ninein loss-of-function neurons also showed stunted axonal growth when compared to the controls (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7A</ref>).</s><s>To further evaluate the effect of silencing ninein in vivo, we electroporated shNinein or shLuc in wild-type embryos at E13.5 and analyzed the brains at E17.5 for the formation of CC and CST.</s><s>By E17.5, while shLuc-expressing neurons projected through the CC and across the midline, most shNinein expressing neurons could not (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7B</ref>).</s><s>Examining caudal sections also showed a similar effect on the CST, where GFPpositive axons could not be detected at the level of the CP in case of shNinein electroporation (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S7</ref>).</s><s>These observations were similar to the effects of mosaic deletion of Sip1 (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A  and 2B</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Furthermore, IUE of shLuc + eGFP or shNinein + eGFP at E15.5 and analysis of the brains at P7 showed that while shLuc-expressing neurons extended a robust mesh of axonal branches at layer V ipsilaterally, ninein-silenced neurons showed significantly lesser branching (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7C</ref>).</s><s>Comparing these results with Sip1-negative neurons (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3B</ref>) confirmed that direct downregulation of ninein has an effect on axonal branching similar to that of the loss of Sip1.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Slower Microtubule Growth Contributes to the Stunted Growth of Sip1-Deficient Axons and Is Controlled by ninein</head><p><s>Growth rate of the axon to a large extent is dependent on the growth and dynamics of inner cytoskeletal scaffold formed by MTs <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Conde and Ca ´ceres, 2009)</ref>.</s><s>We hypothesized that Sip1 may control the growth rate of axonal MTs through ninein.</s></p><p><s>To assess this, we used the MT plus-end binding protein EB3 fused with GFP and tracked GFP-EB3 comets through live-imaging experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Stepanova et al., 2003)</ref>.</s><s>Cre-and GFP-EB3-expressing Sip1 fl/wt or Sip1 fl/fl cortical neurons were cultured at E16.5 and imaged at DIV 2. GFP-EB3 comets from 13 to 16 neurons were analyzed per condition, and only the comets that could be tracked for 10 s or more were included in the analysis.</s><s>The average anterograde velocity of GFP-EB3 comets was significantly reduced in Sip1-deficient neurons (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8A</ref>; Movie S1 and Movie S2).</s><s>When we examined axons of Sip1-deficient neurons where ninein expression was restored (Sip fl/fl neurons expressing Cre + Ninein + GFP-EB3), we observed that the average anterograde velocity of GFP-EB3 comets was significantly higher than in the axons of Sip1-deficient neurons and was almost restored to wild-type levels (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8A</ref>; Movie S3).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ninein Influences the Stability of Axonal Microtubules</head><p><s>Apart from MT growth, MT stability is another important factor that alters the underlying cytoskeleton in a cell.</s><s>To understand whether ninein also contributes to the stability of the MTs, we performed nocodazole-mediated MT breakdown assay with Sip1 fl/fl neurons expressing either GFP-IRES-Cre or GFP-IRES-Cre + ninein and with wild-type neurons expressing either eGFP or eGFP + ninein or eGFP + shNinein.</s><s>These groups of neurons were exposed to 5 mM nocodazole for 2, 4, 6, and 8 hr, after which they were fixed and stained for acetylated tubulin (ac-tub), which labels stable MTs.</s><s>The proportion of cells that showed positive ac-tub staining within the axon and the other neurites was counted.</s><s>GFP and ac-tub co-staining on eGFP and eGFP + ninein-expressing wild-type neurons at 2 and 8 hr are shown as examples (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">8B</ref>).</s><s>The proportion of cells with stable MTs was calculated by averaging the percentage obtained from three different coverslips for each condition and time point.</s><s>We observed that with increasing exposure to nocodazole, Sip1-deficient neurons (GFP-IRES-Cre in Sip1 fl/fl neurons) and ninein loss-of-function neurons (eGFP + shNinein in wildtype neurons) showed a steep decline in the proportion of cells with stable MTs, ranging from around 78% at 2 hr and 42% at 6 hr and falling to 21% at 8 hr.</s><s>On the other hand, wild-type neurons (eGFP) showed significantly higher resistance to MT breakdown, where the proportion of cells with stable MTs ranged from 90% at 2 hr to 63% at 6 hr and falling to 22% at 8 hr.</s><s>Ninein overexpression in wild-type neurons (eGFP + ninein) drastically increased their resistance to MT breakdown where 85% of the cells contained stable MTs within the neurites even after 8 hr of nocodazole exposure.</s><s>Furthermore, reexpression of ninein in Sip1-deficient cells (GFP-IRES-Cre + Ninein in Sip1 fl/fl neurons) restored MT stability, with around 47% of neurons showing positive ac-tub staining after 8 hr (Fig- (B) E17.5 wild-type brains electroporated with shLuc + eGFP or shNinein + eGFP at E13.5 show that unlike the axonal projections of shLuc expressing neurons, which crossed the midline, the axonal projections of shNinein expressing neurons failed to do so.</s><s>Quantification of the fluorescence area at the midline relative to the electroporated fluorescence area, mean ± SD: shLuc (n = 4) = 0.692 ± 0.0566, shNinein (n = 3) = 0.0094 ± 0.0031, p value &lt; 0.001 (Student's t test).</s><s>(C) IUE of shLuc + eGFP or shNinein + eGFP at E15.5 in wild-type embryos and analysis at P7 shows that unlike the control brains, shNinein expressing neurons do not form robust ipsilateral axon collaterals at layer V.</s><s>The higher-magnification images correspond to the boxed region in Layer V. Scale bar, 200 mm.</s><s>Quantification of the extent of branching at the level of layer V relative to the number of cells electroporated, mean ± SD: shLuc (n = 4) = 965.168</s><s>± 42.269, shNinein (n = 4) = 340.184</s><s>± 86.160, p value &lt; 0.001 (Student's t test) (see also Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S7</ref>).</s><s>ure 8B).</s><s>Therefore, ninein positively influences the stability of MTs and Sip1 acts through ninein to affect MT stability in cortical neurons.</s><s>Additionally we also compared the ratio of the levels of acetylated tubulin (ac-tub) to the levels of tyrosinated tubulin (tyr-tub) through western blot analysis on E16.5 wild-type and Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre/wt cortical lysates.</s><s>While ac-tub is used as a marker for stable MTs, tyr-tub indicates the unstable MT population.</s><s>Although we did not detect a significant change in the ratios between wild-type and Sip1 mutant, the trend indicated a slight decrease in the Sip1 mutant (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">S8</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>Sip1 is a transcription factor that was shown to be a key regulator of critical developmental processes in the forebrain <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(McKinsey et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Miquelajauregui et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Nityanandam et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Seuntjens et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">van den Berghe et al., 2013)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Here we demonstrate that Sip1 also controls another critical developmental process, the formation of neocortical projections.</s><s>Multiple cortical axonal tracts are affected in the Sip1 mutant.</s><s>Sip1-deficient mice do not form CC, AC, and CST, while the CT tract does not seem to be affected.</s><s>At least with respect to CC, CST, and HC projection neurons, Sip1 deficiency has a cell-autonomous impact on the growth rate of axons.</s><s>Whether a similar mechanism is involved in the formation of the AC as well remains to be investigated.</s><s>In this study we have used mosaic deletion of Sip1 from neocortical neurons in order to detect the axon outgrowth defects with respect to the CC and CST in vivo.</s><s>Using a similar technique for studying the AC was challenging and inconclusive, as electroporations of the piriform cortex were very inconsistent in terms of extent and localization rostrocaudally.</s><s>This, added to the fact that loss of Sip1 affects the rate of growth of axons and not the axonal extension per se, made it extremely difficult to evaluate, in an unbiased manner, the extent of projection within the AC.</s><s>Nevertheless, we think that since neither the expression of Sip1 nor the expression of its downstream effector, ninein, is restricted to a specific subpopulation of cells within the CP at the time of cortical axonogenesis, and a similar mechanism seems to be controlling both commissural (CC) and corticofugal projections (CST), it is likely that such a Sip1mediated cell-autonomous mechanism could be a more general phenomenon, not restricted to one kind of projection neuron.</s><s>That said, the reason for CT projections to be the only cortical axonal tract unaffected in the Sip1 mutant remains to be understood.</s><s>Limited by our current knowledge, we can only speculate that this might be owing to CT axons being the only projections that rely on Sip1-independent noncortical axons (thalamocortical afferents) to aid in tract formation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Deck et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Nishizaki et al., 2014)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Certain apparent contradictions arise at the outset when comparing the Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre/wt mutants with the Sip1 mosaic deletion mutants.</s><s>First, although Cre electroporated neurons in the Sip1 fl/fl cortex are capable of forming the CC, albeit delayed in development, Sip1-deficient callosal neurons in the Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre/wt mutant do not cross the midline also at later stages.</s><s>Second, although Sip1-deficient hippocampal neurons show a similar cell-autonomous defect in axonal extension as that in Sip1-deficient callosal neurons, HC is present in Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre/wt mutants, while CC is not.</s><s>These discrepancies might be attributed to the midline closure defects observed in the Sip1 fl/fl Nex Cre/wt mutant and not in the mosaic deletion model, probably occurring due to non-cell-autonomous effects of Sip1 deletion.</s><s>While ventral to the CC, the midline closure is complete in the Sip1 mutant; the two hemispheres remain separated dorsally, providing a physical barrier for the callosal axons to cross to the contralateral side, thus resulting in the permanent absence of the CC.</s><s>The hippocampal axons that project ventral to the CC do not face such a physical barrier at the midline, and manage to project to the contralateral hemisphere.</s></p><p><s>We have previously shown using the Sip1 fl/fl Emx Cre/wt mutant mice that Sip1 deletion results in a progressive loss of the hippocampus <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Miquelajauregui et al., 2007)</ref>.</s><s>This is a degenerative defect resulting from progressive cell death with an onset from E16.5 onward and increasing postnatally.</s><s>At the developmental stages relevant to this study (E17.5-P7), the hippocampus and the HC are still present, with complete loss occurring only in juveniles, thus making the Sip1-associated hippocampal degeneration irrelevant to the events pertaining to the development of the HC, which occurs around E15.5/E16.5.</s></p><p><s>Neocortical axons frequently branch at specific locations in order to form synapses with multiple targets and establish correct neocortical circuitry (O' <ref type="bibr">Leary and Terashima, 1988)</ref>.</s><s>Different modes of axonal branch formation have been described in vivo, of which the interstitial mode refers to the axonal collateral budding out of the main axonal shaft many days after the growth cone has passed that region <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Acebes and Ferru ´s, 2000)</ref>.</s><s>In this study we have examined the formation of intracortical axonal collaterals by UL neurons on ipsilateral layer V neurons.</s><s>We have, to our knowledge, shown for the first time the time course of development of these intracortical collaterals.</s><s>Although the intercortical callosal projections of UL neurons cross over to the contralateral hemisphere by P0, the intracortical branch formation is initiated only by P4.</s><s>This delayed emergence of axonal collaterals suggests an interstitial mode of branch formation.</s><s>Interestingly, Sip1 also controls the timing of the ipsilateral axon collateral formation aiding in the establishment of intracortical connections as well.</s></p><p><s>The cell-autonomous inability of Sip1-deficient callosal neurons to project to the contralateral hemisphere at the correct developmental stage depends on the protein ninein.</s><s>Sip1 directly activates the expression of ninein in the cortex.</s><s>Ninein was discovered in nonneuronal cells as a centrosome-associated protein acting at MT minus end to help anchor the MTs to the centrosome <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Bouckson-Castaing et al., 1996)</ref>.</s><s>In polarized cells that show the presence of noncentrosomal MTs, ninein is also found in noncentrosomal locations in association with the MT minus end <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Mogensen et al., 2000)</ref>.</s><s>Within the neocortex, ninein is required for the self-renewal of neocortical progenitors in the mouse <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Wang et al., 2009)</ref>, and for maintenance of progenitor character by anchoring of MTs to the centrosome <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Shinohara et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Unlike in progenitors, where ninein is localized to the centrosome, in cortical neurons only noncentrosomal ninein has been observed, and its localization to only the somatodendritic compartment of the cell has been reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Ohama and Hayashi, 2009)</ref>.</s><s>The functional role of ninein in neurons has not been characterized so far.</s><s>In this study we have presented evidence, through immunohistochemistry (IHC) and expression of GFP-tagged protein, that ninein is also present in the axons of cortical neurons.</s><s>In vivo, ninein is expressed in the WM of the neocortex that corresponds to the fasciculated axons of pyramidal neurons.</s><s>In cultured cortical neurons, GFP-ninein could be observed in the somatodendritic compartments as well as in the axons and axonal collaterals.</s><s>These results hence suggest eGFP + ninein = 96.92%</s><s>± 1.35, eGFP + shNinein = 76.12% ± 3.4, Sip1 À/À = 78.48%</s><s>± 2.73, Sip1 À/À + Ninein = 95.63%</s><s>± 1.77; 4 hr: eGFP = 75.77%</s><s>± 5.00, eGFP + ninein = 94.61% ± 0.77, eGFP + shNinein = 64.31%</s><s>± 1.13, Sip1 À/À = 62.49% ± 2.02, Sip1 À/À + Ninein = 85.49% ± 2.95; 6 hr: eGFP = 64.09%</s><s>± 2.60, eGFP + ninein = 93.02%</s><s>± 2.88, eGFP + shNinein = 42.4% ± 1.78, Sip1 À/À = 50.03%</s><s>± 3.97, Sip1 À/À + Ninein = 73.54%</s><s>± 2.12; 8 hr: eGFP = 22.17% ± 5.41, eGFP + ninein = 85.04% ± 4.36 eGFP + shNinein = 24.60%</s><s>± 2.84 Sip1 À/À = 21.59%</s><s>± 0.71 Sip1 À/À + Ninein = 47.69% ± 0.89.</s><s>Two-way ANOVA p value: Sip1 À/À and eGFP = 0.0010, Sip1 À/À and Sip1 À/À + Ninein &lt; 0.001, Sip1 À/À and eGFP + shNinein = 0.2478, eGFP + shNinein and eGFP = 0.009, eGFP and eGFP + Ninein &lt; 0.001 (see also Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">S8</ref>).</s><s>that ninein plays a more extensive role in neurons that is not restricted to the soma and dendrites.</s></p><p><s>Our experiments with re-expression of ninein in Sip1-deficient neurons showed that ninein partially rescued the axon extension defects both in vitro and in vivo.</s><s>The lack of a complete rescue suggests that there should be other molecules downstream of Sip1 that are involved in the control of axonal growth.</s><s>It was also interesting to observe that axon collaterals formed by UL neurons at the level of Layer V neurons in the CP were completely restored on expressing ninein in the Sip1-deficient cells.</s><s>Furthermore, direct downregulation of ninein in wild-type neurons using an shRNA against ninein had a similar effect as Sip1 loss on axonal extension and branching.</s><s>These experiments together suggest that similar ninein-dependent microtubular mechanisms might be involved in the process of axonal elongation and branching.</s></p><p><s>Neurons are strongly polarized cells, and the bulk of MTs in neurons are present as free MTs in axons and dendrites, which allows for their characteristic morphology and functionality <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Ahmad and Baas, 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Keating et al., 1997)</ref>.</s><s>It has been proposed that although the free MTs are not attached to the centrosome at the minus end, in order to remain stable, these MTs bind to other minus end-stabilizing molecules <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Keating and Borisy, 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Murphy et al., 1977;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Stearns and Kirschner, 1994;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Zheng et al., 1995)</ref>.</s><s>Although previous findings have indicated that centrosomeassociated ninein plays an important role as a stabilizing molecule for the radial MT asters <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Dammermann and</ref><ref type="bibr">Merdes, 2002, Mogensen et al., 2000)</ref>, the role of noncentrosomal ninein has not been investigated in great detail.</s><s>Here we have for the first time shown that noncentrosomal ninein plays an MT-stabilizing role in the axons of neurons.</s><s>Ninein loss of function, either through Sip1 deletion or direct downregulation through shNinein, severely reduces the stability of the MTs against nocodazole, an MT-destabilizing agent.</s><s>Re-expression of ninein in Sip1-deficient neurons or overexpressing ninein in wild-type neurons significantly increases their resistance to MT depolymerization.</s><s>These data correlate to the effects on axon extension and branching wherein conditions with reduced MT stability correspond to reduced axonal length/branching and increased stability to longer axons/more robust branching.</s><s>These experiments taken together also indicate that stability of MTs is an important contributing factor to the process of axon elongation and branch formation.</s></p><p><s>The MT cytoskeleton forms the inner scaffold of growing axons.</s><s>Hence the growth rate of MTs to a large extent determines the growth rate of the axon <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Conde and Ca ´ceres, 2009)</ref>.</s><s>As the growth rate of MTs at the plus end is faster than at the minus end, MT plus end dynamics serves as a good indicator of net MT growth rate <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Akhmanova and Steinmetz, 2008)</ref>.</s><s>EB3 being an MT plus-end binding protein enables the tracking of MT plus-end dynamics by using GFP-EB3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Stepanova et al., 2003)</ref>.</s><s>Plus-end dynamics of MTs was significantly slower in the absence of Sip1 but was restored to wild-type levels when ninein expression was restored, indicating that, apart from MT stability, ninein also influences MT growth.</s><s>The mechanism by which ninein, being a minus-end binding protein, influences the plus-end dynamics is not evident so far.</s><s>It could be hypothesized that ninein bound to the minus end of the MT primarily stabilizes the growing MT polymer to which new tubulin dimers are added, and in the absence of ninein, this MT lattice is rendered weak, hence reducing the rate at which polymerization takes place.</s><s>In support of this hypothesis, presence of MT-destabilizing factors such as nocodazole has been previously shown to reduce MT plus-end growth rate <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Vasquez et al., 1997)</ref>.</s><s>Also, a role for a minus-end binding protein in regulating the dynamics of the plus end has been shown with the g-TurC complex in Drosophila S2 cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Bouissou et al., 2009)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES</head><p><s>For list of antibodies, plasmids, and primers used, please refer to Supplemental Information.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mouse Mutants</head><p><s>All mouse experiments were carried out in compliance with German law approved by the Bezirksregierung Braunschweig and Landesamt fu ¨r Gesundheit und Soziales, Berlin.</s><s>Wild-type, Sip1 fl/wt Nex wt/wt , Sip1 fl/fl Nex wt/wt , and Sip1 fl/wt Nex Cre/wt were used interchangeably as controls.</s><s>For ease of depiction and consistency, controls have been labeled as Sip1 fl/wt Nex Cre in all figures.</s></p><p><s>DiI Labeling, Nissl Staining, and Immunohistochemistry Detailed methods for DiI labeling are described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Molna ´r et al., 2006.</ref></s><s>Nissl staining and IHC were done as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Miquelajauregui et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">Seuntjens et al., 2009)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>In Utero Electroporation</head><p><s>The procedure of IUE was performed as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Saito, 2006)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chromatin Immunoprecipitation Assay and Luciferase Assay</head><p><s>The ChIP-IT express kit (Active Motif) was used according to the manufacturer's instructions.</s><s>For the luciferase assay, the PCR products were cloned into pMCS-GL (Thermo Scientific) and transfected along with pCMV-alkaline phosphatase, with or without pCAG-Sip1 in HEK293T cells.</s><s>Forty-eight hours posttransfection, cell media were assayed using the Secrete-Pair Dual Luminescence assay kit (Genecopoeia) and Glomax luminescence reader (Promega).</s></p><p><s>Neuron Culture and Nocodazole Assay E16.5/E17.5 embryonic brains were isolated in 13 HBSS followed by trypsinization at 37 C for 30 min and DNase treatment (Worthington).</s><s>The tissue was then dissociated in Neurobasal media (GIBCO), centrifuged, and resuspended in warm Neurobasal media supplemented with Glutamax, Penicillin-Streptomycin, and B27 (GIBCO).</s><s>For the nocodazole assay on DIV 2 or DIV 3, 5 mM nocodazole in neurobasal complete medium was added to the neurons.</s><s>Coverslips were collected 2, 4, 6, and 8 hr after treatment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Microtubule Plus-End Tracking Using GFP EB3</head><p><s>Cortical neurons expressing GFP-EB3 were cultured on FluroDish tissue culture dish.</s><s>At DIV 2, live imaging of GFP-EB3 comets was performed using a Zeiss Spinning Disc system CXU-S1 at 1 fps for 200 s and analyzed using the Kymograph ImageJ plug-in.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Analysis</head><p><s>All data have been represented as mean ± SD.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SUPPLEMENTAL INFORMATION</head><p><s>Supplemental Information includes eight figures, three movies and Supplemental Experimental Procedures and can be found with this article at http:// dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2015.01.018.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Commissural and Corticofugal Connections Are Affected in the Sip1 Mutant</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,53.12,101.71,322.79,558.43" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Sip1-Deficient CC and CST Neurons Show Retarded Axonal Growth (A) IUE of GFP-IRES-Cre at E12.5 and analysis at E18.5 shows that GFP/Cre/Sip1-positive axons in Sip1 fl/wt embryos cross the midline, while GFP-positive/ Cre-positive/Sip1-negative axons in Sip1 fl/fl embryos do not.</s><s>Scale bar, 800 mm.</s><s>Higher-magnification images correspond to the midline.</s><s>Scale bar, 200 mm.</s><s>Quantification of the CC fluorescence area at the midline relative to the electroporated fluorescence area (mean ± SD): Sip1 fl/wt = 0.2656 ± 0.06457, Sip1 fl/fl = 0.0025 ± 0.0005, p value = 0.002, Student's t test, n = 3.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,95.70,101.59,418.28,562.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. Sip1-Deficient Upper-Layer Neurons Do Not Form Ipsilateral Intracortical Axon Collaterals to Layer V</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,59.75,101.71,322.79,444.36" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. Sip1 Directly Binds to the ninein Enhancer Region and Activates Its Expression</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,53.12,101.71,322.79,454.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. Ninein Localizes to the Axon and Rescues the Stunted Axonal Growth in Sip1-Deficient Neurons In Vitro (A) DIV 2 cortical dissociated neurons transfected at DIV 1 with eGFP-ninein, pCAG-dsRed and immunostained with anti tau-1 antibody show that eGFP-Ninein puncta are localized to the soma, dendrites, axon, and the axonal growth cone.</s><s>Scale bar, 20 mm.</s><s>Higher-magnification images correspond to the boxed regions.</s><s>Scale bar, 10 mm.</s><s>(B) DIV7 cortical neurons transfected at DIV1 with eGFP-ninein and pCAG-dsRed.</s><s>GFP-ninein puncta localize to axonal and dendritic branches.</s><s>Scale bar, 100 mm.</s><s>Higher-magnification images correspond to the boxed regions Scale bar, 20 mm.</s><s>(C) GFP-IRES-Cre expressing Sip1 fl/fl neurons at DIV2 have shorter axons when compared to Sip1 fl/wt neurons.</s><s>The axon length is rescued by coexpression of pCAG-FMF-eGFPNinein with GFP-IRES-Cre in Sip1 fl/fl neurons.</s><s>Scale bar, 50 mm.</s><s>Mean ± SD; Sip1 fl/wt + Cre (n = 258) = 379.43</s><s>± 89.09, Sip1 fl/fl + Cre (n = 233) = 241.36</s><s>± 75.51, Sip1 fl/fl + Cre + ninein (n = 166) = 322.41</s><s>± 72.82; all p values &lt; 0.001, Student's t test (see also Figure S5).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,59.75,101.71,322.79,456.89" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6.</s><s>Restoration of ninein Expression Rescues the CC and Ipsilateral Axonal Collateral Formation in Brains with Mosaic Deletion of Sip1 (A) pCAG-FMF-eGFPNinein coexpressed with GFP-IRES-Cre in Sip1 fl/wt and Sip1 fl/fl embryos at E12.5 and analyzed at E18.5.</s><s>GFP-positive axons project through the CC in Sip1 fl/fl brains expressing Cre + ninein, unlike Sip1 fl/fl brains expressing only Cre.</s><s>Scale bar, 800 mm.</s><s>Higher-magnification images correspond to the midline.</s><s>Scale bar, 200 mm.</s><s>(B) IUE of pCAG-FMF-eGFPNinein and GFP-IRES-Cre in Sip1 fl/wt and Sip1 fl/fl embryos at E15.5 and analysis at P7. Sip1 fl/fl brains with Cre + ninein coexpression form ipsilateral layer V axon collaterals, unlike Sip1 fl/fl brains expressing only Cre.</s><s>Higher-magnification images of boxed area in panel.</s><s>Scale bars, 200 mm.</s><s>(C) Quantification of the relative fluorescence area of the CC at the midline, mean ± SD: Sip1 fl/fl + Cre and ninein (n = 3) = 0.0972 ± 0.0215, compared to Sip1 fl/wt + Cre and ninein (n = 3) = 0.2170 ± 0.0594, p value = 0.0303 compared to Sip1 fl/fl + Cre (n = 3) = 0.0025 ± 0.0005, p value = 0.016, Sip1 fl/wt + Cre (n = 3) = 0.2656 ± 0.06457 compared to Sip1 fl/wt + Cre and ninein, p value = 0.3918 (Student's t test).</s><s>(D) Quantification of the axonal branching at layer V, mean ± SD: Sip1 fl/fl + Cre and ninein (n = 3) = 837.28</s><s>± 18.154, when compared to Sip1 fl/fl + Cre (n = 3) = 147.05</s><s>± 57.909, p value = 0.001, when compared to Sip1 fl/wt + Cre and ninein (n = 3) = 854.712</s><s>± 38.879, p value = 0.5351, Sip1 fl/wt + Cre (n = 3) = 850.78</s><s>± 78.598 when compared to Sip1 fl/wt + Cre and ninein, p value = 0.9430 (Student's t test) (see also Figure S6).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,59.75,101.71,322.79,448.38" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 7. Downregulation of ninein in Wild-Type Neurons Recapitulates the Phenotype of Sip1-Deficient Neurons (A) DIV 2 dissociated cortical wild-type neurons expressing shRNA against ninein (shNinein) have shorter axons when compared to neurons expressing shRNA against Luciferase (shLuc).</s><s>Scale bar, 50 mm.</s><s>Mean ± SD; shLuc (n = 235) = 422.379</s><s>± 111.399, shNinein (n = 220) = 340.771</s><s>± 105.867, p value &lt; 0.001, Student's t test.(B)</s><s>E17.5 wild-type brains electroporated with shLuc + eGFP or shNinein + eGFP at E13.5 show that unlike the axonal projections of shLuc expressing neurons, which crossed the midline, the axonal projections of shNinein expressing neurons failed to do so.</s><s>Quantification of the fluorescence area at the midline relative to the electroporated fluorescence area, mean ± SD: shLuc (n = 4) = 0.692 ± 0.0566, shNinein (n = 3) = 0.0094 ± 0.0031, p value &lt; 0.001 (Student's t test).</s><s>(C) IUE of shLuc + eGFP or shNinein + eGFP at E15.5 in wild-type embryos and analysis at P7 shows that unlike the control brains, shNinein expressing neurons do not form robust ipsilateral axon collaterals at layer V.</s><s>The higher-magnification images correspond to the boxed region in Layer V. Scale bar, 200 mm.</s><s>Quantification of the extent of branching at the level of layer V relative to the number of cells electroporated, mean ± SD: shLuc (n = 4) = 965.168</s><s>± 42.269, shNinein (n = 4) = 340.184</s><s>± 86.160, p value &lt; 0.001 (Student's t test) (see also FigureS7).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="11,53.12,101.71,322.79,451.67" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 8. Ninein Stabilizes Axonal Microtubules and Influences Microtubule Growth</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="12,59.75,101.59,490.31,487.11" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>A) Time series images tracking the movement of GFP-EB3 labeled +TIPs over 10 s in the axons of Cre-expressing Sip1 fl/wt and Sip1 fl/fl neurons and Cre + nineinexpressing Sip1 fl/fl neurons.</s><s>Kymographs, tracking the movement of GFP-EB3 comets over time, were plotted, and the average velocities of the GFP-EB3 comets were calculated.</s><s>Graph represents the average velocity (in pixels/second) of GFP-EB3 comets.</s><s>Mean ± SD; Sip1 fl/wt + Cre-expressing neurons = 1.65 ± 0.42, Sip1 fl/fl + Cre-expressing neurons = 1.40 ± 0.37, Sip1 fl/fl + ninein + Cre-expressing neurons = 1.59 ± 0.50.</s><s>Comparing control and Sip1-deficient neurons p value &lt; 0.001, Sip1-deficient neurons with and without ninein p value &lt; 0.001, control and Sip1-deficient neurons with ninein p value = 0.1663 (Student's t test).</s><s>(B) Panel shows example images of wild-type, eGFP, and ninein + eGFP-expressing neurons after 2 and 8 hr of Nocodazole exposure.</s><s>Ac-tubulin staining can be seen in the axons of both types of neurons (arrow heads) at 2 hr, but at 8 hr Ac-tubulin staining can be seen in the axons of ninein-overexpressing neurons, but not in control neurons (arrowheads).</s><s>Scale bar, 50 mm.</s><s>(C) Graph comparing the MT breakdown resistance of neurons against increasing duration of Nocodazole exposure between (a) wild-type, eGFP-expressing neurons, (b) ninein + eGFP-expressing neurons, (c) eGFP + shNinein-expressing neurons, (d) GFP-IRES-Cre-expressing Sip1 fl/fl neurons (Sip1 À/À ), and (e) GFP-IRES-Cre + Ninein-expressing Sip1 fl/fl neurons (Sip1 À/À + Ninein).</s><s>Both Sip1-deficient neurons and ninein-deficient neurons are significantly less resistant to nocodazole-mediated MT breakdown.</s><s>Re-expression of ninein in Sip1-deficient neurons restores MT stability.</s><s>Mean ± SD; 2 hr: eGFP = 89.56%</s><s>± 2.27, (legend continued on next page)</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="998">Neuron 85, 998-1012, March 4, 2015 ª2015 Elsevier Inc.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1002">Neuron 85, 998-1012, March 4, 2015 ª2015 Elsevier Inc.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Neuron 85, 998-1012, March 4, 2015 ª2015 Elsevier Inc. 1003</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1004">Neuron 85, 998-1012, March 4, 2015 ª2015 Elsevier Inc.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Neuron 85, 998-1012, March 4, 2015 ª2015 Elsevier Inc. 1005</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1006">Neuron 85, 998-1012, March 4, 2015 ª2015 Elsevier Inc.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Neuron 85, 998-1012, March 4, 2015 ª2015 Elsevier Inc. 1007</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>We would like to thank the following individuals for kindly gifting us with valuable plasmids and antibodies: Dr.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cellular and molecular features of axon collaterals and dendrites</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Acebes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ferru ´s</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="557" to="565" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microtubules released from the neuronal centrosome are transported into the axon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Baas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2761" to="2769" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tracking the ends: a dynamic protein network controls the fate of microtubule tips</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Akhmanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Steinmetz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distribution of the microtubule-related protein ninein in developing neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Baird</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Myers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mogensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Moss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Baas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuropharmacology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="677" to="683" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular characterisation of ninein, a new coiled-coil protein of the centrosome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Bouckson-Castaing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moudjou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ferguson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mucklow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Belkaid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Milon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Crocker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="190" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">gamma-Tubulin ring complexes regulate microtubule plus end dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bouissou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ve ´rollet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sousa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sampaio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Sunkel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Merdes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Raynaud-Messina</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">187</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="327" to="334" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intrinsic connections of rat primary visual cortex: laminar organization of axonal projections</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Burkhalter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comp. Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">279</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="186" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microtubule assembly, organization and dynamics in axons and dendrites</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Conde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ca ´ceres</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="319" to="332" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Terminal axon branching is regulated by the LKB1-NUAK1 kinase pathway via presynaptic mitochondrial capture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Courchet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Courchet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Liou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aizawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Polleux</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1510" to="1525" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assembly of centrosomal proteins and microtubule organization depends on PCM-1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dammermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Merdes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">159</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="266" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathfinding of corticothalamic axons relies on a rendezvous with thalamic projections</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Deck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lokmane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chauvet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mailhes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Keita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Niquille</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yoshida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yoshida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lebrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="472" to="484" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development, specification, and diversity of callosal projection neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fame</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Macdonald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Macklis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mowat-Wilson syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Garavelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mainardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Orphanet J. Rare Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">42</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic targeting of principal neurons in neocortex and hippocampus of NEX-Cre mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Goebbels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Bormuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Bode</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Hermanson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schwab</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nave</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genesis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="611" to="621" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Higashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maruhashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Nelles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Van De Putte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Verschueren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Miyoshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Yoshimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kondoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Huylebroeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generation of the floxed allele of the SIP1 (Smad-interacting protein 1) gene for Cre-mediated conditional knockout in the mouse</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genesis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="84" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Centrosomal and non-centrosomal microtubules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Keating</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Borisy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="329" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microtubule release from the centrosome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Keating</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Peloquin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Rodionov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Momcilovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Borisy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5078" to="5083" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intrinsic circuit organization of the major layers and sublayers of the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex in the rhesus monkey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kritzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Goldman-Rakic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Comp. Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">359</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dlx1&amp;2-dependent expression of Zfhx1b (Sip1, Zeb2) regulates the fate switch between cortical and striatal interneurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mckinsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lindtner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Trzcinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Visel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pennacchio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Huylebroeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Higashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rubenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="98" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Smad-interacting protein-1 (Zfhx1b) acts upstream of Wnt signaling in the mouse hippocampus and controls its formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Miquelajauregui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Van De Putte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Polyakov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nityanandam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Boppana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Seuntjens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Karabinos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Higashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Huylebroeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Tarabykin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12919" to="12924" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microtubule minus-end anchorage at centrosomal and non-centrosomal sites: the role of ninein</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mogensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Malik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Piel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Bouckson-Castaing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bornens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3013" to="3023" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Molna ´r</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Blakey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Bystron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Carney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Neuroanatomical Tract-Tracing 3</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neuronal subtype specification in the cerebral cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Molyneaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Arlotta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Menezes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Macklis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="427" to="437" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identity and polymerization-stimulatory activity of the nontubulin proteins associated with microtubules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Vallee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Borisy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2598" to="2605" />
			<date type="published" when="1977">1977</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SIP1 expression patterns in brain investigated by generating a SIP1-EGFP reporter knock-in mouse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Nishizaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Takagi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Matsui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Higashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genesis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Postnatal subventricular zone of the neocortex contributes GFAP+ cells to the rostral migratory stream under the control of Sip1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nityanandam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Parthasarathy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Tarabykin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">366</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="356" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cortical axons branch to multiple subcortical targets by interstitial axon budding: implications for target recognition and &apos;&apos;waiting periods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>O'leary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Terashima</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="901" to="910" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Relocalization of a microtubule-anchoring protein, ninein, from the centrosome to dendrites during differentiation of mouse neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ohama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Histochem. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="515" to="524" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ntf3 acts downstream of Sip1 in cortical postmitotic neurons to control progenitor cell fate through feedback signaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Parthasarathy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Srivatsa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nityanandam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Tarabykin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3324" to="3330" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vivo electroporation in the embryonic mouse central nervous system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Saito</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1552" to="1558" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sip1 regulates sequential fate decisions by feedback signaling from postmitotic neurons to progenitors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Seuntjens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nityanandam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Miquelajauregui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Debruyn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stryjewska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Goebbels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nave</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Huylebroeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Tarabykin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1373" to="1380" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ninein is essential for the maintenance of the cortical progenitor character by anchoring the centrosome to microtubules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Shinohara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Sakayori</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Takahashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Osumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="739" to="749" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unc5C and DCC act downstream of Ctip2 and Satb2 and contribute to corpus callosum formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Srivatsa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Parthasarathy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Britanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Bormuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Donahoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ackerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Richards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Tarabykin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3708</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vitro reconstitution of centrosome assembly and function: the central role of gamma-tubulin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Stearns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kirschner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="623" to="637" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualization of microtubule growth in cultured neurons via the use</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Stepanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Slemmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hoogenraad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lansbergen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dortland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>De Zeeuw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Grosveld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Van Cappellen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Akhmanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Galjart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1011</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003-03-04">2003. March 4, 2015 ª2015</date>
			<publisher>Elsevier Inc</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EB3-GFP (end-binding protein 3-green fluorescent protein)</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2655" to="2664" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional maps of neocortical local circuitry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Thomson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Directed migration of cortical interneurons depends on the cell-autonomous action of Sip1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Van Den Berghe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Stappers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Vandesande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dimidschstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kroes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Francis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Conidi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Lesage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dries</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cazzola</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nanomolar concentrations of nocodazole alter microtubule dynamic instability in vivo and in vitro</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vasquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Howell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Yvon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wadsworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Cassimeris</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Biol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="973" to="985" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SIP1, a novel zinc finger/homeodomain repressor, interacts with Smad proteins and binds to 5 0 -CACCT sequences in candidate target genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Verschueren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Remacle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Collart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kraft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tylzanowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Nelles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wuytens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bodmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">274</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20489" to="20498" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Activity-dependent development of callosal projections in the somatosensory cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Duan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Xiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11334" to="11342" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Imai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Lian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Vallee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymmetric centrosome inheritance maintains neural progenitors in the neocortex</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">461</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="947" to="955" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dual-mode modulation of Smad signaling by Smad-interacting protein Sip1 is required for myelination in the central nervous system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Weng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Shou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Higashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Van Den Berghe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="713" to="728" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Further delineation of the phenotype associated with heterozygous mutations in ZFHX1B</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mowat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Dastot-Le</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Moal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Cacheux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ka ¨a ¨ria ¨inen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Donnai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Clayton-Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Townshend</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Curry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Med. Genet. A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nucleation of microtubule assembly by a gamma-tubulin-containing ring complex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Alberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mitchison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">378</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="578" to="583" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
