<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Biomarker threshold adaptive designs for survival endpoints</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2019-01-22">2019 January 22.</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Guoqing</forename><surname>Diao</surname></persName>
							<email>gdiao@gmu.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">George Mason University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Fairfax</settlement>
									<region>Virginia</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jun</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Amgen Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Thousand Oaks</settlement>
									<region>California</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Donglin</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Chapel Hill</settlement>
									<region>North Carolina</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Chunlei</forename><surname>Ke</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Amgen Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Thousand Oaks</settlement>
									<region>California</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alan</forename><surname>Rong</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Astellas Pharma US, Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Los Angeles</settlement>
									<region>California</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Joseph</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Ibrahim</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Chapel Hill</settlement>
									<region>North Carolina</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Statistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">George Mason University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Fairfax</settlement>
									<region>Virginia</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Biomarker threshold adaptive designs for survival endpoints</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2019-01-22">2019 January 22.</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F611BAABCE53A921CE9BC0AFD8CAEF99</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1080/10543406.2018.1434191</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:24+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Adaptive enrichment design</term>
					<term>predictive biomarker</term>
					<term>survival endpoint</term>
					<term>two-stage design</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Due to the importance of precision medicine, it is essential to identify the right patients for the right treatment.</s><s>Biomarkers, which have been commonly used in clinical research as well as in clinical practice, can facilitate selection of patients with a good response to the treatment.</s><s>In this paper, we describe a biomarker threshold adaptive design with survival endpoints.</s><s>In the first stage, we determine subgroups for one or more biomarkers such that patients in these subgroups benefit the most from the new treatment.</s><s>The analysis in this stage can be based on historical or pilot studies.</s><s>In the second stage, we sample subjects from the subgroups determined in the first stage and randomly allocate them to the treatment or control group.</s><s>Extensive simulation studies are conducted to examine the performance of the proposed design.</s><s>Application to a real data example is provided for implementation of the first-stage algorithms.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Many new anticancer agents are molecularly targeted and therefore may only benefit a subgroup of a histologically defined population.</s><s>Predictive biomarkers have been utilized to identify the sensitive subset to optimize treatment efficacy and safety in clinical practice.</s><s>For example, in recurrent or metastatic squamous-cell carcinoma of the head and neck (SCCHN), loss of phosphate and tensin homolog (PTEN) expression had a negative effect on tumor response to epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) monoclonal antibodies <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Mao et al., 2010)</ref>; and EGFR expression level has been negatively associated with overall survival <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Ang et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Grandis et al., 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Nicholson et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Reimers et al., 2007)</ref>, which makes EGFR a potential positive prognostic factor for anti-EGFR antibodies.</s><s>The SPECTRUM study is a phase-3 trial of chemotherapy with or without panitumumab (an anti-EGFR antibody) in patients with SCCHN <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Vermorken et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>EGFR and PTEN data had been collected retrospectively using stored samples.</s><s>It is of interest to prospectively evaluate the predictive value of EGFR and PTEN for panitumumab in SCCHN, while preliminary information may be derived from the SPECTRUM study.</s><s>The benefits and challenges of incorporating biomarkers into the development of anticancer agents have been increasingly discussed <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Renfro et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>Many design options have been proposed in the literature.</s></p><p><s>A biomarker is typically measured as a continuous or semi-continuous variable.</s><s>The target subset is defined based on a chosen cutpoint of the biomarker.</s><s>If the cutpoint is known but it is not known whether the biomarker is predictive, a biomarker-by-treatment interaction design (all-comer) can be employed where the study is stratified by the biomarker status and the hypotheses can be set up based on the overall population or the biomarker positive subset.</s><s>If there exists strong evidence that the treatment is only effective in the positive biomarker subgroup, e.g., from early phase studies, an enrichment design can be utilized to limit the study population only to the positive subset.</s><s>In addition, a subgroup enrichment design can include an interim analysis to decide whether or not the treatment is only effective in the positive subset and thus discontinue enrollment of patients in the nonsensitive subset.</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Freidlin et al. (2010)</ref> provided detailed discussions on phase-3 clinical trials that integrate treatment and biomarker evaluation.</s></p><p><s>In practice, there may be limited data available to identify a single biomarker or to determine a known cutpoint to define a sensitive subset before initiation of the phase-3 study.</s><s>Then the selection of the cutpoint will be based on the study itself and will be part of the study objective.</s><s>A number of methods have been suggested to prospectively including selection of the cutpoint into the study design <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Renfro et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>For example, adaptive signature design (ASD) enrolls all comers into two stages <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Freidlin and Simon, 2005)</ref>.</s><s>A classifier (i.e., cutpoint) is developed using data from stage-1 patients only, and the classifier is not used to restrict enrollment in stage 2 but to define a subset of sensitive patients.</s><s>Note that when there are multiple biomarkers or the treatment effect is not monotonic as a function of the biomarker under the alternative, there may not exist a simple cutpoint.</s><s>For clarification, we emphasize here that we use "cutpoint" only when there is only one biomarker and the treatment effect is monotonic as a function of the biomarker under the alternative.</s><s>In the final analysis, the comparison can be made based on the overall population using data from all patients enrolled in both stages or on the sensitive subset accrued during stage 2 together with some multiplicity adjustment procedure.</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Freidlin et al. (2010)</ref> extended ASD to crossvalidated ASD where the stage-1 data is also used to test the sensitive subset to improve efficiency.</s><s>A subgroup enrichment design can also be developed to limit enrollment of the second-stage patients to the sensitive subset.</s></p><p><s>treatment.</s><s>The appropriate primary null hypothesis of this design is that no subpopulation benefits from treatment over control.</s><s>Therefore, this design may not be able to draw a conclusion about which subset of patients will benefit the most from the treatment.</s><s>Consequently, the AED of <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Simon and Simon (2013)</ref> essentially reduces to a non-adaptive design when all patients respond to the treatment, even though the treatment effect may be different on subjects with different biomarker values.</s><s>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Simon and Simon (2013)</ref>, there was little detailed discussion regarding the algorithm to enrich the study particularly for survival endpoints, which are commonly used in clinical trials for anticancer agents.</s><s>Additionally, little was discussed on the data used in the final analysis.</s><s>More recently, <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Renfro et al. (2014)</ref> proposed an adaptive design by selecting the biomarker threshold for which the interaction effect between the biomarker and the treatment is the most significant.</s><s>However, the design assumes that the experimental treatment is hypothesized to work better for patients with higher biomarker values than patients with lower biomarker values.</s><s>This assumption may not be true in practice and consequently may lead to loss of power.</s></p><p><s>In this manuscript, we will propose a new AED design, called the biomarker threshold adaptive design (BTAD).</s><s>Similar to the AED design in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Simon and Simon (2013)</ref>, our design does not adaptively adjust the total sample size after stage 1 or the sample size in stage 2. The stage-1 analysis can be based on historical or pilot studies.</s><s>The enrichment in stage 2 is expected to increase power for hypothesis testing using either data from stage 2 alone or combined data from both stages.</s><s>The Cox regression model for survival endpoints is employed for the AED.</s><s>However, the proposed methods can be easily generalized to any other applications where a regression model is mainly used for inference.</s><s>Different criteria for determination of the biomarker cutpoint based on stage-1 data are proposed.</s><s>Our algorithm can potentially provide better enrichment in stage 2 than that of <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Simon and Simon (2013)</ref>, and thus result in a more powerful procedure.</s><s>Furthermore, while motivated by cancer studies, the proposed design is general and can be readily applied to clinical trials on other diseases.</s><s>This paper is organized as follows.</s><s>In the next section, we use a group sequential framework and propose an optimal algorithm to determine, at a given interim analysis, which patient population will be enrolled next to enrich the study.</s><s>Factors that may impact the algorithm are investigated.</s><s>Furthermore, we discuss valid statistical methods for the final data analysis.</s><s>We then evaluate the performance of the proposed design through extensive simulations.</s><s>A real data example from the SPECTRUM study is used to demonstrate the determination of the biomarker cutpoint and to evaluate the performance of the proposed design compared with the non-adaptive design as well.</s><s>We conclude the paper with some discussions.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Biomarker threshold adaptive design</head><p><s>We consider a BTAD to identify one or more predictive biomarkers.</s><s>Specifically, our goal is to identify a subset of patients according to a biomarker of interest such that the treatment achieves the maximum beneficial effect compared to the control in this subset.</s><s>One can then oversample patients in that subset to improve the overall efficiency of the design.</s><s>In the simplest case, there exists a threshold for a single biomarker, such that the treatment effect is larger (or smaller) in one group than the other.</s><s>Let T, X and A denote the survival endpoint, the biomarker of interest and the treatment indicator, respectively.</s><s>The treatment indicator A takes value 1 for the new treatment and 0 for the control.</s><s>We propose two ways to determine the threshold.</s><s>In this paper, we refer to the subject subset with either X ≤ c or X &gt; c identified by our methods with better treatment effect as the "biomarker positive subgroup", and the complement as the "biomarker negative subgroup."</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BTAD1.</head><p><s>For a given cutpoint c, we first consider the following Cox models for the two subgroups X ≤ c and X &gt; c, respectively</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">λ t X ≤ c, A = λ 1c t exp β 1c A and λ t X &gt; c, A = λ 2c t exp β 2c A .</formula><p><s>Note that the smaller the regression coefficients β 1c and β 2c , the better the effect of the new treatment compared to the control.</s><s>Based on the observed data in the first stage</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_1">Y i = min T i , C i , Δ i = I T i ≤ C i , X i , A i , i = 1, …, n 1</formula><p><s>, where Ci, and ∆ i are the censoring time and event indicator, respectively, we can obtain the estimators of β 1c and β 2c , denoted by β 1c and β 2c .</s><s>We denote the total sample size and that of stages 1 and 2 as n, n 1 and n 2 , respectively.</s><s>We select the threshold c to minimize min β 1c , β 2c for c ∈ , where is the support of X.</s><s>In the second stage, we then sample the remaining n 2 = nn 1 subjects only from subgroup X ≤ c if β 1c &lt; β 2c , and subgroup X &gt; c otherwise.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BTAD2.</head><p><s>Alternatively, we can fit a Cox model including both the main effects of X and A and their interaction effect</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_2">λ t X, A = λ c t exp γ 1c I X &gt; c + γ 2c A + γ 3c I X &gt; c A .</formula><p><s>Based on the observed data from the n 1 subjects in the first stage, we can obtain the estimate of the treatment by biomarker interaction effect γ 3c , denoted by γ 3c .</s><s>We select the threshold c to maximize γ 3c for c ∈ .</s><s>In the second stage, we sample the remaining n 2 = nn 1 subjects from subgroup X ≤ c if γ 3c &gt; 0 and X &gt; c otherwise.</s></p><p><s>It is worth clarifying that by "biomarker negative subgroup", we do not mean that in this group the treatment is not promising.</s><s>Instead, we mean that the treatment effect is better in the "biomarker positive subgroup" than in the "biomarker negative subgroup."</s><s>Therefore, it is possible that the treatment is promising for the overall population, but the proposed designs intend to identify the subpopulation such that the treatment is more promising than the other.</s><s>One limitation is that the proposed designs may fail to recruit patients for which there is also treatment effect but the treatment is not as effective as in the other subgroup.</s></p><p><s>There are a few differences between BTAD1 and BTAD2.</s><s>First of all, BTAD1 aims to identify the subgroup that responds the best to the treatment whereas BTAD2 aims to identify a subgroup that responds to the treatment better than the other subgroup and the threshold is chosen such that the difference between treatment effects in these two subgroups is the greatest.</s><s>Second, compared to BTAD1, BTAD2 has an additional assumption that the hazard functions in the control group are proportional between the two biomarker subgroups.</s><s>On the other hand, when the proportional hazards assumption is valid, BTAD2 tends to yield more efficient parameter estimators and is numerically more stable especially when the sample size is small.</s></p><p><s>We can use a grid search method, for example, at certain sample percentiles of X, to select the threshold.</s><s>To ensure reliable estimates of the unknown parameters, especially when the sample size is small or moderately large, we also suggest selecting the threshold such that there are at least 30% of subjects in each biomarker subgroup.</s><s>A computer program in C language implementing BTAD1 and BTAD2 is available freely at http://mason.gmu.edu/</s><s>gdiao/software/BTAD.</s></p><p><s>Once we collect all the data, it is of interest to test the hypothesis</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_3">H 0 : λ t X = x, A = 0 = λ t X = x, A = 1 , t ∈ 0, τ , x ∈ 𝒳 ,<label>(1)</label></formula><p><s>where is the support of X and τ is the end of study.</s><s>That is, under the null hypothesis, there is no difference between the hazard functions in the treatment group and control group for any biomarker value.</s><s>Furthermore, one may be interested in estimating the treatment effect.</s><s>A natural question is which dataset to use in the final analysis after collecting all the data from the first and second stages.</s><s>One can consider three types of datasets: (a) data from the second stage only; (b) all the data including both stages; and (c) data with subjects from the biomarker positive group only from both stages, that is, data including subjects selected according to the determined threshold from the first stage and all subjects from the second stage.</s><s>We emphasize here that while using the first two types of data can preserve the type-I error rate, using the third type of data will lead to an inflated type-I error rate.</s><s>When the null hypothesis is true, regardless of the threshold selected in the first stage, the data in the second stage are still collected under the null hypothesis; therefore, using the first two types of data can still preserve the type-I error rate.</s><s>However, since we determine the threshold by selecting a subgroup in the first stage in which the treatment effect is better than the other subgroup, biased sampling arises and leads to an inflated type-I error rate if we include only the biomarker positive group in the final analysis.</s><s>This observation is evident in the simulation studies in Section 3.</s></p><p><s>Note that the null hypothesis defined in (1) is general.</s><s>In practice, to test this null hypothesis, one has to impose certain model assumptions.</s><s>For example, by testing β = 0 in the Cox model with only the treatment indicator A as the covariate, i.e.,</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_4">λ t A = λ 0 t exp βA ,</formula><p><s>besides the Cox model assumption, we assume that patients within each biomarker subgroup have equal chances to receive either treatment or that there is no biomarker effect on the survival endpoint.</s><s>On the other hand, if we assume the model</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_5">λ t X, A = λ 0 t exp β 1 A + β 2 X + β 3 X × A , (2)</formula><p><s>then testing the null hypothesis defined in ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_3">1</ref>) is equivalent to testing β 1 = β 3 = 0.</s><s>Under the null hypothesis defined in (1), all these tests using the appropriate data sets with correct model specification can control the type-I error; however, they will lead to different powers given different alternative hypothesis (for example, see Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> in the Simulation Studies Section).</s></p><p><s>Suppose the true model is (2).</s><s>We consider three models in the final analysis.</s><s>The first model includes the treatment effect only,</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_6">λ * t X, A = λ 0 * t exp β 1 * A .</formula><p><s>This is a misspecified model if β 2 ≠ 0 or β 3 ≠ 0. Therefore β 1 * is not a consistent estimator of β 1 or β 3 .</s><s>Instead, β 1 * may have a complicated form involving all the parameters in the true model.</s><s>The second model we consider includes both treatment and biomarker main effects</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_7">λ * t X, A = λ 0 * t exp β 1 * A + β 2 * X .</formula><p><s>In this case, β 1 * ≈ β 1 + β 3 E X .</s><s>If β 1 = 0 and E(X) = 0, we may fail to detect the true treatment effect.</s><s>Hence, one needs to use caution when interpreting the results under this model.</s><s>We may also fit the correctly specified model in the final analysis including both main effects and the interaction effect between the treatment and biomarker.</s><s>We will still have consistent parameter estimates under this model using both the first-stage and secondstage data, as is evident by the simulation studies in Section 3. In all three models, we propose to use a Wald-type test statistic to test the null hypothesis H 0 of no treatment effect.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Simulation studies</head><p><s>We conducted extensive simulation studies to examine the performance of BTAD and we compare it to that of the standard non-adaptive design.</s><s>We consider a two-arm trial with one biomarker X.</s><s>We generate data from the exponential distribution under the following two scenarios:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_8">λ t X, A = exp β 1 A + β 2 X + β 3 X × A (3) and λ t X, A = exp β 1 A + β 2 I X &gt; c + β 3 I X &gt; c A , (<label>4</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_9">)</formula><p><s>where c is the population median of the distribution of X.</s><s>Under both scenarios, the baseline hazard is equal to 1.</s><s>We considered three different distributions for X : (1) Uniform(0,1); (2) N(0; 1); and (3) EXP(1).</s><s>The regression parameters are set to be</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_10">β 1 = 0, β 2 = − 0.5, β 3 = 0, − 0.1, …, − 0.6.</formula><p><s>Under model ( <ref type="formula">3</ref>), the hazard ratio between the treatment group and control group given X = x is exp(β 1 + β 3 x).</s><s>Therefore, for a positive number x, the above hazard ratio decreases as β 3 decreases.</s><s>Consequently the smaller the value of β 3 , the better the treatment effect for positive values of X.</s><s>For example when X = 0.5, the hazard ratio ranges from 1 to 0.741 as j 3 varies from 0 to −0.6.</s><s>On the other hand, when X = -0.5, the hazard ratio ranges from 1 to 1.350.</s><s>For each simulation, we generate 1,000 replicates with n = 200 or n = 300.</s><s>In all simulations, we fix the censoring time at 10.</s></p><p><s>In the first set of simulation studies, we compare the performance of the non-adaptive design, BTAD1, and BTAD2.</s><s>Specifically, we sample n 1 = n/2 subjects from the general population.</s><s>Based on these n/2 subjects, we determine the threshold c and biomarker positive group.</s><s>We use a grid search method for selecting the threshold from the 30th, 40th,..., and 70th sample percentiles of the biomarker data.</s><s>We then sample subjects from the biomarker positive group only in the second stage.</s><s>In the final analysis, we evaluate the treatment effect based on all n subjects from both the first stage and the second stage with or without adjusting for the biomarker.</s></p><p><s>Table <ref type="table">1</ref> presents the frequencies of selected groups X ≤ c and X &gt; c with n = 200 and n = 300 under different scenarios with β 3 fixed at −0.6.</s><s>This table suggests that increasing the sample size can improve the frequency of a correctly selected biomarker subgroup.</s><s>Histograms of the selected cutpoints under data generation model (3) with β 3 = -0.6 for n = 300 are presented in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</s><s>Similar results are obtained under data generation model (4) (data not shown).</s></p><p><s>Using all the data in both stages, we compare the powers of detecting the treatment effect of the following 10 methods with different designs and different analyses:</s></p><p><s>1. non-adaptive design and X adjusted;</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.</head><p><s>non-adaptive design and X not adjusted;</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.</head><p><s>adaptive design using BTAD1, X adjusted;</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.</head><p><s>adaptive design using BTAD1, X not adjusted;</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5.</head><p><s>adaptive design using BTAD2, X adjusted;</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>6.</head><p><s>adaptive design using BTAD2, X not adjusted;</s></p><p><s>a. adaptive design using BTAD1 under the constraint such that only the subgroup X &gt; c is selected, X adjusted;</s></p><p><s>b. adaptive design using BTAD1 under the constraint such that only the subgroup X &gt; c is selected, X not adjusted; c. adaptive design using BTAD2 under the constraint such that only the subgroup X &gt; c is selected, X adjusted;</s></p><p><s>d.</s></p><p><s>adaptive design using BTAD2 under the constraint such that only the subgroup X &gt; c is selected, X not adjusted.</s></p><p><s>Note that methods ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>)-( <ref type="formula">10</ref>) assume that subjects with larger values of the biomarker respond better to the new treatment as in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Simon and Simon (2013)</ref>.</s><s>This assumption may not be true in practice.</s><s>Figures <ref type="figure">2 and 3</ref> present the type-I error rates and powers for testing the null hypothesis H 0 under data generation models (3) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_8">4</ref>), respectively.</s><s>The tests under the proposed adaptive design have correct control of the type-I error rate and are consistently more powerful than the tests under the non-adaptive design.</s><s>The analyses with and without adjusting for the biomarker effect yield comparable results in most cases; however, the test of the treatment effect without adjusting for the biomarker effect can be substantially more powerful than the one adjusting for the biomarker effect when the mean biomarker value and the main treatment effect are close to 0. For example, as shown in Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> when X~N(0, 1), since the treatment effect β 1 * under the model adjusting for X is approximately</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_11">β 1 + β 3 E X = 0</formula><p><s>, there is essentially no power to detect treatment effect under the nonadaptive design.</s><s>Methods 7-10 show that if the assumption on the constraint is correct, then the power is higher, as expected.</s><s>BTAD1 and BTAD2 show similar performance in all simulations in Figures <ref type="figure">2 and 3</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In the second set of simulations, we investigate which types of datasets are suitable for the final analysis under the proposed BTAD.</s><s>In particular, we compare the type-I error rates and powers of the tests for testing H 0 at the nominal significance level of 0.05 using the three different types of data in the final analysis as described in Section 2. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref> displays the results based on the adaptive design using BTAD1.</s><s>It is obvious that using the biomarker positive group only can lead to an inflated type-I error rate, while using the second-stage data only or all the data including both first and second-stage data preserves the type-I error rate.</s><s>The tests using all the data are more powerful than those using the second-stage data only with the exception when X~N(0, 1).</s><s>As discussed in the end of Section 2, the treatment effect β 1 * under the fitted models is approximately β 1 + β 3 E X .</s><s>Therefore, the power of the test depends on both the sample size in the final analysis and the approximate effect size β 1 + β 3 E X .</s><s>Although the sample size in the combined data set including both stages is larger than the sample size in the second stage only, the expectation of X in the second-stage data set can be much larger than that in the combined data set leading to a larger effect size and consequently a larger power.</s></p><p><s>Finally, we conducted simulation studies to examine the estimates of the regression coefficients by fitting the true model including both the main effects of biomarker and treatment and their interaction effect.</s><s>We considered a non-adaptive design, BTAD1 and BTAD2 using the second-stage data only, using both the first-stage and second-stage data, and using data from biomarker positive subgroup only.</s><s>The results for data generation model (3) are presented in Table <ref type="table">2-4</ref>.</s><s>By fitting the full model with interaction effects using all the data, we can still estimate the parameters consistently, although there is some efficiency loss compared to the non-adaptive design.</s><s>Using the biomarker positive subgroup only will lead to a biased estimate of the treatment effect.</s><s>Furthermore, using the second-stage data only or the biomarker positive subgroup data only leads to substantial efficiency loss of the parameter estimates.</s><s>BTAD1 and BTAD2 have similar performance.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SPECTRUM study</head><p><s>We consider a head and neck cancer clinical trial as a case study to demonstrate how to determine the cutpoint using our algorithms for biomarkers with different patterns of biomarker-outcome relationship as described in Section 2. The SPECTRUM study is a multicenter, randomized, open-label, phase-3 trial of chemotherapy with or without panitumumab in patients with recurrent or metastatic SCCHN <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Vermorken et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>The primary endpoint was overall survival.</s><s>For our analysis, 526 (80.0%) subjects were randomly selected from the 657 subjects in the SPECTRUM trial for demonstration purpose.</s></p><p><s>The dataset with 526 subjects is treated as the data collected in stage 1.</s><s>There are no stage-2 data; therefore, the inference after stage 2 is not available in this analysis.</s></p><p><s>In a literature review of more than 200 tumor studies by <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Nicholson et al. (2001)</ref>, EGFR is reported to act as a prognostic factor for OS in solid tumors with increased EGFR expression generally associated with a reduced OS rate.</s><s>In SCCHN, a correlation between higher EGFR expression and poorer OS was claimed by <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Ang et al. (2002)</ref>.</s><s>The OS rates for subjects with high EGFR expressing SCCHN ( &gt; median mean absorbance) compared to those with low EGFR expressing SCCHN were significantly lower (p = 0.0006).</s><s>These studies (reporting mean absorbance) were performed using automated image analysis to quantify expression levels.</s><s>EGFR-negative tumors have shown a tendency toward a better prognosis in OS (70% vs. 45%, p = 0.10) by <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Reimers et al. (2007)</ref>.</s><s>In addition, when tumor levels of EGFR expression (intensity and tumor cell extent) were analyzed as continuous variables, causespecific survival was reduced among subjects with higher levels of EGFR (p = 0.0001) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Grandis et al., 1998)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In SCCHN, PTEN has been shown to be frequently altered at the genetic and biochemical level <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Pedrero et al., 2005)</ref>.</s><s>In metastatic colorectal cancer, the prevailing hypothesis is that lack of PTEN expression predicts resistance to EGFR antibody therapy.</s><s>There have been four small studies that have evaluated the association of PTEN expression and patient response to EGFR antibodies and a meta-analysis of these data showed that loss of PTEN expression had a negative effect on tumor response to EGFR monoclonal antibodies (pooled risk ratio, 0.22; 95% confidence interval, 0.10-0.50;</s><s>P = 0.001) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Mao et al., 2010)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>We first perform an exploratory analysis on two biomarkers MEMASPE (tumor cell percentage with membrane staining total 1±3% for EGFR) and CYTOSPPT (Tumor cell percentage with cytoplasmic staining total 1±3% for PTEN).</s><s>Among the total number of 526 subjects, 163 subjects have non-missing MEMASPE values and 290 subjects have nonmissing CYTOSPPT values.</s><s>Subjects with missing biomarker values were excluded from the analysis.</s><s>For each biomarker, we first plot the histogram.</s><s>Additionally, we fit the following Cox model allowing for biomarker-dependent treatment effects,</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_12">λ t X = x, A = λ 0 t exp g 0 x + d x A ,<label>(5)</label></formula><p><s>where g 0 (x) and d(x) are estimated nonparametrically by using B-splines.</s><s>The results are presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>.</s><s>Both biomarkers are left skewed with a spike around a value of 100.</s><s>It appears that the treatment effect, as a function of MEMASPE, is monotonically increasing; that is, patients with larger values of MEMASPE respond to the treatment better.</s><s>In contrast, the treatment effect as a function of CYTOSPPT, is not monotone.</s><s>The treatment doesn't appear to have a beneficial effect on patients with CYTOSPPT values around 20 whereas patients with CYTOSPPT values around 80 respond to the treatment the best.</s></p><p><s>We used a grid search approach ranging from the 30th sample percentile to the 70th sample percentile with a step size of 2% to determine the biomarker positive subgroup.</s><s>For MEMASPE, both BTAD1 and BTAD2 identify the positive subgroup with MEMASPE &gt; 94.6, which is the 66th sample percentile.</s><s>This result agrees well with the results presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>, and the proposed methods correctly identify the biomarker subgroup which responds to the treatment the best.</s><s>For CYTOSPPT, BTAD1 identifies the positive subgroup with CYTOSPPT &gt; 92.5 (sample median) and BTAD2 identifies the positive subgroup with CYTOSPPT &gt; 76.05 (30th sample percentile).</s><s>Although the proposed methods do not identify the subgroup in which the treatment effect is the largest, they still identify a subgroup with beneficial treatment effect compared to a majority of the other patients.</s><s>More discussion on this topic is provided in Section 5.</s></p><p><s>Finally, we conducted a simulation study based on the SPECTRUM study to examine the performance of the proposed BTAD using the biomarker MEMASPE.</s><s>In the first stage, we randomly sampled 60 patients from the entire dataset and then determine the cutpoint using BTAD1 and BTAD2.</s><s>In the second stage, we randomly sampled up to 30 patients with positive biomarkers from the remaining 103 patients.</s><s>We then repeated this procedure 1,000 times and estimated the treatment effect using all the data from both the first stage and the second stage.</s><s>With the biomarker adjusted, the empirical powers for testing the treatment effect at the significance level of 0.05 are 91.6% and 89.6% based on BTAD1 and BTAD2, respectively, compared to a power of 62.2% based on the non-adaptive design.</s><s>Without adjusting for the biomarker, the empirical powers are 85.9%, 83.0%, and 50.7% based on BTAD1, BTAD2, and the non-adaptive design, respectively.</s><s>In about 25% of the 1000 simulated datasets, there are fewer than 30 patients with positive biomarkers in the second stage.</s><s>Even though the sample sizes are smaller on average in the BTAD than the nonadaptive design, there is substantial power increase of the BTAD over the non-adaptive design.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>In this paper, we proposed a method to determine the threshold based on the estimates of the treatment effect in each biomarker subgroup.</s><s>Naturally, one would want to take into account the variation of the parameter estimates in the decision process.</s><s>For example, one may use a statistic for testing the treatment effect in each subgroup to select the threshold.</s><s>However, such an approach may lead to selecting the biomarker negative group with a larger sample size in the first stage.</s></p><p><s>Renfro et al. ( <ref type="formula">2014</ref>) considered the same model as in BTAD2 including the interaction effect between treatment and biomarker.</s><s>Assuming that patients with higher biomarker values respond to the treatment better, the threshold was selected such that the treatment-bybiomarker interaction is most significant.</s><s>To relax the assumption on the direction of the interaction effect, we can extend the approach of <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Renfro et al. (2014)</ref> such that the threshold c is selected the same way but in the second stage we sample subjects from subgroup with X ≤ c if γ 3c &gt; 0 and X &gt; c otherwise.</s><s>Our limited simulation studies suggest that in general the performance of this extension is comparable with BTAD2; however, compared to BTAD1 and BTAD2, this approach tends to select threshold near the sample median of the biomarker value and can have reduced power, particularly when X is generated from a normal distribution.</s></p><p><s>We have assumed that treatment effect is monotone as a function of the biomarker, in particular, a model with a change point, at which the treatment effect changes.</s><s>In practical applications, it is possible that the treatment effect curve is not monotone.</s><s>Violation of the monotonicity assumption may lead to inaccurate identification of the biomarker positive subgroup.</s><s>In this case, we may consider the general model (5) as described in Section 4. In particular, when d(x) is a step function with a change-point at c, the above model reduces to the model under consideration in this paper.</s><s>The general model ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_12">5</ref>) also includes settings such that the marginal treatment effect is not 0 and/or the interaction effect is not linear on the biomarker scale.</s><s>In general, we can estimate g 0 (x) and d(x) nonparametrically, e.g., using smoothing splines.</s><s>We can then determine the biomarker positive group as</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_13">ℛ c = {x: d x &lt; c},</formula><p><s>for a constant c.</s><s>The constant c can be chosen to minimize</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_14">ℛ c d x dF X x ℛ c dF X x − ℛ c C d x dF X x ℛ c C dF X x , subject to min ℛ c dF X x , ℛ c C dF X x } ≥ q, for a pre − specified value q,</formula><p><s>where ℛ c C is the complement set of ℛ c , and F X (x) is the cumulative distribution function of X. Future research is warranted along this direction.</s></p><p><s>When there is no interaction effect between the biomarker of interest and treatment, this biomarker is not a predictive biomarker.</s><s>Therefore, such a biomarker is not an appropriate candidate for identifying subpopulations of patients who are most likely to respond to the treatment.</s><s>In view of this, we can first perform hypothesis testing to test H 0 : β 1c = β 2c for BTAD1 and H 0 : γ 3c = 0 for BTAD2.</s><s>Then, we continue the algorithm of the adaptive design given that there is some level of evidence of an interaction effect between the biomarker and the treatment.</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Simon and Simon (2013)</ref> proposed to sample all subjects from the positive biomarker group.</s><s>Such a design may not differ much from the non-adaptive design if the treatment is better than the control in every biomarker group.</s><s>On the other hand, our proposed methodology is based on sampling subjects who will benefit the most from the treatment.</s><s>Even if the treatment is better than the control in every biomarker group, our proposed design aims to select the group who respond to the treatment the best.</s><s>Therefore, our proposed methods tend to be more powerful than the method of <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Simon and Simon (2013)</ref> because of larger effect sizes.</s></p><p><s>We can extend our proposed methods to two or more biomarkers X.</s><s>For example, for p biomarkers, we can have a pdimensional search for the thresholds (C 1 ,…,C P ).</s><s>However, the computational burden increases geometrically as the number of biomarkers increase.</s><s>An alternative approach is to first construct a composite score or risk factor β T X, which can be obtained by fitting a Cox model</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_15">λ t X , A = λ t exp β T X + γA .</formula><p><s>We then treat the composite score as a new biomarker and apply the aforementioned methods to determine a threshold for this composite score.</s><s>This is a current area of research.</s></p><p><s>When comparing the non-adaptive and adaptive approaches, we assume that the sample sizes used are the same.</s><s>Like many other enrichment designs, the proposed adaptive approaches can be more costly compared to a non-adaptive design as the adaptive designs typically require additional screening and more patients need to be recruited in order to have sufficient number of biomarker positive patients in the second stage.</s><s>It would be interesting to conduct cost-benefit analysis to compare the non-adaptive and adaptive designs.</s></p><p><s>In this paper, we focus on survival endpoints and assume a Cox model for the relationship between treatment and the survival outcome.</s><s>However, the proposed methods can be generalized to regression models for different types of outcome data, such as binary, count, and normal outcomes.</s><s>Second, when the proportional hazards assumption does not hold, the proposed methods can still preserve type-I error under the null hypothesis but may not be as powerful as seen now.</s><s>Alternatively, other regression models for survival endpoints such as the proportional odds model, accelerated failure time model, or additive hazard model can be considered.</s><s>Histograms of selected cutpoints under data generation model (3) with β 3 = -0.6.</s><s>From the left panel to the right panel, the distributions of X are Uniform(0,1), N(0,1), and EXP(1), respectively.</s><s>The upper and lower panels correspond to the results from BTAD1 and BTAD2, respectively.</s><s>The magenta bars correspond to selected groups X&gt;c, and the blue bars for X ≤ c.</s><s>Type-I error rates and powers under data generation model (3).</s><s>All data from both stages are included in the analysis.</s><s>The dotted reference line corresponds to the y-axis at 0.05.</s><s>Type-I error rates and powers under data generation model (4).</s><s>All data from both stages are included in the analysis.</s><s>The dotted reference line corresponds to the y-axis at 0.05.</s><s>Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Relative frequencies of selected subgroups.</s><s>Under the true simulation models, the subgroup (X &gt; c) is expected to be selected.</s><s>Note: the true regression parameters (β 1 ,β 2 ,β 3 ) are set to be (0, -0.5, -0.6).</s></p><p><s>Table <ref type="table">2</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Parameter</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="14,106.44,62.00,459.12,432.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="15,105.36,62.00,461.28,432.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="16,108.24,62.00,455.52,432.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4.Type-I error rates and powers for BTAD1 under data generation model (3) using different types of data in the final data analysis.</s><s>The dotted reference line corresponds to the y-axis at 0.05.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="17,111.84,62.00,448.32,432.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. Results for MEMASPE (tumor cell percentage with membrane staining total 1±3% for EGFR) and CYTOSPPT (tumor cell percentage with cytoplasmic staining total 1±3% for PTEN).</s><s>Among the total number of 526 subjects, 163 subjects have non-missing MEMASPE values and 290 subjects have non-missing CYTOSPPT values.</s><s>The dotted vertical lines represent the selected thresholds by using BTAD1 (94.6 for MEMASPE and 92.5 for CYTOSPPT).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="18,112.92,62.00,446.16,432.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>estimates based on the full model under various designs for data generation model (3</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">J Biopharm Stat. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 22.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author Manuscript</head><p><s>Diao et al.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author Manuscript</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of epidermal growth factor receptor expression on survival and pattern of relapse in patients with advanced head and neck carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Ang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Berkey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H-Z</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hammond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Fu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Milas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7350" to="7356" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 12499279</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The cross-validated adaptive signature design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Freidlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-09-1357</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical Cancer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="691" to="698" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 20068112</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive signature design: An adaptive clinical trial design for generating and prospectively testing a gene expression signature for sensitive patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Freidlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-05-0605</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical Cancer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7872" to="7878" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 16278411</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asynchronous modulation of transforming growth factor alpha and epidermal growth factor receptor protein expression in progression of premalignant lesions to head and neck squamous cell carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Grandis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tweardy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Melhem</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical Cancer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 9516947</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Loss of PTEN expression predicts resistance to EGFR-targeted monoclonal antibodies in patients with metastatic colorectal cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Liao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/sj.bjc.6605575</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British Journal of Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">940</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 20160728</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EGFR and cancer prognosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Nicholson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jmw</forename><surname>Gee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Harper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0959-8049(01)00231-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="15" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 11165124</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Frequent genetic and biochemical alterations of the pi 3-k/AKT/PTEN pathway in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jmg</forename><surname>Pedrero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Carracedo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pinto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Zapatero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Rodrigo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Nieto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Gonzalez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/ijc.20711</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="242" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 15543611</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combined analysis of HPV-DNA, p16 and EGFR expression to predict prognosis in oropharyngeal cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Reimers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Kasper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Weissenborn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Stutzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Preuss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hoffmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ejm</forename><surname>Speel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dienes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pfister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Guntinas-Lichius</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/ijc.22355</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1731" to="1738" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 17236202</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive randomized phase ii design for biomarker threshold selection and independent evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Renfro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Coughlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Grothey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sargent</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chinese Clinical Oncology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical trial designs incorporating predictive biomarkers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Renfro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mallick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M-W</forename><surname>An</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sargent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mandrekar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ctrv.2015.12.008</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Treatment Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 26827695</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive enrichment designs for clinical trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/biostatistics/kxt010</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biostatistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="613" to="625" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 23525452</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cisplatin and fluorouracil with or without panitumumab in patients with recurrent or metastatic squamous-cell carcinoma of the head and neck (spectrum): An open-label phase 3 randomised trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Vermorken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stohlmacher-Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Davidenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Licitra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Winquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Villanueva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Foa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rottey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Skladowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tahara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S1470-2045(13)70181-5</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Lancet Oncology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="697" to="710" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 23746666</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
