<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Shadow over abdomen</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-07-26">26 July 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Devdeep</forename><surname>Mukherjee</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Neonatal Intensive Care Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">St Mary&apos;s Hospital</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Neonatal Intensive Care Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">St Mary&apos;s Hospital</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sajit</forename><surname>Nedungadi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Neonatal Intensive Care Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">St Mary&apos;s Hospital</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nedungadi</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bmj</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Neonatal Intensive Care Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">St Mary&apos;s Hospital</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Case</forename><surname>Rep</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Neonatal Intensive Care Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">St Mary&apos;s Hospital</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Shadow over abdomen</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-07-26">26 July 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">39A29A651D020731244E6E55F7CD20E9</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bcr-2018-226024</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:24+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DesCripTion</head><p><s>Male neonate was born by normal vaginal delivery at 38 weeks.</s><s>He was antenatally diagnosed to have dextrocardia, congenitally corrected transposition of great arteries, moderate ventricular septal defect and pulmonary atresia.</s><s>He was born in good condition and cried at birth.</s><s>However, he was noted to have saturation of 65%-70% in air and started on continuous positive airway pressure and transferred to neonatal intensive care unit for further monitoring.</s><s>Postnatal echocardiography confirmed the diagnosis, and he was started on prostaglandin E1 (PGE1) at 5 nanogram/kg/min.</s></p><p><s>On day 3 of life, he underwent a cardiac gated CT angiography (CTA) for further understanding of anatomy and confirmation of diagnosis.</s><s>In view of need for PGE1 until transfer to tertiary cardiac surgical centre, a peripherally inserted central venous catheter was inserted in the following 12 hours.</s><s>He underwent an abdominal X-ray to check long line position (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Abdominal X-ray showed a homogenous opacity within the urinary bladder due to retention of contrast.</s><s>Long line was visualised to the right.</s><s>The homogenous opacity was an incidental finding when X-ray was done to confirm the long line position.</s></p><p><s>The neonate was administered intravenous iohexol 350, which is a non-ionic water soluble contrast medium. 1 Iso-osmolar and hypo-osmolar contrast agents (300 mg I/mL or greater) are preferred as they cause less adverse reactions and extravasation in children undergoing CTA. 2 CTA accurately depicts the cardiac anatomy as well as the extracardiac structures in babies with complex congenital heart disease and thus serve as complimentary tools to echocardiography. <ref type="bibr">2 3</ref> Ninety per cent of iohexol undergoes renal excretion within the first 24 hours.</s><s>Renal opacification is seen within the first minute following intravenous injection.</s><s>Iohexol is also used for performing urograms.</s><s>Renal failure impairs opacification of the renal tract due to decreased excretion through the kidneys and increased excretion into the small intestine through the gall bladder.</s><s>This phenomenon is also noted in neonates with immature kidneys. <ref type="bibr">1</ref> Unless patients are well hydrated before the procedure, there is a likelihood of acute renal failure especially in infants and in the paediatric population.</s><s>Osmotic action of the contrast further potentiates dehydration due to diuresis. 1 Our patient was on maintenance intravenous fluids, and the X-ray  images in… repeated 6 hours after the previous showed further excretion of the contrast from the bladder (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</s></p><p><s>It is well-known fact that iodinated, non-ionic, water-soluble contrast agents are excreted by the kidneys.</s><s>Contrast media-induced nephropathy has been noted in children with normal renal function.</s><s>The documentation of a homogenous opacity within the urinary bladder was an incidental finding as an abdominal X-ray was done to confirm the long line tip position.</s><s>We would like to highlight the need for monitoring evidence of dehydration and renal function before the administration of contrast agents to the paediatric population. 1 4 Our patient's urea and creatinine preprocedure was 1.1 mmol/L and 64 µmol/L.</s><s>Postprocedure urea remained the same, and creatinine was 63 µmol/L.</s><s>Urine output remained between 2 mL/kg/h and 3 mL/kg/h.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure1Homogenous dense shadow within urinary bladder.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="1,145.67,448.93,197.55,271.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2 Normal X-ray of abdomen 6 hours later.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="1,355.72,123.88,197.55,317.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>We acknowledge the parents of this baby who gave consent for the images to be published.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Contributors</head><p><s>Both authors have been involved in conception and design of the article, data interpretation and writing the draft.</s><s>The final draft has been approved by both authors.</s><s>Both authors have been involved in patient care.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Competing interests</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Learning points</head><p><s>► Iodinated, non-ionic, water-soluble contrast agents are excreted by the kidneys.</s><s>► Babies should be adequately hydrated and their renal function should be checked before they are injected with contrast agents prior to any procedure.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
