<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">7A387474DE8E2FF4B956BE6711146F80</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jaci.2015.12.1338</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:24+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>autoinflammatory syndromes including other IL-1b mediated diseases.</s><s>This demonstrates for the first time alterations in the adaptive immune system in patients with autoinflammatory syndromes.</s><s>(J Allergy Clin Immunol 2016;138:1161-9.)</s><s>Key words: Autoinflammation, Schnitzler syndrome, T H 17 cells, IL-10, IL-1b T H 17 cells have been recognized as critical players in the pathogenesis of autoimmune diseases and in the clearance of extracellular pathogens and fungi. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref></s><s>In mice terminal differentiation of T H 17 cells is dependent on IL-23, which abrogates the induction of IL-10 and promotes IFN-g coexpression in IL-17-producing T helper cells.</s><s>This confers pathogenicity to T H 17 cells, as evidenced most strikingly in the EAE mouse model of multiple sclerosis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s>In human subjects 2 types of stable T H 17 cells have recently been identified in vivo. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>They differ in their property to coexpress either IL-10 or IFN-g and in their microbial antigen specificities.</s><s>These distinct phenotypes are generated with differential requirements for IL-1b during the polarization phase.</s><s>In humans IL-1b, but not IL-23, strongly suppresses IL-10 and promotes IFN-g/T-bet induction. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>espite this differential cytokine coexpression pattern, it has not been demonstrated so far whether these distinct human T H 17 cell phenotypes indeed translate into different functionalities.</s><s>Although both subsets continue to express proinflammatory IL-17, the question of whether anti-inflammatory IL-10 might confer a dominant immunosuppressive functionality on T H 17 cells is warranted.</s><s>This would necessitate a rethinking about the general concept of T H 17 cells being major mediators of inflammatory tissue destruction.</s></p><p><s>Autoinflammatory syndromes are characterized by overproduction of IL-1b caused by mutations in the inflammasome, a large intracellular multiprotein complex that leads to maturation of IL-1b and IL-18. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref></s><s>Due to the absence of inflammasome expression in cells of the adaptive immune system, autoinflammation has been considered to be caused solely by abrogations in innate immunity, although this could potentially also translate into downstream alterations of adaptive immune functions.</s><s>Schnitzler syndrome belongs to this group of very rare autoinflammatory syndromes.</s><s>It presents with a chronic urticarial rash, intermittent fever, arthralgia or arthritis, hepatomegaly and/or splenomegaly, lymphadenopathy, leukocytosis, and an increased erythrocyte sedimentation rate. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>We recently demonstrated 2 variant cases with somatic mosaicism of NLRP3 mutations in the myeloid lineage, leading to spontaneous IL-1b secretion by PBMCs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref></s><s>Furthermore, increased IL-1b secretion by LPS-stimulated PBMCs was reported. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref></s><s>Hence, apart from the monoclonal IgM gammopathy, the immunologic significance of which is unknown, and IL-1b overproduction, no immune-related abnormalities have been detected in patients with Schnitzler syndrome so far. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s>ecause IL-1b is the critical switch factor that determines whether T H 17 cells can coexpress IL-10, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> Schnitzler syndrome represents an ''experiment of nature'' in which alterations in adaptive immunity caused by systemic IL-1b overproduction can be studied in vivo in human subjects.</s><s>In addition, immunologic perturbations, such as systemic in vivo inhibition of IL-1b by targeted therapies with IL-1 receptor antagonist (IL-1Ra; anakinra) and IL-1b-neutralizing antibodies (canakinumab and gevokizumab), can be performed in vivo in this disease setting.</s><s>This revealed the existence of 2 functionally distinct subsets of human T H 17 cells, which can be categorized into proinflammatory versus anti-inflammatory subsets because of the dominant role of IL-10 and despite the heterogeneous cytokine repertoire of both T H 17 cell subsets.</s><s>We also demonstrate a loss of anti-inflammatory T H 17 cells in patients with Schnitzler syndrome, which could be restored to physiological levels upon therapeutic IL-1b inhibition.</s><s>This could have implications for disease pathogenesis and future therapeutic strategies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cell purification and sorting</head><p><s>CD14 1 monocytes and CD4 1 T cells were isolated from PBMCs after density gradient sedimentation with Ficoll-Paque Plus (GE Healthcare, Fairfield, Conn) by means of positive selection with CD14-or CD4-specific microbeads, respectively (Miltenyi Biotec, Bergisch Gladbach, Germany).</s><s>T helper cell subsets were sorted to greater than 97% purity as follows:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">T H 1 subset, CCR6 2 CCR4 2 CXCR3 1 CD45RA 2 CD25 2 CD8 2 ; T H 2 subset, CCR6 2 CCR4 1 CXCR3 2 CD45RA 2 CD25 2 CD8 2 ; and T H 17 subset, CCR6 1 CCR4 1 CXCR3 2 CD45RA 2 CD25 2 CD8 2 .</formula><p><s>The following antibodies were used for fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS): phycoerythrinconjugated anti-CCR6 (11A9; BD Biosciences, San Jose, Calif), phycoerythrin-indotricarbocyanine-conjugated anti-CCR4 (1G1; BD Biosciences), allophycocyanin-conjugated anti-CXCR3 (1C6/CXCR3; BD Biosciences), phycoerythrin-Cy5-conjugated anti-CD45RA (HI100, BD Biosciences), R phycoerythrin cyanin 5.1-conjugated anti-CD8 (B9.11;</s><s>Coulter Immunotech, Krefeld, Germany), and fluorescein isothiocyanate-conjugated anti-CD25 (B1.49.9;</s><s>Immunotech).</s><s>Naive T cells were isolated as CD45RA 1 CD45RO 2 CCR7 1 CD25 2 CD8 2 to a purity of greater than 99% after staining with the aforementioned antibodies against CD45RA, CD25, and CD8, as well as fluorescein isothiocyanate-conjugated CD45RO (UCHL1; Immunotech) and anti-CCR7 (150503; R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, Minn), followed by staining with biotinylated anti-IgG 2a (1080-08; SouthernBiotech, Birmingham, Ala) and streptavidin-Pacific blue (Molecular Probes, Invitrogen, Eugene, Ore).</s><s>Permission for experiments with human primary cells was obtained from the ethics committee of the Charit e-Universit€ atsmedizin Berlin (EA1/221/11), the ethics committee of the University of Wuerzburg (protocol no.</s><s>239/10), and the Radboud University Medical Center, Nijmegen, with approval by the local medical ethics committee, as well as from the ethics committee of the Technical University of Munich (195/15s).</s><s>Samples from patients with Schnitzler syndrome from the NCT01390350 10 cohort were obtained before and at different time points after treatment with canakinumab during a proof-of-principle immunologic study at the Charit e-Universit€ atsmedizin Berlin.</s><s>Patients were eligible for enrollment in the study if they had active Schnitzler syndrome.</s><s>All patients selected for this study responded to treatment with complete remission, as defined by physician's global assessment on overall autoinflammatory disease activity.</s><s>For more information on clinical trial details, we refer to NCT01390350 and Krause et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> Samples from patients with Schnitzler syndrome after treatment with gevokizumab were obtained from the Nijmegen Center for Immunodeficiency and Autoinflammation.</s><s>Clinical trial information is deposited in the EU Clinical Trials Register (EudraCT no.</s><s>2013-002562-39).</s><s>PBMCs of patients with systemic juvenile idiopathic arthritis (Still disease) who were naive for any biologic treatment were obtained from the Laboratory of Pediatric Rheumatology and Special Immunology, University Children's Hospital, University of Wuerzburg and the German Registry for Autoinflammatory Diseases (AID-Net).</s></p><p><s>Abbreviations used FACS: Fluorescence-activated cell sorting IL-1Ra: IL-1 receptor antagonist Treg: Regulatory T Cell sorting was performed with a FACSAria III or MoFlo (Beckman Coulter, Brea, Calif).</s><s>Flow cytometry was performed with a CytoFLEX (Beckman Coulter), FACSCanto (BD Biosciences), and MACSQuant (Miltenyi Biotec).</s><s>Flow cytometric data were analyzed with FlowJo software (TreeStar, Ashland, Ore).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cell culture</head><p><s>Cells were cultured in RPMI-1640 medium supplemented with 2 mmol/L glutamine, 1% (vol/vol) nonessential amino acids, 1% (vol/vol) sodium pyruvate, penicillin (50 U/mL), streptomycin (50 mg/mL; all from Invitrogen, Carlsbad, Calif), and 5% (vol/vol) human serum (Charit e Blood Center).</s><s>T cells were labeled with carboxyfluorescein succinimidyl ester (CFSE), according to standard protocols.</s><s>Monocytes were cultured for 24 hours with or without LPS (100 ng/mL; Sigma-Aldrich, St Louis, Mo).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Suppression assays</head><p><s>Naive CD45RA 1 CFSE-labeled CD4 1 T cells were cocultured as responder T cells with equal or titrated numbers of different T helper cell subsets in the presence of equal numbers of irradiated anti-CD3-coated (OKT3) PBMCs (28 Gy) as feeder cells.</s><s>In some experiments naive but also T helper cell subsets were used as responder cells, where indicated.</s><s>CFSE dilution was analyzed on day 4 by FACS.</s><s>For IL-10 neutralization, purified rat anti-human IL-10 (clone JES3-19F1, isotype control rat IgG 2a ) was used at a concentration of 10 mg/mL.</s><s>For suppression assays with material from patients, we cocultured the patients' T H 17 cells with healthy allogeneic naive T cells, which allowed us to assess the suppressive properties of the patients' T H 17 cells, irrespective of any potential alterations in the patients' naive T-cell (responder cell) proliferation capacity.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cytokine analyses</head><p><s>For intracellular cytokine staining, T cells were restimulated for 5 hours with phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate and ionomycin in the presence of brefeldin A (all from Sigma-Aldrich) for the final 2.5 hours of culture.</s><s>Monocytes were stimulated for 40 hours with LPS (100 ng/mL, Sigma) in the presence of brefeldin A and the absence of phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate and ionomycin.</s><s>Cells were fixed and made permeable with Cytofix/Cytoperm, according to the manufacturer's instructions (BD Biosciences).</s><s>Cells were stained with phycoerythrin-or allophycocyanin-conjugated anti-IL-10 (both JES3-19F1; BD Biosciences) and Alexa Fluor 647-or fluorescein isothiocyanate-conjugated anti-IL-17 (both eBIO64-DEC17; eBioscience, San Diego, Calif), PE/Cy7-conjugated TNF-a (BioLegend, San Diego, Calif), and phycoerythrin-or allophycocyanin-conjugated anti-GM-CSF (R&amp;D Systems).</s><s>Flow cytometric data were analyzed with FlowJo software.</s><s>Cytokines in T-cell culture supernatants were measured by using ELISA according to a standard protocol after restimulation of cultured T cells (5 3 10 4 cells in 200 mL) with phorbol-12-13-dibutyrate (50 nmol/L, Sigma-Aldrich) and plate-bound anti-CD3 (1 mg/mL, TR66) for 8 hours.</s><s>Data were analyzed by the Softmax program.</s><s>IL-1b and TNF-a secretion by monocytes was measured by using the cytometric bead array, according to the manufacturer's instructions (BD Biosciences), as well as by ELISA (DuoSet ELISA Kits; R&amp;D Systems).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistics</head><p><s>The Student t test was used to test the statistical significance of the results.</s><s>P values of .05 or less were considered statistically significant.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Human T H 17 cells have IL-10-dependent suppressive properties</head><p><s>T H 17 cells have a heterogeneous cytokine profile that goes beyond production of their lineage identifying cytokines IL-17 and IL-22. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> To investigate whether human T H 17 cells have anti-inflammatory properties, we performed T-cell suppression assays, which are classical surrogate assays to demonstrate regulatory activities of regulatory T (Treg) cells in both mice and human subjects.</s><s>T H 17 cells from healthy control subjects were sorted according to the differential expression of CCR6, CXCR3, and CCR4, which we have previously shown to highly enrich for the T H 17 cell subset at the exclusion of T H 1 and T H 2 cells. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref></s><s>To further exclude potentially contaminating Treg cells, we performed negative sorting for CD25 expression.</s><s>Surprisingly, T H 17 cells suppressed the proliferation of naive responder T helper cells in a dose-dependent manner (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1, A</ref>).</s><s>We next addressed the mechanism of T H 17 cell-mediated responder T-cell suppression.</s><s>IL-10 is a classical antiinflammatory cytokine that can be produced by the CCR6 1 CXCR3 2 CCR4 1 T H 17 cell subset. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>Compared with the T H 1 and T H 2 cell subsets, T H 17 cells have the highest IL-10 coexpression at the single-cell level after polyclonal stimulation with plate-bound CD3 and CD28 mAbs (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1, B and C</ref>).</s></p><p><s>For this reason, we analyzed whether IL-10 mediated the suppression of responder T cells.</s><s>Blocking IL-10 with neutralizing antibodies was indeed sufficient to reverse responder T-cell suppression by T H 17 cells to levels of responder cell proliferation seen in the absence of suppressor cells (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1, D</ref>).</s><s>This demonstrates that their ability to produce IL-10 provides T H 17 cells with net immunosuppressive functions.</s><s>This was surprising considering that they continue to produce proinflammatory cytokines, such as GM-CSF, which has been reported to confer pathogenic functions to T H 17 cells in the EAE mouse model <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> and correlates with multiple sclerosis in human subjects (see Fig E1 in this article's Online Repository at www.jacionline.org). <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref></s><s>herefore IL-10 exerts a dominant immunosuppressive functionality on human T H 17 cells despite coexpression of other proinflammatory cytokines, such as IL-17 and GM-CSF.</s></p><p><s>We have also dissected the ability of T H 17-IL-10 1 cells to differentially suppress distinct T helper cell subsets in addition to naive T helper cells.</s><s>Our data demonstrate that T H 17 cells can suppress the proliferation of not only naive responder cells but also effector T helper cell subsets of different lineages with variable efficiency (see Fig E2 in this article's Online Repository at www.jacionline.org).</s></p><p><s>Together, these data demonstrate IL-10-dependent suppressive properties of human T H 17 cells in an in vitro suppression assay.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Activation increases regulatory properties of human T H 17 cells</head><p><s>Human T H 17 cells have previously been demonstrated to upregulate IL-10 expression upon T-cell receptor stimulation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>To test whether T H 17 cell activation translates into more potent suppressive properties, we preactivated human T H 17 cells for 48 hours with CD3 and CD28 mAbs and assessed responder T-cell suppression (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</s><s>For comparison of regulatory strengths, we also performed suppression assays with professional CD25 high CD127 low Treg cells, which expressed greater than 90% forkhead box protein 3 (see Fig E3 in this article's Online Repository at www.jacionline.org).</s><s>In cultures with T H 17 cells that were not preactivated but only received weak activation stimuli from allogeneic anti-CD3-coated feeder cells during the coculture period, 29.6% 6 4.5% (mean 6 SEM) of responder cells proliferated.</s><s>This low stimulation strength was consistent with low IL-10 expression levels by nonpreactivated T H 17 cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> and correlated with low suppressive function (Fig 2 <ref type="figure">, B</ref>).</s></p><p><s>In cultures with Treg cells, only 3.2% 6 1.0% (mean 6 SEM) of responder cells proliferated compared with 53% 6 5.2% in the absence of suppressor cells.</s><s>As expected, polyclonal preactivation with plate-bound CD3 and CD28 antibodies induced IL-10 upregulation in T H 17 cells (not preactivated, 2.0% 6 0.8%; preactivated, 13.8% 6 2.4%).</s><s>This correlated with an increase in their suppressive function (responder cell proliferation, 2.7% 6 0.6%).</s><s>Interestingly, the suppressive strength of activated IL-10-producing T H 17 cells was even comparable with that of Treg cells (no significant difference, P 5 .7;</s><s>Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>), which are specialized in immunosuppression by multiple mechanisms. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Two types of human T H 17 cells that differ in regulatory properties</head><p><s>Human T H 17 cell subsets with distinct antigen specificities and differential priming requirements for IL-1b, which determines either IL-10 or IFN-g coexpression patterns, have been described recently. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>Whether this phenotypic diversity within the T H 17 cell subset translates into functional differences has not been analyzed yet.</s><s>We hypothesized that there are differential suppressive properties of IL-10 1 versus IL-10 2 T H 17 cells.</s><s>To test this, CCR6 1 CXCR3 2 CCR4 1 T H 17 cells, which we had demonstrated to coproduce IL-10, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> were restimulated with IL-1b for 48 hours.</s><s>This completely suppressed the ability of T H 17 cells to express IL-10, which is in accordance with published data (see Fig <ref type="figure">E4</ref> in this article's Online Repository at www.jacionline.org). <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>L-1b2treated and untreated T H 17 cells, which differed in their ability to coexpress IL-10, were then used for suppression assays.</s><s>In accordance with our hypothesis, we observed that both T H 17 cell subsets differed in their suppressive functions.</s><s>With IL-10 2 T H 17 cells, responder cell proliferation amounted to 83.5% of the control responder T-cell proliferation in the absence of suppressive T cells.</s><s>This did not differ statistically from control responder T-cell proliferation (P 5 .2),</s><s>whereas with IL-10 1 T H 17 cells, responder T-cell proliferation was strongly impaired (&gt;3-fold reduction, Fig <ref type="figure">3</ref>).</s><s>This demonstrated that IL-1b acts as a critical switch factor for determining proinflammatory versus anti-inflammatory functionalities of human T H 17 cells.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Two types of T H 17 cells that differ in their property to modulate innate cytokine secretion</head><p><s>Suppression assays are considered powerful surrogates for determining the regulatory properties of T cells in vitro.</s><s>Even though they have clearly demonstrated the suppressive properties of Treg cells previously, it has been questioned whether in vivo properties of T cells with regulatory functions are reflected by this in vitro assay with high fidelity. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref></s><s>To corroborate our finding of differential regulatory properties of T H 17-IL-10 1 and T H 17-IL-10 2 cells, we also used another experimental readout for regulatory functions.</s><s>We therefore tested the ability of both T H 17 types to downregulate production of proinflammatory cytokines, in particular IL-1b, by antigenpresenting cells, such as monocytes.</s><s>CD14 1 monocytes were stimulated with LPS, which is sufficient for induction of IL-1b secretion in human subjects in accordance with published data. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref></s><s>They were cocultured with 48-hour preactivated T H 1, T H 2, and T H 17 cells, which were isolated according to their differential expression of CXCR3, CCR4, and CCR6.</s><s>T H 17 cells efficiently suppressed the secretion of bioactive IL-1b by monocytes (Fig 4 <ref type="figure">, A</ref>).</s><s>Interestingly, the T H 17 cell subset was the most efficient T helper cell subset for innate IL-1b suppression compared with the T H 1 and T H 2 cell subsets.</s><s>This correlated with its ability to produce the highest levels of IL-10 upon activation (Fig 4 <ref type="figure">, B</ref>).</s><s>This suppressive property was not only restricted to IL-1b secretion.</s><s>T H 17 cells, but not T H 1 and T H 2 cells, also significantly suppressed the secretion of other proinflammatory cytokines, such as TNF-a, by monocytes in response to LPS (see Fig <ref type="figure">E5, A</ref>, in this article's Online Repository at www.jacionline.org),</s><s>although the frequency of TNF-a 1 monocytes was not altered after coculture with different T helper cell subsets (see Fig <ref type="figure">E5, B</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To test whether the 2 distinct T H 17 cell subsets differed in their ability to suppress proinflammatory cytokine secretion by monocytes, T H 17 cells that were preactivated in the presence (T H 17-IL-10 2 ) or absence (T H 17-IL-10 1 ) of IL-1b were cocultured with LPS-stimulated monocytes (Fig 4 <ref type="figure">, C</ref>).</s><s>Only T H 17-IL-10 1 cells suppressed IL-1b secretion.</s><s>This was dependent on their IL-10 secretion because addition of IL-10neutralizing antibodies to the coculture abrogated their ability to downregulate IL-1b secretion.</s><s>Exogenous addition of recombinant IL-10, on the other hand, resulted in reduced IL-1b secretion, even in coculture with T H 17-IL-10 2 cells, highlighting a role of soluble IL-10 as a potent suppressor of IL-1b secretion.</s><s>Interestingly, our control condition with LPS-stimulated monocytes alone demonstrated that addition of IL-10-neutralizing antibodies also increases IL-1b secretion in the absence of T cells, indicating autocrine IL-10 secretion by monocytes as a negative feedback mechanism for the proinflammatory IL-1b production.</s></p><p><s>Together, these results demonstrate a novel property of T H 17 cells.</s><s>They can downregulate the inflammatory properties of antigen-presenting cells, such as monocytes, by reducing secretion of proinflammatory cytokines, including IL-1b and TNF-a.</s><s>In addition, we revealed that T H 17 cells differed in their ability to mediate this anti-inflammatory function depending on whether they belonged to the IL-10 1 or IL-10 2 subset.</s></p><p><s>T H 17 cells from patients with Schnitzler syndrome have reduced regulatory properties, which are restored with IL-1b-targeting therapies Autoinflammatory syndromes comprise a group of rare, mostly hereditary inflammatory disorders, which present with recurrent fevers, skin rashes, and arthritis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref></s><s>Inflammasome defects lead to overproduction of IL-1, which mediates immunopathology.</s><s>Because we had demonstrated that IL-1b suppressed IL-10 production by T H 17 cells, <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> we hypothesized that patients with autoinflammatory syndromes have reduced regulatory T H 17 cell functions and that IL-1b-blocking therapies, such as IL-1Ra (anakinra) or anti-IL-1b (canakinumab and gevokizumab), would restore regulatory properties in T H 17 cells.</s><s>Therefore autoinflammatory syndromes provide the unique opportunity to study in an ''experiment of nature'' human regulatory T H 17 cell functions and their therapeutic perturbations in vivo.</s></p><p><s>We isolated T H 17 cells from healthy age-matched donors, as well as from patients with Schnitzler syndrome, an autoinflammatory syndrome, <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> and performed suppression assays with healthy memory responder T helper cells.</s><s>Interestingly, T H 17 cells from patients with Schnitzler syndrome showed inferior suppressive functions compared with T H 17 cells from healthy donors in all experiments (Fig 5 <ref type="figure">, A</ref>).</s><s>This correlated with a We next isolated T H 17 cells from patients with Schnitzler syndrome under treatment with IL-1b-blocking drugs.</s><s>We hypothesized that therapeutic abrogation of IL-1b signaling in patients with Schnitzler syndrome would likewise restore regulatory functions of T helper cell subsets.</s><s>Indeed, IL-10 expression was restored to baseline levels after treatment with the IL-1b-neutralizing antibody canakinumab within the same patients after 6 months of treatment (matched pairs).</s><s>All patients had systemic inflammation, including recurrent fevers and arthralgias caused by IL-1b overproduction that subsided on the aforementioned IL-1b-blocking therapies, resulting in complete remission. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref></s><s>o further corroborate this finding, we also analyzed IL-10 expression in T H 17 cells from patients with Schnitzler syndrome undergoing treatment with gevokizumab (n 5 2), another IL-1b mAb, as well as anakinra, an IL-1Ra (n 5 1), which amounts to a total of 6 patients with this very rare disease.</s><s>We observed increased IL-10 expression levels compared with those in patients who did not receive any IL-1b-targeting treatment (P 5 .05;</s><s>Fig <ref type="figure">5, C</ref>).</s><s>Although IL-10 expression was significantly upregulated with gevokizumab and anakinra, it did not amount to the same high levels seen in patients receiving canakinumab treatment.</s><s>Nevertheless, in all of the patients analyzed, irrespective of the mode of IL-1b blockade, we observed increased IL-10 expression on IL-1b-blocking treatments (Fig 5 <ref type="figure">, B and C</ref>).</s><s>In addition, IL-1b-blocking therapy with canakinumab improved the regulatory properties of T H 17 cells in suppression assays (Fig 5 <ref type="figure">, D</ref>). Together, these experiments demonstrate that patients with Schnitzler syndrome have T H 17 cells with reduced regulatory properties, which can be restored by IL-1b-blocking therapies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>T H 17 cells have thus far been considered critical players in autoimmune tissue inflammation, as well as in pathogen clearance.</s><s>Recently, GM-CSF, but not IL-17, has been shown to be the crucial pathogenic T H 17 cell cytokine in the EAE mouse model for multiple sclerosis and to be also associated with human multiple sclerosis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref></s><s>This demonstrates that the pathogenicity of T H 17 cells is determined by specific cytokine coexpression patterns rather than by IL-17 expression alone.</s><s>This also suggests that T H 17 cells can assume different functions depending on their cytokine profile.</s><s>Therefore, T H 17 targeting is expected to have different outcomes depending on whether the downstream signature cytokine IL-17 or upstream T H 17 cell inducers, such as IL-23 or IL-1b, which determine the heterogeneous cytokine repertoire of T H 17 cells, are blocked.</s><s>This has important implications for therapeutic strategies.</s></p><p><s>We have now demonstrated that T H 17 cells, which can coproduce IL-10, have regulatory functions comparable with those of Treg cells because of their ability to suppress T helper cell proliferation.</s><s>In addition, they have the ability to downregulate proinflammatory innate cytokine production by monocytes, an anti-inflammatory property that Treg cells do not possess. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref></s><s>owever, T H 17 cells, which were generated in the presence of IL-1b, did not have these properties.</s><s>This demonstrates the existence of 2 functionally distinct types of T H 17 cell subsets, which, B C FIG 4. T H 17 cells suppress IL-1b secretion by monocytes through IL-10 production.</s><s>A, Monocytes were stimulated with LPS for 48 hours and cocultured with T H 1, T H 2, and T H 17 cell subsets that have been isolated according to the differential expression of CXCR3, CCR4, and CCR6 and preactivated for 48 hours with CD3 and CD28 mAbs before coculture for 48 hours.</s><s>IL-1b was analyzed by using a cytometric bead array.</s><s>Data show means 6 SEMs (n 5 3).</s><s>Numbers indicate P values (paired Student t test).</s><s>B, T H 1, T H 2, and T H 17 cell subsets were isolated ex vivo as in Fig <ref type="figure">4, A</ref>, and stimulated for 48 hours with plate-bound CD3 and CD28 mAb.</s><s>IL-10 levels were measured by ELISA after restimulation of equal numbers of preactivated T cells with phorbol-12-13-dibutyrate and platebound anti-CD3 (1 mg/mL, TR66) for 8 hours.</s><s>Data show mean 6 SEMs (n 5 3).</s><s>C, Monocytes were stimulated as in Fig <ref type="figure">4, A</ref>, in the presence or absence of T H 17-IL-10 1 or T H 17-IL-10 2 cells that had been generated by restimulation of T H 17 cells (CCR6 1 CCR4 1 CXCR3 2 memory T cells) in the presence or absence of IL-1b, respectively.</s><s>IL-10-blocking mAbs (10 mg/ml) or recombinant IL-10 (10 ng/mL) was added where indicated.</s><s>Supernatant was analyzed after 48 hours by cytometric bead array.</s><s>Data show mean 6 SEMs (n 5 3).</s></p><p><s>due to differential IL-10 coexpression patterns that can be modulated by IL-1b, possess either proinflammatory or antiinflammatory functions.</s><s>This provides a functional basis for the previous phenotypic characterization of IL-10-producing human T H 17 cells. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>Therefore, the view of T H 17 cells as major culprits of autoimmune pathogenesis needs to be refined to take into consideration a novel functionality with opposite effects.</s></p><p><s>Having T H 17-IL-10 1 cells join the family of Treg helper cell subsets elicits the question of the differential contribution of T H 17 cells to immunoregulation as compared to other Treg cell subsets.</s><s>IL-10 is a regulatory cytokine shared by Treg cells, T R 1 cells, and T H 17-IL-10 1 T cells.</s><s>Although Treg cells are professional anti-inflammatory T cells based on several mechanisms beyond IL-10 production, <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> T R 1 and T H 17-IL-10 1 T cells share coexpression of IL-10 with the proinflammatory cytokines IFN-g or IL-17, respectively. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref></s><s>Although the functional significance of simultaneous IFN-g and IL-10 coexpression in T R 1 cells has not been clarified, T H 17-IL-10 1 cells show a kinetic segregation of IL-17 and IL-10 expression upon activation at the singlecell level. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>This allows early proinflammatory IL-17 production upon antigen recognition, which is followed by IL-10 upregulation as a self-regulatory feedback loop. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>This could potentially limit bystander tissue inflammation through IL-10-mediated downregulation of antigen presentation and costimulation by antigen-presenting cells and, as we have now demonstrated, proinflammatory cytokine production.</s><s>Treg cells have been reported to acquire the ability to express proinflammatory cytokines in inflammatory microenvironments.</s><s>This has been interpreted as instability or plasticity, including loss of regulatory activities. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref></s><s>However, more recent studies have demonstrated that regulatory functions in Treg cells could be stably maintained despite IL-17 coexpression. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref></s><s>This distinguishes IL-10 1 IL-17 <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Treg cells from IL-10 1 IL-17 1 T H 17 cells on a functional level, despite similar phenotypes.</s><s>In addition, we showed that the anti-inflammatory ability to suppress proinflammatory cytokine production by innate cells is a property of T H 17-IL-10 1 cells but not Treg cells. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref></s><s>verproduction of IL-1b causes considerable inflammation and tissue damage, as seen in patients with mutations in the inflammasome who suffer from autoinflammatory syndromes. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref></s><s>herefore mechanisms must be in place to curtail inflammasome activation.</s><s>While a lot of emphasis has been placed on modes and mechanisms of inflammasome activation so far, little is known on how to suppress it.</s><s>Recently, T cells have been reported to dampen innate immune responses through inhibition of NLRP1 and NLRP3 inflammasomes through cell contact-dependent mechanisms. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26</ref></s><s>We have now demonstrated that a subset of human T H 17 cells, IL-1b-independent T H 17 cells (T H 17-IL-10 1 ), can efficiently suppress innate IL-1b secretion through their ability to produce IL-10.</s><s>This shows that human T H 17 cells can also limit innate inflammation.</s><s>In the future, it will be interesting to dissect the mechanistic details of how T H 17 cells affect distinct components of the inflammasome machinery to curtail IL-1b secretion.</s></p><p><s>We further showed that in the autoinflammatory disorder Schnitzler syndrome, the ability of T H 17 cells to produce IL-10 is reduced.</s><s>This is consistent with overexuberant inflammasome activation and thus IL-1b secretion in autoinflammation, which cannot be sufficiently counterbalanced due to abrogated T H 17-IL-10 1 cell-mediated feedback mechanisms.</s></p><p><s>In conclusion, we provide novel insights into the immunoregulation of autoinflammatory syndromes by demonstrating loss of IL-10 production by T H 17 cells, which could be reversed by therapeutic IL-1b targeting.</s><s>This could have implications for the pathogenesis of autoinflammatory and other chronic inflammatory diseases, as well as for future therapeutic strategies, because IL-10 1 and IL-10 2 T H 17 subsets exist with self-regulatory versus proinflammatory functions, respectively.</s><s>Therefore the contribution of T H 17 cells to the pathogenesis of different diseases should be assessed considering their existence as 2 functionally distinct subsets.</s></p><p><s>We thank Dr Anna Simon, internist at the Radboud University Medical Center in Nijmegen, The Netherlands, for patient recruitment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Key messages</head><p><s>d This is the first report of functional alterations of human T H 17 cells in patients with autoinflammatory syndromes, such as Schnitzler syndrome.</s></p><p><s>d Systemic IL-1b blockage can restore anti-inflammatory functionalities in human T H 17 cells and thus could potentially serve as a therapeutic target in T H 17-driven inflammatory diseases, even beyond autoinflammatory syndromes.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIG 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIG 1. Human T H 17 cells have IL-10-dependent regulatory functions.</s><s>A, T H 17 cells were isolated as CXCR3 2 CCR4 1 CCR6 1 CD25 2 T helper cells and cocultured at different ratios with naive CFSE-labeled responder T cells in the presence of feeder cells for 3 days.</s><s>Data are representative of 3 individual experiments.</s><s>B and C, Intracellular staining and flow cytometry of human T helper cell subsets on day 5 after 48 hours of stimulation with CD3 and CD28 mAbs.</s><s>T helper cell subsets were isolated according to the differential expression of CXCR3, CCR4, and CCR6, as indicated.</s><s>Different symbols indicate individual donors.</s><s>D, The suppression assay was performed as in Fig 1, A, with equal numbers of responder and T H 17 cells with or without addition of anti-IL-10 (10 mg/mL).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,45.47,65.59,490.31,382.17" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FIG 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIG 2. Regulatory properties of human T H 17 cells increase after T-cell receptor activation.</s><s>A and B, Suppression assays with T H 17 and control Treg cells with and without prior stimulation with CD3 and CD28 mAbs for 48 hours were performed.</s><s>Numbers in vertical gates indicate percentages of IL-10 1 cells (small regular font) and percentages of proliferating cells (large boldface font) among all viable cells.</s><s>Dot plot presentation was chosen to simultaneously demonstrate proliferation by means of CFSE dilution, as well as cytokine expression of CFSE-unlabeled T H 17 and Treg cells.</s><s>Data are representative of 3 experiments (Fig 2, A) and cumulative data (Fig 2, B).</s><s>Error bars indicate means 6 SEMs (n 5 3).</s><s>n.s.,</s><s>Not significant.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>10 FIG 5 .</head><label>105</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIG 5. Regulatory properties of T H 17 cells are abrogated in patients with Schnitzler syndrome but can be restored upon IL-1b-blocking treatments.</s><s>A and D, Suppression assays with T H 17 cells from healthy donors and patients with Schnitzler syndrome (SchS) before and after treatment with canakinumab were performed by using allogeneic, healthy, naive, CFSE-labeled responder cells.</s><s>Numbers in vertical gates indicate percentages of IL-10 1 or IL-17 1 cells (small regular font) and percentages of proliferating cells (large boldface font) among all acquired cells.</s><s>Dot plot presentation was chosen to simultaneously demonstrate proliferation by CFSE dilution, as well as cytokine expression of CFSE-unlabeled T H 17 cells, which served as suppressor cells.</s><s>Data are representative of 3 experiments.</s><s>B and C, Intracellular cytokine staining and flow cytometric analysis of T H 17 cells from healthy donors, symptomatic patients with Schnitzler syndrome, and the identical patients (matched pairs) after at least 6 months of treatment with canakinumab with a complete clinical response.</s><s>Numbers in gates indicate percentages as in Fig 5, A. Data are representative of 3 experiments (3 matched patient pairs before and after treatment; Fig 5, C) or cumulative data (healthy control subjects [n 5 6], patients with Schnitzler syndrome without IL-1b-blocking treatment [n 5 5], and patients with Schnitzler syndrome with canakinumab treatment [n 5 3], including additional treatment conditions with gevokizumab [n 5 2] and anakinra [n 5 1]; Fig 5, B).</s><s>Error bars indicate mean 6 SEMs.</s><s>IL-10 expression was analyzed by using intracellular cytokine staining and FACS analysis of T H 17 cells stimulated for 48 hours with CD3/CD28 mAbs on day 5 of culture, just like patient samples from canakinumab-treated patients.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,59.84,315.73,66.74,66.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>d</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIG E1.</s><s>IL-10 1 and IL-10 2 T H 17 cells both coexpress proinflammatory GM-CSF and IL-17.</s><s>A, T H 17 cells were isolated as CXCR3 2 CCR4 1 CCR6 1 T cells and restimulated in the presence (T H 17-IL-10 2 ) or absence (T H 17-IL-10 1 ) of IL-1b (10 ng/mL) for 48 hours with plate-bound CD3 and CD28 mAbs.</s><s>On day 5, intracellular staining and flow cytometry after phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate and ionomycin stimulation for 5 hours was performed.</s><s>Shown is 1 representative experiment out of 8 experiments.</s><s>B, Cumulative data (n 5 8, mean 6 S.E.M).</s><s>n.s.,</s><s>Not significant (Student t test).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>+ CCR6 -) Th17 (CXCR3 -CCR6 + ) Th2 (CXCR3 -CCR4 + )</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIG E2.</s><s>T H 17-IL-10 1 cells can suppress proliferation of distinct T helper cell subsets.</s><s>T H 17 cells were isolated as CXCR3 2 CCR4 1 CCR6 1 T cells and restimulated for 48 hours with plate-bound CD3 and CD28 mAbs and expanded for another 3 days, which gave rise to T H 17-IL-10 1 cells as shown previously.<ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>T H 17-IL-10 1 cells were then used for suppression assays with naive CD45RA 1 CFSE-labeled T helper cells from the same donors or responder cells isolated as distinct T helper cell subsets according to the indicated expression of chemokine receptor surface markers.</s><s>CFSE dilution was assessed on day 4 by FACS.</s><s>Representative data shown are from 1 donor for naive, T H 1, and T H 17 responder cells and from another donor for T H 2 responder cells because cell number limitations from buffy coats limited the simultaneous analysis of more than 3 different responder cell subsets with T H 17-IL-10 1 cells as suppressor cells.</s><s>Data are representative of 5 suppression assays with naive, T H 1, and T H 17 cells as responder cells and 4 experiments for T H 2 cells as responder cells.</s><s>In 2 experiments T H 2 cells are defined as CCR4 1 CXCR3 2 cells and in the other 2 experiments additionally as CCR6 2 cells.</s><s>In all experiments T H 17-IL-10 1 cells suppressed proliferation of their respective responder cells, although the degree of suppression varied from experiment to experiment, as did the degree of the respective control responder cell proliferation in response to OKT3 and feeder cell stimulation in the absence of T H 17-IL-10 1 suppressor cells.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>FIG E3 .</head><label>E3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIG E3.</s><s>Phenotypic characteristics of Treg cells in suppression assays.</s><s>Treg cells were isolated as CD4 1 T cells by means of MACS separation and FACS sorted as CD127 2 and CD25 high .</s><s>Shown is the representative expression of forkhead box protein 3 (FoxP3) of this cell population, as determined by intracellular staining and flow cytometry followed by analysis with FlowJo software.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="12,54.38,83.17,91.94,91.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIG E6.</s><s>IL-10 expression levels in T cells from patients with Still disease (systemic juvenile idiopathic arthritis).</s><s>A, Memory T cells were isolated by means of FACS sorting as CD45RA 2 CD4 1 CCR6 1 CXCR3 T cells and stimulated with plate-bound CD3 and CD28 mAbs for 48 hours and expanded for another 3 days before intracellular cytokine staining after phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate and ionomycin stimulation.</s><s>Shown are representative FACS plots for 3 patients with systemic juvenile idiopathic arthritis and 1 patient with adult-onset Still disease who were not receiving IL-1b-blocking treatments.</s><s>Numbers in quadrants indicate percentages of positive cells, as determined by intracellular cytokine staining.</s><s>B, Cumulative data for patients with systemic juvenile idiopathic arthritis.</s><s>Data show mean 6 SEMs (n 5 3).</s><s>*P &lt; .03</s><s>(Student t test).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="15,67.22,91.75,98.71,98.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="1,70.92,204.21,442.21,176.43" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Two types of T H 17 cells that differ in their suppressive properties.</s><s>A and B, Th17 cells were isolated as CXCR3 2 CCR4 1 CCR6 1 T cells and restimulated in the presence (T H 17-IL-10 2 ) or absence (T H 17-IL-10 1 ) of IL-1b (10 ng/mL) for 48 hours with plate-bound CD3 and CD28 mAbs.</s><s>T H 17-IL-10 2 and T H 17-IL-10 1 cells were then used for suppression assays with naive CFSE-labeled T helper cells from the same donors.</s><s>CFSE dilu-Fig E6 in this article's Online Repository at www.jacionline.</s><s>org).</s><s>IL-17 production was variable and did not show statistical differences between patients and healthy control donors (cumulative data not shown).</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Count A</cell><cell>56.5% responder cells no suppressor cells</cell><cell>Count</cell><cell>18.5% +Th17-IL-10 + responder cells</cell><cell>Count</cell><cell>47.4% +Th17-IL-10 -responder cells</cell><cell>B proliferation (% of control)</cell><cell>0 20 40 60 80 100</cell><cell>p = 0.0007</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>CFSE</cell><cell></cell><cell>CFSE</cell><cell></cell><cell>CFSE</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">T h 1 7 -I L -1 0 -T h 1 7 -I L -1 0 +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>FIG 3.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>tion was assessed on day 4 by using FACS.Bars indicate percentages of proliferating responder cells among all viable cells.Data are representative of 6 experiments (Fig 3, A) or cumulative data (Fig 3, B).Error bars indicate means 6 SEMs (n 5 6).Due to variability of responder T-cell proliferation in different experiments, the proliferating responder cell fraction in the absence of suppressor cells (control condition) is set to 100%.Shown is the percentage of proliferating responder cells in the presence of suppressor cells in relation to the control condition (Fig 3, B).No significant difference in proliferation of responder cells in the absence of suppressor cells (control) and in the presence of T H 17-IL-10 2 was detected (P 5 .18).significantly reduced ability of T H 17 cells from patients with Schnitzler syndrome to produce IL-10 upon polyclonal restimulation (Fig 5, B and C).</s><s>Reduced IL-10 expression levels were not only restricted to T H 17 cells from patients with Schnitzler syndrome but were also observed in T cells from patients with systemic juvenile idiopathic arthritis, another autoinflammatory disease, which is in line with their increased systemic IL-1b levels (see</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref>IG E2.T H 17-IL-10 1 cells can suppress proliferation of distinct T helper cell subsets.T H 17 cells were isolated as CXCR3 2 CCR4 1 CCR6 1 T cells and restimulated for 48 hours with plate-bound CD3 and CD28 mAbs and expanded for another 3 days, which gave rise to T H 17-IL-10 1 cells as shown previously.4TH</s><s>17-IL-10 1 cells were then used for suppression assays with naive CD45RA 1 CFSE-labeled T helper cells from the same donors or responder cells isolated as distinct T helper cell subsets according to the indicated expression of chemokine receptor surface markers.CFSE dilution was assessed on day 4 by FACS.Representative data shown are from 1 donor for naive, T H 1, and T H 17 responder cells and from another donor for T H 2 responder cells because cell number limitations from buffy coats limited the simultaneous analysis of more than 3 different responder cell subsets with T H 17-IL-10 1 cells as suppressor cells.Data are representative of 5 suppression assays with naive, T H 1, and T H 17 cells as responder cells and 4 experiments for T H 2 cells as responder cells.In 2 experiments T H 2 cells are defined as CCR41</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Th17-IL10 +</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>responder cells:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CFSE</cell><cell>CFSE</cell><cell>CFSE</cell><cell>CFSE</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">responder T cells + Th17-IL-10 +</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>T cells alone</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">J ALLERGY CLIN IMMUNOL VOLUME 138, NUMBER 4</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human Th17 subsets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sallusto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Zielinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lanzavecchia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2215" to="2220" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TH17 cells in the big picture of immunology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Schmidt-Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Akdis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Akdis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="247" to="254" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">TGF-beta and IL-6 drive the production of IL-17 and IL-10 by T cells and restrain T(H)-17 cell-mediated pathology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mcgeachy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bak-Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Blumenschein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mcclanahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1390" to="1397" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathogen-induced human TH17 cells produce IFN-gamma or IL-10 and are regulated by IL-1beta</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Zielinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Aschenbrenner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Jarrossay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ronchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gattorno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">484</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="514" to="518" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inflammatory caspases: linking an intracellular innate immune system to autoinflammatory diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Martinon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Tschopp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="561" to="574" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Schnitzler syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lipsker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Orphanet J Rare Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">38</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Schnitzler Syndrome Study Group. Schnitzler syndrome: beyond the case reports: review and follow-up of 94 patients with an emphasis on prognosis and treatment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>De Koning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bodar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Van Der Meer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semin Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Myeloid lineage-restricted somatic mosaicism of NLRP3 mutations in patients with variant Schnitzler syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>De Koning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Van Gijn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stoffels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jongekrijg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zeeuwen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Elferink</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">135</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="561" to="564" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IL-1 blockade in Schnitzler syndrome: ex vivo findings correlate with clinical remission</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Ryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>De Koning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Beck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Booty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kastner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="260" to="262" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effectiveness of canakinumab treatment in Schnitzler&apos;s syndrome: a multi-center randomized placebo-controlled study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Krause</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tsianakas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Weller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Metz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatr Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">O66</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>suppl</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surface phenotype and antigenic specificity of human interleukin 17-producing T helper memory cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Acosta-Rodriguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Rivino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Geginat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Jarrossay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gattorno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lanzavecchia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="639" to="646" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RORgammat drives production of the cytokine GM-CSF in helper T cells, which is essential for the effector phase of autoimmune neuroinflammation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Codarri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gyulveszi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Tosevski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hesske</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fontana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Magnenat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="560" to="567" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The encephalitogenicity of T(H)17 cells is dependent on IL-1-and IL-23-induced production of the cytokine GM-CSF</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>El-Behi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ciric</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Dai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cullimore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Safavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="568" to="575" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IL-17 and GM-CSF expression are antagonistically regulated by human T helper cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Noster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Riedel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Mashreghi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Radbruch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Harms</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Haftmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci Transl Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="280" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulatory T cells: mechanisms of differentiation and function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Josefowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Rudensky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu Rev Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="531" to="564" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanisms of foxp31 T regulatory cell-mediated suppression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shevach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="636" to="645" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ATPinduced IL-1beta specific secretion: true under stringent conditions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stoffels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Zaal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kok</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Van Der Meer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Dinarello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">54</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Autoinflammation: the prominent role of IL-1 in monogenic autoinflammatory diseases and implications for common illnesses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Goldbach-Mansky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kastner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1141" to="1151" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of in vitro and in vivo anakinra on cytokines production in Schnitzler syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Launay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Dutoit-Lefevre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Faure</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Robineau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hauspie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Sobanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e59327</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IL-1 blockade in autoinflammatory syndromes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jesus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Goldbach-Mansky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu Rev Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="244" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tr1 cells, but not Foxp31 regulatory T cells, suppress NLRP3 inflammasome activation via an IL-10-dependent mechanism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vent-Schmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mcgeough</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Steiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">195</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="488" to="497" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanisms and treatment of allergic disease in the big picture of regulatory T cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Akdis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Akdis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="735" to="748" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IL-10-producing forkhead box protein 3-negative regulatory T cells inhibit B-cell responses and are involved in systemic lupus erythematosus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Facciotti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Gagliani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Haringer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Alfen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Penatti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Maglie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="318" to="321" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>e5</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lineage stability and phenotypic plasticity of Foxp3(1) regulatory T cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hori</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunol Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">259</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IL-17-producing human peripheral regulatory T cells retain suppressive function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Beriou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Costantino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ashley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kuchroo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Baecher-Allan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4240" to="4249" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">T cells dampen innate immune responses through inhibition of NLRP1 and NLRP3 inflammasomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Guarda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dostert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Staehli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Cabalzar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Castillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tardivel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">460</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="269" to="273" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
