<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sutureless Aortic Valve Replacement in a Patient with Transfemoral Aortic Valve Replacement and Left Ventricular Hypertrophy</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-07-10">July 10, 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Torsten</forename><surname>Christ</surname></persName>
							<email>torsten.christ@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiovascular Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Pascal</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Dohmen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiovascular Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Laule</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology and Angiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Karl</forename><surname>Stangl</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology and Angiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wolfgang</forename><surname>Konertz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiovascular Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiovascular Surgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sutureless Aortic Valve Replacement in a Patient with Transfemoral Aortic Valve Replacement and Left Ventricular Hypertrophy</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">2194-7635</idno>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-07-10">July 10, 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">49CABFD71E12098FCBEC77CD83334C05</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1055/s-0035-1554991</idno>
					<note type="submission">received March 21, 2015 accepted April 16, 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:25+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>► aortic valve ► heart valve ► TAVI ► cardiomyopathy ► sutureless aortic valve</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Background Transarterial valve intervention (TAVI) is valuable in high-risk patients, however, in case of left ventricular outflow tract (LVOT) obstruction, conventional surgery, including partial myectomy, is indicated.</s><s>Case Description An 84-year-old female patient presented with increasing fatigue after TAVI in 2012, demonstrated a narrowed LVOT.</s><s>Conventional surgery was performed, including removal of the transcathether valve, partial septal myectomy, and implantation of a sutureless valve.</s><s>The postoperative course was uncomplicated.</s><s>Conclusion Aortic valve stenosis combined with severe left-ventricular hypertrophy is not ideal for TAVI.</s><s>Conventional surgery, performing partial septal myectomy and implantation of sutureless aortic prosthesis, seems more appropriate.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p><s>Transaortic valve intervention (TAVI) is a valuable technique in inoperable and very high-risk patients with severe aortic valve stenosis. 1</s><s>These patients often show secondary left ventricular hypertrophy due to chronic pressure overload.</s><s>In case of left ventricular outflow tract (LVOT) obstruction, partial septal myectomy should be considered the most appropriate treatment for most patients. 2</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case Description</head><p><s>An 84-year-old female patient presented with increasing fatigue after transfemoral valve implantation 2 years ago at another hospital.</s><s>A 23-mm Edwards sapien (Edwards Lifesciences LLC, Irvine, CA) transcatheter heart valve was implanted.</s><s>Echocardiographic examination demonstrated severe narrowing of the LVOT at 12 mm with a peak pressure gradient of 30.0 mm Hg due to severe septal hypertrophy (►Fig.</s><s>1) and an elevated pressure gradient across the valve.</s><s>Invasive pressure measurement showed a peak pressure gradient of 74.0 mm Hg between the left ventricle and the ascending aorta.</s><s>After clarifying therapeutic options for the patient (EuroSCORE: 10.1%, Euro-SCORE II: 7.54%, STS score: 16.9%), conventional surgery, including sternotomy, aortic cross-clamp, and cardiopulmonary bypass was preferred.</s><s>The Edwards sapien aortic valve was explanted and the calcified native cusps were removed.</s><s>The prosthetic valve showed thick pannus formation toward the LVOT (►Fig.</s><s>2A), which was confirmed histologically by a pentachrome staining (►Fig.</s><s>2B).</s><s>Additionally, thrombotic material was found at the cusps toward the aorta.</s><s>Partial septal myectomy was performed and a sutureless aortic valve (Sorin Perceval Size M [Sorin Group, Milan, Italy]) was implanted.</s><s>Cross-clamp and cardiopulmonary bypass time was 25 and 43 minutes, respectively.</s><s>The postoperative course of the patient was uncomplicated with stable sinus rhythm and no atrioventricular block occurred.</s><s>Echocardiography showed an enlarged LVOT (►Fig. 3)</s><s>with a peak pressure gradient of 13 mm Hg, a normal function of the prosthesis, and no ventricular septal defect.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>High-risk patients suffering from severe aortic valve stenosis in combination with extensive left ventricular hypertrophy may not be the ideal candidates for TAVI.</s><s>Even though hemodynamic results after TAVI were reported excellent, 3 no resection of the obstruction in the LVOT is possible.</s><s>Therefore, pressure overload after the TAVI-procedure persists and regression of left ventricular mass is either slowed down or inhibited.</s><s>Even minor obstructions in the LVOT can be responsible for this process.</s><s>This led in the reported case even to an increase of left ventricular obstruction, which had 2 years ago not been considered to be relevant.</s><s>The LVOTobstruction caused consecutively hemodynamic turbulences, which are known to trigger the growth of pannus. 4</s><s>This led to an even worse obstruction and the development of an vicious circle of LVOT-narrowing.</s><s>Finally, the necessity of surgical valve replacement in combination with a septal myectomy arose.</s><s>This procedure should be considered even in patients with no evident LVOT-obstruction, but extensive left ventricular hypertrophy.</s></p><p><s>Sutureless valve replacements or fast deployment aortic valves offer advantages in these high-risk patients.</s><s>With simplified implantation techniques, the operation can be performed with minimized myocardial ischemic time <ref type="bibr">5,</ref><ref type="bibr">6</ref> and therefore reduced procedural risk. 7</s><s>Furthermore,  regression of left ventricular mass benefits from the septal myectomy, to prevent the vicious circle of LVOT obstruction.</s></p><p><s>Therefore, we conclude that conventional surgery performing partial septal myectomy and surgical valve replacement seems to be the appropriate option for high-risk patients with extensive left ventricular hypertrophy and even slight LVOT obstruction.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>References</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1 Obstruction of the left ventricular outflow tract in color echocardiography before conventional surgery.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,69.56,62.99,228.08,176.43" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 3 Enlarged left ventricular outflow tract in echocardiography after conventional surgery including septal myectomy.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,325.59,62.99,216.06,260.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Rubino AS, Santarpino G, De Praetere H, et al.</s><s>Early and intermediate outcome after aortic valve replacement with a sutureless bioprosthesis: Results of a multicenter study.</s><s>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg 2014;148(3):865-871, discussion 871 7 Borger MA, Dohmen P, Misfeld M, Mohr FW.</s><s>Current trends in aortic valve replacement: development of the rapid deployment EDWARDS INTUITY valve system.</s><s>Expert Rev Med Devices 2013; 10(4):461-470</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>American College of Cardiology Foundation/American Heart As-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>sociation Task Force on Practice Guidelines. J Thorac Cardiovasc</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Surg 2011;142(6):e153-e203</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>3 Spethmann S, Dreger H, Baldenhofer G, et al. Long-term Doppler</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>hemodynamics and effective orifice areas of Edwards SAPIEN and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>medtronic CoreValve prostheses after TAVI. Echocardiography</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2014;31(3):302-310</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>4 Sakamoto Y, Hashimoto K, Okuyama H, Ishii S, Shingo T, Kagawa H.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Prevalence of pannus formation after aortic valve replacement:</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>clinical aspects and surgical management. J Artif Organs 2006;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>9(3):199-202</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>5 Borger MA, Moustafine V, Conradi L, et al. A randomized multi-</cell></row><row><cell>1 Svensson LG, Blackstone EH, Rajeswaran J, et al; PARTNER Trial</cell><cell>center trial of minimally invasive rapid deployment versus con-</cell></row><row><cell>Investigators. Comprehensive analysis of mortality among pa-</cell><cell>ventional full sternotomy aortic valve replacement. Ann Thorac</cell></row><row><cell>tients undergoing TAVR: results of the PARTNER trial. J Am Coll</cell><cell>Surg 2015;99(1):17-25</cell></row><row><cell>Cardiol 2014;64(2):158-168</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>2 Gersh BJ, Maron BJ, Bonow RO, et al; American College of Cardiol-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ogy Foundation/American Heart Association Task Force on Prac-</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>tice; American Association for Thoracic Surgery; American Society</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>of Echocardiography; American Society of Nuclear Cardiology;</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Heart Failure Society of America; Heart Rhythm Society; Society</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>for Cardiovascular Angiography and Interventions; Society of</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Thoracic Surgeons. 2011 ACCF/AHA guideline for the diagnosis</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>and treatment of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy: a report of the</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgeon Reports Vol. 5 No. 1/2016</s></p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
