<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Metformin and beta cell function in insulin-treated patients with type 2 diabetes: a randomized placebocontrolled 4.3 year trial</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Orcid ID</roleName><forename type="first">Stehouwer</forename><surname>Coen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Orcid ID</roleName><forename type="first">Kooy</forename><surname>Adriaan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wiebe</forename><surname>Top</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Care Group Treant -Location Bethesda Internal Medicine Hoogeveen</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="NL">Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Coen</forename><surname>Stehouwer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">MUMC, Internal Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Maastricht</settlement>
									<country key="NL">Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Philippe</forename><surname>Lehert</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Louvain</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Mons</settlement>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Adriaan</forename><surname>Kooy</surname></persName>
							<email>a.kooy@treant.nl</email>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Treant Zorggroep, Location Bethesda</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hoogeveen</settlement>
									<country key="NL">Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Adrian</forename><forename type="middle">Treant</forename><surname>Kooy</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Zorggroep</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Location Bethesda</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>7909 AA</postCode>
									<settlement>Hoogeveen</settlement>
									<country key="NL">Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Metformin and beta cell function in insulin-treated patients with type 2 diabetes: a randomized placebocontrolled 4.3 year trial</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5697788522111261475FD087CFC4AE58</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/dom.13123</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:25+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Metformin is a key drug in the treatment of type 2 diabetes.</s><s>In our 'Hyperinsulinaemia: the Outcome of its Metabolic Effects (HOME) Study' we showed that metformin vs placebo improved glycemic control and decreased insulin requirements in insulin-treated patients with advanced type 2 diabetes <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In this respect, metformin is generally regarded as an insulin sensitizer.</s><s>Whether metformin also may improve beta-cell function is not clear.</s><s>In the present analysis of the HOME study, we studied the effects of metformin vs placebo on estimates of fasting beta-cell function.</s><s>In addition, we quantified the durability of metformin's effect on these estimates over a period of 4.3 years.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Design and patients</head><p><s>In the HOME trial, 390 insulin-treated patients with advanced type 2 diabetes were randomly allocated to either metformin 850 mg (up to thrice daily if tolerated) or matching identical looking placebo through a computer program.</s><s>Most patients (345) were already using monotherapy insulin, either twice daily premixed NPH/regular insulin (Novomix) or NPH insulin in the evening combined with prandial regular insulin.The remaining 45 patients used a combination of metformin and insulin and stopped metformin three months before randomisation.</s><s>All participants provided written informed consent and the study was approved by the medical ethical committees of the three participating non-academic hospitals.</s><s>Study visits were at baseline, at one month and three monthly after with a follow up of 4.3 years.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Measures</head><p><s>Blood samples for this analysis of the HOME trial were drawn at baseline and after 4, 17, 30, 43, and 52 months, and stored at -80°C until analysis.</s><s>C-peptide plasma samples were available for 363 patients at baseline and at one or more follow up visits (93%), and for 259 patients at their final visit (66%) and was performed with a solid-phase, chemiluminescent enzyme immunoassay (Immulite 2000, DPC).</s><s>Serum insulin was measured by electrochemiluminescence immunoassay (Modular E170, Roche Diagnostics).</s><s>Coefficients of variation are provided in the appendix.</s><s>Because patients used human basal insulin (Insulatard, Novo Nordisk) there was full crossreactivity between endogenous insulin and exogenous insulin in this assay.</s></p><p><s>The primary estimate of beta cell function was the fasting C peptide to fasting plasma glucose ratio (FCPGR).</s><s>To normalise our ratio based on SI units, we used an arbitrary constant of 100 for convenience resulting in the unitless formula FCPGR = 100 * FCP/FPG.</s><s>As secondary measures we used the fasting C-peptide (FCP) and the disposition index (DI), defined as the FCPGR adjusted for insulin sensitivity (IS) resulting in the unitless formula DI = FCPGR * IS 0.2 .</s><s>Insulin sensitivity was calculated from fasting plasma glucose (FPG) and fasting plasma insulin (FPI) using the unitless formula IS = 1000/FPG*FPI.</s><s>For further details we refer to the statistical appendix.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical analysis</head><p><s>We used all measurements to assess the effects of metformin vs placebo during the total period of follow-up.</s><s>In order to quantify the overall treatment effect over time, we used a linear mixed model simultaneously assessing the significance of the main time effect , main metformin treatment effect, and interaction of metformin treatment effect with time (detail in the statistical appendix).</s><s>In addition we did a mediation analysis to assess the indirect (mediating) effect of HbA 1c in the change of FCPGR.</s><s>For this purpose, we added HbA 1c as a covariate in the model and evaluated the mediating HbA 1c effect by the product of the effects (metformin→ HbA 1c ) and ( HbA 1c →FCPGR), and confidence interval calculated by bootstrapping (detail in the statistical appendix).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows the time course of HbA 1c , beta cell function and insulin sensitivity during all visits.</s><s>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> shows the results of the mixed linear model in which, for each variable, the baseline value, time effect, treatment effect and time-treatment interaction are shown.</s><s>Treatment effect in the model is defined as the constant postbaseline change in the metformin group versus placebo, expressed as an absolute change.</s><s>In addition this change is described as a relative change compared to baseline.</s></p><p><s>Compared with placebo group, FCPGR increased in the metformin group.</s><s>Mixed model results showed a constant treatment effect from the first post baseline visit until the end of the trial of 1.48 (95%CI 1.09 -1.87, p&lt;0.001), no change in time (0.00/year, 95%CI -0.001 -+0.0.01; p=0.92) and no time-treatment interaction (-0.010/year, 95%CI -0.021-.001;</s><s>p=0.058).</s><s>Relative to baseline, the treatment effect was 28% (95%CI 23-33).</s></p><p><s>DI showed results comparable to those with the FCPGR: a small decrease in the placebo group and an increase in the metformin group.</s><s>Mixed model results confirmed a significant decrease in time of -0.01/year (95%CI-0.01</s><s>--0.001; p=0.023) for placebo group, a constant treatment effect during the whole post baseline period of 1.50 (95%CI 1.17 -1.83; p&lt;0.001), and no time-treatment interaction (-0.01, 95%CI -0.02 -0.00; p=0.128).</s><s>Relative to baseline, the treatment effect was 32% (95%CI 27-36).</s><s>FCP (nmol/l) decreased in the placebo group and increased in the metformin group.</s><s>Mixed model results showed a non-significant treatment effect (0.034 nmol, (95%CI, -0.005 -0.072; p=0.085), no time effect (0.00 nmol/l/year, 95% CI, -0.00 -0.00; p=0.61), and no time-treatment interaction (0.00 nmol/l/year, 95%CI, -0.00 -0.00; p=0.26).</s><s>Relative to baseline, the treatment effect was 7% (95%CI -1;14).</s><s>HbA 1c (%) increased in the placebo group and decreased in the metformin group.</s><s>Mixed model results confirmed a significant change in time of 0.07 %/year in placebo (95%CI 0.04 -0.10; p&lt;0.001) , a treatment effect of -0.93 % ( (95%CI -1.06 --0.80; p&lt;0.001) from the first post-baseline visit until the end of the trial, and a timetreatment interaction of 0.011 %/year (95%CI 0.008 -0.015; p&lt;0.001).</s></p><p><s>We assessed the indirect (mediating) effect of HbA 1c in FCPGR improvement in adding in the model HbA 1c as covariate.</s><s>In comparing with the initial model, the mediating effect of HbA 1c (Metformin→ HbA 1c →FCPGR) on the overall effect (Metformin→FCPGR) was small (.53, 95%CI .45,</s><s>.73),</s><s>accounting for a small proportion of the variance (36.1%; 95% CI,25.4-49.5).</s></p><p><s>Insulin sensitivity increased in the metformin group and decreased in the placebo group.</s><s>Mixed model results showed a treatment effect of 0.33 (95%CI 0.03-0.63;</s><s>p=0.031), no significant change in time for placebo (0.00/year, 95%CI -0.00 -0.01; p=0.69), and no time-treatment interaction (-0.00/year, 95%CI -0.01 -0.01; p=0.612).</s><s>Relative to baseline, the treatment effect was 36% (95%CI 3-69).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p><s>This article is protected by copyright.</s><s>All rights reserved.</s></p><p><s>The present study shows that metformin vs placebo added to insulin, improves fasting based estimates of beta cell function durably.</s><s>These effects were for the greatest part (64%) independent of changes in glycemic control.</s><s>Also adjusting for insulin sensitivity by calculating the disposition index, did not alter the results.</s><s>Depending on the estimate used, the increase in beta cell function was 28% (95%CI 23-33) for FCPGR and 32% (95%CI 27-36) for DI.</s><s>Insulin sensitivity, assessed by a HOMA-derived fasting index, also improved by 36% (95%CI: 3-69).</s></p><p><s>A C-peptide with a concurrent glucose level of &gt; 8 mmol/l might be considered a nonfasting value <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>.</s><s>This did apply to our population with a mean fasting glucose at baseline of 10 mmol/l.</s><s>To adjust for this hyperglycemic stimulus, we chose the FCPGR as our primary endpoint.</s></p><p><s>Meier et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref>, showed a good correlation of FCPGR with human pancreatic beta cell mass in a small group of patients that underwent pancreatic surgery.</s><s>Okuna <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref> showed in a much bigger population of type 2 diabetes patients, that FCPGR strongly correlates with accepted measures as the HOMA-B (r=0.79) and hyperglycaemic clamp (iAUCins/gluc90, r = 0.721).</s></p><p><s>Because beta cell function depends on prevailing insulin sensitivity, we adjusted for insulin sensitivity by calculating the disposition index.</s><s>The use of exogenous insulin in may confound the assessment of insulin sensitivity, unless a steady state has been achieved without fast changes in glucose transport <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>.</s><s>In our study fasting insulin levels were drawn in the morning during which a standard condition (a certain steady state) of intermediate acting NPH insulin levels had been achieved without fast changes in insulin driven glucose transport.</s></p><p><s>Further, a valid DI should incorporate independent estimates of beta cell function and insulin sensitivity <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref>.</s><s>Because we used C-peptide-based data for our beta cell estimate and insulin-based data for our insulin sensitivity estimate, we avoided intrinsically interdependent estimates.</s><s>To assess this independency, we did an additional correlation analysis that showed a weak correlation (R =0,29 (95% CI 0,19-0,38) for C-peptide and insulin.</s></p><p><s>Although the improvements in beta cell function and IS were maintained during the 4.3 year follow-up period, there was no time-treatment interaction for both beta cell function and IS, indicating that the improvement constitutes an immediate treatment effect without additional change over time relative to placebo.</s></p><p><s>There are two major trials <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8)</ref> which evaluated long-term metabolic changes related to beta cell function in metformin users, as compared to other treatment modalities: the UK Prospective Diabetes Study (UKPDS) and the A Diabetes Outcome Progression Trial (ADOPT).</s><s>Both trials also observed modest improvement of beta cell function in metformin users.</s><s>However, in the UKPDS long term follow up of beta cell function is difficult to interpret because of the slowly rising FPG during the study and its influence on the HOMA-B estimate which was used <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In the ADOPT, apart from HOMA-B, the oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT) was used as an estimate of beta cell function.</s><s>It was shown that metformin during 4 years of follow up improved beta cell function as compared to glyburide, although less pronounced than with rosiglitazone and with a much smaller effect size (2.5%) than in our study (28%).</s><s>This may be partially explained by differences between the study populations.</s><s>Patients included in the ADOPT study were newly diagnosed patients, while in the HOME trial, patients with advanced diabetes on insulin therapy were included.</s><s>Advanced type 2 diabetes is known to have more beta cell failure than new-onset type 2 diabetes, and may have more potential for improvement (provided beta cell damage is partially reversible).</s><s>Moreover our placebo controlled design allows a comparison to placebo instead of the comparator based design of the ADOPT.</s></p><p><s>Although metformin has no direct short term insulin secretory effects in beta cells of normal glucose tolerant individuals <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11)</ref>, multiple mechanisms may explain its beta cell enhancing effect in type 2 diabetes patients.</s><s>Apart from decreased glucotoxicity, an improved incretin secretion <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13)</ref> and a reduced lipotoxicity ( <ref type="formula">14</ref>) may be involved in the action of metformin to improve beta cell function.</s></p><p><s>Our study is limited by studying the effects of metformin on estimates of beta cell function and insulin sensitivity in the fasting state.</s><s>Effects of metformin through the incretin system may also improve prandial beta cell function, which we did not study in the present study.</s></p><p><s>In conclusion, the present study shows that metformin results in long term improvement in fasting estimates of beta cell function in addition to an improvement in insulin sensitivity, contributing to a durably improved glycemic control in insulintreated patients, even in advanced type 2 diabetes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Legends</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 1</head><label>11</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1 Time course of HbA 1c , FCPGR and IS, data are means with SEM</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,71.08,153.88,401.00,211.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,71.25,379.32,403.00,274.45" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,71.09,71.09,419.55,271.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Mixed model fixed effects parameter estimates</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>FCPGR</cell><cell>Disposition index</cell><cell>C-peptide (nmol/l)</cell><cell>Insulin sensitivity</cell><cell>HbA 1c (%)</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">This article is protected by copyright. All rights reserved.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p><s>WMT and PL primary analyzed the data.</s><s>WMT and AK drafted the manuscript, CS and AK reviewed the manuscript.</s><s>AK, CS and PL are the guarantors of this work and, as such, had full access to all the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</s><s>We thank all members of the HOME study group and all patients for their contribution.</s><s>This part of the HOME Trial was supported by grants from Merck, Sharpe, &amp; Dohme and Novo Nordisk.</s><s>The sponsors had no role in the design and conduct of the study; in the collection, analysis, and interpretation of the data; or in the preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript.</s><s>All the authors declare that there are no relevant conflicts of interest to disclose</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>This article is protected by copyright.</s><s>All rights reserved.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long-term effects of metformin on metabolism and microvascular and macrovascular disease in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kooy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lehert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Wulffele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Donker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch Intern Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">169</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="616" to="625" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-03-23">2009 Mar 23</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The clinical utility of C-peptide measurement in the care of patients with diabetes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Hattersley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabetic Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="803" to="817" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional Assessment of Pancreatic β-Cell Area in Humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Meier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Menge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tgk</forename><surname>Breuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabetes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1595" to="1603" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Postprandial serum C-peptide to plasma glucose concentration ratio correlates with oral glucose tolerance test-and glucose clampbased disposition indexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Okuno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Komada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sakaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nakamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hashimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Metabolism</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2013</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1470" to="1147" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use and abuse of HOMA modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Levy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Matthews</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabetes Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1487" to="1495" />
			<date type="published" when="2004-06">2004 Jun</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessment of insulin secretion in relation to insulin resistance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ahren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pacini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Clin Nutr Metab Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="529" to="533" />
			<date type="published" when="2005-09">2005 Sep</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">prospective diabetes study 16. Overview of 6 years&apos; therapy of type II diabetes: a progressive disease. U.K. Prospective Diabetes Study Group</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabetes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1249" to="1258" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-11">1995 Nov</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of Rosiglitazone, Glyburide, and Metformin on β-Cell Function and Insulin Sensitivity in ADOPT</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lachin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zinman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabetes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1552" to="1560" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HOMA-beta in the UKPDS and ADOPT. Is the natural history of type 2 diabetes characterised by a progressive and inexorable loss of insulin secretory function? Maybe? Maybe not?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Reaven</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diab Vasc Dis Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="138" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pancreatic islets from type 2 diabetic patients have functional defects and increased apoptosis that are ameliorated by metformin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Marchetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Del</forename><surname>Guerra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Marselli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lupi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Masini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pollera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Endocrinol Metab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5535" to="5541" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of metformin on insulin sensitivity and insulin secretion in female obese patients with normal glucose tolerance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Binnert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Seematter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Tappy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Giusti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabetes Metab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New aspects of an old drug: metformin as a glucagon-like peptide 1 (GLP-1) enhancer and sensitiser</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kieffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabetologia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="219" to="222" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhanced secretion of glucagon-like peptide 1 by biguanide compounds</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Yasuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Inoue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nagakura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yamazaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem Biophys Res Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">298</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="779" to="784" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lipotoxicity in Human Pancreatic Islets and the Protective Effect of Metformin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lupi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Del</forename><surname>Guerra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fierabracci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabetes</title>
		<imprint>
			<date>February 2002 51</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>suppl 1 S134-S137</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Metformin and -cell function in insulin-treated patients with type 2 diabetes: A randomized placebo-controlled 4.3-year trial Date</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W;</forename><surname>Stehouwer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C;</forename><surname>Lehert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P;</forename><surname>Kooy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Top</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Stehouwer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lehert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kooy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/dom.13123</idno>
		<ptr target="http://hdl.handle.net/11343/293783" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">DIABETES OBESITY &amp; METABOLISM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="730" to="733" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Minerva Access is the Institutional Repository of The University of Melbourne Author/s: Top</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Metformin and -cell function in insulin-treated patients with type 2 diabetes: A randomized placebo-controlled 4.3-year trial</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
