<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Diffusional spread and confinement of newly exocytosed synaptic vesicle proteins</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-09-24">24 Sep 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Niclas</forename><surname>Gimber</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Leibniz Institut fu ¨r Molekulare Pharmakologie (FMP)</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Molecular Pharmacology and Cell Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Freie Universita ¨t Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Robert-Roessle-Strae 10</addrLine>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Georgi</forename><surname>Tadeus</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Leibniz Institut fu ¨r Molekulare Pharmakologie (FMP)</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Molecular Pharmacology and Cell Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Freie Universita ¨t Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Robert-Roessle-Strae 10</addrLine>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tanja</forename><surname>Maritzen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Leibniz Institut fu ¨r Molekulare Pharmakologie (FMP)</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Molecular Pharmacology and Cell Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Freie Universita ¨t Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Robert-Roessle-Strae 10</addrLine>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Schmoranzer</surname></persName>
							<email>jan.schmoranzer@fu-berlin.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Leibniz Institut fu ¨r Molekulare Pharmakologie (FMP)</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Molecular Pharmacology and Cell Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Freie Universita ¨t Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Robert-Roessle-Strae 10</addrLine>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institut fu ¨r Chemie und Biochemie</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Freie Universita ¨t Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Takustrasse 6</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Volker</forename><surname>Haucke</surname></persName>
							<email>haucke@fmp-berlin.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Leibniz Institut fu ¨r Molekulare Pharmakologie (FMP)</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Molecular Pharmacology and Cell Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Freie Universita ¨t Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Robert-Roessle-Strae 10</addrLine>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charite Universita ¨tsmedizin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">NeuroCure Cluster of Excellence</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Virchowweg 6</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institut fu ¨r Chemie und Biochemie</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Freie Universita ¨t Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Takustrasse 6</addrLine>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Diffusional spread and confinement of newly exocytosed synaptic vesicle proteins</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-09-24">24 Sep 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3DAC97A072F3AAB7847A76B15CF0FA4A</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1038/ncomms9392</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 1 Dec 2014 | Accepted 18 Aug 2015 |</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:21+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Neurotransmission relies on the calcium-triggered exocytic fusion of non-peptide neurotransmitter-containing small synaptic vesicles (SVs) with the presynaptic membrane at active zones (AZs) followed by compensatory endocytic retrieval of SV membranes.</s><s>Here, we study the diffusional fate of newly exocytosed SV proteins in hippocampal neurons by high-resolution time-lapse imaging.</s><s>Newly exocytosed SV proteins rapidly disperse within the first seconds post fusion until confined within the presynaptic bouton.</s><s>Rapid diffusional spread and confinement is followed by slow reclustering of SV proteins at the periactive endocytic zone.</s><s>Confinement within the presynaptic bouton is mediated in part by SV protein association with the clathrin-based endocytic machinery to limit diffusional spread of newly exocytosed SV proteins.</s><s>These data suggest that diffusion, and axonal escape of newly exocytosed vesicle proteins, are counteracted by the clathrin-based endocytic machinery together with a presynaptic diffusion barrier.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D</head><p><s>uring synaptic activity non-peptide neurotransmitters are released by exocytic fusion of small clear SVs with the presynaptic membrane at active zones (AZs) followed by compensatory endocytosis of SV membranes from the surrounding periactive zone <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> .</s><s>Although the effect of changes in surface mobility of postsynaptic neurotransmitter receptors on synaptic transmission is well established <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> , comparably little is known about the mobility of newly exocytosed SV proteins (NEP) within the presynaptic terminal.</s><s>This is largely owed to the fact that SV exocytosis operates on a millisecond timescale and is immediately followed by endocytic membrane retrieval, thus, posing technical hurdles to the direct observation of the diffusional behaviour of newly exocytosed SV proteins in primary neurons.</s><s>Plasma membrane pools of SV proteins (that is, originating from previous rounds of exocytosis) have been shown to either be dispersed within the axonal membrane <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> or to cluster at presynaptic sites <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> .</s><s>How these observations relate to the diffusional behaviour of newly exocytosed SV proteins remains unclear though.</s><s>The fate of newly exocytosed SV proteins likely is of key importance for neurotransmission because the unlimited diffusional escape of SV proteins into the axon would counteract the reformation of properly sized SVs of correct composition by endocytosis.</s><s>Interestingly, surface-stranded SV proteins have been shown to be preferentially retrieved by endocytosis to regenerate functional SVs <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> .</s><s>Finally, diffusional dispersion of newly exocytosed SV proteins away from AZs may be crucial for the clearance of release sites during sustained high-level activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> .</s><s>The diffusional behaviour of newly exocytosed membrane proteins has been assayed previously in fibroblasts <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref> and neuroendocrine PC12 cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> , which lack proper SVs and AZ-like release sites.</s><s>Moreover, neuroendocrine cells frequently undergo kiss-and-run exocytosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref> , thereby alleviating the need for a tight coupling between exocytic fusion and endocytic membrane retrieval that is characteristic of neurotransmission in central nervous system neurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> .</s></p><p><s>Here, we study the diffusional fate of newly exocytosed SV proteins in primary hippocampal neurons by high-resolution time-lapse imaging.</s><s>We show that newly exocytosed SV proteins rapidly disperse within the first seconds post fusion until confined within the presynaptic bouton, followed by their slow reclustering.</s><s>Confinement within the presynaptic bouton but not the rate of reclustering is modulated by SV protein association with the clathrin-based endocytic machinery to limit diffusional spread of newly exocytosed SV proteins.</s><s>These data suggest that diffusion and axonal escape of newly exocytosed vesicle proteins are counteracted in part by SV protein association with the clathrin-based endocytic machinery and by the presence of a presynaptic diffusion barrier.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Imaging newly exocytosed SV proteins.</s><s>We expressed SV proteins lumenally tagged with pH-sensitive pHluorin GFP <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> in cultured primary hippocampal neurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> .</s><s>In resting neurons, the pHluorin signal is quenched because of the low intralumenal pH (5.5) of SVs, but is dequenched during stimulation-induced exocytosis to the neutral cell exterior <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>, Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>).</s><s>During subsequent membrane retrieval and reacidification pHluorins are requenched (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>).</s><s>To exclusively image newly exocytosed SV-pHluorin proteins we capitalized on the observation that SV proteins exocytosed and subsequently endocytosed are nonidentical <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> .</s><s>Selective photobleaching or enzymatic digestion 'eclipsed' the pre-existing surface pool of pHluorintagged synaptobrevin 2 (Syb2) ('surface-eclipsed') <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a,b</ref>).</s><s>When prebleached neurons were stimulated with 40 action potentials (APs), we observed a fast initial rise in fluorescence (F) because of SV exocytosis, followed by a small decrease of F (by B15-20%) to a plateau level because newly exocytosed SV proteins were not endocytosed and reacidified <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>).</s><s>As a further confirmation we compared the Syb2-pHluorin responses of prebleached neurons, neurons treated with the vATPase inhibitor folimycin to prevent reacidification <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> , or prebleached folimycin-treated neurons.</s><s>Under all of these conditions we observed a fast exocytic rise in F followed by a small decrease of F to a plateau level (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>), indicating that the large majority of all newly exocytosed proteins remains at the neuronal surface under these conditions rather than being reinternalized.</s><s>The small F decrease at boutons observed post stimulation correlated with an F increase in the axon, suggesting that a minor fraction of newly exocytosed Syb2 escapes into the axon (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1d</ref>), possibly contributing to sharing of SV proteins between neighbouring boutons <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> .</s><s>The majority (Z 80%) of newly exocytosed Syb2, however, remained confined within the presynaptic bouton for up to 80 s (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To image the precise spatiotemporal behaviour of newly exocytosed Syb2-pHluorin we combined high-resolution timelapse imaging with synchronized electric field stimulation of surface-eclipsed neurons and semi-automated image analysis.</s><s>Newly exocytosed pHluorin overlapped with the AZ marker Munc13-1 (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>) with 151 out of 160 boutons containing a single Munc13-1-positive AZ, suggesting that single synapses were imaged.</s><s>Signals for newly exocytosed Syb2-pHluorin were then determined by fitting of the backgroundand bleach-corrected images (DF) to a two-dimensional (2D) Gaussian using a customized software tool (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a</ref>).</s><s>Excellent fits were obtained as demonstrated by the low, noise-like residuals (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a</ref>, bottom).</s><s>Hundreds of intensity and full-width halfmaximum 2 (FWHM 2 ) traces recorded from surface-eclipsed neurons were averaged and quantitatively analysed (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2b,c</ref>).</s><s>FWHM 2 measured from the Gaussian fits of Syb2-pHluorin increased within the first few seconds of stimulation indicating fast local spread of newly exocytosed SV proteins (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a,b</ref>), most likely corresponding to free diffusion (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> and below) within the bouton membrane.</s><s>Diffusional spread within 2 s post stimulation reached a plateau indicative of the confinement of Syb2-pHluorin in an area of about 2 mm 2 , corresponding to the known dimensions of an average presynaptic bouton <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref> .</s><s>The short plateau phase was independent of variable expression levels of Syb2-pHluorin (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1d</ref>) and was followed by a slow decrease of FWHM 2 that continued for about 80 s until it reached about 1 mm 2 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2c</ref>).</s><s>The observed decrease of FWHM <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> was not due to photobleaching (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1e</ref>), but rather reflected the time-dependent reclustering of exocytosed Syb2, consistent with results from stimulated emission depletion (STED) microscopy of fixed samples <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> .</s><s>Moreover, diffusional spread, confinement, and reclustering of newly exocytosed SV proteins similar to that seen in photobleached neurons was observed in neurons expressing a tobacco etch virus (TEV)cleavable variant of Syb2-pHluorin following TEV proteasemediated enzymatic digestion of the pre-existing surface pool of Syb2-pHluorin (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1f-h</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Spread, confinement and reclustering of major SV proteins.</head><p><s>To probe whether diffusional spread, confinement and slow reclustering were specific properties of exocytosed Syb2 or reflect the general behaviour of all SV proteins we monitored the spatiotemporal dynamics of newly exocytosed pHluorin-tagged synaptophysin (Syp) and synaptotagmin 1 (Syt1), two other major SV proteins.</s><s>Syt1 and Syp both exhibited diffusional spread within the first seconds of stimulation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a</ref>) until confined within the 2-2.5 mm 2 -sized area of the bouton (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a,c</ref>), followed by their slow reclustering (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3b,d</ref>) with a t 1/2 of 15-20 s (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3e</ref>).</s><s>To test whether the initial spread of newly exocytosed SV proteins was mediated by free diffusion we fed the experimentally detected stimulation-induced increase in Syb2-pHluorin fluorescence (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3f</ref>) into a free diffusion model based on successively fusing SVs.</s><s>Modelled intensity distributions from single events were summed (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3g</ref>), and the diffusion coefficient was adapted to yield the best-fit between model and experimentally determined FMWH 2 for the initial SV protein spread during stimulation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3h</ref>).</s><s>This analysis revealed that the initial spread of newly exocytosed SV proteins indeed is described well by free  diffusion within the first few seconds.</s><s>We obtained similar diffusion coefficients for the initial dispersion of Syb2, Syt1 and Syp of B0.20-0.35</s><s>mm 2 s À 1 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3i</ref>; Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a,b</ref>), a value resembling that reported for mobile postsynaptic AMPA receptors <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref> .</s><s>This value would translate into a movement of SV proteins away from AZs at a speed of B1 mm in 2 s, explaining the need for confinement of newly exocytosed SV proteins within presynaptic boutons to prevent their substantial loss into axons.</s></p><p><s>The endocytic machinery limits spread and confinement.</s></p><p><s>As surface-stranded SV proteins form a reservoir for endocytic membrane retrieval <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> , we hypothesized that association of SV proteins with the endocytic machinery contributes to their presynaptic confinement.</s><s>To test this, we analysed the postexocytic diffusional behaviour of Syb2 (M46A), a missorted Syb2 mutant <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref> that selectively fails to associate with the Syb2-specific endocytic adaptors AP180 and CALM <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref> resulting in its partial redistribution (B70% of total) to the plasma membrane <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26</ref> (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a</ref>).</s><s>Surface-eclipsing of the large surfacestranded pool of Syb2 (M46A)-pHluorin by enzymatic TEV protease-mediated digestion (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3b</ref>) allowed us to nonetheless reliably track its diffusional fate, albeit with reduced signal-to-noise ratio.</s><s>Syb2 (M46A) displayed rapid diffusional dispersion, confinement and slow reclustering similar to wild-type (WT) Syb2 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4a,b</ref>).</s><s>However, diffusing M46A explored a significantly larger area than WT Syb2 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4a-c</ref>), and this difference in the FMWH 2 remained after M46A had undergone slow reclustering (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4d</ref>), while t 1/2 of reclustering was largely unaffected in the mutant (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4e</ref>).</s><s>Furthermore, kinetic mathematical modelling of our experimental data revealed a significantly increased initial rate of diffusion of M46A compared with WT Syb2 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4f-h</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To further investigate the contribution of the endocytic machinery to presynaptic confinement of newly exocytosed Syb2, we eliminated neuronal expression of the Syb2-specific endocytic adaptor proteins CALM and AP180 (refs 26,27).</s><s>When WT Syb2-pHluorin was expressed in neurons lacking AP180 (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3c</ref>) and depleted of CALM by specific shRNA <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28</ref> (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3d</ref>), newly exocytosed pHluorin molecules explored a significantly larger area compared with WT neurons (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5a-c</ref>), and this difference in the FMWH 2 remained after Syb2-pHluorin had undergone slow reclustering (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5d</ref>), while t 1/2 of reclustering was largely unaffected (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5e</ref>), thus phenocopying the effects of Syb2 (M46A).</s><s>We conclude that sustained abrogation of Syb2 association with its endocytic adaptors AP180 and CALM either by mutation of Syb2 (that is, M46A) or elimination of AP180/CALM expression modulates its diffusional spread and confinement.</s><s>Consistent with these data we observed that acute perturbation of the endocytic machinery by the clathrin inhibitor Pitstop 2 (ref.</s><s>29; see also refs 30-32)  also led to a similar increase in the area of Syb2 confinement (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3e-h</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Collectively, these data suggest that diffusional spread and confinement of newly exocytosed Syb2 are limited at least in part by its association with endocytic proteins.</s><s>To investigate this hypothesis further we analysed the localization and dynamics of the clathrin-based endocytic machinery.</s><s>Live imaging of hippocampal neurons co-expressing Munc13-1-mCherry or Syb2-pHluorin and fluorescent protein-tagged clathrin light chains (LC) showed clathrin to be concentrated in presynaptic boutons, where it localizes at and around AZs (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4a,b</ref>), in close proximity to newly exocytosed SV proteins (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4c,d</ref>).</s><s>The distribution of eGFP-clathrin LC or mRFP-clathrin LC following stimulation of neurons with 40 APs remained grossly unchanged (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4b,d</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To more precisely determine the sub-synaptic localization of endocytic proteins and their spatial relationship with the pool of newly exocytosed SV proteins we turned to multicolour superresolution microscopy.</s><s>We first used three-dimensional (3D) Structured Illumination Microscopy (3D-SIM), a technique that provides an approximately 2-fold gain in both lateral (xy) and axial (z) resolution compared with conventional confocal imaging and allows the use of conventional fluorophores.</s><s>Multicolour 3D-SIM analysis of hippocampal neurons revealed clathrin and AP180 to localize around the AZ labelled with Bassoon (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6a</ref>), and this distribution remained largely unaffected by stimulation of neurons with 40 APs, consistent with live imaging (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4a-d</ref>).</s><s>Finally, to determine the exact spatial relationship between the endocytic machinery and newly exocytosed SV proteins we used spectral demixing direct stochastic optical reconstruction microscopy (SD-dSTORM) <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33</ref> , a dSTORM method that allows registration-free dual-colour imaging (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4g</ref>) with a lateral resolution of 20-35 nm (refs 33,34).</s><s>Dual-colour SD-dSTORM analysis of hippocampal synapses stimulated with 40 APs revealed newly exocytosed Syb2 molecules (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4e,f</ref>) to cluster around the AZ labelled by Bassoon (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6c</ref>).</s><s>Both, AP180 and newly exocytosed Syb2 formed sub-synaptic clusters (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6d</ref>, Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4h</ref>), which partially colocalized, indicated by an overlap of both maxima in the radial intensity profiles on subsynaptic clusters (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6e</ref>) and by the peak in the k-nearest neighbour analysis (B20-30 nm) that lies below the cluster size and within the range of the experimental resolution (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6f</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34</ref> .</s></p><p><s>The sub-synaptic NEP clusters had average radii of B50 nm (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6e</ref>), consistent with a distribution peak at distances of 100 nm (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6d</ref>).</s><s>Interestingly, the surface area of these 100 nm flat clusters is similar to the surface area of native spherical SVs in brain with a diameter of B40-45 nm (ref.</s><s>35).</s><s>This suggests that newly exocytosed SV protein clusters likely correspond to the readily retrievable pool of SV proteins, which following endocytosis gives rise to SVs.</s><s>We conclude that confinement of SV proteins within presynaptic boutons is effected in part by their association with components of the endocytic machinery.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Our data based on high-resolution imaging and Gaussian fit analysis show that newly exocytosed SV proteins following an initial short phase of free diffusion are confined within presynaptic boutons, a process aided by their association with the endocytic machinery (Figs <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4-6</ref>), in agreement with earlier studies in Drosophila employing an acute block of endocytosis in dynamin/shibire ts mutants <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36</ref> .</s><s>However, given the moderate effect of abolishing association of Syb2 with AP180 and CALM by mutation or by depleting neurons of both endocytic proteins, it is likely that escape of newly exocytosed SV proteins from the boutons into the axon is further limited by the presence of a presynaptic diffusion barrier, the identity of which remains unknown.</s><s>We therefore suggest a model according to which newly exocytosed SV proteins diffusionally spread within the bouton, where they are captured by endocytic adaptors (e.g.</s><s>AP180 and CALM for Syb2) localized around AZ release sites (Figs 6,7) <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38</ref> .</s><s>Endocytic SV protein association in this model, thus, not only aids sorting of SV proteins, but also restricts diffusional escape of newly exocytosed vesicle proteins into the surrounding axon.</s><s>This model is also consistent with recent data from neuromuscular junctions, where the pool of actively recycling SVs has been shown to be kept largely separate from the reserve pool <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">39</ref> and with super-resolution imaging of the mesoscale organization of exocytic membrane proteins in neuroendocrine PC12 cells, where they form patches <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40</ref> similar in size to newly exocytosed SV protein clusters observed here (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6</ref>).</s><s>Diffusional spread and confinement of newly exocytosed SV proteins is incompatible with kiss-and-run SV exo-/endocytosis in central nervous system neurons, in which case exocytosed SV proteins would remain confined to the site of fusion for immediate retrieval <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42</ref> without intermixing with plasma membrane components <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref> .</s><s>Similar observations have been reported for the exocytosis and rapid recapture of vesicular acetylcholine transporter in PC12 cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref> , although in this case it has remained unclear to what extent recapture may reflect clathrin-mediated endocytosis of the transporter.</s></p><p><s>Following confinement, we observe slow reclustering of exocytosed SV proteins within the periactive zone.</s><s>The extent but not the rate of reclustering depends on association of SV proteins with the endocytic machinery (Figs 4,5), suggesting the involvement of additional factors.</s><s>These may include interactions between SV proteins themselves <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[43]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[44]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[45]</ref> and/or of SV proteins with membrane lipids such as cholesterol <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46</ref> , or components of the cytoskeleton.</s><s>Interestingly, treatment of neurons with latrunculin A did not affect SV protein diffusion or reclustering in our hands (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>).</s><s>Hence, filamentous actin is unlikely to play an essential role in these processes, although it remains possible that local actin pools in presynaptic boutons are resistant to the drug or that short actin filaments or formin-dependent actin hotspots <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47</ref> suffice to prevent SV protein diffusion and/or to facilitate reclustering.</s><s>Such reclustered SV proteins likely constitute the readily retrievable pool of SVs 12 that may subsequently be internalized by clathrin-dependent <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> or bulk endocytosis mechanisms including ultrafast endocytosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50</ref> .</s><s>We therefore propose that diffusional spread, confinement, and reclustering of SV proteins represent key steps in the SV exo-endocytic cycle that underlies neurotransmission.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p><s>Neuronal cell cultures and transfection.</s><s>Primary hippocampal neuron cultures were prepared from mouse brain (P0-P3) and transfected at 7-8 days in vitro (DIV) by a modified phosphate transfection protocol (Promega).</s><s>Neurons were imaged at 14-15 DIV.</s></p><p><s>Live cell imaging of hippocampal neurons.</s><s>Images were acquired using an inverted fluorescence microscope (Eclipse Ti, Nikon), controlled by MicroManager  4.11 (ref.</s><s>51), equipped with a Â 60 oil-immersion objective (NA ¼ 1.49, Nikon), a sCMOS camera (Neo, Andor) and a 200 Watt mercury lamp (Lumen 200, Prior).</s><s>Images were acquired at 2.5, 0.5 or 0.2 Hz with the corresponding filter set (EGFP/pHluorin: F36-526, mCherry/mRFP: F36-504, AHF Analysentechnik).</s><s>Imaging was performed at 30 °C in physiological imaging buffer (170 mM NaCl, 3.5 mM KCl, 5 mM NaHCO 3 , 5 mM glucose, 1.2 mM Na 2 SO 4 , 1.2 mM MgCl 2 , 1.3 mM CaCl 2 , 0.4 mM KH 2 PO 4 , 20 mM TES (2-[(2-Hydroxy-1,1bis(hydroxymethyl)ethyl)amino]ethanesulfonic acid), pH 7.4).</s><s>50 mM APV (DL-2-Amino-5-phosphonopentanoic acid, Sigma-Aldrich) and 10 mM CNQX (6-Cyano-7-nitroquinoxaline-2,3-dione, Sigma-Aldrich) were added to the imaging buffer to silence spontaneous neurotransmission.</s><s>Unquenched surface pHluorin was either selectively bleached by illuminating the neurons for 400 s prior to stimulation or the pHluorin tag was removed by 5 min enzymatic digestion with 4 mg ml À 1 TEV protease in imaging buffer.</s><s>Both procedures were sufficient to eclipse fluorescence signal from the surface pool of SV proteins such that any change in pHluorin signals after stimulation originated only from newly exocytosed protein, but not from pre-existing surface pools.</s><s>Neurons were stimulated by electric field stimulation with 40 APs (at 20 Hz, 100 mA) in a stimulation chamber (RC-47FSLP, Warner Instruments).</s><s>In Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref> reacidification was blocked by treating neurons for 1 min with 67 nM folimycin (in ethanol, 1 ml ml À 1 imaging buffer).</s><s>For experiments shown in Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3e-g</ref>, hippocampal neurons were treated with DMSO (0.67 ml ml À 1 imaging buffer) and stimulation-induced pHluorin responses were recorded.</s><s>Neurons were then treated for 2 min with 20 mM Pitstop 2 (in DMSO, 0.67 ml ml À 1 imaging buffer) before stimulation to fill endocytic slots with SV cargo.</s><s>Following a second round of surface-bleaching stimulation-induced pHluorin responses were recorded.</s><s>For experiments shown in Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5a</ref>,b hippocampal neurons were treated for 5 min with 10 mM Latrunculin A (in DMSO, 1 ml ml À 1 imaging buffer) or DMSO before stimulation.</s><s>For the experiments shown in Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5c,d</ref> hippocampal neurons were transfected with LifeAct-eGFP.</s><s>Images were taken before (DMSO, 1 ml ml À 1 imaging buffer) and after 5 min of treatment with 10 mM Latrunculin A (in DMSO, 1 ml ml À 1 imaging buffer).</s></p><p><s>Image analysis.</s><s>Identification of responding synapses: synaptic areas displaying stimulation-induced pHluorin responses were identified based on stimulus-evoked changes in local fluorescence signal (F) using a custom-written ImageJ macro <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52</ref> .</s><s>The synaptic area was calculated from the differential image (F after À F before ) based on a histogram-based threshold procedure.</s></p><p><s>Correction for photobleaching and background: Regions of interest containing responding synapses were extracted and intensity traces were fit with an exponential decay (Equation.</s><s>1) for each single pixel until the start of stimulation.</s></p><p><s>Exponential decay:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">I t ð Þ ¼ bg þ a Á e À tÁt<label>ð1Þ</label></formula><p><s>I(t): Intensity at time t; bg: background signal; a: intensity at time 0; t: lifetime The bleach rate was calculated from the lifetime of the pHluorin decay for each pixel (Equation <ref type="formula">.</ref>2).</s></p><p><s>Bleach rate:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_1">l ¼ e À t<label>ð2Þ</label></formula><p><s>l: bleach rate; t: lifetime The bleach rate was used to correct the pixel-specific bleaching over the entire image sequence (Equation.</s><s>3).</s></p><p><s>Bleach correction:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_2">I bc ðtÞ ¼ IðtÞ þ X t i¼0 l Á I i ð Þ À I 0 ð Þ ð<label>3Þ</label></formula><p><s>I bc (t): bleach corrected intensity at time t; I(t): Intensity at time t; : l: bleach rate; I 0 : intensity at time 0.</s></p><p><s>To reduce background and to correct for the residual fluorescence signal after photobleaching or TEV treatment (from partially quenched luminal pHluorin molecules), we subtracted the median of five images before stimulation from the entire image sequence resulting in DF (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Quantification of pHluorin intensity signal and escape: the pHluorin intensity signal over time was measured from selected (responding) synapses (see above).</s><s>The escape of newly exocytosed SV proteins into the axon was quantified by by their association with the endocytic machinery.</s><s>Confinement is followed by SV protein reclustering within the periactive zone (WT, bottom).</s><s>In the absence of a functional endocytic machinery diffusion of newly exocytosed SV proteins is accelerated (bold arrows) and both confinement and the extent, but not the rate, of reclustering are compromised.</s></p><p><s>manually selecting axonal regions of 0.9 mm 2 with a distance of 1.2 mm to a responding synapse.</s></p><p><s>Quantification of local protein spread by Gaussian fit: The bleach and background corrected image sequences of responding synapses were fit frame-byframe to a 2D Gaussian distribution using a custom-written Igor Pro macro (Equations 4-6).</s><s>The maximum FWHM 2 was analysed over time (Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_6">7</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Gaussian fit 2D:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_3">Iðx; yÞ ¼ I 0 þ A Á e À 1 2 x 0 sx ð Þ 2 À 1 2 y 0 sy 2<label>ð4Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">x 0 ¼ x Á cos y ð Þ þ y Á sin y ð Þ Àx 0 Á cos y ð Þ À y 0 Á sin y Þ<label>ð5Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">y 0 ¼ À x Á sin y ð Þ þy Á cos y ð Þþ x 0 Á sin y ð Þ À y 0 Á cos y ð Þ<label>ð6Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_6">FWHM ¼ 2 Á ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 2 Á lnð2Þ p Á s<label>ð7Þ</label></formula><p><s>I(x,y): pixel intensity at the image coordinates x, y; I 0 : intensity offset; A: amplitude; s: s.d.; y: rotation angle; FWHM: full-width at half-maximum intensity; x 0 , y 0 : Gaussian centre.</s><s>Diffraction-limited rendering of SD-dSTORM images: to compare the SD-dSTORM images with images of conventional wide-field resolution the SD-dSTORM images were blurred with a Gaussian in ImageJ using s Render from Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">8</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Rendering:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_7">s Widefield ¼ ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi s dSTORM 2 þ s Render 2 p<label>ð8Þ</label></formula><p><s>s Widefield : standard deviation of wide-field image (Equations 7,9); s dSTORM : standard deviation of SD-dSTORM <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34</ref> ; s Render : standard deviation for rendering.</s></p><p><s>Wide-field resolution:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_8">FWHM ¼ l 2NA<label>ð9Þ</label></formula><p><s>FWHM: full-width at half-maximum intensity; l: emission wavelength of the dye; NA: numerical aperture of the objective Finally, the blurred images were displayed with the camera pixel size of 105 nm.</s><s>Ripley's L(r)-r function (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6d</ref>): Estimation of normalized and edge-corrected Ripley's K(r) and L(r)-r function (Equations 10,11) were calculated using the splancs package for the R software environment for statistical computing <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53</ref> using the following equations <ref type="bibr">54 :</ref> Ripley's:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_9">K r ð Þ ¼ A N X i X j 6 ¼ i Iðd ij orÞ N Á w I i ; I j À Á<label>ð10Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_10">L r ð Þ À r ¼ ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi K r ð Þ p r À r<label>ð11Þ</label></formula><p><s>K(r): edge-corrected Ripley's K to estimate the number of individual localizations (i) within a distance r of another (j) localization normalized by the number of total localizations N per area A; d ij is the distance between localization i and j; I(d ij or) is the indicator function that equals 1 if d ij or or 0 otherwise; w(l i ,l j ) is the weight function for edge correction.</s><s>L(r)-r: normalized K(r) equals 0 for a random distribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">55</ref> .</s><s>Dotted lines (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6d</ref>) represent upper envelopes from 10 simulations of complete spatial randomness (CSR) for each region of interest.</s></p><p><s>K-nearest neighbour: The k-nearest neighbour distribution was calculated from localizations within synaptic region of interests in SD-dSTORM images, using a custom-written ImageJ macro <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52</ref> .</s><s>K ¼ 10 was chosen in order to reduce the likelihood of false positive hits due to noise.</s><s>The negative control for colocalization was generated by performing a toroidal shift of one channel for half a region of interest size against the other channel along the x axis.</s></p><p><s>Radial intensity profiles: Radial intensity profiles were generated with the ImageJ macro <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52</ref> 'radial profile'.</s><s>Local maxima were found automatically with the ImageJ function 'find maxima'.</s><s>Averaged intensity values were plotted against their radial distance to a local maximum in the reference channel (newly exocytosed Syb2).</s></p><p><s>Modelling diffusional spread of successive SV fusions.</s><s>To determine diffusion coefficients of pHluorin-tagged synaptobrevin 2 (Syb2), synaptotagmin 1 (Syt1) and synaptophysin (Syp), we assumed a model of successively fusing SVs during stimulation.</s><s>By using the experimentally determined intensity traces we calculated the relative number of fused SVs at each time point during stimulation.</s><s>Assuming that the spread of the SV proteins is governed by Brownian motion (free diffusion) each vesicle was treated as an individual Gaussian intensity distribution that was added to the previous intensities.</s><s>Each Gaussian distribution was weighted by its corresponding intensity increase (experimental data) and integrated with the previous Gaussian intensity distributions (Equations 12,13).</s><s>The sum of all distributions was fit with another Gaussian (Equation <ref type="formula" target="#formula_13">14</ref>) and plotted as the 'model' in Figs 3h,4f,g and Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>. The diffusion coefficients were determined by matching the mean slope from the experimental FWHM 2 to the FWHM 2 from the model.</s><s>The validity of the model was tested by comparing traces obtained from the model and experimentally obtained traces, using a two-way analysis of variance with repeated measures.</s></p><p><s>Integrated Gaussian:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_11">I r; t ð Þ ¼ X N j¼0 I j À I j À 1 4 Á p Á D Á ðn À jÞ Á e À r 2 4 Á DÁðn À jÞ À Á<label>ð12Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_12">N ¼ t f<label>ð13Þ</label></formula><p><s>I(r, t): intensity at the radial distance r (from Gaussian center) and time t; D: diffusion coefficient; n: frame number; f: frame duration.</s><s>Gaussian Fit 1D:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_13">IðrÞ ¼ I 0 þ A Á e À 1 2 r s ð Þ 2<label>ð14Þ</label></formula><p><s>I(r): intensity at the radial distance r (from Gaussian centre); I 0 : intensity offset; s: s.d.</s></p><p><s>Immunocytochemistry.</s><s>Primary hippocampal neurons were fixed with 4% (w/v) PFA, 4% (w/v) sucrose in phosphate-buffered saline for 15 min at room temperature (RT).</s><s>Cells were permeabilized and blocked for 1 h, RT in blocking buffer (0.23% [v/v] Triton X-100, 385 mM NaCl in 15 mM sodium phosphate buffer pH 7.4, supplemented with 30% [v/v] goat serum or 10% [w/v] bovine serum albumin for staining with goat antibodies) before incubation with the specific primary antibody (1 h, RT) and the secondary antibody (30 min, RT) in blocking buffer.</s></p><p><s>Immunocytochemistry of newly exocytosed proteins.</s><s>Primary hippocampal neurons were transfected with c-myc epitope-tagged Syb2.</s><s>On 14-15 DIV neurons were incubated with primary antibody in imaging buffer (20 min, RT).</s><s>Neurons were washed with imaging buffer, stimulated in an electric field as described above and fixed with 4% (w/v) PFA, 4% (w/v) sucrose in phosphate-buffered saline for 15 min at RT.</s><s>Further labelling steps were carried out in 15 mM sodium phosphate buffer (pH 7.4), supplemented with 30% (v/v) goat serum and 385 mM NaCl.</s><s>Primary antibodies on the neuronal surface were saturated with Alexa 488-labelled Fab fragments of secondary antibody (overnight, RT), followed by a labelling of newly exocytosed proteins with primary (1 h, RT) and Alexa 647 labelled FAB fragments of secondary antibody (30 min, RT).</s><s>Labelling of AP180 and Bassoon was performed with primary and secondary antibodies as described in the paragraph on immunocytochemistry.</s></p><p><s>Image acquisition of fixed hippocampal neurons.</s><s>For acquisition of images from immunostainings without the need for improved resolution were used the inverted fluorescence microscope setup, described above.</s><s>To reduce out of focus fluorescence in neuronal cultures that also contained astrocytes (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3d</ref>) we used a laser-scanning microscope LSM780 from (Carl Zeiss Microscopy GmbH) equipped with an Argon-Laser 488 and an DPSS-Laser.</s><s>Emission was detected at 500-550 or 565-700 nm.</s></p><p><s>Structured illumination microscopy.</s><s>Hippocampal neurons were silenced for 5 min with 50 mM APV and 10 mM CNQX in imaging buffer, stimulated (40 APs, 20 Hz) or directly fixed and stained with primary and secondary antibodies as described before.</s><s>Samples were mounted in Vectashield.</s><s>3D 3-colour SIM images were acquired using the 488, 568 and 643 nm laser lines, standard filter sets and 125 nm z-sectioning of the OMX V4 Blaze (GE Healthcare) system. 100 nm fluorescent beads (Tetraspek, T7284, Invitrogen) were used for registration of detection channels achieving o40 nm registration error for all three channels.</s><s>Images were exported using Imaris 7.6 (Bitplane).</s><s>SD-dSTORM.</s><s>Spectral-demixing (SD)-dSTORM provides registration error free, low crosstalk dual-colour super-resolution imaging with a resolution of B20-35 nm (refs 33,34).</s><s>The system, acquisition and analysis procedure was described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33</ref> .</s><s>Here, we used Alexa Fluor 647 (Invitrogen) and CF680 (Biotium) as dye pairs distinguishable by spectral demixing <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34</ref> .</s><s>The emission splitter was equipped with a dichroic mirror (700-DCXXR, AHF Analysentechnik) and an emission bandpass filter (F76-635, AHF Analysentechnik).</s><s>The overlay of SD-dSTORM channels (NEP/AP180) with the wide-field channel (Bassoon) was done using a custom ImageJ macro <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">52</ref> .</s></p><p><s>Generation of AP180/CALM-depleted neurons.</s><s>AP180 expression was eliminated by gene knockout (KO) in mice using homologous recombination: A floxed neomycin (NEO) resistance cassette was inserted in front of exon 3 and an additional loxP site after exon 6 in hybrid C57BL/6NTac x 129S6/SvEVTac ES cell clones injected into C57BL/6 blastocysts and implanted into pseudopregnant mice.</s><s>Mating of chimeric males with Ella-Cre deleter mice removed exons 3-6 as well as the NEO cassette giving rise to heterozygous mice, which were interbred to obtain WT and AP180 À / À littermates.</s><s>Animals were genotyped by PCR analysis of genomic DNA (see Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3c</ref>).</s><s>The AP180 WT allele was detected with the forward primer ACCTCATGTGAAACGTTGCCTG and the reverse primer TCTGGTGGATAGTGTCACTTAGGTAG (product: 323 nt).</s><s>The AP180 KO allele was detected using the forward primer CCAGATGACCTGAGTTTGTG and the reverse primer TCTGGTGGATAGTGTCACTTAGGTAG (product: 401 nt).</s></p><p><s>Primary hippocampal neuron cultures prepared from AP180 À / À mice (P0-P3) were transfected with pFUGW-based plasmids <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">56</ref> co-expressing mKate and specific shRNA directed against CALM <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28</ref> to obtain AP180/CALM-depleted neurons.</s><s>As a control, hippocampal neurons from WT mice (P0-P3) co-expressing mKate and scrambled control shRNA were used.</s></p><p><s>Plasmids and antibodies.</s><s>Plasmids encoding for Syb2 (WT, rat) and Syt1 (rat) with a TEV protease cleavable superecliptic pHluorin-tag were a kind gift from J. Klingauf (University of Mu ¨nster, Mu ¨nster, Germany) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> .</s><s>Mutant Syb2 (M46A) was cloned into a pHluorin plasmid PCR amplification and standard cloning procedures.</s><s>A PCR based approach was used to introduce a c-myc epitope tag into a plasmid encoding Syb2 (WT).</s><s>The Syp-pHluorin plasmid (rat) was a kind gift from L. Lagnado (University of Sussex, UK) <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref> .</s><s>A plasmid encoding Munc13-1-mCherry (rat) was derived from pEGFP-N1 carrying Munc13-1, kindly provided by N. Brose (MPI for Experimental Medicine, Go ¨ttingen, Germany).</s><s>Clathrin light chain (rat) was fused to mRFP and expressed from pcDNA5/FRT/TO and fused to eGFP, expressed from pcDNA3.</s><s>The plasmid encoding for Lifeact-eGFP <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57</ref> was a kind gift from F. Bradke (Center for Neurodegenerative Diseases, Germany).</s><s>The CALM or scrambled shRNA was coexpressed with mKate from the pFUGW vector.</s><s>The following antibodies were used: AP180 (155003, Synaptic Systems, 1: 100), Bassoon (141004, Synaptic Systems, 1: 500), CALM (sc-6433, Santa Cruz, 1: 100), clathrin heavy chain (ab21679, Abcam, 1: 400) c-myc epitope tag (9E10, purified from ascites, monoclonal, 1: 1,000).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical analysis.</head><p><s>If not indicated differently, traces were recorded from 4-12 neurons per individual experiment.</s><s>From each neuron several tens to hundreds of synapses were analysed.</s><s>Data was pooled in two steps: (i) by calculating the median from all synapses from one neuron; and (ii) by using this value to generate the median for all neurons within each individual experiment.</s><s>N individual experiments were averaged and used for statistical analysis.</s><s>Maximal spread, FWHM 2 of the last time point and the duration of half way reclustering were obtained from median filtered original traces in order to reduce noise.</s><s>All values are depicted as mean±s.e.m.</s><s>Statistical significance was calculated with Prism (Graphpad) using a two-way analysis of variance with repeated measures (for curves) or a two-tailed t-test (all bar graphs).</s><s>Statistical significance is indicated as followed: ** ¼ Po0.01; * ¼ Po0.05.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 |</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1 | Newly exocytosed Syb2 is largely retained within presynaptic boutons.</s><s>(a) Schematic of experimental workflow to monitor newly exocytosed pHluorin-tagged SV proteins.</s><s>(b) Syb2-pHluorin fluorescence (F) before and after selective photobleaching.</s><s>Right, enhanced contrast shows small residual F post-bleaching.</s><s>Scale bar, 5 mm.</s><s>(c,d) Syb2-pHluorin F intensity changes from time-lapse images (400 ms frame À 1 ) of stimulated (40 APs, 20 Hz) surface-eclipsed neurons.</s><s>(c) Presynaptic boutons, (d) axonal areas (mean ± s.e.m.; N ¼ 10 neurons).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,145.49,222.85,156.20,50.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 |</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2 | Syb2 spread, confinement and reclustering within presynaptic boutons.</s><s>(a) Representative images of a Syb2-pHluorin expressing synapse of stimulated (40 APs, 20 Hz) surface-eclipsed neurons, either background subtracted (DF), Gaussian fit (Fit), FWHM (white line) or Gaussian fit residual.</s><s>Scale bar, 1 mm.</s><s>(b,c) FMWH 2 of Gaussian fit over time.</s><s>Fast diffusional spread during and after stimulation, followed by confinement (b) and reclustering (c).</s><s>Mean±s.e.m.; n ¼ 5 independent experiments.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,163.73,506.65,115.95,86.06" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 |</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3 | Diffusional spread, confinement, and reclustering of newly exocytosed SV proteins.</s><s>(a,b) FMWH 2 of Gaussian fit over time shows spreading, confinement (a), and reclustering (b) of Syb2-, Syt1-and Syp-pHluorin in surface-eclipsed stimulated (40 AP, 20 Hz) neurons imaged at 400 ms frame À 1 .</s><s>(c-e) Maximal spread (c), last time point (d) and half-life t 1/2 of reclustering (e).</s><s>(f) Measured Syb2-pHluorin F increase used to model-free diffusion of successively fusing SVs.</s><s>(g) Modelled intensity distributions from successive SV fusions and sum distribution.</s><s>(h) Best-fit of model and experimentally determined FMWH 2 .</s><s>(i) Diffusion coefficients (D) for Syb2, Syt1, Syp.</s><s>Mean±s.e.m.; independent experiments: Syb2 (n ¼ 5), Syt1 (n ¼ 3), Syp (n ¼ 3).</s><s>Statistical analysis was done by two-tailed unpaired t-test (c-e, i) or two-way analysis of variance with repeated measures (h time points 0.8-2 s).</s><s>NS: P40.05.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,357.77,456.25,69.63,100.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 |</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4 | Spread and confinement of Syb2 are modulated by its association with AP180 or CALM.</s><s>(a,b) FMWH 2 of Gaussian fit over time shows spreading, confinement (a), and reclustering (b) of Syb2-pHluorin WT or M46A in surface-eclipsed stimulated (40 AP, 20 Hz) neurons imaged at 400 ms frame À 1 .</s><s>(c-e) Maximal spread (c), last time point (d) and half-life t 1/2 of reclustering (e).</s><s>(f,g) Best-fit of model and experimentally determined FMWH 2 for Syb2 WT and M46A.</s><s>(h) Diffusion coefficients for Syb2 WT and M46A.</s><s>Mean ± s.e.m.; n ¼ 3 independent experiments.</s><s>Statistical analysis was done by two-tailed paired t-test (c-e,h) or two-way analysis of variance with repeated measures (f,g) time points 0.8-2 s).</s><s>**Po0.01,</s><s>*Po0.05,</s><s>NS: P40.05.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,142.49,571.69,107.49,79.82" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 |</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5 | AP180 and CALM modulate spread and confinement of newly exocytosed Syb2.</s><s>(a,b) FMWH 2 of Gaussian fit over time shows spreading, confinement (a) and reclustering (b) of Syb2-pHluorin in surface-eclipsed hippocampal neurons lacking AP180 (KO) and depleted of CALM (knockdown (KD)) or corresponding WT control neurons treated with scrambled (Scr) shRNA (stimulation: 40 AP, 20 Hz).</s><s>(c-e) Maximal spread (c), last time point (d) and half-life t 1/2 of reclustering (e).</s><s>Mean ± s.e.m.; n ¼ 3 independent experiments).</s><s>Statistical analysis was done by two-tailed paired t-test.</s><s>**Po0.01,</s><s>*Po0.05,</s><s>NS: P40.05.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 |</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6 | Newly exocytosed proteins co-cluster with endocytic proteins in the periactive zone.</s><s>(a) 3D-Structured Illumination Microscopy (3D-SIM) analysis of Bassoon (Bass), AP180 and clathrin heavy chain (CHC) in stimulated (40 APs, 20 Hz) or non-stimulated hippocampal neurons.</s><s>Scale bar, 1 mm; zoom, 500 nm.</s><s>(b) Schematic for immunolabeling of the newly exocytosed SV protein pool (NEP).</s><s>(c-e) SD-dSTORM imaging of newly exocytosed SV proteins (stimulation: 40 AP, 20 Hz) in hippocampal neurons expressing Syb2-c-myc.</s><s>(c) 2-colour SD-dSTORM analysis of NEP and AP180, overlaid with wide-field image of Bassoon.</s><s>Scale bar, 1 mm; zoom, 100 nm.</s><s>(d) Ripley's L(r)-r function shows sub-synaptic clustering of NEP and of AP180, indicated by positive L(r)-r values with a maximum at radii of about 100 nm (NEP) and 200 nm (AP180).</s><s>Mean ± s.e.m.; n ¼ 31 synapses.</s><s>Dotted lines represent upper envelopes of complete spatial randomness (CSR).</s><s>(e) Radial intensity profiles of NEP and AP180 signals centred on the maxima of sub-synaptic NEP clusters show colocalization of both proteins (mean ± s.e.m.; n ¼ 47 synapses).</s><s>(f) k-Nearest neighbour analysis (k ¼ 10) of NEP and AP180 showing a maximum at 25 nm.</s><s>The red line represents results after toroidal shift of one channel.</s><s>Values above the red line indicate colocalization of NEP and AP180 (mean ± s.e.m.; n ¼ 31 synapses).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,310.49,347.29,52.45,159.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 7 |</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure7| Model of protein diffusion, confinement and reclustering.</s><s>Schematic model of SV protein confinement and reclustering and the role of the endocytic machinery: following rapid diffusion (WT, top) newly exocytosed SV proteins remain confined within the presynaptic bouton (WT, middle), aided by their association with the endocytic machinery.</s><s>Confinement is followed by SV protein reclustering within the periactive zone (WT, bottom).</s><s>In the absence of a functional endocytic machinery diffusion of newly exocytosed SV proteins is accelerated (bold arrows) and both confinement and the extent, but not the rate, of reclustering are compromised.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,135.65,50.77,324.14,222.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 6:8392 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms9392 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications &amp; 2015 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 6:8392 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms9392 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">&amp; 2015 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>We thank Claudia Schmidt for technical assistance, and Drs Nils Brose (Max-Planck-Institute for Experimental Medicine, Go ¨ttingen, Germany), ¨rgen Klingauf (University of Mu ¨nster, Mu ¨nster, Germany), and Leon Lagnado (University of Sussex, Brighton, UK) for the kind gift of plasmids.</s><s>Supported by grants from the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG HA2686/8-1 to V.H.; MA4735/1-1 to T.M.; SFB 958/Z02 to J.S.) and by a Max-Delbru ¨ck Center predoctoral fellowship (to N.G.).</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author contributions</head><p><s>N.G. and G.T. conducted all imaging experiments and data analysis; T.M. supplied knockout mice; J.S. and V.H. designed the study, analysed data; and together with N.G.</s><s>wrote the manuscript.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional information</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular circuitry of endocytosis at nerve terminals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dittman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="160" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein scaffolds in the coupling of synaptic exocytosis and endocytosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Haucke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Neher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sigrist</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="138" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Saheki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>De Camilli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Synaptic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cold Spring Harb. Perspect. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5645</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular mechanisms of presynaptic membrane retrieval and synaptic vesicle reformation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kononenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Haucke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="484" to="496" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clathrin-mediated endocytosis at the synaptic terminal: bridging the gap between physiology and molecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Royle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lagnado</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Traffic</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1489" to="1497" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diffusional trapping of GluR1 AMPA receptors by input-specific synaptic activity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ehlers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Heine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Groc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Choquet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="447" to="460" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surface mobility of postsynaptic AMPARs tunes synaptic transmission</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Heine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">320</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="201" to="205" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SnapShot: receptor dynamics at plastic synapses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kneussel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Triller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Choquet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">157</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1731</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homeostatic regulation of synaptic GlyR numbers driven by lateral diffusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Levi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="261" to="273" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synaptic vesicles interchange their membrane proteins with a large surface reservoir during recycling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ferna ´ndez-Alfonso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kwan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="186" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">STED microscopy reveals that synaptotagmin remains clustered after synaptic vesicle exocytosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Willig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Rizzoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Westphal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">440</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="935" to="939" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A readily retrievable pool of synaptic vesicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hua</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="833" to="839" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vesicular proteins exocytosed and subsequently retrieved by compensatory endocytosis are nonidentical</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wienisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Klingauf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1019" to="1027" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Calcium dependence of exo-and endocytotic coupling at a glutamatergic synapse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hosoi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Holt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sakaba</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="216" to="229" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What is rate-limiting during sustained synaptic activity: vesicle supply or the availability of release sites</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Neher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front. Synaptic Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">144</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imaging constitutive exocytosis with total internal reflection fluorescence microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schmoranzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goulian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Axelrod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">149</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imaging the post-fusion release and capture of a vesicle membrane protein</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sochacki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1154</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Secretory granules are recaptured largely intact after stimulated exocytosis in cultured endocrine cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Taraska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Perrais</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ohara-Imaizumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nagamatsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Almers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2070" to="2075" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing secretion and synaptic transmission with pH-sensitive green fluorescent proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Miesenbock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>De Angelis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rothman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">394</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="192" to="195" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imaging phluorin-based probes at hippocampal synapses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Royle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Granseth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Odermatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Derevier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lagnado</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">457</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="303" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A selective activity-dependent requirement for dynamin 1 in synaptic vesicle endocytosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ferguson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">316</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="570" to="574" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Constitutive sharing of recycling synaptic vesicles between presynaptic boutons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Darcy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Staras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Collinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Goda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="321" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Composition of isolated synaptic boutons reveals the amounts of vesicle trafficking proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Wilhelm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">344</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1023" to="1028" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surface trafficking of neurotransmitter receptor: comparison between single-molecule/quantum dot strategies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Groc</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12433" to="12437" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Endocytosis of VAMP is facilitated by a synaptic vesicle targeting signal</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Grote</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="537" to="547" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SNARE motif-mediated sorting of synaptobrevin by the endocytic adaptors clathrin assembly lymphoid myeloid leukemia (CALM) and AP180 at synapses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Koo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13540" to="13545" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evidence for CALM in directing VAMP2 trafficking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Harel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Mattson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Traffic</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="417" to="429" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clathrin assembly protein AP180 and CALM differentially control axogenesis and dendrite outgrowth in embryonic hippocampal neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Bushlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10257" to="10271" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of the clathrin terminal domain in regulating coated pit dynamics revealed by small molecule inhibition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Von Kleist</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">146</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="471" to="484" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pitstop 2 is a potent inhibitor of clathrin-independent endocytosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dutta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Williamson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Donaldson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e45799</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clathrin terminal domain-ligand interactions regulate sorting of mannose 6-phosphate receptors mediated by AP-1 and GGA adaptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Stahlschmidt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mccluskey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Haucke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">289</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4906" to="4918" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-specificity of Pitstop 2 in clathrin-mediated endocytosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Willox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sahraoui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Royle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="326" to="331" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-colour direct STORM with red emitting carbocyanines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lampe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Haucke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sigrist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Heilemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schmoranzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="237" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Novel organic dyes for multicolor localization-based super-resolution microscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lehmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lichtner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Klenz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schmoranzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/jbio.201500119</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biophotonics</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular anatomy of a trafficking organelle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Takamori</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="831" to="846" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Redistribution of synaptic vesicles and their proteins in temperature-sensitive shibire(ts1) mutant Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Van De Goor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ramaswami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5739" to="5743" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The endocytic machinery in nerve terminals surrounds sites of exocytosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Roos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1411" to="1414" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Endocytic active zones: hot spots for endocytosis in vertebrate neuromuscular terminals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Teng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wilkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4855" to="4866" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A small pool of vesicles maintains synaptic activity in vivo</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Denker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17177" to="17182" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-protein assemblies underlie the mesoscale organization of the plasma membrane</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Saka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4509</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Turnover of transmitter and synaptic vesicles at the frog neuromuscular junction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ceccarelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hurlbut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mauro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="499" to="524" />
			<date type="published" when="1973">1973</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The dynamic control of kiss-and-run and vesicular reuse probed with single nanoparticles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tsien</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">323</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1448" to="1453" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synaptophysin is required for synaptobrevin retrieval during synaptic vesicle endocytosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gordon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Leube</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cousin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14032" to="14036" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Overlapping functions of stonin 2 and SV2 in sorting of the calcium sensor synaptotagmin 1 to synaptic vesicles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kaempf</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7297" to="7302" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synaptophysin regulates the kinetics of synaptic vesicle endocytosis in central neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kwon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="847" to="854" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cholesterol and F-actin are required for clustering of recycling synaptic vesicle proteins in the presynaptic plasma membrane</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Dason</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Marin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Charlton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">592</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="621" to="633" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A dynamic formin-dependent deep F-actin network in axons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ganguly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">210</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="417" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clathrin-mediated endocytosis is the dominant mechanism of vesicle retrieval at hippocampal synapses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Granseth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Odermatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Royle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lagnado</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="773" to="786" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clathrin/AP-2 mediate synaptic vesicle reformation from endosome-like vacuoles but are not essential for retrieval at central synapses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kononenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="981" to="988" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ultrafast endocytosis at mouse hippocampal synapses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Watanabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">504</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="242" to="247" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Computer control of microscopes using microManager</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Edelstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Amodaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hoover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Vale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Stuurman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Protoc. Mol. Biol. Chapter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NIH Image to ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rasband</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Eliceiri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="671" to="675" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Splancs-spatial point pattern-analysis code in S-Plus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rowlingson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Diggle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Geosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="627" to="655" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dixon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Encyclopedia of Environmetrics</title>
				<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>El-Shaarawi</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Piegorsch</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1796" to="1803" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the use of Ripley&apos;s K-function and its derivatives to analyze domain size</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kiskowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hancock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kenworthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1095" to="1103" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Titration of Syntaxin1 in mammalian synapses reveals multiple roles in vesicle docking, priming, and release probability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Arancillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16698" to="16714" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lifeact: a versatile marker to visualize F-actin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Riedl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="605" to="607" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
