<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Glioma-derived versican promotes tumor expansion via gliomaassociated microglial/macrophages Toll-like receptor 2 signaling</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014-12-01">1 December 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Feng</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Omar</forename><surname>Dildar</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexander</forename><surname>Hahn</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yong</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Rick</forename><forename type="middle">Joey</forename><surname>Scavetta</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Gunnar</forename><surname>Dittmar</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Adrian</forename><forename type="middle">Kamil</forename><surname>Kaczmarek</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kylie</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dunning</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Carmela</forename><surname>Ricciardelli</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Rinnenthal</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Frank</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Heppner</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Seija</forename><surname>Lehnardt</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Synowitz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Susanne</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
							<email>susanne.wolf@mdc-berlin.de</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Helmut</forename><surname>Kettenmann</surname></persName>
							<email>kettenmann@mdc-berlin.de</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Cellular Neurosciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Delbru ¨ck Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Max Delbru ¨ck Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Delbru ¨ck Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Mass Spectrometry</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin, Berlin</settlement>
									<country>Germany (Y.Y.), Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">D.)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Robinson Institute</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Adelaide</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Adelaide</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neuropathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurology and Center for Anatomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurosurgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurosurgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Tongji Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Tongji Medical College</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Huazhong University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>430030</postCode>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China (F.H.</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Cellular Neurosciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Delbru ¨ck Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Robert Ro ¨ssle Str. 10</addrLine>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Glioma-derived versican promotes tumor expansion via gliomaassociated microglial/macrophages Toll-like receptor 2 signaling</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2014-12-01">1 December 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5A271162B30E5C51B8ED0A2CC1D3B0AE</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/neuonc/nou324</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 22 July 2014; accepted 30 October 2014</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:30+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>(F.H.</term>
					<term>O.D.a D.</term>
					<term>A.H.</term>
					<term>S.A.W.</term>
					<term>H.K.); Cancer Genetics glioma</term>
					<term>microglia/brain macrophages</term>
					<term>MT1-MMP</term>
					<term>TLR2</term>
					<term>versican</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Background.</s><s>Accumulation and infiltration of microglia/brain macrophages around and into glioma tissue promote tumor invasion and expansion.</s><s>One tumor-promoting mechanism of microglia/brain macrophages is upregulation of membrane type 1 matrix metalloprotease (MT1-MMP), which promotes the degradation of extracellular matrix.</s><s>MT1-MMP upregulation is induced by soluble factors released by glioma cells activating microglial Toll-like receptor 2 (TLR2).</s></p><p><s>Methods.</s><s>Versican identified by proteomics was silenced in glioma cells by short interference RNA and short hairpin RNA approaches and studied in vitro and after injection into mouse brains or organotypic brain slices.</s></p><p><s>Results.</s><s>The splice variants V0/V1 of the endogenous TLR2 ligand versican are highly expressed in mouse and human glioma tissue.</s><s>Versican-silenced gliomas induced less MT1-MMP expression in microglia both in vitro and in vivo, which resulted in smaller tumors and longer survival rates as compared with controls.</s><s>Recombinant versican V1 induced significantly higher levels of MT1-MMP in wild-type microglia compared with untreated and treated TLR2 knockout microglial cells.</s><s>Using glioma-injected organotypic brain slices, we found that the impact of versican signaling on glioma growth depended on the presence of microglia.</s><s>Moreover, we found that TLR2 expression is upregulated in glioma-associated microglia but not in astrocytes.</s><s>Additionally, an established TLR2 neutralizing antibody reduced glioma-induced microglial MT1-MMP expression as well as glioma growth ex vivo.</s></p><p><s>Conclusions.</s><s>Our results show that versican released from glioma promotes tumor expansion through glioma-associated microglial/macrophage TLR2 signaling and subsequent expression of MT1-MMP.</s><s>This signaling cascade might be a novel target for glioma therapies.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>High-grade gliomas (HGGs) are the most common primary tumors of the central nervous system (CNS) with dismal prognosis despite the advantages of multimodal therapies.</s><s>HGGs are heterogeneous neoplasms that contain stromal cells. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Glioma-associated microglial cells and invaded macrophages (GAMs) make up the largest portion of tumor-infiltrating cells, contributing up to 30% of the entire glioma mass. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s>GAMs show an immune-suppressive phenotype and promote tumor expansion. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref></s><s>Glioma converts GAMs into a protumorigenic phenotype by glioma-released soluble factor(s).</s><s>We have previously shown that these factor(s) activate Toll-like receptor 2 (TLR2) and, subsequently, p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) signaling pathways.</s><s>This activation leads to induction of membrane type 1 matrix metalloprotease (MT1-MMP) expression, which promotes glioma invasion. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>Inhibition of this pathway by minocycline has therapeutic potential in experimental glioma treatment. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref></s><s>LRs are key receptors in the recognition of pathogens and thus play an important role in immunological responses. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref></s><s>Besides the recognition of pathogen-associated molecular patterns, TLRs also bind endogenous ligands created by tissue injury or tumor growth (ie, damage-associated molecular patterns). <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref></s><s>We have previously identified TLR2 expressed by GAMs to be a protumorigenic factor.</s><s>TLR2 is highly expressed in human glioma tissue, which contains GAMs, and its expression is inversely correlated with patient survival. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>here is an increasing list of endogenous ligands for TLRs.</s><s>Versican V1 was reported as an endogenous ligand of TLR2 on macrophages. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref></s><s>Versican, also known as CSPG2, is a member of large chondroitin sulfate proteoglycans that belongs to extracellular matrix components.</s><s>Due to RNA splicing, 4 isoforms have been identified so far (V0, V1, V2, V3, respectively). <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref></s><s>Sequence analyses have revealed that different isoforms contain different glycosaminoglycan (GAG) domains.</s><s>V0, the largest isoform, contains 2 alternatively spliced GAG attachment domains designated as GAG-a and GAG-b, whereas V1 contains only GAG-b, and V2 contains only GAG-a.</s><s>V3 consists only of globular domains.</s><s>Versican is highly expressed in tissue compartments undergoing active cell proliferation and migration, such as smooth muscle tissues and cartilage. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref></s><s>Versican isoforms show distinct functions in the brain.</s><s>V1 induces neuronal differentiation and promotes neurite outgrowth, while V2 is a potent inhibitor of axonal growth. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref></s><s>Versican expression is elevated in several cancers including brain, lung, breast, and ovarian and is associated with cancer relapse and patient prognosis. <ref type="bibr">12,17 -19</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Material and Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Animals</head><p><s>We used C57BL/6 WT mice (Charles River Laboratories) and TLR 2 knockout (KO) mice on a C57BL/6 background.</s><s>The TLR2 KO mice were generated by Dr. Shizuo Akira of Osaka University, Japan, and were obtained from Oriental BioServices Inc. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref> The KO efficiency has been shown previously. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>All mice were handled according to governmental (LaGeSo, G 0268/10, G 0343/10) and internal (MDC) regulations.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Human Materials</head><p><s>All human glioma and normal brain materials in this study were obtained from the Department of Neurosurgery and Department of Neuropathology at Charite ´University Hospital according to the rules of the Ethical Committee (Charite ´, EA4/098/11).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cell Culture</head><p><s>Murine glioma cell line WT GL261 (National Cancer Institute) and human glioma cell line U373 were cultured in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium with supplements (200 mM glutamine, 50 units/mL penicillin, 50 mg/mL streptomycin, and 10% fetal calf serum [FCS], all from Invitrogen).</s><s>EGFP and mCherry GL261 cells were generated as previously described. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>rimary human glioblastoma cells GBM1, GBM2, GBM3, and GBM4 were derived from tumor resections.</s><s>The material was washed and cut into pieces.</s><s>After digestion with 1 mL trypsin/ DNAse, the cell suspension was filtered by a cell strainer (70 mm, BD Falcon), resuspended in culture medium, and transferred to a T25 flask.</s><s>After 2 days, the cells were washed with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), and the medium was changed.</s><s>Cells were cultured adherently until confluency and then passaged.</s><s>Primary microglia were prepared from neonatal C57BL/6 or TLR2 KO mice, as previously described. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>The CHO-K1 cells overexpressing recombinant V1 (rV1) versican (CHO-V1) used for recombinant versican production were kindly provided by Prof. R. LeBaron (Division of Life Sciences, University of Texas at San Antonio) <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21</ref> and were cultured in aMEM supplemented with 10% FCS, 50 units/mL penicillin, 50 mg/mL streptomycin (Sigma-Aldrich), and Plasmocin 5 mg/mL (Invivogen).</s><s>All cells were incubated at 378C in 5% CO 2 .</s><s>Glioma-conditioned medium (GCM) was collected as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> and confirmed to be mycoplasma free.</s><s>For collecting the conditioned medium from the short interference RNA (siRNA) experiments, after silencing cells by siRNA, the same number of cells from control siRNA or versican siRNA treatment groups were seeded, and GCM was collected after 24 hours.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Identification of Secreted Proteins in GCM by Shot-gun Proteomics</head><p><s>Proteins of serum-free GCM were concentrated and converted to peptides.</s><s>Peptides were ionized and sprayed into the mass spectrometer after purification, and the recorded spectra were analyzed.</s><s>(Details of the procedure are available in the Supplementary information.)</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Purification of Versican V1</head><p><s>Full-length recombinant versican (rV1) was purified from CHO -V1-conditioned media using a combination of anion exchange and gel filtration chromatography, as previously described. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref></s><s>The modifications are outlined in the Supplementary information.)</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Total RNA Isolation and Polymerase Chain Reaction</head><p><s>Total RNA isolation and quantitative reverse transcription (qRT-) PCR were performed as previously described. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>(The primer sequence and PCR program are listed in the Supplementary information.)</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Protein Extraction and Western Blot</head><p><s>Protein concentration was determined as described. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>For detecting versican, protein extract was dialyzed against chondroitinase buffer (40 mM Tris, 40 mM sodium acetate, 10 mM EDTA, pH 8) and digested with chondroitinase ABC (Seikagaku; 1 -2 mU/g protein) at 378C overnight before electrophoresis.</s><s>The membranes were blocked and followed by overnight incubation at 48C with rabbit anti-V0/V1 or anti-V0/V2 antibody (a gift from Prof. Dr. Dieter R. Zimmermann, Zurich).</s><s>The membranes were incubated with a secondary anti-rabbit horseradish peroxidase antibody (1:2000; Cell Signaling), developed with SuperSignal West Pico Chemiluminescence substrate kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific), and signal detected by Molecular Imager Gel Doc XR system (Bio-Rad).</s></p><p><s>Versican Knockdown with Short Interference RNA and Short hairpin RNA Approach For transient silencing of versican expression, GL261 cells were transfected with siRNA versican (ON-TARGETplus SMARTpool, Dharmacon) and as control with scrambled nontargeted siRNA with Dharmafect4 (Dharmacon) according to the manufacture's instructions.</s><s>After 24 hours of transfection, cells transfected with siRNA versican and nontargeted siRNA were seeded into 6-well plates, again with the same cell density for generating conditioned medium.</s><s>siGAPDH (control SMARTpool, Dharmacon) was used as a positive control, and transfection efficiency was tested by qRT-PCR and Western blot.</s></p><p><s>For stable versican knockdown, short hairpin RNA (shRNA) was generated with pSUPER retro system (Oligoengine) according to the manufacturer's instructions.</s><s>shRNA sequences are ACTGCGGAGCACACGTAAATA and GGTGGCCCAGAACGGAAATAT, and empty vector was used as a negative control.</s><s>Retroviral supernatant was generated by transfection of Phoenix cells as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23</ref> and applied to GL261 or EGFP GL261 cells to transduce versican genes.</s><s>Infected cells were selected for 3 days with 2 mg/mL puromycin, and cell proliferation of versican knocked-down GL261 and control cells was analyzed by cell counting or BrdU assay according to the manufacturer's instructions (Roche).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Glioma-associated Microglia/Macrophage Isolation by Magnetic-activated Cell Sorting</head><p><s>GAMs were acutely isolated by magnetic-activating cell sorting (MACS), as previously described.</s><s>As with any manipulation, MACS will trigger the activation of microglial cells; however, we observed a clear difference with respect to MT1-MMP expression between MACS isolated cells from normal brain versus those from glioma tissue. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Flow Cytometry</head><p><s>Control brain tissue and tumor tissue were dissociated into cell suspensions, and cells were then washed and incubated with different antibodies for 30 minutes at 48C. (Antibody information is outlined in the Supplementary information.)</s><s>Data were analyzed using FlowJo software (Treestar).</s><s>Flow cytometry data were quantified by median fluorescence intensity (MFI) and presented in histograms.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Organotypic Brain Slice Model and Tumor Inoculation</head><p><s>Organotypic brain slices were prepared, and 5000 EGFP GL261 cells were injected into slices, as described previously. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>For the treatment with a TLR2 antibody, mAb T2.5 or isotype control (both from eBioscience) was applied to the medium after the tumor implantation, and new antibody or isotype was added every other day when the medium was changed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Glioma Implantation</head><p><s>Twenty-thousand WT, shcon (nontargeted control) and shver (versican silenced) GL261 cells were inoculated into mouse brains as described previously. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Immunofluorescent Staining and Image Processing</head><p><s>Free-floating 40 mm thick brain sections from tumor-bearing mice were prepared as previously described. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>(Antibody information is outlined in the Supplementary material.)</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tumor Size Quantification and Survival Analysis</head><p><s>Two groups of wild-type (WT) C57BL/6 (at least 7 in each group) mice were injected with either shcon or shver GL261 cells.</s><s>Tumor size was determined by unbiased stereology using the Stereoinvestigator software (Mbf Bioscience), and survival rate was calculated by Kaplan-Meier method with log-rank analysis.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Analysis</head><p><s>All data represent the average of at least 3 independent experiments.</s><s>Error bars represent standard error of the mean.</s><s>Datasets were analyzed statistically with SPSS11.5 software and tested for normality with the Shapiro-Wilks test.</s><s>The Mann-Whitney U test was used for nonparametric analysis.</s><s>Parametric testing was done with the Student t test.</s><s>Comparisons between multiple groups were done using 1-way ANOVA with the Scheffe ´post hoc test.</s><s>Statistical significance was determined at P values ,.05 (*) and ,.01 (**) while "n.s." implied a nonsignificant P value.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>The Endogenous TLR2 Ligand Versican V0/V1 Is Expressed by Gliomas</s></p><p><s>The expression of versican isoforms was analyzed in microglia, whole adult brain lysate, and GL261 cells by qRT-PCR.</s><s>GL261 cells expressed predominately V0, V1, and V3 mRNA but not V2, while microglial cells did not express any versican isoforms (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>).</s><s>On the protein level, GL261 cells only expressed V0/V1 but not V2 as shown by immunostaining.</s><s>(The oligodendrocyte precursor cell line Oli-neu <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24</ref> was used as a positive control for V2; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>).</s><s>In mouse glioma tissue, versican V0/V1 was only expressed within tumor tissue and was mainly colabeled with mCherry-positive glioma cells (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C, arrows</ref>).</s><s>In the human glioma cell line U373 and 4 primary cultures of human GBM samples (all of them express low levels of the glioma stem cell marker CD133) versican V1 was expressed by all cells, while V2 was expressed only by some primary GBM cells (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1D</ref>).</s><s>In human GBM tissue, versican V0/V1 was also expressed in 3 human samples but not in the normal brain tissue.</s><s>(Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1E</ref> and Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1B</ref>).</s><s>Moreover, we performed mass spectrometry with conditioned medium from GL261 and could detect the presence of versican (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>).</s><s>These results show that versican V0/V1 is highly expressed by mouse and human gliomas compared with the normal brain tissues.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hu et al.: Versican mediates glioma growth via microglia</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recombinant Versican V1 Induces Microglial MT1-MMP Expression</head><p><s>To test whether versican is responsible for MT1-MMP induction on microglia, we first treated primary cultured microglia with recombinant versican V1 and analyzed MT1-MMP expression by qRT-PCR.</s><s>The TLR2 agonist heat-killed Listeria monocytogenes (HKLM; InvivoGen) was used as a positive control.</s><s>Recombinant versican V1 induced MT1-MMP expression on microglia after 6 hours of stimulation (7.1 fold+1.9;</s><s>P ¼ .032)</s><s>(Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>).To exclude the effect from endotoxin in the purified recombinant V1, we used Lipopolysaccharide (LPS) as a control.</s></p><p><s>We observed a small induction of MT1-MMP with LPS (2.1 fold+0.35;</s><s>P ¼ .04);</s><s>however, the induction was significantly less than with V1 (P ¼ .035),</s><s>indicating that the major effect was due to recombinant V1.</s><s>We repeated the same treatment on microglia cultured from TLR2 KO animals.</s><s>As seen in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>, the TLR2 agonist Pam3CSK4 failed to induce MT1-MMP expression (P ¼ .37).</s><s>Although we still observed an upregulation of MT1-MMP in V1 treatment group (P ¼ .01), it was significantly less (P ¼ .037)</s><s>compared with the WT microglia.</s><s>Since the MT1-MMP induction is similar to the LPS treatment group, the V1-induced expression in the TLR2 KO microglia may be due to contaminating endotoxin.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Versican-silenced Gliomas Induced Less MT1-MMP Expression in Microglia, Reduced the Tumor Size, and Prolonged Survival Time of Mice Bearing Glioma</head><p><s>To further identify the role of versican on microglial MT1-MMP regulation, total versican expression in GL261 cells was knocked down by siRNA (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2A</ref>), and gliomaconditioned medium was collected from both nontarget siRNAtransfected (GCM) and versican siRNA-transfected GL261 (TCM).</s><s>Primary cultured microglial cells were then stimulated by both conditioned media for 6 hours, and MT1-MMP expression was analyzed by qRT-PCR.</s><s>After 6 hours of stimulation, MT1-MMP expression was significantly increased in the nontarget siRNA group (GCM, 1.9+0.3</s><s>fold; P ¼ .04)</s><s>while it was not increased in the versican siRNA group (TCM, 0.9+0.3</s><s>fold; P ¼ .01</s><s>compared to GCM treatment group), indicating that versican is an important factor for microglial MT1-MMP regulation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To further verify this effect in situ, we generated control and versican knocked-down GL261 cells with control shRNA (shcon) or versican shRNA (shver) (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2A</ref>).</s><s>These 2 cell lines were implanted into mouse brain (n ¼ 7 in each group).</s><s>After 2 weeks of tumor growth, mice were euthanized, and brain tissue was analyzed by immunohistochemistry. GAMs were identified by immunolabeling with Iba-1 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A</ref>).</s><s>When MT1-MMP fluorescence intensity was analyzed by Image J and normalized to the intensity of DAPI, we observed a significant decrease in MT1-MMP immunoreactivity in GAMs in the shver group (65%+4%; P , .01)</s><s>compared with shcon (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3B</ref>).</s><s>We did not observe any difference in Iba-1 positive cell density between the 2 groups, indicating that versican is not the factor recruiting microglial/macrophages to the tumor Hu et al.: Versican mediates glioma growth via microglia (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C</ref>).</s><s>To further verify the role of versican in regulating MT-1MMP expression ex vivo, we implanted shcon and shver GL261 cells into the brains of WT mice.</s><s>After 2 weeks of tumor growth, GAMs were isolated by MACS (CD11b+), total RNA was collected, and qRT-PCR of MT1-MMP was performed.</s><s>Indeed, we observed a significant decrease of MT1-MMP expression on GAMs in shver tumor compared with shcon (51%+5%; P , .001,</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>).</s><s>These data demonstrate that versican is a glioma-derived mediator that regulates microglial MT1-MMP expression.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hu et al.: Versican mediates glioma growth via microglia</head><p><s>To investigate if ablation of versican in gliomas interferes with tumor expansion in vivo, we injected shcon GL261 and shver GL261 into mouse brains and quantified tumor volumes by unbiased stereological estimation (Cavalieri method).</s><s>Tumor volumes were significantly reduced in versican shRNA GL261-implanted mice (4.07+0.82</s><s>mm 3 ) compared with shcon GL261-implanted mice (7.98+0.6 mm 3 ; P , .01,</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3E</ref>).</s><s>Furthermore, we did another set of tumor inoculations and found that knockdown of versican in GL261 cells led to significantly increased survival rate (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3F</ref>, n ¼ 8; P ¼ .002).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Depleting Microglia From Cultured Brain Slices Abolishes the Effect of Versican Silencing on Glioma Expansion</head><p><s>We tested whether the presence of microglia is essential for the effect of versican silencing on glioma expansion.</s><s>We prepared organotypic brain slices in which we depleted microglia using liposome-encapsulated clodronate.</s><s>We then injected glioma cells into the normal and microglia-depleted slices and analyzed the area occupied by glioma cells 5 days later (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4A</ref>).</s><s>Versican knocked-down glioma cells resulted in significant smaller tumors (shcon-enhanced green fluorescent protein [EGFP] PBS, 1.1+0.36</s><s>mm 2 ; shver EGFP PBS; 0.79+0.25 mm 2 ; P , .001) in slices with normal density of microglia.</s><s>When microglia were depleted, there was no significant difference in glioma expansion comparing the injection of shcon and shver cells (shcon cl, 0.65+.26</s><s>mm 2 ; shver cl, 0.59+0.2</s><s>mm 2 ; P..99), indicating that the role of versican in tumor growth is dependent on the presence of microglia (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conditioned Medium From Microglia but not Astrocytes Induces Glioma Versican Expression in Vitro</head><p><s>To investigate whether microglia or astrocytes can influence the expression of versican by glioma cells, GL261 cells were stimulated with conditioned medium from microglia and astrocytes for 24 hours.</s><s>The microglia-conditioned medium increased the expression of V0, V1, and V3, but not V2.</s><s>As seen in Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S3A</ref>, microglial-conditioned medium (MCM) induced 1.94 (+0.1;</s><s>P , .001) times higher expression in all versican isoforms: 1.5 in V0 (1.44+0.07;</s><s>P , .01),</s><s>1.6 in V1 (1.58+0.09;</s><s>P , .01), and 1.5 but not significant in V3 (1.49+0.2;</s><s>P .</s><s>.05).</s><s>V2 was undetectable.</s><s>GL261 was also stimulated with astrocyte-conditioned medium.</s><s>None of the versican isoforms was significantly changed after the 24 hour treatment (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S3B</ref>).</s><s>These data indicate that microglia, but not astrocytes, induce versican expression in glioma and suggest a feedback loop between microglia and glioma cells.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TLR2 Is Upregulated in Glioma-associated Microglia but not Astrocytes ex Vivo</head><p><s>To investigate how TLRs are expressed and regulated in different cell types within gliomas, we used flow cytometry to detect TLR expression in GAMs and glioma.</s><s>GL261 cells were implanted into the mouse brain; after 2 weeks, tumor and control brain tissue were dissociated and stained with different surface markers and TLR antibodies.</s><s>Resident microglia and infiltrated monocytes could be distinguished by CD45 staining. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">25</ref></s><s>Microglia are CD11b + CD45 Low , infiltrating macrophages CD11b +-CD45 high , and astrocytes CD11b -CD45 -GLAST + (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S4</ref>).</s><s>TLR expression was analyzed with MFI by Flowjo software in these cell subpopulations (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5</ref>).</s><s>As shown in the representative histogram (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5A</ref>) of the tumor tissue, TLR2 on microglia was significantly upregulated (P ¼ .008)</s><s>compared with the naı ¨ve controls (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5B</ref>).</s><s>TLR2 forms heterodimers with either TLR1 or TLR6.</s><s>We observed a slight, but not significant, induction in TLR1 but not TLR6.</s><s>For infiltrating macrophages, we could only demonstrate that TLR2 is expressed due to the difficulties of finding a proper control.</s><s>Compared with naı ¨ve microglia, TLR2 expression is also significantly upregulated (P ¼ .007).</s><s>TLR2 and TLR6 are expressed in naı ¨ve astrocytes, but there was no difference when comparing naı ¨ve astrocytes with tumor-associated astrocytes.</s><s>TLR6, but not TLR2, was expressed in GL261 cells (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S5</ref>).</s><s>Taken together, TLR2 is the subtype of TLRs upregulated in GAMs but not glioma-associated astrocytes, and GAMs are the main TLR2 expressing cells in the glioma microenvironment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TLR2 Neutralizing Antibody Inhibits Glioma-induced Microglial MT1-MMP Expression and Reduces Tumor Growth ex Vivo</head><p><s>The TLR2 monoclonal neutralizing antibody T2.5 has previously been shown to functionally block TLR2 and successfully inhibit gastric cancer growth. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">26</ref></s><s>We first verified that T2.5 blocks microglial TLR2 functionality in vitro.</s><s>T2.5 attenuated the TLR2 agonist Pam3CSK4-induced microglial IL-6 and MT1-MMP induction (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S6</ref>).</s><s>To test whether T2.5 impairs glioma-induced microglial MT1-MMP expression, microglia were stimulated with either GCM in combination with T2.5 or GCM with isotype control antibody for 6 hours.</s><s>GCM treatment with isotype control resulted in an increase of 3.8 fold (+0.7;</s><s>P ¼ .03;</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6A</ref>) of microglial MT1-MMP compared to the untreated cells, T2.5 treatment with GCM induced less MT1-MMP expression (1.7 + 0.3; P ¼ .03),</s><s>which suggests that T2.5 blocked microglial TLR2 signaling.</s></p><p><s>We studied glioma expansion in organotypic brain slices.</s><s>T2.5 or isotype control was applied into the cultured medium after EGFP GL261 cells were injected.</s><s>When tumor size was quantified (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6B</ref>) after 5 days, mAb T2.5 treatment resulted in a significantly reduced tumor area (0.28 mm 2 +0.02 mm 2 ; P , .001) compared with isotype control (0.65+0.04 mm 2 ).</s><s>When we repeated the same experiment with TLR2 KO animals, we did not see a difference between the isotype and mAb T2.5 treatment groups (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S6C</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>We, along with other groups, have previously shown that microglia are important players in glioma growth and expansion <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">27</ref> and that interfering with the GAM phenotype may provide alternative therapy for glioma treatment. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">29</ref></s><s>In the present study, we identified versican as a signaling substance released from glioma cells that promotes tumor expansion via microglia/ macrophages.</s><s>Versican is a ligand for TLR2, and we have previously shown that TLR2 activation induces MT1-MMP expression in microglia, which activates glioma-released MMP2 and thereby promotes glioma invasion and growth.</s></p><p><s>Based on Repository for Molecular Brain Neoplasia Data (REMBRANDT), TLR2 is highly expressed in gliomas compared with nontumor tissue and is also inversely correlated to patient survival. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>These data are, however, obtained from glioma tissue that is a mix of glioma cells and GAMs.</s><s>Hussain et al examined TLR expression on human GAMs by flow cytometry and found TLR2, 3, and 4. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">30</ref> In our previous in vitro study, we found that TLR3 ligand Poly I:C did not induce microglial MT1-MMP expression, <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> while TLR4 ligand LPS and TLR2 ligand Pam3csk4 did.</s><s>However, when we inoculated glioma cells into TLR4 KO mice, we did not see a significant difference in tumor size compared with the WT control (unpublished data).</s><s>Therefore, we focused on TLR2 in the present study.</s><s>We showed the expression of TLR2 and its upregulation in glioma-associated microglia, as compared with control microglia; in contrast, astrocytes and glioma cells expressed only low levels of TLR2.</s></p><p><s>The endogenous agonists of TLRs can be proteins, fatty acids, proteoglycans, or nucleic acids. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref></s><s>Versican is a component of the extracellular matrix and is found in a variety of tumor tissues including gliomas. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref></s><s>Versican is released in lung cancer and activates TLR2 on macrophages, <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref> which results in macrophage TNFa and IL-6 induction and in tumor progression.</s><s>When recombinant veriscan V1 was applied to macrophages, a robust induction of IL-6 and TNFa was observed, but this effect was totally abolished when the same recombinant versican was applied to macrophage from TLR2 KO mice, indicating that versican activates macrophage through TLR2. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref></s><s>Moreover, V1 promoted ovarian cancer progression via macrophage TLR2 signaling and expression of hCAP18/LL-37. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">31</ref></s><s>n order to identify the TLR2 ligand in the glioma context, we first screened for soluble factors released by GL261 cells using mass spectrometry.</s><s>We identified 2 candidates: versican and high mobility group box 1 (HMGB1).</s><s>Curtain et al demonstrated that dying gliomas, when reacting to immunotherapies, released HMGB1 to recruit dendritic cells through TLR2 signaling. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">32</ref></s><s>When we applied recombinant protein HMGB1 to microglial cells, it did not induce MT1-MMP upregulation, while versican V1 significantly induced microglial MT1-MMP expression (data not shown).</s><s>Due to the purification procedure, we could not eliminate endotoxin in our recombinant versican sample; thus, we used LPS as an internal control.</s><s>We only detected a modest upregulation of MT1-MMP in microglia by LPS, which was significantly less when compared with the V1 treatment.</s><s>We repeated the same experiments with TLR2 KO microglia and found a small residual response that was of similar magnitude as that triggered by LPS alone.</s><s>Here, we confirmed that the LPS administration on microglia in our previous study induced a modest upregulation of MT1-MMP, which was not significant. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>Here we show a significant upregulation that is likely due to a larger sample size.</s></p><p><s>Our versican knockdown experiments in vitro and in vivo further demonstrated that versican is the endogenous ligand acting on TLR2 and that it upregulates MT1-MMP and promotes Hu et al.: Versican mediates glioma growth via microglia glioma growth.</s><s>Our data on glioma-injected organotypic brain slices revealed that the impact of versican signaling on glioma growth depended on the presence of microglia.</s><s>Taken together, versican is a glioma-derived endogenous TLR2 mediator that regulates microglial MT1-MMP expression for tumor expansion.</s></p><p><s>A humanized anti-TLR2 antibody (OPN-301 and OPN-305) has been shown to inhibit TLR2-mediated inflammation in a murine model of renal transplantation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">33</ref></s><s>Tye et al have recently used this neutralizing antibody to block TLR2 in a gastric cancer model that inhibited gastric tumorigenesis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">26</ref></s><s>More importantly, this antibody has already been tested in a phase I clinical trial showing its safety and tolerability on healthy subjects; a phase II study in renal transplantation is ongoing. <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">34</ref></s><s>Here we show that GCM-induced microglial MT1-MMP upregulation could be abolished by TLR2 antibody treatment.</s><s>By using an organotypic brain slice model, we also showed that the TLR2 antibody has potential therapeutic benefits in glioma progression.</s><s>Monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) have been used with increasing success against many tumors.</s><s>Bevacizumab, also a humanized monoclonal antibody to vascular endothelial growth factor, was approved in 2009 by the FDA for treatment of recurrent glioblastoma in the United States. <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">35</ref></s><s>Thus, a mAb-targeting TLR2 is a candidate for adjuvant therapy in the treatment of glioma.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1.</s><s>Versican is highly expressed in glioma cells but not by microglia.</s><s>(A) Expression of V0, V1, V2, and V3 in cultured microglia, whole brain, and GL261 glioma cells by qRT-PCR.</s><s>At least 3 adult mouse brains or 3 different preparations of microglia were analyzed in each condition.</s><s>(B) Immunohistochemistry shows the expression of V0/V1, but not V0/V2, in GL261 cells.</s><s>The Oli-neu cell line (stained with an oligodendrocyte marker CNPase) was used as positive control for V0/V2.</s><s>Nuclei were labeled with DAPI in blue.</s><s>Scale bar is 50 mm.</s><s>(C) Tissue sections from a mouse inoculated with mCherry GL261 glioma cells (red) and stained with V0/V1 (blue) and Iba-1 (green).</s><s>Scale bar is 50 mm in the left image and 25 mm in right image.</s><s>(D) Expression of the different versican isoforms in a human glioma cell line (U373) and cells cultured from human GBM samples (GBM1-4) as determined with RT-PCR.</s><s>(E) Sections from a human GBM patient stained with V0/V1 (red), Iba-1 (green), one human GBM (middle), and one normal brain tissue (right) stained with V0/V1.</s><s>Scale bar is 50 mm and 10 mm for the insert.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,61.85,85.32,468.14,397.81" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 2. Recombinant versican V1 induces microglial MT1-MMP expression via TLR2.</s><s>(A) Wild-type and TLR2 KO microglia were stimulated with recombinant versican V1 for 6 hours, and MT1-MMP was analyzed by qRT-PCR.</s><s>The internal control was 4 ng/mL LPS, and Pam3CSK4 was used as a positive control (n ¼ 5).</s><s>(B) Cultured microglia were stimulated with conditioned media from siRNA-versican (TCM) and nontarget transfected GL261 cells (glioma-conditioned medium) for 6 hours, and MT1-MMP expression was analyzed by qRT-PCR (n ¼ 5).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,132.72,85.32,324.59,397.81" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 3. Versican-silenced gliomas induced less MT1-MMP expression in microglia, reduced tumor growth, and prolonged survival.</s><s>(A) Versican knocked down (shver) and control (shcon) GL261 were implanted into wild-type mice, and the glioma tissue sections were stained 14 days after inoculation with DAPI, Iba-1, and MT1-MMP.</s><s>The image on the right is a merge of all 3 images.</s><s>Scale bar is 50 mm and 10 mm for the insert.</s><s>Images were quantified by Image J (n ¼ 6 in each group) to show the difference in MT1-MMP expression normalized to DAPI (B) and Iba-1 positive cell density (C) comparing tissue with shver and shcon GL261 cells.</s><s>(D) WT mice were injected intracerebrally with shcon or shver glioma cells, and glioma-associated microglia/macrophages were isolated 14 days after glioma cell injection by MACS from both naı ¨ve and tumor tissue.</s><s>Differences in MT1-MMP expression were analyzed by qRT-PCR (n ¼ 3 in each group).</s><s>(E) shver and shcon GL261 cells were inoculated into WT mice.</s><s>After 2 weeks, tumor volume was evaluated based on unbiased stereology (n ¼ 7).</s><s>(F) The Kaplan-Meier curves represent the cumulative survival of mice after shver and shcon GL261 injection (n ¼ 8).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,107.21,85.32,378.89,468.28" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 4. Versican-silenced GL261 resulted in smaller tumors depending on the presence of microglia.</s><s>Control and microglia-depleted brain slices (by treatment with clodronate-filled liposomes) from 16 day-old mice were implanted with 5000 shcon or shver EGFP-GL261 cells.</s><s>The area occupied by glioma cells was measured after 5 days.</s><s>(A) The representative fluorescence micrograph of EGFP-labeled glioma cells in both microglia-containing and -depleted slices were injected with shcon (left) and shver (right) cells.</s><s>Scale bar is 10 mm.</s><s>(B) Tumor area was quantified in microglia-containing (+) and -depleted (-) slices injected with shcon and shver glioma cells.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,98.70,85.32,393.31,165.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 5. TLR2 is upregulated in glioma-associated microglia/macrophages ex vivo.</s><s>Mouse naı ¨ve brain or glioma tissue inoculated for 14 days was dissociated immediately after resection.</s><s>Myelin was removed by Percoll gradient centrifugation, and cell pellets were further analyzed by flow cytometry.</s><s>(A) Representative histograms of TLR1, TLR2, and TLR6 expression as detected by TLR subtype-specific antibodies on microglia, macrophages, and astrocytes in both control and glioma-bearing mice (left panel, n≥3).</s><s>The gray label indicates isotype control.</s><s>(B) Median fluorescence intensity of control and tumor was normalized to isotype and quantified by FlowJo software.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,61.85,85.32,468.60,399.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 6.</s><s>Monoclonal antibody T2.5 inhibited glioma-conditioned medium (GCM)-driven microglial MT1-MMP expression as well as glioma growth ex vivo.</s><s>(A) Primary microglial cells were stimulated with GCM, GCM together with 10 mg/mL isotype, and 10 mg/mL T2.5 for 6 hours.</s><s>MT1-MMP was analyzed by qRT-PCR.</s><s>(B) Organotypic brain slices obtained from 16 day-old C57BL/6 mice were inoculated with 5000 EGFP-GL261 cells and treated with isotype or mAb T2.5.</s><s>The tumor area was determined 5 days after injection of glioma cells.</s><s>Representative images of tumors (green) are present on top of the quantification.</s><s>Scare bars are 25 mm.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,121.38,85.32,348.85,199.62" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Neuro-Oncology</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p><s>We sincerely thank Prof. Dieter R. Zimmermann and Dr. Marı ´a T. Dours-Zimmermann from University of Zurich for providing versican antibodies and plasmids.</s><s>We thank Dr. Katyayni Vinnakota for the discussion and suggestions.</s><s>We also thank Irene Haupt, Regina Piske, and Nadine Scharek for excellent technical assistance.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary Material</head><p><s>Supplementary material is available online at Neuro-Oncology (http://neuro-oncology.oxfordjournals.org/).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p><s>This work was supported by the China Scholarship Council stipend (CSC, China) to Feng Hu and by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (SFB-TR 43, KE 329/30-1 SY 144/4-1), NeuroCure, and NIH Grant (U01CA160882-01A1).</s></p><p><s>Conflict of interest statement.</s><s>The authors declare no competing financial interests.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The brain tumor microenvironment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Charles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Holland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gilbertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Glia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="502" to="514" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of microglia in glioma biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Badie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schartner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Microsc Res Tech</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="113" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microglia in brain tumors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Graeber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Scheithauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kreutzberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Glia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="252" to="259" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microglia stimulate the invasiveness of glioma cells by increasing the activity of metalloprotease-2</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Markovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Glass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Synowitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neuropathol Exp Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="754" to="762" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Microglia/macrophages promote glioma progression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Heppner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Tsirka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Glia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="472" to="485" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gliomas induce and exploit microglial MT1-MMP expression for tumor expansion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Markovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Vinnakota</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chirasani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12530" to="12535" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toll-like receptor 2 mediates microglia/brain macrophage MT1-MMP expression and glioma expansion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Vinnakota</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ku</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuro-Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1457" to="1468" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Minocycline reduces glioma expansion and invasion by attenuating microglial MT1-MMP expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Markovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Vinnakota</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Van Rooijen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain Behav Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="624" to="628" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toll-like receptor signalling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Akira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Takeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="499" to="511" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DAMPening inflammation by modulating TLR signalling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Piccinini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Midwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mediators Inflamm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">672395</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tolerance, danger, and the extended family</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Matzinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Rev Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="991" to="1045" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Carcinoma-produced factors activate myeloid cells through TLR2 to stimulate metastasis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Takahashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">457</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7225</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="102" to="106" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterization of the complete genomic structure of the human versican gene and functional analysis of its promoter</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Naso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Zimmermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Iozzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">269</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32999" to="33008" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The interaction of versican with its binding partners</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">La</forename><surname>Pierre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="483" to="494" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Versican V1 isoform induces neuronal differentiation and promotes neurite outgrowth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Sheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Biol Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2093" to="2104" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Brain derived versican V2 is a potent inhibitor of axonal growth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schmalfeldt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bandtlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Dours-Zimmermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cell Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="807" to="816" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Pt 5</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential expression of versican isoforms in brain tumors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Paulus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Baur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Dours-Zimmermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neuropathol Exp Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="528" to="533" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulation of stromal versican expression by breast cancer cells and importance to relapse-free survival in patients with node-negative primary breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ricciardelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Brooks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Suwiwat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1054" to="1060" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of versican, hyaluronan and CD44 in ovarian cancer metastasis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ween</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Oehler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ricciardelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Mol Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1009" to="1029" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential roles of TLR2 and TLR4 in recognition of gram-negative and gram-positive bacterial cell wall components</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Takeuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hoshino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kawai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="451" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hyaluronate binding properties of versican</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lebaron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Zimmermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ruoslahti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">267</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10003" to="10010" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Formation of hyaluronanand versican-rich pericellular matrix by prostate cancer cells promotes cell motility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ricciardelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Russell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Ween</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">282</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10814" to="10825" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic analysis of chemoresistance in primary murine lymphomas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Schmitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Rosenthal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1029" to="1035" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vitro and in vivo characterisation of glial cells immortalised with a temperature sensitive SV40 T antigen-containing retrovirus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Crang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Blakemore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="182" to="196" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Versican mediates glioma growth via microglia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Monocytes in health and disease -Minireview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Karlmark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Tacke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dunay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Microbiol Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">STAT3-driven upregulation of TLR2 promotes gastric tumorigenesis independent of tumor inflammation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Najdovska</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="478" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neurofibromatosis-1 (Nf1) heterozygous brain microglia elaborate paracrine factors that promote Nf1-deficient astrocyte and glioma growth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Daginakatte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gutmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum Mol Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1098" to="1112" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CSF-1R inhibition alters macrophage polarization and blocks glioma progression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pyonteck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Akkari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Schuhmacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1264" to="1272" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reduced microglial CX3CR1 expression delays neurofibromatosis-1 glioma formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Pong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Higer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gianino</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">73</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="303" to="308" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of human glioma-infiltrating microglia/macrophages in mediating antitumor immune responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hussain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Suki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuro-Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="261" to="279" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tumor-produced versican V1 enhances hCAP18/LL-37 expression in macrophages throug activation of TLR2 and vitamin D3 signaling to promote ovarian cancer progression in vitro</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e56616</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HMGB1 mediates endogenous TLR2 activation and brain tumor regression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Curtin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Candolfi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inhibition of TLR2 promotes graft function in a murine model of renal transplant ischemia-reperfusion injury</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Farrar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Keogh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Mccormack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FASEB J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="799" to="807" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, dose-escalating phase I, healthy subjects study of intravenous OPN-305, a humanized anti-TLR2 antibody</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Reilly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Thomson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Pharmacol Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="593" to="600" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phase II trial of single-agent bevacizumab followed by bevacizumab plus irinotecan at tumor progression in recurrent glioblastoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Kreisl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="740" to="745" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Versican mediates glioma growth via microglia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
