<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Novel RNA-Affinity Proteogenomics Dissects Tumor Heterogeneity for Revealing Personalized Markers in Precision Prognosis of Cancer</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Li</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry &amp; Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Chapel Hill</addrLine>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry &amp; Institute of Biomedical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Fudan University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>200032</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wrobel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry &amp; Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Chapel Hill</addrLine>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>, ...,</roleName><forename type="first">Ling</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry &amp; Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Chapel Hill</addrLine>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Harsha</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gunawardena</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry &amp; Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Chapel Hill</addrLine>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Qing</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Chapel Hill</addrLine>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Xian</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
							<email>xianc@email.unc.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry &amp; Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Chapel Hill</addrLine>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Chapel Hill</addrLine>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry &amp; Institute of Biomedical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Fudan University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>200032</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Dongxu</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Giada</forename><surname>Zurlo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry &amp; Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Chapel Hill</addrLine>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Chapel Hill</addrLine>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Huali</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry &amp; Institute of Biomedical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Fudan University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>200032</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Pengyuan</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Chemistry &amp; Institute of Biomedical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Fudan University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>200032</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zefeng</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">CAS Center for Excellence in Molecular Cell Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">CAS Key Laboratory of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">CAS-MPG Partner Institute of Computational Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Shanghai Institute of Biological Science</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>200031</postCode>
									<settlement>Shanghai</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yibing</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Biochemistry &amp; Biophysics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Chapel Hill</addrLine>
									<postCode>27599</postCode>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Novel RNA-Affinity Proteogenomics Dissects Tumor Heterogeneity for Revealing Personalized Markers in Precision Prognosis of Cancer</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">4FD6864BC9882E9C94E5735C2E14B64C</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.chembiol.2018.01.016</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:30+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Highlights d ISE-affinity proteogenomics dissects tumor heterogeneity for biomarker discovery d An oncogenic-active ISE trans-interactome represents the major tumor in a tissue d The oncogenic-active ISE trans-interactomes contain cancer prognostic markers d Patient-specific alterations of select transfactor genes are of prognostic value</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>In Brief</head><p><s>The interpatient tumor-phenotypic heterogeneity hinders discovery of biomarkers for individualized prognosis.</s><s>Wang and colleagues introduce an alternative splicing activity-based proteogenomic method that dissects tumor heterogeneity for de novo discovery of individualized prognostic biomarkers.</s><s>The resulting biomarkers distinguish high-risk patient subpopulations from other patients within each single breast cancer subtype.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p><s>Breast cancer (BC) tumor heterogeneity contributes to diverse clinical outcomes/phenotypes, complicates prognosis, and misleads therapy <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Koren and Bentires-Alj, 2015)</ref>.</s><s>Although global genomic sequencing of metastatic and primary lesions has identified many BC-associated genetic alterations <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Ding et al., 2010)</ref>, and a 50-gene mRNA expression model has classified multiple BC subtypes (PAM50-subtypes) <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Parker et al., 2009)</ref>, these genetic or transcriptomic signatures fail to distinguish, within single PAM50-subtypes, BC patient subpopulations having variable clinical phenotypes and responses to adjuvant therapy.</s><s>This limitation implies that evolution of malignant and metastatic breast neoplasia is due largely to post-transcriptional alterations.</s><s>Because of the limitation in distinguishing patient subpopulations, approximately 20% of women with poor prognosis are either missed at an early stage or relapse with acquired chemoresistance, and most others are unnecessarily subjected to noxious chemotherapy <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Cardoso et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Ozanne et al., 2011)</ref>.</s><s>Thus, to improve prognostic prediction and guide optimal therapy, it is crucial to establish new-generation biomarkers that precisely define patient-specific clinical phenotypes that cannot be discerned using genomic or transcriptomic data alone.</s></p><p><s>Mass spectrometry (MS)-based quantitative proteomics promises discovery of new phenotype-specific (phenotypic) biomarkers by measuring differentially expressed proteins in healthy versus cancer cells.</s><s>However, at the current level of sensitivity, an MS experiment is often performed on a total clinical specimen, making a bulk measurement averaged over different cell types in a heterogeneous tumor tissue.</s><s>Thus, the tumor-phenotypic characteristics of protein expression may be ''diluted'' by expression of the same proteins in surrounding non-tumor cells.</s><s>To restrict proteomic analysis to the tumor, the state-of-the-art platform is laser capture microdissection (LCM), which sorts tumor cells into relatively homogeneous populations prior to nano-LC-MS/MS-based proteomic analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Liu et al., 2014b)</ref>.</s><s>However, LCM-coupled nano-LC-MS/MS platforms are not amenable to disease assessment in the clinic because of a stringent requirement for sufficient tumor area for microdissection and tedious LCM processing with sample-tosample variability.</s><s>In addition, it is extremely challenging to identify proteins having prognostic significance from the hundreds or thousands of proteins differentially expressed in healthy versus cancer proteomes.</s></p><p><s>The sensitivity, depth, and pathological relevance of MSbased proteomic technology could be improved for phenotypic biomarker discovery by ''singling out'' oncogenically active sub-proteomes that define tumor phenotypes.</s><s>In this regard, multiple RNA cis-acting splicing regulatory elements, such as intronic splicing enhancers (ISEs), that interact with trans-acting splicing proteins (trans-factors) <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Wang et al., 2012)</ref>, coordinately regulate the diversity and specificity of aberrant alternative splicing (AS) that promotes tumor growth, survival, and metastasis <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Korneta and Bujnicki, 2012)</ref>.</s><s>Thus, a tumor-phenotypic assembly of ISE-interacting trans-factor complexes (a trans-interactome) could be refined into an oncogenically active subproteome, which would be a reservoir of tumor-phenotypic markers.</s><s>Therefore, we designed a robust, ISE-affinity, label-free quantitative (LFQ) proteomic approach in which ISEs are used as AS activity-based affinity probes to capture and sort BC-phenotypic trans-interactomes.</s><s>The sorted interactomes enable the specificity and sensitivity of MS to be fully utilized for directed, indepth analysis of these low-abundance, tumor-phenotypic sub-proteomes.</s></p><p><s>By a cell line-to-tissue LFQ cross-referencing analysis, we demonstrate that, without LCM, our ISE probes sort in situ the trans-interactome assembled in any predominant tumor cell type in a heterogeneous tissue.</s><s>Using the dataset of 463 BC patients from The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) <ref type="bibr">(Cancer Genome Atlas Network, 2012)</ref>, which includes patient-specific genetic or transcriptomic alterations and correlated pathology data, our proteogenomic tools not only confirmed the clinicopathological relevance of our trans-interactome findings but also identified new, additional genes that exhibited interaction-correlated expression patterns (iCEPs) in distinct PAM50 subtypes.</s><s>Importantly, we found that patient variations in mRNA expression resolve the inter-patient tumor-phenotypic heterogeneity that is correlated with diverse clinical outcomes within a single PAM50 subtype.</s><s>Kaplan-Meier (KM) survival analysis revealed that patient-specific co-overexpression of select trans-factorencoding genes marked distinct subsets of PAM50-subtype patients having poor prognosis.</s><s>This result agreed with gene expression alterations that are prognostically significant <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Ng et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>Specifically, our functional characterization of particular basal-like/triple-negative BC (BLBC/TNBC)-specific trans-factors involved in distinct interactive AS sub-networks revealed that ISE trans-factors are involved in driving tumor invasion.</s><s>Like a recent report that distinct copy-number variations (CNVs) distinguish patients with different therapeutic responses <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Carter et al., 2016)</ref>, we revealed that PAM50-subtypic CNVs account for the patient-specific mRNA expression alterations of the iCEP genes; thus, these CNVs are signatures of distinct patient subsets having a high risk of relapse or metastasis.</s></p><p><s>Our ISE-affinity proteogenomic identification of new prognostic biomarkers can be conducted directly on clinical specimens.</s><s>The method bypasses sizable efforts involving xenotransplantation and score modeling that have been made to distinguish but a few prognostically significant genes from the mRNA expression of &gt;20,000 genes <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Ng et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>As a result, we have discovered a reservoir that is rich in patient-specific, tumor-phenotypic biomarkers for guiding therapeutic decisions for patient subsets with distinct clinical outcomes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head><p><s>Overall Workflow for De Novo Discovery of Personalized BC Markers Our LCM-independent strategy starts with in situ sorting of BCphenotypic ISE trans-interactomes from the predominant tumor cell type or phenotype in a tissue (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>).</s><s>To prove the clinicopathological accuracy and specificity of ISE enrichment of a trans-interactome representing the predominant malignant or aggressive tumor type/subtype in a tissue, we designed an LFQ cross-referencing scheme involving multiple BC cell lines and primary tissues of similar PAM50 subtypes to compare the compositions of ISE pull-downs.</s><s>The rationale for this scheme is that, in homogeneous BC cell lines, irrelevant contamination exists in association with cell immortalization such that tissue proteomic data often contain protein abundance profiles averaged over different cell types in a heterogeneous tissue.</s><s>The cross-referencing scheme uses the ISE-affinity-correlated LFQ ratios of ISE trans-factors identified in a homogeneous PAM50subtype cell line to distinguish similar subtype trans-factors from the same proteins in other cell types, meanwhile the LFQ ratios filter out ISE-captured proteins from cells arising from immortalization.</s></p><p><s>From the PAM50-subtypic composition of trans-interactomes that we identified by LFQ LC-MS/MS, a PAM50-subtypic interaction-correlated expression pattern (iCEP) could be established for most trans-factors in the TCGA patient database.</s><s>Further, PAM50-subtypic, patient-specific mRNA expression alterations of some combinations of iCEP genes were found to be prognostically significant by KM survival analysis, marking the distinct subsets of BC patients having different prognosis within single PAM50-subtypes.</s></p><p><s>ISE Probes Selectively Sort a PAM50-Subtypic trans-Interactome from the Predominant BC Subtype in a Tissue Our ISE library contained six biotinylated RNA oligomers corresponding to known ISEs <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Wang et al., 2012)</ref>; we used a scrambled RNA sequence as a non-specific control.</s><s>The RNA probes were immobilized on NeutrAvidin-agarose beads.</s><s>To test whether the ISE probes could selectively enrich PAM50-subtypic ISE trans-interactomes from single PAM50 subtypes that predominate in heterogeneous tissues, we performed ISE pulldown experiments with various BC subtypes from different sample origins, i.e., cell lines and clinical specimens.</s><s>These samples included (1) a cell line series of PAM50-classified subtypes in homogeneous populations (sorted subtype control), such as the non-malignant mammary epithelial cell line MCF10A, the luminal subtype T47D, and the BLBC subtype MDA-MB-231, and (2) frozen clinical specimens (unsorted) including two luminal patients estrogen receptor (ER)+ progesterone receptor (PR)À and two basal patients paired with adjacent non-malignant mammary tissue as controls.</s></p><p><s>To ensure that this ISE-affinity platform is amenable to the clinic, we coupled on-beads processing with LFQ for determining compositional differences in BC-subtypic trans-interactomes on a clinical sample scale (60-100 mg total protein mass per nLC-MS/MS run).</s><s>Following repeated washing to remove non-specific proteins, and on-beads tryptic digestion, we performed nLC-MS/MS experiments on each ISE pull-down in three replicates.</s><s>Compared with the non-ISE control, ISEs showed selectivity in binding to specific sets of proteins in the BLBC MDA-231 cells for which the protein LFQ (peak intensity) ratios were quantitatively correlated with the relative affinities of ISEs versus non-ISEs trans-factors (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1A</ref>).</s><s>We then evaluated the accuracy of the LFQ ratios of the captured proteins that were directly correlated with their ISE associations.</s><s>Because amino acid-coded mass tagging (AACT) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Chen et al., 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Zhu et al., 2002)</ref> (SILAC) is still the gold standard for accurate quantitation of relative protein abundance differences, we first used ISE probes to pull down protein complexes from the AACTlabeled cell line set.</s><s>We identified 577 proteins in common in two biological replicates, of which 530 proteins showed higher association with ISEs in either MDA-MB-231 or T47D compared with the same proteins in MCF10A (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1</ref> and Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>).</s><s>The scatterplots for two biological replicates indicated good reproducibility of AACT measurements of ISE binding (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1D  and S1E</ref>).</s><s>We then examined the correlation of the PAM50-subtypic, ISE-affinity ratios measured by LFQ versus AACT.</s><s>Notably, although we used different sample processing and quantitation schemes, i.e., on-beads digestion with LFQ versus in-gel digestion with AACT, we found good cross-method correlation (Pearson correlation 0.54) for the 442 proteins that were quantified by both LFQ and AACT (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1F</ref>), confirming the specificity and reproducibility of ISE probes in binding to PAM50-subtypic trans-factors.</s><s>In sum, combined results from AACT and LFQ indicated that LFQ ratios were accurately correlated with PAM50subtypic ISE affinities, and on-beads sampling/processing coupled to LFQ was a reliable, clinically practical scheme.</s></p><p><s>Further, based on their ISE-affinity-correlated LFQ ratios, we identified four distinct trans-factor clusters showing significantly increased ISE affinities with no binding to non-ISE RNAs <ref type="bibr">(Figure 1B)</ref>.</s><s>A cluster of proteins with increased ISE binding in the BLBC MDA231 cells and another cluster that showed increased binding in the luminal T47D cells were among the trans-factors that showed PAM50-subtypic, anti-correlated ISE affinities (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1B</ref>).</s><s>In view of the enriched gene ontology molecular functions <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Huang et al., 2009)</ref>, most of the ISE-affinity trans-factor proteins in each cluster are RNA-binding proteins, including 164 previously characterized spliceosome components <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Bessonov et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Hegele et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Jurica and Moore, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Rappsilber et al., 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Valadkhan and Jaladat, 2010)</ref>.</s><s>This finding further demonstrated the specificity of the ISE probe library in enriching RNA/ISE-binding proteins.</s><s>Although some basal trans-factors with increased ISE affinities found in MDA231 cells but not in the non-malignant cells are specifically involved in cell proliferation, metastasis, and BC-related pro-cesses, more luminal trans-factors are implicated in epithelialmesenchymal transition (EMT) and neoplasia of epithelial tissue (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Next, we applied our on-beads-LFQ scheme to analyze the ISE pull-downs from each corresponding PAM50 subtype from different sample origins (Table <ref type="table">S2</ref>).</s><s>Because the ratios of the ISE-captured proteins quantified by either LFQ or AACT were well correlated, we combined all cell line trans-factors quantified by both schemes.</s><s>As a result, we identified and quantified 722 and 881 proteins with ISE affinities from each sample origin (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref> and Tables <ref type="table">S1 and S2</ref>), including 125 spliceosome components <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Bessonov et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Jurica and Moore, 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Rappsilber et al., 2002)</ref> in the clinical specimens (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2A</ref> and Table <ref type="table">S3</ref>).</s><s>Based on the distribution of LFQ ratios of all proteins pulled down from different cell lines or tissue subtypes, with respect to either non-malignant MCF10A or healthy tissues, we identified two major clusters of proteins that exhibited either reciprocal ISE binding in the luminal versus basal PAM50 subtype.</s><s>These clusters included one luminal-specific trans-factor cluster showing increased ISE affinity specifically in the luminal subtype but decreased association in the basal subtype <ref type="bibr">(Figure 2B,</ref><ref type="bibr">left)</ref>, and another basal trans-factor cluster showing an opposite ISE-binding pattern (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>, right).</s><s>Combined results of LFQ cross-referencing analyses of similar PAM50 subtypes indicated that the ISE probes selectively enrich the PAM50-subtypic trans-interactome from any predominant subtype in a heterogeneous tissue, whose composition is consistently preserved with minimum sample-to-sample variability in either living homogeneous cells or frozen heterogeneous tissues.</s></p><p><s>For in-depth clinicopathological characterization, we found 236 trans-factors whose luminal-or basal-specific ISE affinities were best correlated across all sample origins (Pearson correlation coefficient at 0.67, R 2 at 0.45) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2B</ref>) with their functional categories (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2C</ref>) and their cross-sample ISE affinities (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>).</s><s>Specifically, in STRING protein interaction networks (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B and 2C</ref>), some known trans-factors all showed luminal-specific ISE affinities, including ESRP1 and ESRP2 along with known ESRP1/2-co-regulatory factors, and a series of the interactive sub-networks involving CTNND1 and a tight junction protein TJP3.</s><s>These findings indicated that ISE probes enrich networked trans-factors from PAM50 subtypes (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S3</ref>).</s><s>Because ESRP1/2 are the key nodes in the luminal trans-factor network, which regulates AS of epithelial and mesenchymal FGFR2 isoforms <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Warzecha et al., 2009a)</ref>, we compared the luminal versus basal splicing of FGFR2 and found the luminalenhanced ISE-binding of ESRP1/2 activates the expression of the luminal FGFR2 isomer in the luminal cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Hovhannisyan et al., 2006</ref>) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S3C</ref>), a result consistent with a previous  <ref type="table">Figures S2 and S3; Tables S1, S2, S3 and S4.</ref></s><s>TCGA samples  report <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Warzecha et al., 2009b)</ref>.</s><s>Accordingly, because ESRP1 positively regulates a CD44 isoform (CD44v) over another isomer CD44c <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Yae et al., 2012)</ref>, we also found that the CD44v/CD44c ratio was significantly higher in the luminal subtype, a finding that correlated with the higher luminal ISE binding of ESRP1 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S3D</ref>) and which indicated that ISE-bound ESRP1/2 promotes the luminal aberrant splicing of both FGFR2 and CD44.</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">ISE transfactors ALDOA ATIC CDK9 CPT1A CTNND1 DDX17 DDX23 ESRP1 ESRP2 FAM120A FASN FOXA1 H1FX HNRNPH1 HSPB1 ICT1 MRPL52 NUDT16L1 STRBP TJP3 CPSF6 CPSF7 CSDE1 DDX50 DHX36 FBL FIP1L1 FXR2 HNRNPH3 IFI16 KARS LSM6 LYAR NAP1L1 NCBP1 NCBP2 NOP56 PKP1 PLOD1 QKI RPL30 RPL5 SF3B2 SF3B3 SF3B4 SNRPA SNRPA1 SNRPB2 SNRPD1 SRPK1 SSB TSR1 VIM YBX1 mRNA expression 4 2 0 −2 −4</formula><p><s>Because of the established links of these luminal sub-networks to various EMT-dependent processes, our data further indicated that these trans-factors regulate EMT-associated AS events by luminal-specific binding to ISEs.</s></p><p><s>We also identified interactive sub-networks associated with RNA splicing, RNA metabolism, RNA processing, and protein synthesis over-represented by the basal-specific ISE trans-factors (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2E</ref>); this identification was coincident with an 11-protein BLBC/TNBC signature in which ribonucleoproteins are involved in the over-presenting pathways related to poor prognosis of TNBC patents <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Liu et al., 2014b)</ref>.</s><s>Specifically, YBX1, a component of the RNA splicing subnetwork, stabilizes oncogenic transcripts and mediates their enhanced expression for BC progression <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Goodarzi et al., 2015)</ref>.</s><s>SRPK1 was identified as a BC metastasis determinant <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(van Roosmalen et al., 2015)</ref>.</s><s>LYAR, a ribosome-associated protein, was characterized as a key regulator of the migration and invasion of human CRC cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Wu et al., 2015)</ref> and a regulator of translation associated with cell proliferation <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Yonezawa et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>Further, using some spliceosome components as subnetwork nodes, we identified the RNA metabolic subnetwork as another interactive pathway in the basal subtype.</s><s>Again, our data further illustrate the ISEassociated functions of these basal trans-factors.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Most trans-Factors Showed a PAM50-Subtypic Interaction-Correlated Expression Pattern</head><p><s>To determine the clinicopathological relevance of ISE-enriched trans-factors, we first examined patient-specific mRNA expression patterns of all trans-factor-encoding genes in the TCGA BC patient pool (n = 463); this pool contains a broad spectrum of PAM50-classified BLBC/TNBC, luminal-A and -B, Her2+, and normal-like BC subtypes.</s><s>We found that the ISE affinities of these trans-factors quantitatively correlated in a PAM50-subtypic manner across cell lines and clinical specimens (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2C  and 2E</ref>), although we selected some trans-factors that were identified only in cell lines because of their networking with ESRP1/2 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S3</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Hierarchical clustering analysis revealed that most trans-factor genes showed iCEPs in which their PAM50-subtypic ISE binding was positively correlated with mRNA overexpression of their encoding genes in the corresponding patient PAM50 subtypes (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3A</ref>), thereby identifying new additional genes that also describe the same PAM50 subtype.</s><s>Specifically, 28 of 34 BLBC/basal trans-factors showed highly statistically significant mRNA overexpression in most of the BLBC patients compared with luminal patients (p &lt; 0.001, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3B</ref>); 65 of 81 of the BLBC TCGA patients were also of the TNBC subtype.</s><s>Most luminal trans-factor genes showed higher mRNA levels over luminal-A and -B patients compared with those in BLBC patients.</s><s>Although the mRNA expression of a key luminal trans-factor ESRP1 showed little difference between luminal-A/-B and basal patients (p = 0.4, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3B</ref>), ESRP1 showed statistically significant mRNA overexpression in luminal-B patients (p &lt; 0.001, Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S4</ref>), indicating that the apparently less significant ESRP1 luminal-specific mRNA overexpression occurred because its luminal-B-specific expression was averaged over all luminal-A/-B patients.</s><s>Further, consistent with their PAM50subtypic mRNA overexpression, we found by immunoblotting that some trans-factor genes showed PAM50-subtypic iCEPs at the protein level (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>).</s><s>Notably, although ESRP1 mRNA or protein expression was also detected in basal-like cell lines or tissues, its ISE binding was luminal specific.</s><s>Conversely, ESRP2 showed luminal-specific protein expression and ISE binding.</s></p><p><s>Importantly, we observed patient-to-patient variations in mRNA expression of individual PAM50-subtypic genes with iCEP, i.e., not all basal or luminal iCEP genes were simultaneously overexpressed in each individual basal or luminal patient (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3A</ref>).</s><s>To assess a correlation between patient-specific mRNA expression alterations of iCEP genes and clinical outcome, we evaluated by KM survival analysis the prognostic significance of the PAM50-subtypic trans-factors having iCEPs; we used both a log rank p value and a hazard ratio (HR) with 95% confidence intervals to determine prognostic sensitivity and specificity.</s><s>In general, we found that most of the identified trans-factors, when showing a statistically significant PAM50subtypic altered mRNA expression, either individually or in combination, were indicative of the distinct clinical outcomes of specific BC patient subpopulations.</s><s>First, compared with all TCGA patients (n = 463), the statistically significant mRNA overexpression (Z score &gt; 1) of individual luminal trans-factors was correlated with poor prognosis of the distinct subsets of TCGA patients (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S4</ref>).</s><s>Further, in addition to their individual prognostic value in marking different subpopulations of luminal-B patients, the mRNA co-overexpression of differently combined luminal trans-factors (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S4</ref>) more specifically marked other small subpopulations of TCGA luminal-B patients.</s><s>Note that The expression values for the ISE trans-factor genes were obtained from the cBioPortal (mRNA expression Z scores compared with diploid tumors) for 463 TCGA BRCA patients.</s><s>(A) Heatmap for ISE trans-factor genes (rows) with mRNA expression from the TCGA sample set (columns).</s><s>These TCGA samples were clustered using unsupervised hierarchical clustering of their mRNA expression for the ISE trans-factor genes.</s><s>ISE trans-factor genes were grouped by their corresponding trans-factor subtype.</s><s>The distinct PAM50 subtypes and the ER, PR, and HER2 status is indicated for the TCGA samples.</s><s>(B) Box plots showing the statistically significant altered mRNA expression (x axis) for basal-like and luminal trans-factor genes.</s><s>Luminal trans-factor genes identified only in cell lines are indicated by *.</s><s>For each trans-factor gene, the distribution of mRNA expression for PAM50 basal-like patients is shown on the left in red, and for PAM50 luminal (luminal-A and luminal-B combined) patients on the right in blue.</s><s>Outliers are indicated as circles.</s><s>The median is indicated by the black bar inside each box.</s><s>The mRNA expression as a Z score is displayed on the y axis with values &gt;1 considered to be significantly upregulated and values &lt;À1 to be significantly downregulated; not altered = Z score between À1 and 1.</s><s>A Mann-Whitney-Wilcoxon test was performed on each pair to judge differences in expression levels, and the p value is displayed above the x axis.</s><s>p values &lt;0.05 are colored red if expression is higher for basal-like samples and blue if expression is higher for luminal samples.</s></p><p><s>CPT1A is a recently characterized driver of proliferation in luminal subtype BC <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Gatza et al., 2014)</ref> and a new BC drug target <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Pucci et al., 2016)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Co-overexpression of Networked BLBC trans-Factors Precisely Marks the Distinct Subsets of TNBC Patients with Worst Prognosis</head><p><s>Because TNBC is the most aggressive form of the disease, we searched for trans-factors that could mark subsets of TNBC patients with the worst prognosis.</s><s>Because most of the basal transfactors are involved in multiple interactive sub-networks (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>), we performed KM analysis on any combination of these trans-factor genes to correlate the clinical outcomes of the TCGA patients who simultaneously overexpressed select networked trans-factors.</s><s>A good prediction of poor survival was made for 23 of 81 (28%) BLBC patients who showed concurrent overexpression of SRPK1, YBX1, SNRPA1, and RPL30 (p = 0.03) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>).</s><s>In addition to the concurrent overexpression of these trans-factor genes, we observed more precise correlations with poor survival for the BLBC patients who also overexpressed a basal trans-factor, QK1 (p = 0.0066), or who showed downregulated mRNA for claudin-related luminal-trans-factor genes such as TJP3 (p = 0.0017) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>).</s><s>For the BLBC patients who showed co-overexpression of the foregoing spliceosome subnetwork, with no patient identified with co-overexpression of more than five trans-factors, we made a high-confidence prediction of poor prognosis for this small subpopulation (n = 7, p = 1.2 3 10 À5 ).</s><s>In addition, the worst survival with a significant 50% reduction in 20 survival months was precisely correlated with the patients who showed co-upregulation of these five trans-factor genes plus upregulated QKI (5% of all BLBC patients, p = 1.0 3 10 À7 ) or downregulated TJP3 (p = 2.4 3 10 À7 ) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Somatic CNVs Correlate with Distinct Clinical Outcomes of Patient Subsets</head><p><s>To clarify the molecular causes of the mRNA expression variations that correlated with diverse phenotypes, we investigated the effects of different types of genetic alterations on the PAM50-subtypic iCEPs.</s><s>We first looked at mutations in all trans-factor genes in TCGA patients.</s><s>Similar to previous observations for most BC-related genes (Cancer Genome Atlas Network, 2012), we found that the mutation frequency for most trans-factor genes was low, i.e., we detected only a few percent of BC patients carrying somatic mutations (Table <ref type="table">S5</ref>).</s><s>Indeed, the most frequently mutated trans-factor gene, the luminal trans-factor FOXA1, had a mutation frequency of only 1.7% of TCGA BC patients.</s><s>The other trans-factor genes had either no mutations or less than 1% mutations.</s><s>All of the mutations are unique, except for I176M in FOXA1 that was found in two TCGA patients.</s><s>In addition, few TCGA samples had more than one mutation in any transfactor gene.</s><s>Further, only one somatic mutation in FOXA1 in one out of all luminal patients was statistically correlated with altered FOXA1 mRNA expression (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S5</ref>).</s><s>Thus, genetic alterations other than somatic mutations likely contribute to the prognostic specificity of mRNA overexpression.</s></p><p><s>To detect other types of genetic alterations that contribute to tumor subtype identity, we used GISTIC to examine the BC subtype distribution of CNVs in the genes encoding various PAM50-subtypic trans-factors.</s><s>GISTIC identifies CNV-target, cancer-driving genes.</s><s>We compared the CNV correlation with the mRNA overexpression of individual trans-factor genes in either BLBC or various luminal patients.</s><s>First, using a Mann-Whitney-Wilcoxon test, we compared the mRNA expression distribution of trans-factor genes for the TCGA patients who carry CNVs with expression of the same trans-factor genes in diploid copy number (Table <ref type="table">S6</ref>).</s><s>As expected, in many cases, there were significant differences in the mRNA expression distribution when either copy-number gain (CNG) or copy-number loss (CNL) was compared with diploid copy number, with the mean mRNA expression lower for CNL compared with diploid and higher for CNG compared with diploid.</s></p><p><s>To further explore the impact of CNV on particular trans-factor mRNA expression, we examined percentages of TCGA samples that carried CNG, or CNL, or were diploid in each trans-factor gene.</s><s>Specifically, 16 of 34 basal trans-factors showed R10% CNGs that were correlated to mRNA overexpression with the mean value representing a Z score R 1 in the basal-like TCGA samples (p &lt; 0.05 for mRNA expression distribution when CNG was compared with diploid), whereas only six of these trans-factors showed similar correlations in the luminal samples.</s><s>Also, we found 7 of 20 luminal trans-factors with R10% CNGs that were correlated to mRNA overexpression with the mean value representing a Z score R 1 in the luminal TCGA samples, whereas only 3 of these trans-factors showed similar correlations in the BLBC patients (Table <ref type="table">S6</ref>).</s><s>For example, 26% of BLBC patients contained CNGs in the basal-trans-factor gene YBX1, a characterized driver of breast carcinogenesis <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Goodarzi et al., 2015)</ref>  Correlation between Kaplan-Meier survival plots of the clinicopathological outcomes and mRNA cooverexpression of indicated trans-factor genes.</s><s>N, number of TCGA patients; NE, number of events (overall survival status = deceased).</s><s>Each plot shows the log rank p value and hazard ratio (HR) with 95% confidence interval (CI) between the two groups.</s><s>The red line refers to the patient group(s) showing statistically significant alterations at the mRNA expression level (defined by Z score) for basal trans-factor(s).</s><s>The blue line indicates unaltered groups of TCGA patients not showing statistically significant alterations for mRNA expression in the basal subtype or not belonging to the subtype with or without significant alterations in mRNA expression.</s><s>See also Figures S4, S6, S7; Table <ref type="table">S7</ref>.</s><s><ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">6A and 6B</ref>).</s><s>In basal patients, increasing CNGs in YBX1 were well correlated with increasing YBX1 mRNA (p &lt; 0.002), whereas decreased YBX1 mRNA expression in luminal patients was correlated with CNLs of YBX1 (p &lt; 0.001; Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">6B</ref>).</s><s>In addition to the percentage of the TCGA patients associated with each type of CNA that was correlated with the averaged mRNA expression level (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">6C</ref>), we further identified the TCGA patient subpopulations with the CNV-driving mRNA alterations (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">6C</ref>), including basal patients with poor prognosis (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>).</s><s>For instance, 24% of basal-like TCGA patients showed mRNA overexpression associated with CNGs in YBX1, whereas 54% of the patients with a diploid copy number displayed mRNA overexpression (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">6C</ref>).</s><s>Similarly, other basal trans-factor genes, including SNRPA1 and SNRPD1, showed similar PAM50-subtypic CNG-overexpression patterns (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">6</ref>).</s><s>Conversely, many of the genes encoding luminal trans-factors, such as CDK9 <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Romano, 2013)</ref> and ESRP1, showed mRNA-overexpression-correlated CNGs in percentages similar to either luminal or basal patients (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S5</ref>).</s><s>Luminal trans-factors CPT1A and NUDT16L1 with CNGs showed luminal-specific mRNA overexpression.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>YBX1 (Figures</head><p><s>Because of the high-frequency CNVs in BC-subtypic transfactor genes, we further evaluated the impact of CNVs on the prognostic significance of either basal or luminal trans-factors.</s><s>In the statistically significantly, KM-correlated, gene-specific CNVs (p &lt; 0.05), the patients with diploid trans-factor genes generally showed better survival than those carrying CNVs.</s><s>(A) A series of three box plots is displayed for networked, basal-like/TNBC trans-factors YBX1, SNRPA1, SNRPD1 for basal-like/TNBC TCGA patients.</s><s>Box plots comparing CNAs (CN loss = GISTIC values of À1 or À2, diploid = GISTIC value of 0, CN gain = GISTIC value of 1 or 2) on the x axis with mRNA expression (Z score) on the y axis for the TCGA samples with indicated BC subtype.</s><s>The percentages of TCGA patients for different CNA types are indicated.</s><s>A Mann-Whitney-Wilcoxon test was performed to judge differences in expression levels between CNL and diploid (p value listed under loss) and between CNG and diploid (p value listed under gain).</s><s>x axis labels for loss are colored blue where the Mann-Whitney-Wilcoxon test p value is less than 0.05 and the average mRNA expression is less for loss compared with diploid.</s><s>x axis labels for gain are colored red where the Mann-Whitney-Wilcoxon test p value is less than 0.05 and the average mRNA expression is greater for gain compared with diploid.</s><s>Data points for each TCGA sample are indicated as circles, with solid circles representing TCGA patients with an overall survival status of deceased.</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_1">(n=0) (n=1) (n=0) (n=0) (n=43) (n=15) (n=0) (n=0) (n=19) (n=2) (n=0) (n=0)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">(n=4) (n=20) (n=35) (n=5) (n=65) (n=126) (n=46) (n=6) (n=7) (n=2) (n=0) (n=11) (n=76) (n=148)<label>(</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">(n=6) (n=6) (n=3) (n=1) (n=26) (n=14) (n=2) (n=0) (n=21) (n=1) (n=0) (n=0)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">(n=9) (n=19) (n=23) (n=20) (n=53) (n=112) (n=47) (n=17) (n=8) (n=4) (n=3) (n=38) (n=70) (n=135)<label>(</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_5">(n=8) (n=19) (n=21) (n=24) (n=53) (n=110) (n=48) (n=15) (n=11) (n=4) (n=1) (n=41) (n=72) (n=133)<label>(</label></formula><p><s>(legend continued on next page) than those with CNVs (p 0.017-0.025),</s><s>whereas CNLs in SNRPB2 and CNGs in CPSF6 were associated with poor survival (n = 35, 98, p 0.003-0.025)</s><s>(Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">S6</ref>).</s><s>Although the CNVs of a few trans-factor genes showed linear correlations with both mRNA expression and KM survival, from the distributions of trans-factors in the context of percentage of TCGA samples, statistically significant mRNA expression changes, CNVs, and PAM50 subtype, different patient subsets could be identified in which overexpression of some basal trans-factors was associated with either CNGs, or diploid, or even CNLs (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">6</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Co-overexpression of BLBC-Subtypic trans-Factors with iCEP Contributes to BC Invasiveness</head><p><s>To validate the clinicopathological relevance of the BLBC/ TNBC trans-factors described above (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>), we investigated in vitro their individual and combined roles in cell proliferation and migration/invasion.</s><s>First, CRISPR/Cas9-mediated knockdown <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Sanjana et al., 2014)</ref> of SNRPB2, SNRPD1, SF3B4, and LYAR caused decreases in both the proliferation and the invasive potential of the BLBC MDA231 cells (Figures <ref type="figure">7A and 7B</ref>).</s><s>Further, we clarified the networked roles of these trans-factors in determining the BLBC subtype by transfecting into non-invasive MCF7 cells each individual or combinations of FLAGtagged versions of SRPK1, QK1, SNRPD1, SNRPB2, SNRPA1, and LSM6.</s><s>Accordingly, as indicated by the decreased expression of E-cadherin, which is a hallmark of EMT, compared with its endogenous level in the luminal MCF7 cells, we found reduced E-cadherin expression in the MCF7 cells transfected with multiple basal trans-factor genes (Figure <ref type="figure">7C</ref>).</s><s>Similarly, wound-healing assays performed under the same conditions showed that co-overexpression of multiple trans-factors in combinations in non-invasive MCF7 cells more efficiently promoted the migration of co-transfected cells compared with MCF7 cells transfected with single trans-factor genes (Figure <ref type="figure">7D</ref>).</s><s>Thus, co-overexpression of these networked trans-factors significantly increased the migration/invasive potential of non-invasive MCF7 cells, which acquired the behavior of BLBC/TNBC.</s><s>In agreement with the observation that overexpression of individual basal trans-factors in sub-networks was of less prognostic significance in most of the basal patients (p &gt; 0.1) (Figure <ref type="figure">S7</ref>), overexpression of single trans-factors had little effect on the non-invasive potential of MCF7 cells, clearly due to the interdependent nature of these networked trans-factors (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>).</s></p><p><s>In summary, the results here demonstrate that the interconnectivity of the BLBC trans-factors in defined pathways/sub-networks drives the aggressiveness or metastatic splicing switches of BLBC/TNBC, and this interconnectivity, therefore, predicts the distinct subsets of TNBC patients with poor prognosis.</s><s>Specifically in clinical practice, these networked trans-factors together can serve as ''systematic prognostic signatures'' to precisely discriminate the subsets of basal-like patients having the poorest survival.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>Our advance in dissecting inter-patient tumor-phenotypic heterogeneity was made possible by the front-end enrichment of ISE-affinity trans-interactomes from single, predominant tumor phenotypes in heterogeneous tissues.</s><s>This ISE-affinity enrichment eliminated the need for either animal-or LCM-based sorting of homogeneous phenotypic populations.</s><s>In addition, this AS activity-based enrichment scheme is readily applicable to any frozen, archived tumor sample, from which it is possible to directly sort, in the context of an oncogenically active, phenotypically assembled ISE trans-interactomes, a tumor-phenotypic subpopulation with distinct clinical outcome.</s><s>Thus, our new ISE-affinity quantitative proteomic approach effectively translates nano-LC-MS/MS technology into routine clinical practice for tumor-phenotypic biomarker discovery and disease evaluation.</s></p><p><s>The on-beads ISE-affinity platform is simple, robust, and biospecimen compatible for concurrent nano-LC-MS/MS analysis in routine clinical practice.</s><s>The tight association between biotin and NeutrAvidin beads minimizes sample consumption and enables repetitive washing to remove non-specific proteins and MS-incompatible contaminants, e.g., detergents and salts; likewise, the neutral pI of NeutrAvidin minimizes non-specific adsorption.</s><s>Retained proteins are immediately subjected to reduction, alkylation, and on-bead tryptic digestion.</s><s>Further, because tryptic digests of large antibodies (&gt;150 kDa) may suppress the peptide signals from low-abundance proteins, the smaller NeutrAvidin (60 kDa) is particularly suitable for on-bead digestion.</s><s>By cross-referencing data from different sample processing steps (on-beads or on-gel), and using different quantitative schemes (LFQ or AACT) or different MS instruments (Velos-LTQ or Q-exactive), we demonstrated the high specificity and high reproducibility of ISE probes in enriching oncogenically active trans-factors.</s><s>The ISE affinities of trans-factors were quantitatively correlated or conserved in similar pathological phenotypes across different sample types, from homogeneous cell lines to heterogeneous tumor tissues.</s><s>Thus, we have bridged the phenotypic data gaps between cell lines and clinical specimens.</s></p><p><s>For most trans-factors that showed PAM50-subtypic ISE associations, we discovered a statistically significant, PAM50subtypic iCEP in TCGA BC patients.</s><s>Thus, these trans-factor genes are fully translated into oncogenically active proteins in a PAM50 subtype-specific manner, unlike other genes that exhibit discrepancies between mRNA and protein levels.</s><s>Further, individual or networked PAM50-subtypic trans-factors with iCEP, when detected as overexpressed or co-overexpressed in distinct patient subpopulations within either luminal or basal subtype, had high significance in precisely predicting patient prognosis or risk of metastasis (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">5 and 6</ref>).</s><s>Notably, although each of these patient subpopulations was previously diagnosed at mixed pathological grades spread over stages I-III (Table <ref type="table">S7 and Figure</ref>  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">5</ref>), overexpression or (B) Similar plots to (A), but for luminal TCGA patients.</s><s>(C) Summary of percentages represented as bars for basal-like and luminal TCGA samples for mRNA expression versus CNA subgroups for indicated trans-factor genes.</s><s>The percentages of TCGA patients (larger font) and count (smaller font) are listed below the percentage bar under each subgroup.</s><s>See also Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S5</ref>; Tables <ref type="table">S5 and S6</ref>.</s><s>co-overexpression of particular luminal or basal trans-factor(s) constitutes new prognostic markers that discriminate patient subpopulations with different clinical outcomes distinct from other patients within the same PAM50 subtype.</s><s>Specifically, in the distinct subpopulations of BLBC patients, co-overexpression of multiple BLBC trans-factors involved in particular sub-networks showed strong correlations with patient subpopulations having the poorest prognoses.</s><s>These correlations were supported by our functional characterization data; CRISPR/ Cas9-mediated knockdown of selected splicing factors in the networks caused reductions in proliferation of the BLBC cells.</s><s>In addition, co-overexpression of these networked trans-factors significantly increased the aggressiveness of MCF7 cells and converted their luminal nature to basal, whereas only a small effect was observed for overexpression of single factors (Figure <ref type="figure">7B</ref>).</s><s>Thus, these iCEP trans-factors in particular networks together define patient-specific tumor phenotypes.</s><s>In addition, our findings provide pathologically relevant clues for mechanistic investigations of these trans-factors using animal models (to be reported elsewhere).</s></p><p><s>Because mRNA expression patterns of known PAM50 genes are insufficient to distinguish the patient subsets of a PAM50 subtype with different prognoses, our establishment of PAM50-subtype iCEPs in trans-factor-encoding genes led to identification of new PAM50 genes.</s><s>Further, patient-specific mRNA expression variations of select iCEP genes correlated with the inter-patient tumor-phenotypic heterogeneity within the same PAM50-subtypic patients, and the mRNA expression variations marked the distinct patient subsets having particular prognoses.</s><s>Thus, our ISE-affinity proteogenomic method dissects the BC-phenotypic inter-patient heterogeneity that is far more precise than might be predicted from the available genetic or transcriptomic biomarkers.</s></p><p><s>Mechanistically, consistent with the fact that ribosomal protein genes are frequently amplified across 16 cancer types <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Reschke et al., 2013)</ref>, we further revealed that BC-subtypic trans-factor genes have incurred primarily somatic CNVs and not mutations; these CNVs drive BC-subtypic aberrant AS, and, in turn, patient variations in the TCGA mRNA expression profiles.</s></p><p><s>In summary, our ISE-affinity quantitative proteogenomic methodology identified oncogenically active trans-factors bearing patient-specific genomic/transcriptomic alterations that correlated with specific prognoses of distinct patient subsets within a single PAM50 subtype, demonstrating the clinicopathological sensitivity and patient specificity of our discovered markers.</s><s>Specifically, this oncogenically active, tumor-phenotypic biomarker reservoir contains personalized, clinical-risk predictors to precisely identify distinct subpopulations of patients who may develop metastatic or invasive breast tumors.</s><s>Quantitative mRNA expression assays of our identified trans-factor genes may aid early diagnosis and clinical decision making.</s><s>In addition, some trans-factor proteins may be druggable or therapeutic targets, establishing foundations for personalized medicine.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SIGNIFICANCE</head><p><s>All tumors are heterogeneous, with differences between patients in rates of tumor growth, metastasis, and postopera-tive recurrence.</s><s>This inter-patient tumor-phenotypic heterogeneity hinders discovery of biomarkers for individualized prognosis.</s><s>In breast cancer (BC) patients, five different BC subtypes (PAM50 subtypes) are classified by 50 gene expression (GE) patterns that, however, are insufficient to discriminate, within single PAM50 subtypes, individual patients with different clinical outcomes.</s><s>This limitation exists because cancer gene/protein expression profiling is usually performed on heterogeneous tissues in which is buried (inaccessible) information about tumor aggressiveness.</s><s>Bypassing clinically incompatible sampling steps, we introduce a robust, clinically practical, activity-based proteogenomic method that identifies, in their oncogenically active states, genes bearing patient-specific GE or copy-number alterations (CNAs) of prognostic significance.</s><s>First, we used RNA probes containing intronic splicing enhancers (ISEs) to sort in situ ISE-interacting trans-acting protein factors (trans-interactomes) directly from a heterogeneous tumor for subsequent mass spectrometry (MS) characterization.</s><s>In a retrospective, proteogenomic analysis of a TCGA patient dataset, we identified ISE trans-factor-encoding genes that showed PAM50-subtypic interaction-correlated expression patterns (iCEPs) as additional genes that describe distinct PAM50 subtypes.</s><s>Further, we resolved inter-patient heterogeneity from the proteogenomic findings of patient-specific co-alterations in mRNA expression of select iCEP genes, distinguishing high-risk patient subsets/subpopulations from other patients within a single PAM50 subtype.</s><s>In vivo cell-based function assays further confirmed that a tumor-phenotypic trans-interactome contained the drivers of oncogenic splicing switches, representing the predominant tumor cell type in a tissue.</s><s>Thus, ISE-affinity sorting of distinct BC phenotypes into homogeneous populations translates MS-based proteomics into routine clinical practice, from which novel personalized biomarkers were characterized/validated for precise prognostic prediction and subsequent personalized alignment of optimal therapy.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>STAR+METHODS CONTACT FOR REAGENT AND RESOURCE SHARING</head><p><s>Further information and requests for resources and reagents should be directed to, and will be fulfilled by, the Lead Contact, Xian Chen (xianc@email.unc.edu).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPERIMENTAL MODEL AND SUBJECT DETAILS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bacterial Strains</head><p><s>For plasmid propagation, DH5a and stbl3 electro-competent bacterial cells were used and cultured in LB media (plus ampicillin at 50 mg/ml for selection) at 37 C with shaking.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cell Lines</head><p><s>The human embryonic kidney cell line 293T (Female), MCF10A(female), MCF7(female), and MDA-MB-231(female) cells were cultured in DMEM medium (Gibco), whereas T47D(female) was maintained in RPMI 1640 medium (Gibco), all supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (Gibco), 1% penicillin, and streptomycin.</s><s>For AACT experiments, MCF10A or MDA-MB-231 cells were cultured in DMEM medium containing stable isotope-enriched 13 C6 14 N2-Lysine/ 13 C6 14 N4-arginine (Heavy) (Cambridge Isotope Laboratories), whereas T47D cells were cultured in the RPMI 1640 medium containing 13 C6-Lysine/ 13 C6-arginine (Medium) supplemented with 10% dialyzed fetal bovine serum (Thermo Fisher), 1% penicillin, and streptomycin for 7 passages and tested for full incorporation before proteomic analysis.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHOD DETAILS</head><p><s>Immunoblotting and Antibodies All primary antibodies were incubated overnight at 4 C. Antibodies included Espr1 (Thermo Fisher, PA5-25833), Esrp2 (Thermo Fisher, PA5-32143), ZO3/TJP3 (Thermo Fisher, 36-4100), g-Tubulin (abcam, ab11316), Flag (Sigma,F1804), E-cadherin (Cell Signaling,5296), SRSF1 (Santa Cruz, sc-73026), Hnrnpf (Santa Cruz, sc-32309), Hnrnph2 (Abgent, AP13497b), QKI (Bethyl, A300-183A), SNRPA1 (Proteintech, 17368-1-AP), DDX50 (Proteintech, 10358-1-AP), SF3B4 (Proteintech, 10482-1-AP), SSB (Proteintech, 11720-1-AP), SNRPB2 (Proteintech, 13512-1-AP), SRPK1 (Proteintech, 14073-1-AP), KARS (Proteintech, 14951-1-AP), TSR1 (Proteintech, 16887-1-AP), RPL30 (Proteintech, 17403-1-AP), LYAR (Proteintech, 24433-1-AP).</s><s>All secondary antibodies were used at 1:10,000 for 1 h at room temperature (Cell Signaling, 7074V and 7076V).</s><s>Blots were washed three times for 5 minutes with TBS-T after primary and secondary antibodies and developed with a chemiluminescent HRP antibody detection reagent (Denville Scientific, E2400).</s><s>Images were collected by ChemiDoc TM MP imaging system (BioRad).</s></p><p><s>Protein Extraction from Cells, Clinical Tissues Cells in a 10 cm tissue culture plate were harvested and pelleted when the confluency reached over 90%.</s><s>Each pellet of $10 million cells was re-suspended in 0.75 ml buffer containing 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, protease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma-Aldrich), and 0.5 mM PMSF.</s><s>A 2 X lysis buffer containing 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 15 mM NaN 3 , 1% CA630, protease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma-Aldrich), and 0.5 mM PMSF was added and mixed thoroughly in a 1.5 ml centrifuge tube.</s><s>Total cell lysate was obtained following a centrifugation for 20 min at 12,000 x g, and protein concentration was determined by BCA assay.</s><s>Each frozen human tissue ($0.2 g) from UNC Tissue Procurement Facility was cut into small pieces, 1 ml homogenization buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 15 mM NaN 3 , 0.5%CA630, protease inhibitor cocktail, 0.5 mM PMSF) was added, and the solution was dounced until homogeneous.</s><s>Samples were centrifuged twice for 20 min at 4 C at 12,000 x g; the supernatants contained 2 -10 mg total protein (determined by BCA assay).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ISE Pull-downs</head><p><s>One mg protein extracted from either cell lines or clinical tissues was incubated with 10 ml biotinylated non-ISE RNA or ISE probes (0.75 mM) at 4 C for 2 h or overnight.</s><s>Fifty ml NeutrAvidin-agarose (Thermo-Fisher) was then added for an additional 2 h at 4 C, and washed 3 times with 1 ml lysis buffer to remove non-specific proteins.</s><s>For a gel-based approach, the RNA/ISE-bound proteins were eluted, heated for 5 min at 95 C in 40 ml 2 X SDS loading buffer, separated by SDS PAGE for in-gel trypsin digestion, and desalted with a C18 stage tip.</s><s>The peptide elutes were subjected to nanoLC-MS/MS.</s><s>For on-beads sampling and processing, in addition to three washings with lysis buffer, a washing buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl) was used five times to remove residual detergents.</s><s>On-beads tryptic digestion was performed with 125 ml buffer containing 2 M urea, 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 1 mM DTT, 600 ng trypsin (Promega) for 30 min at room temperature on a mixer (Eppendorf).</s><s>The tryptic digests were eluted twice with a 100 ml buffer containing 2 M urea, 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 5 mM iodoacetamide.</s><s>Combined elutions were acidified with 5 ml trifluoroacetic acid (TFA, MS grade, Thermo-Fisher) and desalted by C18 stage tip.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LC-MS/MS Analysis</head><p><s>Desalted peptide mixtures were dissolved in 30 ml 0.1% formic acid (Thermo-Fisher), of which 4 ml containing the peptides from 60-100 mg total protein was injected and analyzed by a ultra2D nanoLC system (Eksigent) coupled to a Velos LTQ Orbitrap mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, San Jose, CA) or an Easy nanoLC 1000 coupled to a Q-Exactive Orbitrap mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, San Jose, CA).</s><s>In the nanoLC-Velos setup, peptides were first loaded on to a 2 mm 3 0.5 mm reverse-phase (RP) C18 trap column (Eksigent) at a flow rate of 1 ml/min, then eluted and fractionated on a 25 cm C18 RP column (360 mm 3 75 mm 3 3 mm) with a gradient of 5-40% buffer B (ACN and 0.1% formic acid) at a constant flow rate of 250 nl/min over 180 min.</s><s>In the Easy nanoLC-Q Exactive setup, peptides were loaded on to a 15 cm C18 RP column (280 mm 3 75 mm 3 2 mm, Acclaim Pepmap RSLC, Thermo-Fisher) and eluted with a gradient of 1-30% buffer B at a constant flow rate of 300 nl/min for 110 min.</s><s>The Velos LTQ Orbitrap was operated in the positive-ion mode with a data-dependent automatic switch between survey Full-MS scan (m/z 300-1800) (externally calibrated to a mass accuracy of &lt;5 ppm and a resolution of 60,000 at m/z 400) and CID MS/MS acquisition of the top 15 most intense ions.</s><s>The Q-Exactive was also operated in the positive-ion mode but using a data-dependent top 20 method.</s><s>Survey scans were acquired at a resolution of 70,000 at m/z 400.</s><s>Up to the top 20 most abundant isotope patterns with charge R 2 from the survey scan were selected with an isolation window of 3 m/z and fragmented by HCD with normalized collision energies of 28.</s><s>The maximum ion injection times for the survey scan and the MS/MS scans were 250 ms and 120 ms, respectively, and the ion target values were set to 1e6 and 2e5, respectively.</s><s>Selected sequenced ions were dynamically excluded for 20 seconds.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CRISPR/Cas9 Construction and Transfection</head><p><s>For the CRISPR/Cas9 constructs, oligonucleotides for the sgRNAs of SNRPB2, SNRPD1, SF3B4, and LYAR, as described below, were annealed and cloned in BsmBI-digested lentiCRISPRv2(Addgene plasmid #52961) <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Sanjana et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>The empty vector was used as a negative control.</s><s>Viral production was performed with a standard protocol.</s><s>In brief, a total of 10 mg of plasmids, including target plasmid, pMD2.G (Addgene plasmid #12259) and psPAX2 (Addgene plasmid #12260) with a ratio of 10:5:9, was co-transfected into 293T cells with jetPRIME TM .</s><s>Virus-containing media were collected 48 hours after transfection.</s><s>MDA-MB-231 cells at 60-80% confluency were incubated with the virus containing media for 24-48 hours, and then subjected to 1.0 mg/mL puromycin selection.</s><s>After 4-7 days puromycin selection, the stably transfected cells were collected for further analysis.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cell Proliferation Assay</head><p><s>Cell proliferation was assessed by the Cell Counting kit-8 (CCK-8; Dojin, Tokyo, Japan).</s><s>Briefly, MDA-MB-231 cells stably transfected with empty vector or target gene CRISPR vectors were seeded at a density of 1310 3 /well in 96-well culture plates at 37 C for 4 days, and every 24 h each well was incubated with 10 ml of Cell Counting kit-8 solution for 3 h at 37 C.</s><s>The absorbance at 450 nm was measured with a spectrophotometer.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cell Invasion Assay</head><p><s>MDA-MB-231 cells (1310 5 cells/Transwell) were plated in triplicate in the top chamber of Transwells (Corning 354480) with a Matrigel (2 mg/ml)-coated membrane containing 8-mm diameter pores in 500 ml serum-free DMEM.</s><s>Medium containing 2% FBS was added to the lower chamber.</s><s>After 22 h at 37 C, cells remaining on the upper membrane surface were removed by cotton swab scrubbing; cells on the lower surface of the membrane were fixed in methanol and acetic acid (3:1, v/v) at room temperature for 10 min and stained for 5 min with 1.25 g/L Thiazine dye mixture in Diff-Quik TM stain set (SIEMENS: B4132-1A).</s><s>The excess dye was washed away with ddH 2 O.</s><s>After drying, the stained cells were observed in a light microscope at 40 3 objective.</s><s>The cell number in five random fields was counted for each chamber.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Constructs and Transfection</head><p><s>The human ORF clones (v5.1) of LSM6, SNRPA1, SNRPB2, SNRPD1, QKI, and SRPK1 were purchased from Open Biosystems; the full-lengths of the genes were amplified by indicated primers and cloned into pcDNA 4.1 vector (Invitrogen) with a FLAG tag at their N-termini.</s><s>MCF7 cells were seeded in 6-well plates for 24 h before transfection, and the constructs were transfected or co-transfected into MCF7 cells using reagent jetPRIME (Polyplus).</s><s>After 24 h, the cells were lysed directly in the plates by adding SDS-PAGE sample buffer, heating at 95 C for 5 min, and sonicating for 5 seconds to clear the lysate for immunoblotting.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Wound Healing Assay</head><p><s>Twenty-four hours after MCF7 cells were transfected with constructs in 12 wells plate, the cell monolayers were gently scratched with a new 1 ml pipette tip across the center of the well, then scratched with another straight line perpendicular to the first line to create a cross in each well.</s><s>After scratching, the cells were gently washed twice in the wells with medium to remove detached cells, and the wells were refilled with fresh medium.</s><s>Cells were allowed to grow another 48 h, then washed once with PBS, fixed in methanol and acetic acid (3:1, v/v) at room temperature for 10 min, and stained with 1.25 g/L Thiazine dye mixture in Diff-QuikTM stain set (SIEMENS:B4132-1A) for 5 min; excess dye was washed away with ddH 2 O.</s><s>The well were air dried for 10 min, then photographed in a light microscope.</s><s>Multiple views of each well were captured, and each condition was repeated twice.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>QUANTIFICATION AND STATISTICAL ANALYSIS</head><p><s>Mass Spec Data Analysis Mass spectral processing and peptide identification were performed on the Andromeda search engine in MaxQuant software (Version 1.5.2.8) against a human UniProt database.</s><s>All searches were conducted with a defined modification of cysteine carbamidomethylation, with methionine oxidation and protein amino-terminal acetylation as dynamic modifications.</s><s>Peptides were confidently identified using a target-decoy approach with a peptide false discovery rate (FDR) of 1% and a protein FDR of 5%.</s><s>A minimum peptide length of 7 amino acids was required, maximally two missed cleavages were allowed, initial mass deviation for precursor ion was up to 7 ppm, and the maximum allowed mass deviation for fragment ions was 0.5 Da.</s><s>For AACT/SILAC quantification, the multiplicity was set at 2 or 3 (2-plex K0R0, K8R10, 3-plex K0R0, K6R6, K8R10).</s><s>For LFQ analysis, a match between runs option was enabled and time window at 0.7 minutes.</s><s>Data processing and statistical analysis were performed on Perseus (Version 1.5.1.6)</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Cox and Mann, 2011)</ref>.</s><s>Protein quantitation was performed on biological replicate runs, and a two-sample t-test statistics was used with a p-value of 5% to report statistically significant expression fold-changes.</s><s>The AACT ratios of the proteins were derived from the comparison of the extracted ion chromatogram peak areas of all matched light (L) peptides with those of the medium (M) or heavy (H) peptides.</s><s>The ratios of M/L or H/L were also verified by visual inspection of the raw mass spectra.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Combined Intronic Splicing Enhancer (ISE)-Affinity Quantitative Proteomics and Clinicopathological Analysis to Identify Prognostic Predictors of Subsets of BC Patients (A) Schematic representation of sorting and characterizing phenotypic markers of prognostic significance from distinct BC PAM50 subtypes in the tumor microenvironment.</s><s>LFQ, label-free quantitation; iCEP, interaction-correlated expression pattern.</s><s>Shown is the tissue-compatible LFQ approach to compare BC subtype-specific ISE-affinity protein complexes captured from cell lines and human biospecimens to determine the compositional differences of the ISE-interacting trans-factors (ISE trans-interactome) in different BC subtypes.</s><s>(B) A heatmap of hierarchical clustering summarizes the relative ISE-binding strengths of the proteins captured from each indicated cell line (each with three biological replicates).</s><s>Indicated are the functional categories overpresented by the proteins showing differential ISE affinities in different cell types.</s><s>See also Figure S1.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,91.96,101.59,412.53,541.87" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2.</s><s>With Minimum Sample-to-Sample Variability, RNA (ISE) Probes Selectively Enrich the BC PAM50-Subtypic ISE trans-Interactome from a Heterogeneous Tumor Tissue (A) Venn diagram (right) showing identified/quantified proteins in the ISE-associated complexes captured from different sample origins, and the ranked biological processes of the overlapping proteins identified in all sample origins (left).</s><s>(B) Volcano plot of the proteins identified in human specimens showing either BC basal-or luminal-specific ISE affinities correlated with the log2 LFQ ratios (basallike/luminal) normalized against the same proteins from adjacent non-malignant tissues.</s><s>The proteins showing log2 LFQ ratios &gt;1 or À1 and Àlog10 p value &gt;1 are putative BC-subtypic trans-factors of statistical significance.</s><s>(C) The over-represented biological processes of BC-subtypic trans-factors.</s><s>(D) The LFQ heatmap summarizes cross-sample variations in the BC-subtypic trans-factor affinities to ISEs.</s><s>(E) The interactive sub-networks of basal trans-factors.</s><s>See also Figures S2 and S3; TablesS1, S2, S3 and S4.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. PAM50-Subtypic ISE trans-Factors Show Statistically Significant iCEPs</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. Immunoblotting Shows the PAM50-Subtypic ISE-Binding of Some trans-Factors in Agreement with MS Identifications Immunoblotting analysis of PAM50-subtypic ISE-binding of some trans-factors in either cell lines (left and middle panel) or human tissues (right panel).</s><s>ISEs, intronic splicing enhancers; PD, pull-down; Lum, luminal subtype; Bas, basal subtype; N, normal cell lines or non-malignant adjacent tissue; T, tumor tissue.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. Patient-Specific mRNA Expression Alterations of ISE trans-Factor Genes Are of Prognostic Significance in Marking Distinct Patient Subsets within Single PAM50 Subtypes</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>YBX1</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>For example, patients with diploid basal trans-factors, such as SNRPB2 (n = 292) and CPSF6 (n = 339), had better survival Cell Chemical Biology 25, 619-633, May 17, 2018 627</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6.</s><s>Somatic CNAs Drive the BC-Subtypic, Patient-Specific mRNA Alterations of ISE trans-Factors and Correlate with the Survival of Distinct Patient Subsets</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="1,55.16,194.12,285.82,285.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>; only 1% showed CNLs.</s><s>In contrast, luminal patients showed a reciprocal copy-number alteration (CNA) distribution, i.e., 19% of luminal patients carried CNLs and only 5% had CNGs in</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">up = SRPK1,YBX1,SNRPA1,RPL30</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">up = SRPK1,YBX1,SNRPA1,RPL30,QKI</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>p value: 0.03</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">p value: 0.007</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.8</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">HR: 95% CI: 1.055 8.395 2.976</cell><cell>0.8</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">HR: 95% CI: 1.369 14.67 4.482</cell></row><row><cell>Overall Survival</cell><cell>0.4 0.6</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Overall Survival</cell><cell>0.4 0.6</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.0</cell><cell cols="3">altered in Basal (N=23, NE=4)</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.0</cell><cell cols="3">altered in Basal (N=11, NE=3)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">not altered in Basal or not Basal (N=440, NE=54)</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">not altered in Basal or not Basal (N=452, NE=55)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>150</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>150</cell><cell>200</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Months Survival</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Months Survival</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">up = SRPK1,YBX1,SNRPA1,RPL30</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">down = TJP3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">up = YBX1,SNRPA1,SF3B4,SNRPD1,LSM6</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>p value: 0.002</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">p value: 1.2e 05</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.8</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">HR: 95% CI: 1.604 12.755 4.523</cell><cell>0.8</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">HR: 95% CI: 2.732 30.321 9.102</cell></row><row><cell>Overall Survival</cell><cell>0.4 0.6</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Overall Survival</cell><cell>0.4 0.6</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.0</cell><cell cols="3">altered in Basal (N=16, NE=4)</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.0</cell><cell cols="3">altered in Basal (N=7, NE=3)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">not altered in Basal or not Basal (N=447, NE=54)</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">not altered in Basal or not Basal (N=456, NE=55)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>150</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>150</cell><cell>200</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Months Survival</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Months Survival</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">up = YBX1,SNRPA1,SF3B4,SNRPD1,LSM6</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">up = YBX1,SNRPA1,SF3B4,SNRPD1,LSM6,QKI</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">down = TJP3</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">p value: 1e 07</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">p value: 2.4e 07</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.8</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">HR: 95% CI: 3.779 41.807 12.569</cell><cell>0.8</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">HR: 95% CI: 3.599 39.89 11.981</cell></row><row><cell>Overall Survival</cell><cell>0.4 0.6</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Overall Survival</cell><cell>0.4 0.6</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0.0</cell><cell cols="3">altered in Basal (N=4, NE=3)</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.0</cell><cell cols="3">altered in Basal (N=5, NE=3)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">not altered in Basal or not Basal (N=459, NE=55)</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">not altered in Basal or not Basal (N=458, NE=55)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>150</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>150</cell><cell>200</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Months Survival</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Months Survival</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Cell ChemicalBiology 25, 619-633, May 17, 2018 621(legend on next page)</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">e3 Cell Chemical Biology 25, 619-633.e1-e5, May 17, 2018</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Cell ChemicalBiology 25, 619-633.e1-e5, May 17, 2018 e4</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">e5 Cell Chemical Biology 25, 619-633.e1-e5, May 17, 2018</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>(B) Representative image of stained cells that were infected with an empty vector (crtl) or CRISPR/Cas9 construct targeting either SNRPB2, SF3B4, SNRPD1, or LYAR.</s><s>*p &lt; 0.01.</s><s>(C) Expression of the epithelial marker E-cadherin was measured by immunoblotting of the MCF-7 cells overexpressing FLAG-tagged gene(s) either alone or in combination.</s><s>These human genes included LSM6, SNRPA1, SNRPB2, SNRPD1, QKI, and SPRK1.</s><s>(D) A wound-healing assay was performed 24 hr after transfection, and images representing two biological replicates were collected at day 0 and day 2. Data are presented as means ± SD. *p &lt; 0.01 as indicated in the graph.</s><s>See also Table <ref type="table">S8</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Detailed methods are provided in the online version of this paper and include the following:</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</head><p><s>L.W. performed sample preparation and processing of some cell lines and clinical tissues for MS/MS experimental analysis, analyzed data, and performed functional characterization of trans-factors.</s><s>J.A.W. developed the software and performed KM analysis of clinical TCGA data and proteogenomic analysis.</s><s>L.X. prepared samples and performed some LFQ MS/MS analysis, and H.P.G. and Y.P. performed AACT proteomic analysis of cell lines.</s><s>D.X.L. created CRISPR/Cas9 knockdowns of trans-factor genes and performed cell proliferation assays.</s><s>G.Z. and Q.Z.</s><s>assisted with in vivo cell-based function assays.</s><s>H.S. and P.Y. assisted in some immunoblotting experiments.</s><s>Z.W. provided the first set of ISE probes.</s><s>X.C. conceived and designed the project and experiments, analyzed and interpreted data, and wrote the manuscript.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DECLARATION OF INTERESTS</head><p><s>The authors declare no competing financial interests.</s><s>Analysis of Functional Category and Networks Similar to our earlier report <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Liu et al., 2014a)</ref>, the biological processes and molecular functions of the ISE-interacting proteins were categorized by IPA (http://www.ingenuity.com/),</s><s>DAVID (http://david.abcc.ncifcrf.gov/)</s><s>and STRING (http://string-db.org/).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TCGA Data Analysis</head><p><s>All TCGA data used in our study were retrieved from cBioPortal <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Cerami et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Gao et al., 2013)</ref> using the 'cgdsr' R package (version 1.2.5) <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Jacobsen, 2015)</ref>.</s><s>We used complete samples (case list id = brca_tcga_pub_complete) with mutation, copy-number, and mRNA expression data provided (n = 463) from cancer study brca_tcga_pub (Breast Invasive Carcinoma (TCGA, Nature 2012)).</s></p><p><s>The mRNA expression data sets for ISE interactor genes were obtained from TCGA Genetic Profile: brca_tcga_pub_mrna_merged_ median_Zscores, containing mRNA expression Z-scores compared with diploid tumors (diploid for each gene).</s><s>The copy-number data sets for ISE trans-factor genes were obtained from TCGA Gene Profiles: brca_tcga_pub_gistic for putative copy-number from GISTIC 2.0 for each gene.</s><s>Clinical data were obtained from TCGA case list id: brca_tcga_pub_complete, which included information on patient survival, PAM50 subtype <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Parker et al., 2009)</ref>, estrogen receptor (ER) status, progesterone receptor (PR) status, and HER2 enrichment (HER2) status.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Heatmap Construction</head><p><s>The heatmap of mRNA expression levels for ISE-interacting trans-factor genes from the TCGA BRCA dataset was constructed using the 'ComplexHeatmap' R package (version 1.6.0)</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Gu et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>Hierarchical clustering was performed using the euclidean distance method and complete linkage was applied.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Analyses</head><p><s>Kaplan-Meier curve plotting and statistical analysis for differences of overall survival based on mRNA expression of ISE-interactor genes among TCGA BRCA samples were performed using the 'survival' R package (2.38.3) (Terry M. Therneau and Patricia M. <ref type="bibr">Grambsch (2000)</ref>.</s><s>Modeling Survival Data: Extending the Cox Model.</s><s>Springer, New York.</s><s>ISBN 0-387-98784-3).</s><s>Kaplan-Meier estimator and log-rank tests were performed using the survival functions Surv, survfit, and survdiff.</s><s>Cox proportional hazard survival analysis was performed using the survival function coxph.</s><s>Mann-Whitney-Wilcoxon Test was performed using the wilcox.test</s><s>function in R.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DATA AND SOFTWARE AVAILABILITY</head><p><s>The mass spectrometry proteomics data have been deposited to the ProteomeXchange Consortium via the PRIDE partner repository with the dataset identifier PXD008642.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isolation of an active step I spliceosome and composition of its RNP core</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bessonov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Anokhina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Will</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Urlaub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Luhrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">452</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="846" to="850" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comprehensive molecular portraits of human breast tumours</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Genome Atlas Network</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">490</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Nature</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">70-Gene signature as an aid to treatment decisions in early-stage breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cardoso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Veer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bogaerts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Slaets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Viale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Delaloge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Pierga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Brain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Causeret</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Delorenzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N. Engl. J. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">375</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="717" to="729" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular analysis of circulating tumor cells identifies distinct copynumber profiles in patients with chemosensitive and chemorefractory smallcell lung cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Carter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Rothwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mesquita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Smowton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Leong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fernandez-Gutierrez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Burt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Antonello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Morrow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="114" to="119" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The cBio cancer genomics portal: an open platform for exploring multidimensional cancer genomics data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cerami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Dogrusoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Gross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Sumer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aksoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jacobsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Byrne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Heuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Larsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Discov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="404" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Site-specific mass tagging with stable isotopes in proteins for accurate and efficient protein identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bradbury</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anal. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1134" to="1143" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative, high-resolution proteomics for data-driven systems biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="299" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genome remodelling in a basal-like breast cancer metastasis and xenograft</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ellis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Larson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wallis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mclellan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Fulton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fulton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">464</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="999" to="1005" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrative analysis of complex cancer genomics and clinical profiles using the cBioPortal</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Aksoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Dogrusoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dresdner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Sumer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jacobsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sinha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Larsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Signal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An integrated genomics approach identifies drivers of proliferation in luminal-subtype human breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gatza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Parker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Perou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1051" to="1059" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Endogenous tRNA-Derived fragments suppress breast cancer progression via YBX1 displacement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Goodarzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Fish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Tavazoie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">161</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="790" to="802" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Complex heatmaps reveal patterns and correlations in multidimensional genomic data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Eils</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schlesner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2847" to="2849" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamic protein-protein interaction wiring of the human spliceosome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hegele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kamburov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Grossmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Sourlis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wowro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Weimann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Will</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Pena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Luhrmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Stelzl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="567" to="580" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterization of sequences and mechanisms through which ISE/ISS-3 regulates FGFR2 splicing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hovhannisyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Warzecha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Carstens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="373" to="385" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic and integrative analysis of large gene lists using DAVID bioinformatics resources</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Sherman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lempicki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">cgdsr: R-Based API for Accessing the MSKCC Cancer Genomics Data Server (CGDS). R package version 1.2.5</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jacobsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://github.com/cBioPortal/cgdsr" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pre-mRNA splicing: awash in a sea of proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jurica</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Breast tumor heterogeneity: source of fitness, hurdle for therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Koren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bentires-Alj</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="537" to="546" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intrinsic disorder in the human spliceosomal proteome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Korneta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bujnicki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Comput. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1002641</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A chromatin activity-based chemoproteomic approach reveals a transcriptional repressome for gene-specific silencing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wrobel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gunawardena</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5733</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014a</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparative proteome analysis revealing an 11-protein signature for aggressive triple-negative breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Stingl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Look</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Smid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Braakman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>De Marchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sieuwerts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Span</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sweep</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Linderholm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Natl. Cancer Inst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">376</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014b</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A 17-gene stemness score for rapid determination of risk in acute leukaemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcleod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ibrahimova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Arruda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Popescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Gupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Schimmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">540</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="433" to="437" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterizing the impact of 25 years of DCIS treatment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ozanne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bouzan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Esserman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Breast Cancer Res. Treat</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Supervised risk predictor of breast cancer based on intrinsic subtypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Parker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mullins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cheang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Leung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Voduc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Vickery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fauron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clin. Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1160" to="1167" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Carnitine palmitoyl transferase-1A (CPT1A): a new tumor specific target in human breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Zonetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fisco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Polidoro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bocchinfuso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Palleschi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Novelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Spagnoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mazzarelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncotarget</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19982" to="19996" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Large-scale proteomic analysis of the human spliceosome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rappsilber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Ryder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Lamond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1231" to="1245" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterization and analysis of the composition and dynamics of the mammalian riboproteome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Reschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Clohessy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Seitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Breitkopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Schmolze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Ala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Asara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Beck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Pandolfi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1276" to="1287" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deregulations in the cyclin-dependent kinase-9-related pathway in cancer: implications for drug discovery and development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Romano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ISRN Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">305371</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tumor cell migration screen identifies SRPK1 as breast cancer metastasis determinant</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Van Roosmalen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Le Devedec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Golani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Smid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Pulyakhina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Timmermans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Look</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Pont</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>De Graauw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Clin. Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1648" to="1664" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improved vectors and genome-wide libraries for CRISPR screening</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Sanjana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Shalem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="783" to="784" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The spliceosomal proteome: at the heart of the largest cellular ribonucleoprotein machine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Valadkhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Jaladat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proteomics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4128" to="4141" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intronic splicing enhancers, cognate splicing factors and context-dependent regulation rules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wang</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1044" to="1052" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ESRP1 and ESRP2 are epithelial cell-type-specific regulators of FGFR2 splicing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Warzecha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Sato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Nabet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hogenesch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Carstens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="591" to="601" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009a</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The epithelial splicing factors ESRP1 and ESRP2 positively and negatively regulate diverse types of alternative splicing events</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Warzecha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Carstens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RNA Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="546" to="562" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009b</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LYAR promotes colorectal cancer cell mobility by activating galectin-1 expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ju</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncotarget</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32890" to="32901" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternative splicing of CD44 mRNA by ESRP1 enhances lung colonization of metastatic cancer cell</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tsuchihashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ishimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Motohara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yoshikawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Yoshida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Masuko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Mogushi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">883</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yonezawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sugihara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Oshima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Matsuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nadano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lyar, a cell growth-regulating zinc finger protein, was identified to be associated with cytoplasmic ribosomes in male germ and cancer cells</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">395</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="229" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Amino acid residue specific stable isotope labeling for quantitative proteomics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bradbury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rapid Commun. Mass Spectrom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2115" to="2123" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Chemical Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">633</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018-05-17">May 17. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
