<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Unitary Properties of AMPA Receptors with Reduced Desensitization</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wei</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<email>weizhang@hebmu.edu.cn</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institution of Chinese Integrative Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hebei Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Shijiazhuang, Hebei</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven, Connecticut</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Clarissa</forename><surname>Eibl</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Leibniz-Institut f€ ur Molekulare Pharmakologie and Cluster of Excellence</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">NeuroCure</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>Charit</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Humboldt Universit€ at zu Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Cellular Biophysics</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Autumn</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weeks</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven, Connecticut</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Irene</forename><surname>Riva</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Leibniz-Institut f€ ur Molekulare Pharmakologie and Cluster of Excellence</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">NeuroCure</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>Charit</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Humboldt Universit€ at zu Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Cellular Biophysics</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yan-Jun</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institution of Chinese Integrative Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hebei Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Shijiazhuang, Hebei</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Model Animal Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">State Key Laboratory of Pharmaceutical Biotechnology and MOE Key Laboratory of Model Animal for Disease Study</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nanjing University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nanjing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><forename type="middle">J R</forename><surname>Plested</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Leibniz-Institut f€ ur Molekulare Pharmakologie and Cluster of Excellence</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">NeuroCure</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>Charit</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Humboldt Universit€ at zu Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Cellular Biophysics</addrLine>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
							<email>james.howe@yale.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yale University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Haven, Connecticut</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Universit€ atsmedizin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Unitary Properties of AMPA Receptors with Reduced Desensitization</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">6DF5209F7F9CCE893C7AB79A0871B24C</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.bpj.2017.07.030</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted April 27, 2017, and accepted for publication July 25, 2017.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:31+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Wild-type AMPA receptors display a characteristic rapidly desensitizing phenotype.</s><s>Many studies point to the dimer interface between pairs of extracellular ligand binding domains as the key region controlling the rate at which the receptors desensitize.</s><s>However, mutations at the extracellular end of the pore-forming regions (near the putative ion channel gate) have also been shown to alter desensitization.</s><s>Here we report the behavior of single GluA4 receptors carrying one of two mutations that greatly reduce desensitization at the level of ensemble currents: the dimer interface mutation L484Y and the Lurcher mutation (A623T, GluA4-Lc) in the extracellular end of M3 (the second true transmembrane helix).</s><s>Analysis of unitary currents in patches with just one active receptor showed that each mutation greatly prolongs bursts of openings without prolonging the apparent duration of individual openings.</s><s>Each mutation decreases the frequency with which individual receptors visit desensitized states, but both mutant receptors still desensitize multiple times per second.</s><s>Cyclothiazide (CTZ) reduced desensitization of wild-type receptors and both types of mutant receptor.</s><s>Analysis of shut-time distributions revealed a form of short-lived desensitization that was resistant to CTZ and was especially prominent for GluA4-Lc receptors.</s><s>Despite reducing desensitization of GluA4 L484Y receptors, CTZ decreased the amplitude of ensemble currents through GluA2 and GluA4 LY receptor mutants.</s><s>Single-channel analysis and comparison of the GluA2 L483Y ligand binding domain dimer in complex with glutamate with and without CTZ is consistent with the conclusion that CTZ binding to the dimer interface prevents effects of the LY mutation to modulate receptor activation, resulting in a reduction in the prevalence of large-conductance substates that accounts for the decrease in ensemble current amplitudes.</s><s>Together, the results show that similar nondesensitizing AMPA-receptor phenotypes of population currents can arise from distinct underlying molecular mechanisms that produce different types of unitary activity.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p><s>AMPA receptors are ionotropic glutamate receptors that mediate fast synaptic transmission in the mammalian central nervous system.</s><s>Individual receptors consist of four core subunits that form a transmembrane cation-selective pore.</s><s>Each potential pore-forming subunit of the AMPA receptor (GluA1-4) is composed of an N-terminal domain, a ligandbinding domain (LBD), three transmembrane helices, a cytoplasmic reentrant pore loop, and an intracellular C-terminal domain <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref>.</s><s>AMPA receptors activate and desensitize very rapidly.</s><s>Activation appears to be initiated by closing of the clamshell-like LBD after glutamate docks within the cleft between lobes D1 and D2 of the LBD of individual subunits <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>.</s><s>Closing of the LBDs results in presumably unstable transition states in which the channel pore and the LBDs of one or more subunits are closed; and activation and desensitization proceed in parallel from these short-lived closed states <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Structural information from x-ray crystallography and cryo-EM studies has highlighted separation of the D1-D1 interface within each receptor dimer as the primary trigger for receptor desensitization <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>.</s><s>Key residues within the alternative flip/flop splice cassettes map to this interface, and destabilization of the dimer interface promotes desensitization, whereas stabilization of this interface reduces it <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>.</s><s>For example, exposing the receptor to cyclothiazide (CTZ), a positive allosteric modulator, or substituting leucine for tyrosine at a position at the back of the LBD, stabilizes the dimer interface and greatly reduces the decline in receptor-mediated currents during sustained applications of agonists <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>.</s><s>However, other studies have identified mutations of residues within the linkers connecting the LBD to the transmembrane regions <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21)</ref>, as well as mutations in the so-called hydrophobic box or extracellular collar <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">23)</ref>, that also reduce the fade of ensemble currents during sustained applications.</s><s>The so-called Lurcher mutation (an alanine to threonine switch at the extracellular end of the universally conserved SYTANLAAF motif in the second true transmembrane helix) also results in receptors that display reduced fade <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref>.</s><s>In total, available results suggest that multiple receptor regions impact the likelihood that AMPA receptors desensitize and the rate at which they do so.</s></p><p><s>Although by definition a decline in the ensemble current evoked by a sustained application of agonist is desensitization, changes in the rate or extent of this decline do not necessarily mirror changes in the microscopic rate constants for entry into and exit from desensitized states.</s><s>Because activation and desensitization occur in parallel from the same closed states <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27)</ref>, typical reaction schemes for AMPA receptors admit multiple ways to produce population responses with different rates or extent of current fade, and it is therefore uncertain whether similar nondesensitizing phenotypes arise from similar changes in microscopic rate constants.</s></p><p><s>Here we compared ensemble and unitary currents through GluA4 receptors that carried one of two well-studied mutations known to greatly reduce macroscopic desensitization, namely the dimer interface mutant (GluA4 L484Y) and the Lurcher mutation (A623T) near the putative ion channel gate.</s><s>Both mutations decreased the frequency and duration of visits to long-lived closed states and increased the proportion of time the receptors spend at large-conductance open levels.</s><s>We also studied the effect of the positive allosteric modulator CTZ, which potentiated currents through both wild-type and Lurcher GluA4 receptors (GluA4-wt and GluA4-Lc).</s><s>In contrast, CTZ reduced the amplitude of both ensemble and unitary currents through GluA4 L484Y receptors and also reduced the amplitude of currents through the corresponding GluA2 dimer interface mutant (GluA2 L483Y).</s><s>Comparison of the crystal structures of the glutamate-bound LBD dimer from the GluA2 L483Y mutant with and without CTZ revealed similar structures, except that CTZ binding to the LY mutant reduced the direct interprotomer contact area at the D1-D1 interface by $20%.</s><s>Surprisingly, CTZ dominated the functional character of receptors harboring the LY mutation, preventing the effects of the LY mutation to speed receptor activation and to slow deactivation.</s><s>Finally, our analysis of shut-time distributions revealed a form of short-lived desensitization that is resistant to CTZ and is evident in records for both types of mutant receptor.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MATERIALS AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mutagenesis</head><p><s>The L484Y and A623T mutations were introduced into full-length GluR4 flip encoding a glutamine at the Q/R editing site with PCR.</s><s>The L483Y mutation was introduced to GluA2 flip using the same approach.</s><s>All constructs were verified by sequencing.</s><s>Numbering for GluA2 and GluA4 assumes a 21-amino-acid signal peptide is cleaved from both proteins.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patch-clamp recording and single-channel analysis</head><p><s>For the studies on GluA4 receptors, tsA201 cells were maintained and transfected as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>.</s><s>Recordings from outside-out patches held at À100 mV were performed 12-24 h after transfection at room temperature with an EPC 9 amplifier (HEKA Elektronik, Lambrecht/Pfalz, Germany).</s><s>The external solution contained the following: 150 mM NaCl, 3 mM KCl, 2 mM CaCl 2 , 1 mM MgCl 2 , 5 mM glucose, and 10 mM HEPES, pH 7.4.</s><s>The internal solution contained the following: 135 mM CsF, 33 mM CsOH, 2 mM MgCl 2 , 1 mM CaCl 2 , 11 mM EGTA, and 10 mM HEPES, pH 7.4.</s><s>Patch pipettes were pulled from thick-walled borosilicate glass capillaries (GC-150F; Harvard Apparatus, Edenbridge, UK), coated with Sylgard resin (Dow Corning, Corning, NY) and fire polished.</s><s>When filled with internal solution, recording pipettes had open-tip resistances of 10-15 MU.</s><s>Glutamate and CTZ (Tocris Bioscience, Avonmouth, UK) were added to the external solution and applied with q-pipettes mounted on a piezoelectric bimorph (Morgan Electro Ceramics, Windsor, UK).</s><s>The rate of solution exchange time estimated from open-tip potentials was typically 100-200 ms.</s><s>In the experiments where the rise-times of population currents through wild-type and mutant receptors were compared, care was taken to use application pipettes that gave open-tip rise-times of 80-100 ms to ensure solution exchange was as fast as possible.</s><s>The speed of solution exchange was checked at the beginning and end of each experiment, and recordings from patches containing wild-type and mutant receptors were interleaved to avoid introducing any systematic bias due to patch-to-patch variability in the rate of solution exchange that might skew the comparisons.</s></p><p><s>For the studies of GluA2 receptors, HEK-293 cells (DSMZ, Braunschweig, Germany) were transfected with a total of 2 mg DNA of wild-type and L483Y GluA2 receptors using polyethylenimine.</s><s>Cells transfected with GluA2 L483Y were supplemented with 40 mM NBQX (Abcam, Cambridge, UK).</s><s>Recordings were made at room temperature 24-48 h after transfection.</s><s>Outside-out patches were voltage-clamped at a holding potential of À60 mV during 500 ms and 1 s applications of 10 mM glutamate.</s><s>Currents were low-pass filtered at 5 kHz using an Axopatch 200B amplifier (Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA) and acquired with Axograph X software (Axograph Scientific; https://axograph.com).</s><s>The external solution contained: 150 mM NaCl, 0.1 mM MgCl 2 , 0.1 mM CaCl 2 , and 5 mM HEPES, titrated to pH 7.3 with NaOH.</s><s>The pipette solution contained: 115 mM NaCl, 10 mM NaF, 0.5 mM CaCl 2 , 1 mM MgCl 2 , 5 mM Na 4 BAPTA, 5 mM HEPES, and 10 mM Na 2 ATP, pH 7.3.</s><s>Glutamate was applied to outside-out patches via a piezo-driven fast perfusion system (PI, Karlsruhe, Germany).</s><s>Cyclothiazide (100 mM; Hello Bio, Bristol, UK) was included in both the wash and the glutamate barrels of the perfusion tool.</s><s>Typical 10-90% solution exchange times were faster than 300 ms, as measured from junction potentials at the open tip of the patch pipette.</s></p><p><s>Single-channel glutamate-evoked currents were analog low-pass filtered at 10 kHz, sampled at 25-50 kHz, and written directly to the hard drive of two computers.</s><s>One computer stored the records in PULSE format (the software used to run the EPC 9), and the other stored the data in QuB (http://www.qub.buffalo.edu)</s><s>format (the software used for single-channel analysis).</s><s>Most single-channel analysis was done on currents recorded during 1-5 min continuous applications of glutamate without or with CTZ.</s><s>Before these applications were made, we collected responses to at least 50 concentration jumps (500 ms applications).</s><s>For all patches containing wild-type GluA4 receptors, and the majority of patches containing mutant receptors, data were collected in both the absence and presence of 100 mM CTZ.</s><s>The open probability at the onset of the concentration jumps and during continuous glutamate applications in the presence of CTZ was high (&gt;0.5),</s><s>allowing us to detect the presence of multiple receptors in the patches from careful inspection of the records.</s><s>Although quantifying receptor number is complicated by the presence of multiple open levels for individual receptors, given the high open probability conditions in our experiments, deciding that a patch had just one active receptor was not difficult and we are confident that all the patches used for analysis of unitary currents contained just a single active receptor.</s></p><p><s>Single-channel data recorded during continuous agonist applications were subjected to digital Gaussian low-pass filtering at 3.5 or 4 kHz (À3 dB), which resulted in closed-channel root-mean-square noise values (300-350 fA) that were less than half the smallest difference in current amplitudes between adjacent conductance levels.</s><s>The closed-channel current was manually set to zero, and the entire filtered data set from a given patch was idealized with the segmental k means (SKM) algorithm of QuB to identify single-channel transitions and estimate conductance levels and event durations <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29)</ref>.</s><s>Because our data appeared to contain many rapid transitions between several closely spaced open levels, we empirically tested different sampling rates and resolutions <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref>.</s><s>Sampling at 50 kHz and a time resolution of four sample intervals (80 ms, 0.8 filter rise-times) consistently gave good results.</s><s>The kinetic model used for the SKM idealization of the results contained two closed states and one open state for each of four open levels.</s><s>The states were connected to allow all types of transitions between the five different conductance levels.</s></p><p><s>After visually inspecting the idealized record and removing dubious events, open and shut times were exported to Channelab (Synaptosoft, Decatur, GA), and histograms (10-12 bins per decade) of the dwell times were displayed and fitted with log-likelihood log-binned subroutines.</s><s>Distributions were fitted with one to five exponential components.</s><s>Log-likelihood ratios or comparison of c 2 values were used to determine the number of components required to adequately fit the data <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref>.</s><s>Histograms of unitary current amplitudes for open events with duration R2 filter rise-times (200 ms) were fitted in IGOR Pro (WaveMetrics, Lake Oswego, OR) with equations consisting of four Gaussian components.</s></p><p><s>Deactivation and desensitization decays of currents through wild-type and mutant GluA4 receptors, as well as recovery data from two-pulse protocols, were acquired and analyzed as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17)</ref>.</s><s>Peak currents and deactivation decays of wild-type and L483Y GluA2 receptors were measured by applying 10 mM glutamate for 500 ms and 1 s in the presence and absence of 100 mM CTZ. Deactivation decays were calculated from fits with two, in some cases three, exponential components, and weighted t-values calculated from the time constants and relative amplitudes of each component.</s><s>At least 5-6 patches from three different transfections were obtained for both wild-type and L483Y GluA2.</s><s>Approximately 30 episodes were collected for each recording condition.</s><s>Patches in which recordings were unstable, or in which there was excessive rundown of the responses, or solution exchange was slower than 0.5 ms, were excluded.</s><s>To compare the rate of activation for the three GluA4 receptors, fast applications of 10 mM glutamate were made on patches containing many receptors with the precautions noted above.</s><s>The rising phases of the inward population currents were fitted with a Hodgkin-Huxley-type equation:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">I(t) ¼ (I max</formula><p><s>(1/m) À (I max (1/m) )*exp(Àt/t act )) m , and the fits were used to measure 10-90% rise-times for the currents through each type of receptor.</s><s>Statistical comparisons of sample means from the electrophysiological data were made with two-tailed Student's t-tests or ANOVA as indicated.</s><s>p values &lt;0.05 were considered statistically significant.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Protein expression and purification</head><p><s>The flop isoform of rat GluA2 LBD (S1S2 fusion) in pET22b vector was kindly provided by E. Gouaux.</s><s>The flip mutations N754S, L758V, and the nondesensitizing mutation L483Y, were introduced by overlap mutagenesis and verified by DNA sequencing.</s><s>Protein expression and purification was carried out as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(32)</ref>.</s><s>Briefly, we expressed the LBD in Escherichia coli Origami BL21 (DE3).</s><s>The lysate was clarified by centrifugation and purified by metal affinity chromatography.</s><s>After a Trypsin digest, the protein was further purified by size-exclusion chromatography.</s><s>The pooled protein fractions were concentrated to 11.5 mg/mL before crystallization.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Crystallization and data collection</head><p><s>The GluA2 L483Y LBD was crystallized using sitting drop vapor diffusion at 4 C. Several crystals were obtained by mixing equal volumes of precipitant solution (200 mM Li 2 SO 4 , 20.0% w/v PEG 3350) using a Gryphon Robot (Art Robbins Instrument, Sunnyvale, CA).</s><s>Crystals were flash frozen in liquid nitrogen after a quick bath in cryo-protectant (10% PEG200 in reservoir solution).</s><s>Diffraction data were collected on beamline BL 14.1 at the BESSY II electron-storage ring, Helmholtz Zentrum Berlin f€ ur Materialien und Energie.</s><s>Data were processed using XDSAPP <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(33)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phasing and refinement</head><p><s>The best crystal of the GluA2 L483Y LBD diffracted to 1.44 A ˚resolution and was indexed in space group P2 1 2 1 2. The structure was solved by molecular replacement using Phaser-MR (34) from the CCP4 Suite and the GluA2 LDB in complex with glutamate (PDB: 1FTJ, chain A) as a search model (4).</s><s>Model building using Coot <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(35)</ref> and Phenix <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(36)</ref> in iterative cycles led to a model of the GluA2 L483Y LBD with an R work and R free of 14.7 and 20.5%, respectively.</s><s>R free was calculated using 5% of the reflections, which we omitted at random from the refinement.</s><s>The final model includes two molecules in the asymmetric unit (from Gly 1 -Ser 263 in chain A to Asn 3 -Ser 263 in chain B).</s><s>Structure visualization and analysis were done in PyMOL (The PyMOL Molecular Graphics System, Version 1.8, Schro ¨dinger, New York).</s><s>Analysis of the surfaces of the CTZ binding sites was done in PyMOL using cavity detection of three solvent radii and a cutoff of one solvent radius, giving the most generous interpretation of the cavities.</s><s>In the 5ns9 structure, a purely solvent accessible surface did not include the CTZ cavities (data not shown).</s><s>The structure factors and coordinates were deposited in the RCSB PDB under accession code: PDB: 5NS9.</s><s>Data collection and refinement statistics are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>. Interface analysis was done with the PISA server <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(37)</ref>.</s><s>The interface area per subunit was defined as half the difference of the total accessible surface areas of isolated and interfacing structures.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GluA4 L484Y receptors exhibit desensitization</head><p><s>Although the LY mutant receptor is used widely as an example of a nondesensitizing AMPA receptor <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18)</ref>, previous work has demonstrated that this mutation in GluA1-flip produces receptors that show significant fade of ensemble currents in fast application studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>.</s><s>To test whether this is also true for the analogous mutation in GluA4-flip, we made rapid applications of glutamate to outside-out patches from tsA201 cells transiently expressing GluA4 L484Y receptors.</s><s>In preliminary experiments, we found that the size of population currents evoked by 1 and 10 mM glutamate was virtually identical for GluA4 L484Y receptors, a result that was also true for GluA4-Lc receptors.</s><s>All subsequent experiments were done using 10 mM glutamate, which is essentially a saturating concentration for wild-type GluA4 and both mutant receptors.</s></p><p><s>Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> shows GluA4 L484Y receptor responses to 10 mM glutamate.</s><s>The currents through GluA4 L484Y receptors showed substantial fade during sustained applications of saturating glutamate, although desensitization was slower and less complete than for wild-type GluA4 receptors (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 a</ref>).</s><s>Whereas wild-type GluA4-flip receptors give steady-state plateau currents that are only 1-2% of the peak currents evoked by saturating concentrations of glutamate, and desensitization is largely monoexponential and complete within 15 ms (9), the mean plateau/peak current ratio for the L484Y mutant receptors was 0.64 5 0.03 (n ¼ 7), and fitting the fade of the GluA4 L484Y currents required two exponential components that gave mean time constants of 16.8 5 1.7 and 124.1 5 18.9 ms.</s><s>The fits gave a weighted desensitization time constant of 81.9 5 8.3 ms (n ¼ 7), which is $27-fold slower than published values for GluA4-flip wild-type homomers <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The GluA4 L484Y deactivation decays (obtained from the current decays at the end of a 1 ms pulse of 10 mM glutamate) were also biexponential and slower than for GluA4 wild-type receptors (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 b</ref>).</s><s>The weighted time constants obtained from biexponential fits gave a value of 1.6 5 0.2 ms for the L484Y mutant receptors compared with 0.6 5 0.2 ms for wild-type GluA4 (n ¼ 5; p &lt; 0.05).</s><s>The results indicate that glutamate dissociates 2-3 times more slowly from GluA4 L484Y receptors than from GluA4-wt receptors.</s></p><p><s>Because GluA4 L484Y receptors showed significant desensitization, we could measure recovery from desensitization with two-pulse protocols.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure">1 c</ref> shows representative results from one patch, and the mean data from several patches are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">1 d</ref>.</s><s>Although the overall speed of recovery was like that of GluA4 wild-type homomeric receptors <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>, a portion of the receptors recovered very quickly.</s><s>The recovery time-course obtained from the mean data was fitted best by two Hodgkin-Huxley equations (39) that gave time constants of 7.4 and 26 ms with relative amplitudes for the fast and slow components of 0.33 and 0.67.</s><s>The weighted recovery time constant of 19.8 ms for L484Y mutant receptors was similar to the recovery time constant (17.9 ms) for GluA4 wild-type receptors <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In total, our analysis is consistent with previous conclusions that the primary effect of the LY mutation at the D1-D1 interface is to reduce desensitization <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18)</ref>.</s><s>For GluA4-flip receptors, however, this reduction is far from complete, and there is a less substantial slowing of FIGURE <ref type="figure">1</ref> Population currents through GluA4 L484Y mutant receptors.</s><s>(a) Shown here is the current (average of 20 trials) evoked by 500 ms applications of 10 mM glutamate in an outsideout patch containing 100 of GluA4 L484Y mutant receptors.</s><s>The large steady-state current is roughly half the initial peak current at the start of the application.</s><s>The decay of the current was fitted with a biexponential function (solid curve; individual components shown as dashed lines).</s><s>The time constants of each component and their relative amplitudes are indicated.</s><s>(b) Here is current evoked by a brief (1 ms) application of 10 mM glutamate to another outside-out patch containing GluA4 L484Y mutant receptors.</s><s>The deactivation decay of the current followed a biexponential time course.</s><s>The biexponential fit to the decay is superposed on the current trace (solid line).</s><s>The time constants (and relative amplitude) of the fast and slow components were 1.2 ms (90%) and 8.5 ms (10%).</s><s>The current trace is the average of 20 consecutive records.</s><s>(c and d) Recovery from desensitization shows fast and slow components.</s><s>(c) Example of the results from a two-pulse protocol to measure recovery from desensitization with 10 mM glutamate.</s><s>(d) Mean 5 SE) data from five patches.</s><s>For each recovery interval, the amplitude of the peak current evoked by the second pulse was divided by the amplitude of the peak current evoked by the first application with which it was paired (peaks were measured from the steady-state current at the end of the first application).</s><s>The data were fitted with two Hodgkin-Huxley-type components, reflecting the fact that approximately one-third of the receptors recovered substantially faster than predicted from the time-course of the recovery for intervals &gt;20 ms.</s><s>deactivation as well as a change in the shape of the recovery time-course.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The effect of cyclothiazide on currents through GluA4 L484Y receptors</head><p><s>Cyclothiazide is a well-known AMPA receptor modulator that potentiates AMPA receptor currents by reducing desensitization <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41)</ref>, and CTZ is known to bind at the D1-D1 interface where, like the LY mutation, it is thought to stabilize the interface and slow receptor entry into desensitized states <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42)</ref>.</s><s>Because the LY mutation only partially reduced steady-state desensitization for GluA4flip receptors, we tested whether CTZ would remove the residual desensitization.</s></p><p><s>As in the example shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref> a, CTZ virtually abolished the fade in the population response in all patches tested, suggesting that CTZ did reduce desensitization.</s><s>Although CTZ typically increases the peak response ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>), 100 mM CTZ reduced the amplitudes of both peak and steady-state currents through GluA4 L484Y receptors (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2 a</ref>).</s><s>On average, the peak and steady-state currents were reduced by 33.3 5 4.1% (n ¼ 13) and 8.3 5 2.7% (n ¼ 8), respectively.).</s></p><p><s>To investigate the mechanistic basis of this result, and presumably similar earlier findings for GluA1 receptors <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(43)</ref>, we performed single-channel recording for GluA4 L484Y mutant receptors in the absence and presence of 100 mM CTZ.</s><s>The high open probability in the recordings ensured that all the patches used for the analysis contained only one active receptor.</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref> b shows typical rapid application results (10 mM glutamate, 500 ms) for a GluA4 L484Y receptor in the absence and presence of CTZ.</s><s>As expected from the prominent fade of the ensemble currents seen with the L484Y mutant, the 500 ms jumps contain long gaps between activations that presumably correspond to sojourns in desensitized states.</s><s>Although the frequency of these gaps was reduced, such long closings were still evident in the presence of CTZ (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>b). Both with and without CTZ, receptor activity consisted of bursts of openings with considerable open-channel noise due to the presence of rapid transitions between multiple open levels (30).</head><p><s>Even with the open-channel noise, however, it was clear from visual inspection of the records that the mean single-channel current was reduced in the presence of CTZ.</s></p><p><s>To quantify the reduction in unitary current, we recorded single-channel activity from patches with one active GluA4 L484Y receptor in the continuous presence of 10 mM glutamate, with and without 100 mM CTZ. Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref>, c and d, shows 25 s of results obtained from an outside-out patch containing one GluA4 L484Y receptor during continuous exposure to 10 mM glutamate (the five traces in each panel are contiguous).</s><s>In the absence of CTZ, the record consists of long bursts of openings that are separated by frequent closed periods of similarly long duration (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2 c</ref>).</s><s>Such closed periods were much less frequent and were shorter when CTZ was present in the external solution (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2 d</ref>; arrows).</s><s>The maximum amplitude of the single-channel currents was also clearly reduced in CTZ (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2 d</ref>).</s><s>The open-channel currents appeared to consist of rapid flickering between adjacent open levels (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2 e</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To compare the single-channel data for GluA4 L484Y receptors with results for GluA4-wt receptors under similar conditions, continuous records of glutamate-evoked unitary currents were idealized with the software QuB (https:// milesculabs.biology.missouri.edu/QuB.html).</s><s>Only patches that contained just one active receptor (as confirmed by careful examination of currents at the onset of concentration jumps and in the presence of CTZ; see Materials and Methods) were included in the analysis.</s><s>Examples of the data obtained for the amplitude of the unitary currents are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>. Four open levels were detected in each patch analyzed.</s><s>For wild-type GluA4 receptors in control external solution, most openings were to the two smallest open levels (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3 a</ref>; Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>In CTZ, there was an increased frequency of openings to the larger conductance levels (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3 b</ref>; Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>Whereas, on average, CTZ had no effect on the conductance values obtained for GluA4wt receptors (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>), the proportion of O1 openings was significantly reduced and openings to each of the largest three levels were significantly more common in the presence of CTZ (p &lt; 0.03, Student's t-tests).</s></p><p><s>Large-conductance openings were common for GluA4 L484Y receptors and were even more prevalent than for GluA4-wt in CTZ (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3 c</ref>).</s><s>Indeed, openings to the smallest open level seen for wild-type receptors ($8 pS on average) were absent, and the four open levels detected spanned the range defined by the three largest levels detected for GluA4-wt channels (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>Restricting the fits to three Gaussian components resulted in SDs for the individual components that were roughly twice the corresponding closed-channel value, suggesting there may be an additional open level between the O3 and O4 levels detected for wild-type receptors, an open level that is unresolved in the records from wild-type receptors because of the rarity of large-conductance events.</s><s>In any case, the largest open level seen for L484Y was not different from that seen for GluA4-wt (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, p ¼ 0.71), and the primary effect of the L484Y mutation on unitary current amplitudes was a much greater proportion of large-conductance openings.</s><s>Whereas openings to conductance levels below 20 pS represented slightly &gt;95% of the events detected for GluA4-wt, they represented only 12% of the openings for GluA4 L484Y (p &lt; 0.0001, Student's t-test, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s></p><p><s>In contrast to its effect on wild-type GluA4 receptors, CTZ reduced rather than increased the relative frequency of large-conductance openings for GluA4 L484Y receptors.</s><s>Additionally, each of the four levels for GluA4 L484Y receptors was consistently smaller in CTZ, although the smallest level was still larger than the O1 level measured for GluA4-wt receptors (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3 d</ref>; Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>Together, these changes resulted in a significant decrease in the weighted mean unitary conductance for the GluA4 L484Y receptors in the presence of CTZ (control: 31.2 5 1.4 pS; CTZ: 22.9 5 01.3 pS, n ¼5, p &lt; 0.01, Student's t-test).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Structure of the GluA2 LY dimer alone and in complex with cyclothiazide</head><p><s>The effect of CTZ to reduce the mean amplitude of unitary currents through GluA4 L484Y receptors was unexpected.</s></p><p><s>Because both the LY mutation and CTZ target the monomer-monomer interface within LBD dimers, we hypothesized that changes in LBD dimer geometry could underlie the different current amplitudes.</s><s>Therefore, we compared the structure of the AMPA receptor LBD for the LY mutant in the absence and presence of CTZ.</s><s>We chose to use the well-studied GluA2 LBD construct (4) for the structural comparison, and first determined whether CTZ also reduced ensemble currents through full-length GluA2 L483Y mutant receptors, as it did for the corresponding GluA4 L484Y receptors.</s></p><p><s>Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>, a and b, shows the effect of CTZ on peak currents evoked by repeated brief applications of 10 mM glutamate for GluA2-wt and GluA2 L483Y receptors.</s><s>In some patches, after an initial rundown of the peak current, GluA2-wt currents were potentiated by CTZ (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref> a, left).</s><s>In other recordings, the peak current declined when CTZ was added.</s><s>In contrast, CTZ consistently reduced peak currents through GluA2 L483Y receptors (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref> a, right).</s><s>On average, the peak amplitude of GluA2-wt currents was not significantly altered by CTZ, whereas peak currents through GluA2 L483Y receptors were reduced significantly by CTZ (Fig. <ref type="figure">4 b</ref>).</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure">4 c</ref> shows example results for single sustained (500 ms) applications of glutamate.</s><s>In addition to reducing the currents through GluA2 L483Y receptors, CTZ also increased the rate at which the currents decayed at the end of glutamate application.</s><s>The weighted time constants for GluA2 L483Y receptors in the absence and presence of CTZ correspond to a more than threefold increase in the rate of deactivation when CTZ is present, making it similar to the rate of deactivation for GluA2-wt with or without CTZ (Fig. <ref type="figure">4 d</ref>).</s><s>The deactivation decays were faster for GluA4 L484Y receptors than for the corresponding GluA2 mutant, but CTZ also increased the rate of deactivation for GluA4 L484Y receptors (weighted t: 0.9 5 0.1 ms with CTZ versus 1.6 5 0.2 ms without CTZ, n ¼5, p &lt; 0.005), whereas it slowed deactivation for GluA4-wt receptors (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 b</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To better define the mechanisms by which CTZ reduces ensemble and unitary currents through LY mutant receptors, we crystallized the GluA2 LBD carrying the LY mutation (GluA2_LBD_LY) in complex with glutamate, to compare it with the structure of GluA2_LBD_LY in complex with CTZ and glutamate (GluA_LBD_LY_CTZ; PDB: 3TKD) <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(44)</ref>.</s><s>As for the GluA2_LBD_LY_CTZ structure, we introduced the flip mutation N745S into our GluA2_LBD_LY construct and crystallized it in the glutamate-bound form.</s><s>We measured one GluA2_LBD_LY crystal that diffracted to approximately the same resolution (1.44</s><s>A ˚) as the PDB: 3TKD structure, facilitating the comparison.</s><s>Likewise, the data indexed into the same space group P2 1 2 1 2 and we found two molecules in the asymmetric unit (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>).</s><s>Structural alignment of the C-a atoms of GluA2_LBD_LY and GluA2_LBD_LY_CTZ indicates similarity with a root-mean-square deviation of 0.31 A (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5 a</ref>).</s><s>Consistent with the original structure of GluA2 with the LY mutation in complex with AMPA, and the CTZ/ glutamate cocrystal <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>, the D1 interface in the GluA2_LBD_LY is intact and is formed by the same residues of both chains A and B (Ile 481 -Val 484 , Glu 486 , Glu 487 , Phe 491 -Pro 494 , Ser 497 , Phe 658 , Ser 662 , Ile 664 , Leu 727 -Lys 730 , Lys 738 , Asn 744 , Asn 747 -Ala 749 , Leu 751 , Lys 752 , Ser 754 -Gly 757 , Asp 760 , Lys 761 ; insets of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5 b</ref>).</s><s>Despite the almost indistinguishable structures, we observed a clear difference in the interprotomer interface between chains A and B. In the GluA2_LBD_LY_CTZ, the interface buries 1500 A ˚2, compared to 1860 A ˚2 in GluA2_LBD_LY.</s><s>The reduced interface in GluA2_LBD_LY_CTZ is explained by the two CTZ molecules binding within the D1 interface, thereby reducing the buried area between chain A and B. Each CTZ molecule adds 440 A ˚2 to the total buried surface area.</s><s>Moreover, there is a halo of atoms from each subunit that interacts with both CTZ and the alternate protomer (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5 b</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Comparison of our structure of the GluA2_LBD_LY with the CTZ-bound form confirms that the entry to the buried CTZ binding sites is formed from the same four residues in each case, with Ser 497 , Ser 729 , Asp 760 , and Lys 761 defining a narrow fenestration.</s><s>However, this crevicelike region at the base of the active dimer interface is narrower in the LY mutant structure without CTZ.</s><s>These observations, facilitated by our comparison at high resolution, support the notion that CTZ cannot easily bind to, or unbind from, the active dimer form that is favored by the LY mutation.</s><s>Notably, although in crystal structures two cyclothiazide molecules are bound, the low potency of CTZ means that dimers with a single, buried CTZ molecule are quite likely to occur; in contrast, the L483Y mutation is always present in double copy.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Characteristics of GluA4-Lc receptors</head><p><s>The Lurcher mutation, an alanine to threonine mutation in the conserved SYTANLAAF motif at the extracellular end of the second transmembrane helix, is also known to produce AMPAR population currents that show substantially reduced current fade during sustained applications of glutamate <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46)</ref>.</s><s>We first sought to compare ensemble currents for GluA4-Lc receptors (GluA4 A623T) in the absence and presence of 100 mM CTZ. Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> a shows examples of ensemble currents evoked by a 1 ms application of 10 mM glutamate for GluA4-Lc receptors (peak currents scaled to have the same amplitude).</s><s>As reported previously for GluA1-Lc receptors <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>, the deactivation decays for GluA4-Lc receptors are complex mixtures of three exponential components.</s><s>As for GluA4-wt receptors (Fig. <ref type="figure">1 b</ref>), and in contrast to the speeding of deactivation seen for the LY mutants, 100 mM CTZ produced a modest slowing of these decays (weighted t: 44.3 5 8.2 vs. 61.9 5 11.1 ms, n ¼ 5, p &lt; 0.05).</s></p><p><s>Examples of responses to a 200 ms application of glutamate are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> b.</s><s>In the absence of CTZ, the peak currents through GluA4-Lc receptors showed evidence of residual desensitization.</s><s>The time constants obtained from single exponential fits to the fade of the population current during sustained applications of 10 mM glutamate gave a mean value of 10.7 5 1.8 ms (n ¼ 10), approximately threefold slower than the corresponding value for wildtype GluA4i receptors <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>.</s><s>The mean steady-state current expressed as a fraction of the maximum inward current evoked at the onset of the glutamate application was 73.7 5 3.6% (n ¼ 10).</s><s>The addition of 100 mM CTZ to the external solution abolished the fade in the population response (n ¼ 5), and lengthened the decay, not unlike the effects of CTZ on GluA4 complexes with stargazin <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(47)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>We also analyzed unitary currents in patches that contained just one active GluA4-Lc receptor.</s><s>The multiple open levels seen for GluA4-Lc receptors were similar to those observed for GluA4-wt receptors, but openings to the largest two conductance levels were more prevalent for GluA4-Lc receptors (Fig. <ref type="figure">6 c</ref>; Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, p &lt; 0.01, oneway ANOVA).</s><s>In contrast to GluA4 L484Y receptors, the proportion of time that single GluA4-Lc receptors spent in the largest two open levels was increased when 100 mM CTZ was added to the external solution with 10 mM glutamate (Fig. <ref type="figure">6 d</ref>; Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, p &lt; 0.01).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Open probability of GluA4-wt, GluA4 L484Y, and GluA4-Lc receptors</head><p><s>In addition to the prevalence of openings to large-conductance substates, the most obvious difference between GluA4-wt and the GluA4 mutants in the single-receptor recordings was in steady-state open probability (P open ).</s><s>In patches containing one GluA4-wt receptor, long-lived shut periods were common and P open was low in the presence of continuous 10 mM glutamate (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>).</s><s>In contrast, both GluA4 L484Y and GluA4-Lc receptors spent most of their time in open states (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>), although the increase in P open was larger for GluA4 L484Y than for GluA4-Lc.</s><s>Interestingly, CTZ increased the steady-state P open for all three receptor types.</s><s>The P open values for GluA4-wt and GluA4 L484Y receptors in CTZ were virtually identical.</s><s>The results support the conclusion that CTZ further reduces desensitization for GluA4 L484Y mutant receptors and that interference with this primary effect of CTZ is not responsible for the effect of CTZ to reduce steady-state currents through GluA4 L484Y channels.</s></p><p><s>It is firmly established that activation and desensitization of AMPA receptors normally proceed in parallel from the same set of short-lived, pregating, closed states (8-10,13,27,30).</s><s>As a result, some wild-type AMPA receptors desensitize without opening when the receptors are rapidly exposed to saturating concentration of glutamate, and the fraction that do so is determined by the ratio of the rate constants for channel opening and receptor desensitization (b/d; Fig. <ref type="figure">7 a</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30)</ref>).</s><s>Manipulations that increase this ratio, by increasing b and/or decreasing d, will increase the probability that receptors open in response to a rapid application of saturating glutamate (prob open ).</s><s>For our one-channel patches, this value was easily obtained by counting the number of blank records during a long series of repeated rapid jumps into 10 mM glutamate (openings that occurred &gt;5 ms after the onset of the application were ignored for this analysis because they likely represented receptors escaping from desensitized states).</s><s>Values for prob open are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> and were compared with a one-way ANOVA.</s><s>As expected from its effect to reduce d <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48)</ref>, CTZ increased prob open for GluA4-wt receptors (p &lt; 0.05).</s><s>The prob open values measured for GluA4 L484Y and GluA4-Lc receptors without CTZ present were significantly greater than those for GluA4-wt receptors (p &lt; 0.05) and slightly higher even than those for wildtype receptors in CTZ.</s><s><ref type="bibr">FIGURE 6</ref> Cyclothiazide potentiates population and unitary currents through GluA4-Lc receptors.</s><s>(a) Given here are currents evoked by a brief (1 ms) application of 10 mM glutamate to an outside-out patch containing GluA4 receptors carrying the Lurcher (Lc) mutation (A623T).</s><s>The traces are averages of 20 trials in the absence (black) and presence (red) of 100 mM CTZ.</s><s>The complex, prolonged deactivation decays were fitted with three exponential components (the fits, gray, are superposed on the traces).</s><s>The time constants (relative amplitudes) of the three components are given on the figure.</s><s>(b) Given here are currents (averages of 20 trials) evoked by 200 ms applications of 10 mM glutamate to another outside-out patch containing GluA4-Lc mutant receptors.</s><s>In the absence of CTZ (black trace), the current decays to a large steadystate current along a single exponential time-course with a time constant of 11.1 ms.</s><s>The desensitization decay is not evident in the presence of 100 mM CTZ (red trace).</s><s>(c and d) Shown here are examples of unitary currents (4 kHz filtering) and amplitude histograms for open-channel currents through GluA4-Lc mutant receptors without (c) and with (d) the addition of 100 mM CTZ to the external solution.</s><s>The amplitude histograms were fitted (solid line) with the mixture of four Gaussian components (dashed lines) that gave the indicated conductance values.</s><s>Large conductance events were more frequent in the presence of CTZ.</s><s>To see this figure in color, go online.</s><s>The reduced frequency of long-lived closed states seen for the two mutants (see below) suggests that reduced rates of entry into desensitization (decreased d) are in part responsible for the significant increase in prob open seen for both GluA4 L484Y and GluA4-Lc receptors.</s><s>To test whether enhanced activation rates (increased b) also contributed to the increases in prob open , we compared the rise-times for population currents through the three different receptors.</s><s>Because such measurements at saturating glutamate are sensitive to the speed of solution exchange, care was taken to minimize the impact of such potential artifacts on the comparisons (see Materials and Methods).</s><s>Examples of fits to the rising phase of currents evoked by rapid jumps into 10 mM glutamate are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">7</ref> b.</s><s>As can be seen, the rise-times of the population currents are faster for both GluA4 mutant receptors than they are for GluA4-wt receptors.</s><s>The difference was statistically significant for GluA4 L484Y receptors (Fig. <ref type="figure">7 c</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Although a decrease in d will increase prob open , there is little reason to expect that this effect alone would increase rise-times.</s><s>Indeed, CTZ, which reduced the frequency of long-lived shut times like each of the two mutations, slowed the rise of currents for each of the three types of GluA4 receptors (30-115%).</s><s>One possible explanation for this slowing is that CTZ unmasks the contribution of receptors that activate with long latency-to-first-opening values (for example, because they transit multiple times among R, RG, and RG* states; Fig. <ref type="figure">7 a</ref>).</s><s>Such receptors may open during the falling phase of the current when desensitization is intact, but contribute to the peak response when desensitization is reduced by CTZ.</s><s>Indeed, it was a common observation that the population current continued to increase in CTZ at times after the peak population response had occurred before CTZ was applied.</s><s>An example of this can be seen for the GluA4-Lc population currents in Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref> b.</s><s>The faster rise-times for both GluA4 L484Yand GluA4-Lc receptors therefore suggest that in addition to reducing desensitization both mutations also speed transitions along the activation pathway.</s><s><ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>).</s><s>With CTZ present, the prob open values for GluA4wt and GluA4 L484Y receptors were not different (0.89 vs. 0.86, p ¼ 0.68, two-tailed Student's t-test; n ¼ 3 and five patches), as was the case for the steady-state P open values (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>).</s><s>The results suggest that when CTZ is bound to the D1-D1 interface, GluA4-wt and GluA4 L484Y receptors are functionally similar and that CTZ binding masks the effect of the LY mutation to speed activation.</s><s>In contrast, for GluA4-Lc receptors, CTZ caused a further increase in prob open (further decreased the proportion of blank trials where the receptor desensitized without opening).</s><s>The prob open values in the absence and presence of CTZ were significantly different for GluA4-Lc (p ¼ 0.035, two-tailed Student's t-test; n ¼ 6 and nine patches, 760 and 1250 total trials, respectively; Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>).</s><s>This result presumably reflects the effect of CTZ to reduce long desensitization gaps (see below), and the paucity of blanks in the records (12 of a total 1250 trials) indicates that the b/d ratio (Fig. <ref type="figure">7 a</ref>) is large for GluA4-Lc receptors in CTZ.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Open time distributions</head><p><s>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> gives values for the mean duration of openings to each of the four open levels detected in the single-channel records for the three GluA4 receptor types in the absence and presence of CTZ.</s><s>Most of the open-time distributions were adequately fitted with a single exponential component, although occasionally there was evidence of a small additional component.</s><s>In the latter case, the open duration was taken as the weighted mean of the two components.</s><s><ref type="bibr">FIGURE 7</ref> The L484Y and Lurcher mutations speed activation.</s><s>(a) Given here is the simplified AMPA receptor kinetic mechanism that shows glutamate binding, LBD closing/opening, and the parallel nature of activation and desensitization.</s><s>(b) Shown here are population currents (dotted lines, averages of 15-30 trials) evoked by fast applications of 10 mM glutamate for GluA4-wt, GluA4 L484Y, and GluA4-Lc receptors (the applications were 100-500 ms in duration so the vast majority of the responses are off-scale).</s><s>The currents have been aligned to the onset of the glutamate application and the rising phases of the currents were fitted with H-H equations (solid lines).</s><s>The fits were used to calculate 10-90% rise-times for each trace, which for the traces shown were 301 ms (GluA4 L484Y), 309 ms (GluA4-Lc), and 384 ms (GluA4-wt).</s><s>(c) Mean rise-times (bars indicate mean 5 SE) for the three GluA4 receptor types (six patches per group).</s><s>The value for GluA4 L484Y was significantly different from the value for GluA4-wt receptors (*, p &lt; 0.05) when the three groups were compared with a one-way ANOVA.</s><s>A two-tailed Student's t-test comparison of the results for GluA4-wt and GluA4-Lc receptors gave p ¼ 0.066.</s></p><p><s>Individual dwells at the various open levels were brief, typically 200-300 ms (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>).</s><s>As we reported before for GluA2 receptors <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref>, the majority of these events were bounded on either side by dwells in an adjacent conductance level, consistent with previous conclusions that transitions between conductance levels reflect incremental changes in the number of subunits contributing to gating <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50)</ref>.</s><s>When the mean dwell times for the four open levels and six groups in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> were compared with two-way ANOVA, the only significant differences between conductance levels (with one exception) were that openings to O1 were significantly longer than openings to larger levels.</s><s>Open times for GluA4-wt and GluA4-Lc receptors in control external solution were not significantly different from each other but were significantly longer than open times for the other four groups (none of which were significantly different from each other).</s><s>Thus, neither the presence of CTZ nor either mutation caused a significant increase in open times relative to GluA4-wt receptors, suggesting that the phenotypic changes in desensitization and deactivation evident in ensemble currents do not arise from direct stabilization of open states, but rather from a change in the burst properties (see below).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Shut times include a desensitized state resistant to CTZ and the LY and Lc mutations</head><p><s>In contrast to the minimal changes in open times, the shuttime distributions were substantially different for the six groups of results given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>.</s><s>Three or four components gave adequate fits to the distributions in most cases.</s><s>Shuttime distributions for GluA4-wt receptors were fitted with five components.</s><s>Although inclusion of the fifth component did not always significantly improve the fit <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(31)</ref>, it did in some cases.</s><s>Consideration of all the results convinced us inclusion of the additional component was justified and led to more sensible comparisons with the shut-time distributions for the other data sets.</s><s>Examples of shut-time distributions from individual patches for the six different groups are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>.</s><s>The mean time constants and relative areas for the shut-time components detected for each group are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>.</s></p><p><s>For each data set in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>, the two components of brief shuttings are likely to arise from transitions of glutamatebound receptors through closed states along the activation pathway.</s><s>Estimation of the forward rate constant for binding to individual GluA4-wt subunits (from double-jump experiments) gave a value of 1 Â 10 7 M À1 s À1 (9).</s><s>Thus, at 10 mM glutamate, binding kinetics do not make a significant contribution to the shut times in our one-receptor records.</s><s>The mean time constants of the two briefest shuttime components are longer for GluA4-wt receptors than for the other five groups.</s><s>However, small-conductance openings were much more common for GluA4-wt receptors in the absence of CTZ, which would limit the resolution of brief shuttings within individual receptor activations.</s><s>Given the multiple types of open-open and open-closed transitions <ref type="bibr">FIGURE 8</ref> Shut times for wild-type and mutant GluA4 receptors.</s><s>Shown here are examples of shut-time distributions for GluA4-wt, GluA4 L484Y, and GluA4-Lc receptors activated by glutamate without (a) or with (b) CTZ and fit with 3-5 exponential components using log-binned fitting procedures (dashed lines).</s><s>(c) Shown here are portions (500 ms in length) of activity in one-receptor patches recorded at À100 mV in 100 mM CTZ for GluA4-wt (left), GluA4 L484Y (middle), and GluA4-Lc (right) receptors.</s><s>Singlechannel openings are downward.</s><s>The examples were selected to illustrate the type of shuttings (at arrowheads) that contribute to the 5-9 ms component seen in all conditions except GluA4wt without CTZ, which reflects a form of shortlived desensitization.</s></p><p><s>in the records, there is no consistent time resolution that is equally good for all the different types of events (51) and we have not attempted to quantify this limitation, but it likely contributes to the longer brief shuttings for wildtype receptors.</s><s>If, as we suggest above, the GluA4 L484Y and GluA4-Lc mutations speed activation, this would also be expected to shorten the duration of dwell times in closed states that lie along the activation pathway, so some of the difference may be real.</s></p><p><s>The time constant for the third component detected in shut-time distributions for GluA4-wt receptors (20.8 ms) is similar to the mean duration of dwell times in desensitized states that was estimated for the same receptors from two-pulse recovery protocols (18-21 ms ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>)).</s><s>The two additional components (190 and 1400 ms, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>) presumably account for the incomplete recovery typically seen in two-pulse protocols when the longest recovery intervals are 100 ms <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>.</s><s>None of these three components were large enough to fit when similar data were collected in CTZ.</s><s>Their virtual elimination in CTZ suggests that they represent visits to desensitized states that arise from rearrangement of the D1-D1 interfaces within LBD dimers <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Long shut times were also present in the continuous recordings at saturating glutamate for the GluA4 L484Y and GluA4-Lc mutants, although such shuttings were less frequent than for wild-type receptors.</s><s>The longest duration shut-time components were absent for both mutants in CTZ, indicating that residual desensitization due to separation of the dimer interface remains for GluA4 L484Y receptors and also occurs for GluA4-Lc.</s><s>Although the frequency of such events was low for both GluA4 L484Y and GluA4-Lc, and the time constants varied considerably, shuttings that lasted tens (even hundreds) of milliseconds were seen for both types of mutant receptor in each patch examined in the absence of CTZ.</s><s>Thus, for both mutants, individual receptors spend a significant fraction of their time in desensitized states.</s></p><p><s>Strikingly, for each data set except for GluA4-wt receptors without CTZ, we could detect a shut-time component with a time constant of 5-9 ms (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>).</s><s>The duration of these shuttings is too long for them to reflect dwells in closed states along the activation pathway.</s><s>Both the rise-times reported here, and latency-to-first-opening measurements <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref>, support this conclusion, and the shuttings seem more likely to represent visits to a short-lived desensitized state.</s><s>If this is the case, such visits are the predominant type of desensitization for both GluA4 L484Y and GluA4-Lc, and they are resistant to modulation by CTZ, because such events are present for both GluA4-wt and GluA4 L484Y receptors in 100 mM CTZ; they are the predominant type of shutting for GluA4-Lc receptors when CTZ is present in the external solution (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>).</s><s>The shuttings indicated by arrows in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref> d are examples of events representative of this shut-time component.</s><s>Additional examples observed in CTZ for GluA4-wt, GluA4 L484Y, and GluA4-Lc receptors are illustrated in Fig. <ref type="figure">8 c</ref>.</s><s>Whether this type of desensitization is also present for wild-type receptors (but is missed because of the complexity of the shut-time distributions), or it is only enabled when conventional desensitization due to D1-D1 interface separation is reduced, is unclear from our data.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Burst durations</head><p><s>Activations of ligand-gated receptor-channels typically occur in a burst, a series of openings separated by brief shuttings and bounded on either side by longer closings.</s><s>Bursts can be defined by setting a critical time, t crit , that separates brief shuttings (gaps within bursts) from longer closed times (gaps between bursts) <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(52,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">53)</ref>.</s><s>The duration of these bursts is exponentially distributed and the time constants obtained by fitting the distribution of burst durations give the mean duration of individual receptor activations.</s></p><p><s>Bursts are a common feature of AMPA receptor records.</s><s>The character of these bursts differs from that described classically for nicotinic acetylcholine receptors <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(53)</ref>, or for NMDA receptors <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(54)</ref>, because AMPA receptor bursts consist primarily of transitions between adjacent open levels rather than individual openings separated by brief shuttings <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38)</ref>.</s><s>We defined bursts by choosing t crit values (2-5 ms, Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>) between the time constants for the second and third briefest components in the shut-time distributions from the same one-channel patches (minimizing the total number of misclassifications).</s></p><p><s>Given the conditions of our experiments (continuous application of a saturating concentration of glutamate), bursts begin when the receptor exits desensitized states and opens, and bursts end when the receptor reenters desensitized states.</s><s>The duration of bursts is determined by the rate constants for transitions into desensitized states and the proportion of time the receptor spends in states from which such transitions occur.</s><s>If the proportion of time spent in such predesensitized states is similar, then burst durations give an indication of the relative rate constants for entry into desensitized states (d in Fig. <ref type="figure">7 a</ref>) for the six data sets in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Examples of burst duration distributions are shown in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">9</ref>. Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> gives mean burst durations for each of the six data sets.</s><s>To simplify the comparison when multiple components were detected for burst durations from individual patches, we calculated weighted means in which the time constants were multiplied by their relative amplitudes (fitting done in Igor Pro) and summed.</s><s>The results in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref> indicate that CTZ prolongs bursts for GluA4-wt receptors 24-fold.</s><s>Burst durations are 140 times greater for GluA4 L484Y receptors than for GluA4-wt, and are further prolonged by CTZ.</s><s>In contrast, burst duration is only prolonged 16-fold for GluA4-Lc receptors (relative to GluA4-wt) and CTZ has a larger additional effect than for GluA4 L484Y.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>The fast desensitization of AMPA receptors, and its block by pharmacological tools and mutations, has been extensively studied over the last 25 years.</s><s>However, the activity of individual receptors in corresponding conditions is much less widely reported.</s><s>By examining patches containing just one receptor, we could observe unexpected features in the activation of wild-type AMPA receptors and two well-studied mutant receptors in the presence and absence of the allosteric modulator CTZ.</s><s>First, we show that CTZ and the LY mutation, despite a similar site of action, have different effects on channel gating.</s><s>Secondly, we can clearly resolve regular visits to stable desensitized states in all conditions, even if blockers of desensitization reduce the frequency of these visits.</s><s>Third, dwell-time distributions revealed a shut state with a mean duration too long to be involved in the activation pathway, but which was not blocked by the either the LY or Lc mutations or by CTZ.</s><s>Overall, the experiments, to our knowledge, provide new evidence for a clear difference in action between CTZ and the LY mutant, with the former acting purely on desensitization, and the latter acting additionally on agonist affinity and/or receptor gating.</s><s>The different effects on activation and desensitization also result in different effects on the prevalence of receptor substates (see below).</s></p><p><s>In high concentrations of glutamate, an individual receptor is barely active-the steady-state P open of GluA4-wt receptors is low (1-5%).</s><s>At a concentration of 100 mM, CTZ virtually eliminates the three longest components in distributions of shut times for GluA4-wt.</s><s>These long components have time constants that are consistent with them representing visits to desensitized states, because they agree well with previous data from two-pulse recovery protocols with the same receptors <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>.</s><s>The frequency of similar long-lived shuttings is substantially less for both GluA4 mutants with reduced desensitization, although neither mutation eliminates such events.</s><s>These findings are consistent both with the much larger steady-state currents and the residual presence of significant fade in the population currents for both GluA4 L484Y and GluA4-Lc, as was shown previously for the corresponding GluA1 mutants <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25)</ref>.</s><s>Our results with GluA2 L483Y are consistent with a previous report that the decline of ensemble currents, although present, is less evident for homomeric channels formed from the (b) Shown here are corresponding distributions from the same three patches obtained in the presence of 100 mM CTZ.</s><s>The weighted mean burst durations from the fits are increased $18-fold for Glu4-wt receptors in CTZ (51.1 vs. 3.66 ms).</s><s>The presence of CTZ has little effect on burst durations for the L484Y mutation, but bursts for GluA4 L484Y in control solution are longer by more than a factor of 50 compared with GluA4-wt receptors (295 vs. 3.66 ms).</s><s>Burst durations for GluA-Lc receptors (17 ms) are longer than for GluA4-wt receptors but shorter than for GluA4 L484Y, and the prolongation in the presence of CTZ (12-fold) is greater than for GluA4 L484Y.</s></p><p><s>GluA2 core subunit <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>.</s><s>These differences in population currents do not have a facile explanation from the dimer interfaces between LBDs; the GluA4 LBD active dimer interface is very similar to that of GluA2, as previously shown (PMID: 19102704).</s></p><p><s>As noted before <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(55)</ref>, the absence of a detectable decline in ensemble currents is not in itself evidence that desensitization is removed.</s><s>In CTZ, population currents for GluA4-wt and GluA4 L484Y receptors showed no evidence of decay, yet the P open values for these receptors indicate that the receptors still spend &gt;10% of their time in stable closed states that are indistinguishable from desensitized states.</s><s>The data also suggest that CTZ does not remove all forms of desensitization; although the current responses are approximately square, mutant receptors visit desensitized states multiple times per second.</s><s>All receptors studied here spent a substantial fraction of their time in such states.</s><s>Our single-channel data support previous reports that some residual desensitization remains even for flip isoforms in CTZ <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43)</ref>.</s><s>These observations might also provide an explanation for why numerous structures of the full-length receptor have been crystallized with a closed ion channel domain despite being bound by high-affinity modulators and agonists.</s></p><p><s>Perhaps the most interesting finding from the analysis of shut times is the presence of a shut-time component for GluA4-wt in CTZ, and for the GluA4 L484Y and GluA4-Lc mutant receptors with and without CTZ, which is too long to arise from transitions along the activation pathway.</s><s>This component seems to represent a form of short-lived desensitization that is resistant to modulation by CTZ.</s><s>Given the complexity of the shut-time data for GluA4-wt receptors in the absence of CTZ, our data do not exclude the presence of similar shuttings in the records for wildtype channels.</s><s>The similar mean duration values for this component (5-9 ms) in the other five data sets do not require that all such shuttings arise from similar conformational rearrangements or speak directly to the receptor regions involved.</s><s>With these caveats, however, the resistance of these shuttings to CTZ, as well as their prominence in the GluA4-Lc records and the location of the Lurcher mutation at the extracellular end of the SYTANLAAF motif near the ion channel gate (3), suggest that the short-lived desensitization may arise from conformational changes in the linker regions <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref> or the gate itself rather than the D1-D1 interface.</s><s>The fact that the events are most prominent when steady-state P open is high raises the possibility that they represent desensitization from the open state, which is rare when conventional closed-state desensitization is intact.</s><s>Whatever the source of these CTZ-resistant desensitization gaps, they make a significant contribution to desensitization for both GluA4 L484Y and GluA4-Lc, as well as for GluA4wt receptors in the presence of CTZ.</s></p><p><s>It has been shown before that CTZ reduces the amplitude of currents through LY mutant receptors <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(43)</ref>.</s><s>Our singlechannel data show that this is primarily the result of the reduced prevalence of large-conductance openings.</s><s>The conductance of the open levels seen for GluA4 L484Y is also modestly reduced, although some of this may be related to truncation of the amplitude of brief events because the open-channel noise was especially large for GluA4 L484Y receptors in CTZ.</s><s>Comparison of the structures of the GluA2 L483Y LBD without and with CTZ bound confirmed that the geometry of the LBD dimer is unchanged by CTZ binding and that CTZ binds to residues that otherwise constitute part of the interface.</s><s>The single-channel data show that the effect of CTZ on conventional desensitization for wild-type and LY mutant receptors is similar; CTZ eliminated the longest shut-time component for GluA4 L484Y and increased the steady-state P open value for these receptors.</s><s>Interestingly, however, CTZ reduced prob open for GluA4 L484Y receptors, and the P open and prob open values for GluA4 L484Y in CTZ were virtually identical to the corresponding values for GluA4-wt receptors in CTZ, as were the structures of the D1-D1 interface for wild-type and LY LBDs with CTZ bound.</s><s>The faster rise-times and larger prob open values observed for both GluA4 L484Y and GluA4-Lc are evidence that both mutations speed receptor activation.</s><s>Our single-channel and structural data indicate that the speeding of activation seen for GluA4 L484Y receptors is blocked when CTZ is bound at the dimer interface.</s></p><p><s>In part because glutamate binding to a single GluA subunit is sufficient to trigger desensitization <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30)</ref>, any manipulation that significantly shifts receptor occupancy away from desensitized states toward open states is expected to increase the prevalence of large-conductance openings.</s><s>For individual AMPA receptor subunits, the probability that they contribute to receptor gating under steady-state conditions is strongly influenced by the ratio b/d in Fig. <ref type="figure">7 A</ref>; the greater this ratio, the more likely that multiple subunits will simultaneously be in the permissive O state and the greater the prevalence of openings to large-conductance substates <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">50)</ref>.</s><s>Thus, the effect of CTZ to increase the prevalence of larger substates for GluA4-wt receptors results from its action to reduce d, the rate constant for entry into desensitized states.</s><s>Both the LY and Lc mutants also increased the prevalence of large-conductance substates.</s><s>In these cases, however, CTZ reduced this prevalence for GluA4 L484Y and increased this prevalence for GluA4-Lc.</s><s>The substate results are consistent with the corresponding results for prob open values (which also depend strongly on the b/d ratio) and the conclusion that both mutant receptors promote the activation pathway (increase b) but that they do so differently.</s><s>For the GluA4 L484Y receptor, the effect on activation localizes to the dimer interface and is prevented when CTZ (which does not share this effect on activation) is bound.</s><s>Although our results do not delineate the structural basis for these findings, recent work indicates that the dimer interface plays an important role in initiating receptor activation <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(56,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">57)</ref>.</s><s>For GluA4-Lc, where the mutation is located near the activation gate itself <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13)</ref> The effect of CTZ on single-channel currents confirms independently that the LY mutant subunits desensitize at the D1 interface, because the CTZ binding sites are buried and almost certainly inaccessible when the D1-D1 interface is intact.</s><s>The tail of cyclothiazide is solvent exposed when it is bound.</s><s>However, the bulk of the benzothiadiazide of CTZ is incompatible with transit through the narrow entryway to the binding site (see Fig. <ref type="figure">S1</ref>).</s><s>These observations suggest that CTZ binding to the active dimer must be very slow, if it occurs at all, and they suggest that CTZ may bind initially to dimers with broken D1 dimer interfaces <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The low potency and low water solubility of CTZ mandates that electrophysiological recordings were done at nonsaturating concentrations, opening the door to heterogeneous occupancy of the CTZ binding sites in active D1 dimer interfaces.</s><s>In contrast, the LY mutation is always present in double copy.</s><s>Although crystal structures did not reveal major structural differences, it is likely that the properties of CTZ and its binding site contribute to altered dimer dynamics that translate into the unitary properties we observed.</s><s>The LY mutation is located only two residues away from the universally conserved binding site arginine.</s><s>Therefore, it seems possible that the LY mutation not only stabilizes the dimer interface, but might also promote LBD closure once glutamate docks, and that this effect of the mutation is prevented when CTZ is bound at the interface.</s><s>There is evidence from cross-linking, FRET, and LRET studies that the LBD adopts multiple apo conformations and that the D1-D1 interface may not be fully assembled in preactivation states <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(58)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(59)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">(60)</ref>.</s><s>In addition, recent cryo-EM studies emphasize the flexible nature of the extracellular domains and emphasize the dynamic role they likely play in receptor gating <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">61,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b61">62)</ref>.</s><s>Computational approaches may shed further light on the processes of dimer stabilization and modulator binding <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(63)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Speeding activation, like slowing microscopic desensitization, would be expected to favor openings to largeconductance levels <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(30)</ref>; both effects increase the likelihood that multiple individual subunits can contribute to activation gating.</s><s>The mutations studied here seem to both reduce the rate constant for entering desensitized states (d in Fig. <ref type="figure">7 a</ref>) and increase the speed of activation.</s><s>In contrast, CTZ slowed rather than speeded the rise-times of population currents.</s><s>Whereas it has been reported that CTZ slows deactivation of AMPA receptors, CTZ increased the rate of deactivation for the GluA4 and GluA2 LY mutants, as shown previously for the corresponding mutation in GluA1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(43)</ref>, and had only modest effects on deactivation for GluA4-wt and GluA4-Lc receptors.</s><s>Neither the mutations, nor CTZ, prolonged open times.</s><s>Our results indicate that the primary effect of CTZ is a large decrease in the rate constant for entry into desensitized states.</s><s>We believe that the modest slowing of deactivation decays seen here (and in many prior publications) for wild-type receptors indicates that desensitization can contribute to the decay of the population currents evoked by deactivation protocols.</s><s>It also seems likely that the faster deactivation seen in CTZ for the LY mutants arises because CTZ occludes the effect of the mutation to speed activation.</s><s>An effect of the LY mutation to speed activation would be expected to prolong deactivation because, on average, there will be more channel openings before the LBDs open and allow glutamate to dissociate (increased b/CO in Fig. <ref type="figure">7 a</ref>).</s><s>We would also note, however, that our results do not exclude a direct effect of either mutation to stabilize the closed LBD (decrease in CO).</s><s>When desensitization is reduced, any changes that increase the b/CO ratio would be expected to increase the prevalence of large-conductance openings, slow the rate at which glutamate dissociates from the receptor, and increase the apparent affinity of glutamate by decreasing EC 50 values relative to those for wild-type receptors.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p><s>The largely nondesensitizing phenotypes of the GluA4 L484Y and GluA4-Lc mutant receptors reflect both enhanced activation and reduced entry into desensitization.</s><s>Both these effects shift steady-state receptor occupancy toward open states.</s><s>Removal of desensitization is incomplete, however, and individual mutant receptors spend significant fractions of their time in desensitized states.</s><s>Our singlechannel data reveal, to our knowledge, a novel form of AMPA receptor desensitization, which is short-lived, resistant to modulation by CTZ, and likely arises from structural rearrangements away from the dimer interface.</s><s>Cyclothiazide reduces the mean unitary conductance and speeds deactivation of LY mutant receptors by blocking the effect of the mutation to speed activation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SUPPORTING MATERIAL</head><p><s>One figure is available at http://www.biophysj.org/biophysj/supplemental/</s><s>S0006-3495(17)30861-5.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIGURE 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 2 Cyclothiazide reduces population currents through GluA4 L484Y mutant receptors.</s><s>(a) Shown here are currents evoked by 500 ms applications of 10 mM glutamate in an outside-out patch containing GluA4 L484Y receptors in the absence (black trace) and presence of 100 mM CTZ (red trace).</s><s>Although CTZ reduces the fade of the current during the application, it also attenuates the amplitude of the glutamate-evoked current.</s><s>(b) Given here are examples of unitary currents evoked by 500 ms applications of 10 mM glutamate in an outside-out patch containing a single active GluA4 L484Y mutant receptor in control external solution (top) and in the presence of 100 mM CTZ (bottom).</s><s>In control solution, each trial shown contains bursts of openings separated by long periods (&gt;4 ms) when the receptor is inactive.</s><s>The long shut periods presumably reflect sojourns in desensitized states.</s><s>Such long shut periods are still evident in CTZ (bottom three traces), but the bursts tend to be longer in duration.</s><s>Note the increase in openchannel noise when CTZ is present and the reduction in the mean unitary current.</s><s>(c and d) Given here are portions of recordings from another one-receptor patch during the continuous application of 10 mM glutamate in the absence (c) and presence (d) of 100 mM CTZ.</s><s>In both (c and d), the five 5 s segments show 25 s of continuous data.</s><s>Although the desensitization gaps are shorter in CTZ (d), they are still present (arrows point to examples).</s><s>Calibration bars in (c and d) are identical.</s><s>(e) Given here is a portion of the record in (d) on an expanded timescale.</s><s>The SKM idealization (red) is superposed on the current trace (black).</s><s>Amplitude levels were estimated from a maximum log-likelihood fit to the entire 5 min record (50 kHz sampling).</s><s>To see this figure in color, go online.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,53.41,356.88,322.79,322.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FIGURE 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 3 GluA4 wild-type and mutant channels open to multiple conductance levels in the absence and presence of CTZ.</s><s>(a-d) Shown here are single-channel currents during the continuous application of 10 mM glutamate and amplitude histograms for the entire data set from the same patches for GluA4-wt (a and b) and GluA L484Y (c and d) receptors in normal control solution (a and c) and in 100 mM CTZ (b and d).</s><s>Data were low-pass filtered at 4 kHz and sampled at 50 kHz.</s><s>Amplitude histograms of single-channel open events (inward currents at -100 mV) from each patch were fitted with the mixture of four Gaussian components (solid line; individual components shown as dashed lines).</s><s>Amplitudes were the mean value of data points within individual open events identified by SKM idealization of the entire data set.</s><s>For the L484Y mutant receptors, but not wild-type GluA4 receptors, CTZ reduced the mean conductance estimates for each of the four open levels detected.</s><s>Calibrations in (a) apply to all four panels.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,53.41,398.95,322.79,302.51" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>FIGURE 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 5 Structural comparison of GluA2_LBD_L483Y and GluA2_LBD_L483Y_CTZ.</s><s>(a) Shown here is structural alignment of the dimeric GluA2_LBD_L483Y in complex with glutamate (purple) and the corresponding complex with CTZ (cyan, PDB: 3TKD).</s><s>The CTZ molecules, binding between the D1 interface, are shown in sphere representation.</s><s>(b) Given here are features of the D1 active dimer interface.</s><s>A single protomer is shown, face-on to the interface, for each complex.</s><s>Atoms participating in the D1 interface are colored yellow on the surface representation of Chain A of GluA2_LBD_L483Y (left) and GluA2_LBD_ L483Y_CTZ (right).</s><s>Atoms participating purely in CTZ binding are colored orange.</s><s>Atoms that participate both in the interprotomer interface and CTZ binding are colored dark green.</s><s>The inset indicates the orientation of protomer and the bound CTZ molecules.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,53.46,58.51,239.02,231.65" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>The effect of CTZ on prob open values is relevant to the effect of the mutants to speed activation.</s><s>For GluA4 L484Y, although CTZ increased steady-state P open and eliminated residual long shuttings (desensitization gaps, see below), CTZ decreased prob open values (0.96 vs. 0.86 without and with CTZ, p ¼ 0.057, two-tailed Student's t-test; n ¼ 6 and five patches, 880 and 940 total trials, respectively; Table</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>FIGURE 9</head><label>9</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 9  Burst durations for GluA-wt, GluA4 L484Y, and GluA4-Lc receptors in the absence and presence of CTZ.</s><s>(a) Shown here are examples of burst-duration distributions for the three GluA4 receptor types.</s><s>Bursts were defined as series of openings to any open level that were separated by shut periods &lt;4 ms in duration.</s><s>Each distribution was fitted with two exponential components with the indicated time constants (in milliseconds) and relative amplitudes.</s><s>(b) Shown here are corresponding distributions from the same three patches obtained in the presence of 100 mM CTZ.</s><s>The weighted mean burst durations from the fits are increased $18-fold for Glu4-wt receptors in CTZ (51.1 vs. 3.66 ms).</s><s>The presence of CTZ has little effect on burst durations for the L484Y mutation, but bursts for GluA4 L484Y in control solution are longer by more than a factor of 50 compared with GluA4-wt receptors (295 vs. 3.66 ms).</s><s>Burst durations for GluA-Lc receptors (17 ms) are longer than for GluA4-wt receptors but shorter than for GluA4 L484Y, and the prolongation in the presence of CTZ (12-fold) is greater than for GluA4 L484Y.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="14,92.35,58.51,418.28,262.04" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>, CTZ further reduces the d without blocking the mutation-associated increases in b, thus further increasing the b/d ratio, steady-state P open , prob open , and the prevalence of large-conductance substates.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>W</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>.Z. designed and performed research, analyzed data, and wrote and edited the article.</s><s>C.E. designed and performed research, analyzed data, and wrote and edited the article.</s><s>A.M.W. performed research, analyzed data, and edited the article.</s><s>I.R. designed and performed research, analyzed data, and wrote and edited the article.</s><s>A.J.R.P designed research and wrote and edited the article.</s><s>J.R.H. designed research and wrote and edited the article.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,53.41,386.76,322.79,291.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,53.41,466.47,322.79,215.38" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,53.41,58.57,322.79,277.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="12,53.41,409.04,322.79,297.92" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE 1 Substate</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Properties for Wild-Type, L484Y, and Lurcher GluA4 Receptors SE values are from five or six patches.</s><s>Statistical comparisons are given in the Results.</s><s>Insets show normalized decays.</s><s>(d) Decays of the current after glutamate removal were on average $3 times longer for the GluA2 L483Y mutant than in any other condition (p ¼ 0.009).</s><s>Solid circles represent the traces in (c).</s><s>To see this figure in color, go online.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>GluA4-wt</cell><cell cols="2">GluA4 L484Y</cell><cell></cell><cell>GluA4-Lc</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Glutamate</cell><cell>Glutamate þ CTZ</cell><cell>Glutamate</cell><cell>Glutamate þ CTZ</cell><cell>Glutamate</cell><cell>Glutamate þ CTZ</cell></row><row><cell>Conductance (pS)</cell><cell>O1</cell><cell>8.5 5 0.2</cell><cell>9.6 5 0.5</cell><cell>17.3 5 1.6</cell><cell>14.3 5 1.2</cell><cell>8.7 5 0.8</cell><cell>12.9 5 0.3</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>O2</cell><cell>18.9 5 0.5</cell><cell>18.0 5 0.7</cell><cell>26.8 5 0.9</cell><cell>23.7 5 1.4</cell><cell>16.3 5 0.9</cell><cell>21.3 5 0.3</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>O3</cell><cell>29.3 5 0.5</cell><cell>25.6 5 1.3</cell><cell>34.7 5 0.6</cell><cell>31.5 5 1.5</cell><cell>25.1 5 0.5</cell><cell>28.3 5 0.6</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>O4</cell><cell>40.1 5 0.3</cell><cell>36.3 5 2.6</cell><cell>40 5 0.9</cell><cell>36.4 5 2.0</cell><cell>33.7 5 0.6</cell><cell>36.1 5 0.8</cell></row><row><cell>Relative occupancy (%)</cell><cell>O1</cell><cell>79.4 5 4.2</cell><cell>34.6 5 3.3</cell><cell>12.2 5 1.6</cell><cell>31.1 5 2.9</cell><cell>40.0 5 8.4</cell><cell>4.3 5 1.1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>O2</cell><cell>16.4 5 3.5</cell><cell>37.5 5 1.8</cell><cell>35.5 5 4.3</cell><cell>44.6 5 1.7</cell><cell>22.1 5 3.9</cell><cell>20.2 5 2.2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>O3</cell><cell>3.21 5 0.89</cell><cell>21.7 5 2.9</cell><cell>24.4 5 1.4</cell><cell>17.0 5 2.0</cell><cell>26.2 5 5.7</cell><cell>51.5 5 4.2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>O4</cell><cell>0.97 5 0.35</cell><cell>8.36 5 2.0</cell><cell>28.0 5 6.1</cell><cell>7.2 5 2.5</cell><cell>11.7 5 2.7</cell><cell>24.0 5 3.8</cell></row><row><cell cols="8">Single-channel currents were recorded in outside-out patches in response to applications of saturating glutamate (10 mM) for GluA4-wt, GluA4 L484Y, and</cell></row><row><cell>GluA4-Lc). Mean 5</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>(a).</s><s>(c) Examples of responses to 10 mM glutamate in the presence and absence of CTZ.</s><s>Note the much longer decay of the L483Y mutant, which is truncated in the presence of CTZ (red trace).</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 2 Data</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Collection and Refinement Statistics</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>GluA2_LBD_LY</cell></row></table><note><p><s>aValues in parentheses are for the highest-resolution shell.</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>TABLE 3 Unitary</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Kinetics of GluA4-wt, GluA4 L505Y, and GluA4-Lc Receptors</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">GluA4-wt</cell><cell cols="2">GluA4 L484Y</cell><cell cols="2">GluA4-Lc</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>10 mM Glu</cell><cell>Glu þ CTZ</cell><cell>10 mM Glu</cell><cell>Glu þ CTZ</cell><cell>10 mM Glu</cell><cell>Glu þ CTZ</cell></row><row><cell>Steady-state P open a</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.03 5 0.01</cell><cell>0.86 5 0.03</cell><cell>0.71 5 0.12</cell><cell>0.87 5 0.02</cell><cell>0.56 5 0.06</cell><cell>0.95 5 0.01</cell></row><row><cell>Prob open b</cell><cell></cell><cell>0.76 5 0.08</cell><cell>0.89 5 0.03</cell><cell>0.96 5 0.01</cell><cell>0.86 5 0.05</cell><cell>0.91 5 0.04</cell><cell>0.99 5 0.01</cell></row><row><cell>Open times (ms) c</cell><cell>O1</cell><cell>0.77 5 0.14</cell><cell>0.25 5 0.02</cell><cell>0.18 5 0.01</cell><cell>0.22 5 0.01</cell><cell>0.53 5 0.06</cell><cell>0.28 5 0.05</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>O2</cell><cell>0.30 5 0.04</cell><cell>0.19 5 0.01</cell><cell>0.22 5 0.02</cell><cell>0.24 5 0.01</cell><cell>0.20 5 0.04</cell><cell>0.19 5 0.01</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>O3</cell><cell>0.23 5 0.01</cell><cell>0.20 5 0.02</cell><cell>0.24 5 0.02</cell><cell>0.19 5 0.01</cell><cell>0.32 5 0.03</cell><cell>0.31 5 0.01</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>O4</cell><cell>0.43 5 0.07</cell><cell>0.34 5 0.08</cell><cell>0.38 5 0.06</cell><cell>0.23 5 0.02</cell><cell>0.23 5 0.03</cell><cell>0.26 5 0.03</cell></row><row><cell>Shut times a</cell><cell>t1 (ms) area (%)</cell><cell>0.79 5 0.25</cell><cell>0.27 5 0.05</cell><cell>0.29 5 0.08</cell><cell>0.26 5 0.05</cell><cell>0.19 5 0.12</cell><cell>0.09 5 0.02</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(46.3 5 6.07)</cell><cell>(38.6 5 5.6)</cell><cell>(47.6 5 11.5)</cell><cell>(56.7 5 8)</cell><cell>(41.2 5 8.7)</cell><cell>(13.1 5 4.4)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>t2 (ms) area (%)</cell><cell>3.13 5 1</cell><cell>1.23 5 0.37</cell><cell>1.82 5 0.27</cell><cell>0.94 5 0.18</cell><cell>0.95 5 0.26</cell><cell>1.62 5 0.48</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(27.0 5 2.1)</cell><cell>(57.5 5 5.31)</cell><cell>(24.3 5 6.2)</cell><cell>(39.3 5 7.1)</cell><cell>(19.6 5 2.5)</cell><cell>(9.2 5 4.2)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>t3 (ms) area (%)</cell><cell>20.8 5 3.3</cell><cell>7.98 5 3.4</cell><cell>7.5 5 0.85</cell><cell>4.7 5 1.04</cell><cell>8.67 5 2.52</cell><cell>7.6 5 0.4</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(14.9 5 5.7)</cell><cell>(3.83 5 0.72)</cell><cell>(24.8 5 10.5)</cell><cell>(3.83 5 1.5)</cell><cell>(32.5 5 7.8)</cell><cell>(82.1 5 8.7)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>t4 (ms) area (%)</cell><cell>188.9 5 72</cell><cell></cell><cell>167 5 37</cell><cell></cell><cell>36 5 12</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(8.4 5 1.7)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(3.1 5 1.4)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(6.7 5 1.4)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>t5 (ms) area (%)</cell><cell>1402 5 439</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(3.1 5 1.1)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Burst duration (ms) a</cell><cell></cell><cell>2.90 5 0.29</cell><cell>68.6 5 8.2</cell><cell>402 5 196</cell><cell>582 5 201</cell><cell>46.7 5 6.8</cell><cell>245 5 25</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(t crit 3-5)</cell><cell>(t crit 2-3)</cell><cell>(t crit 3-5)</cell><cell>(t crit 3-5)</cell><cell>(t crit 3-5)</cell><cell>(t crit 3-5)</cell></row></table><note><p><s>Single-channel currents were recorded in outside-out patches in response to applications of saturating glutamate (10 mM) for GluA4-wt, GluA4 L484Y, and GluA4-Lc.</s><s>The probability of opening (prob open ) was defined as: 1 -(number of blanks/number of trials) in fast application experiments where repeated applications of 10 mM glutamate were made at 2 s intervals.</s><s>Statistical comparisons are given in the Results.</s><s>a Values are mean 5 SE from 5-6 patches.</s><s>b Values are mean 5 SE from 3-9 patches.</s><s>c Values are mean 5 SE from 4-6 patches.</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Biophysical Journal 113, 2218-2235, November 21, 2017 2221</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Biophysical Journal 113, 2218-2235, November 21, 2017 2223</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Biophysical Journal 113, 2218-2235, November 21, 2017 2225</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Biophysical Journal 113, 2218-2235, November 21, 2017 2229</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Biophysical Journal 113, 2218-2235, November 21, 2017 2231</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>(NIH) grant NS057725 and Yale University grant to J.R.H., the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) ''DynIon'' FOR 2518 to A.J.R.P., the DFG Cluster of Excellence ''NeuroCure'' (EXC-257) to A.J.R.P., and an Erwin-Schro ¨dinger Postdoctoral Fellowship (J3682-B21) of the Austrian Science Fund (FWF) to C.E. A.J.R.P. is a Heisenberg Professor, supported by the DFG (DFG PL619-3).</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glutamate receptor ion channels: structure, regulation, and function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Traynelis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wollmuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dingledine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacol. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="405" to="496" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional insights from glutamate receptor ion channel structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="337" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and gating of tetrameric glutamate receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Sobolevsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">593</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="38" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanisms for activation and antagonism of an AMPA-sensitive glutamate receptor: crystal structures of the GluR2 ligand binding core</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Armstrong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gouaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="181" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure of a glutamatereceptor ligand-binding core in complex with kainate</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Armstrong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gouaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">395</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="913" to="917" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural basis for AMPA receptor activation and ligand selectivity: crystal structures of five agonist complexes with the GluR2 ligand-binding core</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hogner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kastrup</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gouaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">322</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="109" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural basis for partial agonist action at ionotropic glutamate receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Banke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gouaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="803" to="810" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AMPA receptor binding cleft mutations that alter affinity, efficacy, and recovery from desensitization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Robert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Armstrong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3752" to="3762" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How AMPA receptor desensitization depends on receptor occupancy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Robert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="847" to="858" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanism of glutamate receptor desensitization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Olson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gouaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">417</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="245" to="253" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measurement of conformational changes accompanying desensitization in an ionotropic glutamate receptor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Armstrong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Jasti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gouaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="97" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural mechanism of glutamate receptor activation and desensitization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Meyerson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Subramaniam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">514</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="328" to="334" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural bases of desensitization in AMPA receptor-auxiliary subunit complexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Twomey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Yelshanskaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Sobolevsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="569" to="580" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>e5</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Heteromeric AMPA receptors assemble with a preferred subunit stoichiometry and spatial arrangement</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mansour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nagarajan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rosenmund</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="841" to="853" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AMPA receptor flip/ flop mutants affecting deactivation, desensitization, and modulation by cyclothiazide, aniracetam, and thiocyanate</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Partin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Fleck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6634" to="6647" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selective modulation of desensitization at AMPA versus kainate receptors by cyclothiazide and concanavalin A</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Partin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Patneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Buonanno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1069" to="1082" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subunit interactions and AMPA receptor desensitization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Robert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Irizarry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5574" to="5586" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A point mutation in the glutamate binding site blocks desensitization of AMPA receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Stern-Bach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Russo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rosenmund</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="907" to="918" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural determinants of allosteric regulation in alternatively spliced AMPA receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Partin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bowie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="833" to="843" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A charge-inverting mutation in the &apos;&apos;linker&apos;&apos; region of a-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazolepropionic acid (AMPA) receptors alters agonist binding and gating kinetics independently of allosteric modulators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Harms</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Benveniste</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Partin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">289</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10702" to="10714" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Block of AMPA receptor desensitization by a point mutation outside the ligandbinding domain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Yelshansky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Sobolevsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wollmuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4728" to="4736" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A molecular determinant of subtype-specific desensitization in ionotropic glutamate receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alsaloum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kazi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wollmuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2617" to="2622" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of the ion channel extracellular collar in AMPA receptor gating</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Yelshanskaya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mesbahi-Vasey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">,</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Sobolevsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1050</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of cyclothiazide on binding properties of AMPA-type glutamate receptors: lack of competition between cyclothiazide and GYKI 52466</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kessler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Arai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lynch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of the Lurcher mutation on GluR1 desensitization and activation kinetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4941" to="4951" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Lurcher mutation identifies d2 as an AMPA/kainate receptor-like channel that is potentiated by Ca 2þ</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wollmuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kuner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Zuo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5973" to="5980" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mechanism of a-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazolepropionate receptor desensitization after removal of glutamate</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Raman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Trussell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Restoration of single-channel currents using the segmental k-means method based on hidden Markov modeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Qin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1488" to="1501" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimating single-channel kinetic parameters from idealized patch-clamp data containing missed events</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Qin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Auerbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sachs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="264" to="280" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural and single-channel results indicate that the rates of ligand binding domain closing and opening directly impact AMPA receptor gating</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="932" to="943" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical methods for model discrimination. Applications to gating kinetics and permeation of the acetylcholine receptor channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Horn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="263" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanism of partial agonism in AMPA-type glutamate receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Salazar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Eibl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Plested</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14327</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">XDSAPP: a graphical user interface for the convenient processing of diffraction data using XDS</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Krug</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Mueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Appl. Cryst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="568" to="572" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Solving structures of protein complexes by molecular replacement with Phaser</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mccoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="41" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coot: model-building tools for molecular graphics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Emsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Cowtan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2126" to="2132" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PHENIX: a comprehensive Python-based system for macromolecular structure solution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Afonine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Zwart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Crystallogr. D Biol. Crystallogr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="221" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inference of macromolecular assemblies from crystalline state</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Krissinel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Henrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">372</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="774" to="797" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stargazin modulates AMPA receptor gating and trafficking by distinct domains</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tomita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Adesnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bredt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">435</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1052" to="1058" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationship between agonist potency and AMPA receptor kinetics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Robert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1336" to="1346" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cyclothiazide differentially modulates desensitization of a-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazolepropionic acid receptor splice variants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Partin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Patneau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="138" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Benzothiadiazides inhibit rapid glutamate receptor desensitization and enhance glutamatergic synaptic currents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Yamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3904" to="3915" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural and functional analysis of two new positive allosteric modulators of GluA2 desensitization and deactivation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Timm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Benveniste</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Partin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="280" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Targeting AMPA receptor gating processes with allosteric modulators and mutations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Fleck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biophys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2392" to="2402" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermodynamics and structural analysis of positive allosteric modulation of the ionotropic glutamate receptor GluA2</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Krintel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Frydenvang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kastrup</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">441</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutation of a glutamate receptor motif reveals its role in gating and d2 receptor channel properties</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kohda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yuzaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="322" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Lurcher mutation of an a-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazolepropionic acid receptor subunit enhances potency of glutamate and converts an antagonist to an agonist</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Taverna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Xiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Macdonald</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">275</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8475" to="8479" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Superactivation of AMPA receptors by auxiliary proteins</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Carbone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Plested</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10178</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Negative allosteric modulation of wild-type and mutant AMPA receptors by GYKI 53655</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Partin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="148" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The tetrameric structure of a glutamate receptor channel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rosenmund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Stern-Bach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stevens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">280</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1596" to="1599" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Concentration-dependent substate behavior of native AMPA receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="992" to="997" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Currents through single glutamate receptor channels in outside-out patches from rat cerebellar granule cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cull-Candy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Colquhoun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">432</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the stochastic properties of bursts of single ion channel openings and of clusters of bursts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Colquhoun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hawkes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">300</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="59" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fluctuations in the microsecond time range of the current through single acetylcholine receptor ion channels</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Colquhoun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sakmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">294</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="464" to="466" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the kinetics of large-conductance glutamate-receptor ion channels in rat cerebellar granule neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Howe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Colquhoun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B Biol. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">233</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="407" to="422" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Cull-Candy</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crosslinking the ligand-binding domain dimer interface locks kainate receptors out of the main open state</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Daniels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bowie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">591</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3873" to="3885" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defining the structural relationship between kainate-receptor deactivation and desensitization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dawe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Musgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bowie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1054" to="1061" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinct structural pathways coordinate the activation of AMPA receptor-auxiliary subunit complexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Dawe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Musgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bowie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1264" to="1276" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structural landscape of isolated agonist-binding domains from single AMPA receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Landes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Rambhadran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jayaraman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="168" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AMPA receptor ligand binding domain mobility revealed by functional cross linking</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Plested</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11912" to="11923" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Role of dimer interface in activation and desensitization in AMPA receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gonzalez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jayaraman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9891" to="9896" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and dynamics of AMPA receptor GluA2 in resting, pre-open, and desensitized states</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>D€ Urr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Gouaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">158</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="778" to="792" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The dynamic AMPA receptor extracellular region: a platform for synaptic protein interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Garcı ´a-Nafrı ´a</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Herguedas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Greger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">594</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5449" to="5458" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Steered molecular dynamics simulations predict conformational stability of glutamate receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Musgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Biggin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Chem. Inf. Model</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1787" to="1797" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
