<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Proliferative glomerulonephritis with linear immunoglobulin deposition: is this atypical antiglomerular basement membrane disease?</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-03-02">2 March 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Catarina</forename><surname>Teixeira</surname></persName>
							<email>acteixeira.ct@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Centro Hospitalar e Universitario de Coimbra</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nephrology, Coimbra</settlement>
									<country key="PT">portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Helena</forename><surname>Pinto</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Centro Hospitalar e Universitário de Coimbra</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nephrology, Coimbra</settlement>
									<country key="PT">portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nuno</forename><surname>Oliveira</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Centro Hospitalar e Universitário de Coimbra</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nephrology, Coimbra</settlement>
									<country key="PT">portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Carol</forename><surname>Marinho</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">pathology Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Centro Hospitalar e Universitario de Coimbra epe</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Coimbra</settlement>
									<country key="PT">portugal</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Proliferative glomerulonephritis with linear immunoglobulin deposition: is this atypical antiglomerular basement membrane disease?</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-03-02">2 March 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">9F997C38A37EECFCE2FD61AEA2A2473F</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bcr-2017-223198</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:31+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>To cite: teixeira aC, pinto H, oliveira N, et al.</s><s>BMJ Case Rep published online First: [please include Day Month Year].</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BaCkground</head><p><s>Antiglomerular basement membrane (anti-GBM) antibody disease is a classical form of glomerular disease in which circulating antibodies are directed against an antigen intrinsic to the GBM, resulting in an acute/rapidly progressive renal failure.</s></p><p><s>The antibodies are typically directed against the non-collagenous domain of the type IV collagen's α3 chain.</s><s>The inciting events that induce the autoimmune response are not fully understood.</s><s>It is thought that a critical step in the development of anti-GBM disease is a pathological conformational change in the α3NC1 and α5NC1 subunits that exposes cryptic epitopes, which in turn can trigger an autoimmune reaction. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref></s><s>The binding of anti-GBM autoantibody to the epitope requires dissolution of sulfilimine bounds and dissociation of the hexamer; when this happens, the reactivity against the antigen increases considerably. <ref type="bibr">2 3</ref></s><s>n the usual form, the anti-GBM disease is characterised by the formation and deposition of antibodies on the basement membranes of glomeruli and alveoli causing rapid and progressive glomerulonephritis and pulmonary haemorrhage. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>An atypical form of anti-GBM disease has been described and is estimated to represent around 10% of all cases.</s><s>In these forms, the serum anti-GBM antibody is not detected by the conventional immune essays. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Therefore, the findings on the renal biopsy (linear deposition of polyclonal immunoglobulin, along the basement membrane) are the key to the diagnosis and remain the diagnostic gold standard.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CaSe preSenTaTion</head><p><s>A 24-year-old Caucasian man presented to the emergency department with a week's progressive swelling of his legs.</s><s>There was no recent infection or other relevant personal or family history of disease.</s><s>He was a smoker, was under no chronic medication and did not take any illicit drugs.</s><s>Previous routine laboratory results made 8 months before were available showing a serum creatinine of 87 µmol/L.</s></p><p><s>On physical examination, there was marked lower limbs oedema with no other findings.</s></p><p><s>The initial laboratory evaluation showed massive proteinuria (11 g on 24-hour urine collection), hypoalbuminaemia (20 g/L) and acute renal injury (Cr: 150 µmol/L).</s><s>Total and low-density lipoprotein cholesterol were normal (4.8 mmol/L and 3.00 mmol/L, respectively) and the triglycerides were moderately elevated (2.3 mmol/L); the C reactive protein was negative (&lt;0 mg/dL).</s><s>Urine analysis was positive for proteinuria and haematuria, the urinary sediment showing many erythrocyte casts.</s><s>The chest radiograph obtained on admission was interpreted as within normal limits and the renal ultrasound scan showed no changes.</s></p><p><s>Therapy was started with furosemide, losartan, enalapril and prophylactic anticoagulation.</s><s>There was clinical improvement with regression of the oedema and a weight loss of 7 kg.</s></p><p><s>Additional investigations were performed including: antinuclear antibodies (positive, titre of 1/160-dense thin granular pattern), negative serology for hepatitis C virus and HIV and showing immunity for hepatitis B virus, negative extractable nuclear antigens and antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibodies (ELISA test by Euroimmun for proteinase 3 and myeloperoxidase), negative anti-GBM antibodies (ELISA test by Euroimmun, specific for alpha-3 chain of type IV collagen isolated from bovine kidney), normal C3, C4 and CH50 levels, negative anticardiolipin antibodies and normal tumour markers.</s><s>Serum immunoglobulin analysis was significant for an IgG decrease; serum protein immunofixation was negative for the presence of a monoclonal component.</s><s>The urinary electrophoresis showed non-selective glomerular proteinuria.</s></p><p><s>A percutaneous renal biopsy of the left kidney was performed.</s><s>The light microscopy had 21 glomeruli for analysis.</s><s>Ten glomeruli had significant global sclerosis; the remaining glomeruli showed endocapillary and extracapillary proliferation with rare disease crescents present in about 30% (figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>); there was slight interstitial fibrosis and no vascular abnormalities.</s><s>The immunofluorescence (IF) fragment, with nine glomeruli, was analysed for IgG, IgA, IgM, C3, C4 and C1q.</s><s>All glomeruli showed intense IgG deposits (+++) in a linear parietal pattern (figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>); there were also C3 (+) and IgM (+) deposits with a focal and segmental parietal and granular mesangial pattern; it was not possible to stain for IgG subclasses or light chains nor was it possible to perform electron microscopy since these technics are not routinely available in our centre (figures 1 and 2).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TreaTmenT</head><p><s>Despite the negative anti-GBM, a diagnosis, based on the renal biopsy IF pattern, of anti-GBM disease was established and treatment was started with pulse intravenous methylprednisolone (three pulses of 1 g), moving afterwards to prednisolone 1 mg/kg/day with subsequent tapering.</s><s>After sperm collection due to concern with fertility preservation, oral cyclophosphamide (3 mg/kg/day) was started and maintained for 3 months.</s><s>Other supporting therapies, furosemide, losartan and enalapril, sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim and prophylactic anticoagulation, were kept.</s><s>At the end of the cyclophosphamide therapy, the laboratory results showed a serum creatinine of 118.3 µmol/L, massive proteinuria (9.7 g) and hypoalbuminaemia (26 g/L).</s></p><p><s>After a waiting period of 6 months, the patient maintained peripheral oedema associated with heavy proteinuria and hypoalbuminaemia.</s><s>We decided to start therapy with rituximab (375 mg/m 2 for 4 weekly infusions).</s><s>There was marked clinical improvement, with normalisation of urinary sediment and marked regression of proteinuria (to 1.5 g/day); renal function remained stable with serum creatinine of 132.6 µmol/L.</s><s>After a prolonged tapering, corticosteroid therapy was stopped after 9 months of therapy.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ouTCome and follow-up</head><p><s>Presently, about 6 months after the completion of rituximab therapy, the patient maintains clinical remission; serum creatinine is 120 µmol/L, serum albumin 40 g/L and proteinuria is 1.5 g/24 hours with normal urinary sediment.</s><s>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref> summarises the temporal evolution of therapy, proteinuria and serum albumin over time.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>diSCuSSion</head><p><s>Regardless of being rare, anti-GBM disease is one of the archetypal rapidly progressive glomerulonephritis (RPGN); there is pulmonary involvement in about 34% to 62% of cases. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> The diagnosis in this clinical context is usually straightforward: the serum presence of the anti-GBM antibody is normally detected and the kidney biopsy allows confirmation by histologically identifying a crescentic and necrotising glomerulonephritis on light microscopy with the presence on IF of a linear IgG capillary wall deposition. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref></s><s>lthough uncommon, presentations with nephrotic syndrome have been described in patients with anti-GBM disease.</s><s>These atypical presentations are estimated to represent around 10% of all cases.</s><s>They are characterised by an indolent course, slowly progressive renal insufficiency and massive proteinuria.</s><s>The renal prognosis is usually better than in the classical presentation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref></s><s>In spite of being considered rarer than in the classical presentation, pulmonary involvement has been reported in several cases in the literature. <ref type="bibr">6 7</ref></s><s>Also, and in contrast with the classical presentation, exceptional cases of relapsing disease have been reported. <ref type="bibr">7 8</ref></s><s>In this form of anti-GBM disease, the serum antibodies are usually negative. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref></s><s>n both forms of disease, the histological hallmark on renal biopsy is linear deposition of IgG, but there are differences on light microscopy.</s><s>In the atypical form, there is heterogeneous involvement with diffuse endocapillary proliferation, some remodelling of the GBM leading to double contours, and, usually, no crescents.</s><s>In contrast, typical disease presents with a diffuse crescentic and necrotising glomerulonephritis in which the lesions are usually monophasic with no unaffected glomeruli. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref></s><s>ome authors postulate that the deposition of the immunoglobulin in atypical disease may be caused by mechanisms other than the reaction of antibodies to GBM components.</s><s>Possibilities include non-specific physicochemical affinity for GBM and alterations of the GBM itself.</s><s>They suggest the description 'idiopathic linear immunoglobulin deposition' until pathogenicity is proven. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref></s><s>Such mechanisms may explain linear IgG deposition in the GBM in diabetes, old age and heavy chain deposition disease. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref></s><s>ur patient presented with a nephrotic syndrome and did not have RPGN.</s><s>Since serum anti-GBM antibodies were not rare disease detected, the results of renal biopsy and IF were a surprise.</s><s>He was not diabetic and the absence of a monoclonal protein on serum and urinary protein immune fixation excluded heavy chain disease.</s><s>Tests for serum anti-GBM antibodies are usually extremely reliable, with high specificity (94%-100%) and sensitivity (95%-100%). <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> We were concerned that the serum antibody was negative.</s></p><p><s>Proposed mechanisms to explain negative anti-GBM antibody in patients with anti-GBM disease include: low levels of pathogenic antibodies, different IgG subtypes such as IgG4 that are not detected by ELISA and GBM antigens which are not represented in the standard ELISA. <ref type="bibr">2 9</ref> Treatment options for classical anti-GBM disease include schemes with pulse doses of methylprednisolone (15 to 30 mg/ kg to a maximum dose of 1000 mg intravenously over 20 min) followed by oral prednisone (1 mg/kg per day to a maximum of 60 to 80 mg/day) and oral cyclophosphamide (2 mg/kg per day) combined with rapid removal of the antibodies (plasmapheresis).</s><s>Plasmapheresis removes circulating anti-GBM antibodies and other mediators of inflammation, while the immunosuppressive agents minimise new antibody formation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">11</ref></s><s>t remains to be established if the benefits of the aggressive immunosuppressive regimens described above outweigh their side effects in patients with atypical anti-GBM disease. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> This is a pertinent concern since this form of anti-GBM disease has better renal prognosis and, in most cases, there is no pulmonary involvement.</s></p><p><s>Our patient presented with severe nephrotic syndrome, acute renal injury and was a smoker.</s><s>As such, we decided to follow conventional therapy with steroids and alkylating agents.</s><s>Since there was no evidence of pulmonary haemorrhage, it was decided not to initiate plasmapheresis.</s><s>However, the response to this therapy was poor and we had no response up to the moment of reaching the maximal cumulative dosage of cyclophosphamide.</s><s>Thus, we were forced to consider other alternatives.</s></p><p><s>Rituximab is also an option in classical anti-GBM disease, usually reserved for patients that are unable to do cyclophosphamide. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12</ref></s><s>Rituximab is a chimeric monoclonal antibody directed against CD20 positive B-cells.</s><s>Following infusion, rapid B-cell lysis occurs with consequent decline in antibody production, antigen presentation and activation of T-cells and macrophages. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">13</ref></s><s>lthough we had a good response to this therapy and are confident that it was key to inducing remission in our case, we cannot completely exclude that this response reflected a combined effect of both cyclophosphamide and rituximab.</s><s>Our patient had severe proteinuria suggesting that diffuse podocyte injury was present and, despite not being able to confirm this hypothesis on our case because we did not have electronic microscopy available, some authors report that effacement of foot process is present in a significant number of anti-GBM disease cases. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">14</ref></s><s>ituximab may interfere directly with the podocytes, via direct binding with SMPDL-3b, protecting the structure and function of podocytes <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">15</ref> ; this may also be a mechanism by which rituximab was effective in our case.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>learning points</head><p><s>► Occasional patients with proliferative glomerulonephritis have linear immunoglobulin deposition along glomerular basement membranes (GBM) with no detectable serum anti-GBM antibodies.</s><s>► The natural history of these patients is more indolent than classical anti-GBM disease.</s><s>► Rituximab may be effective in patients who do not respond to conventional treatment.</s><s>► Renal biopsy with immunofluorescence remains the surest method of diagnosis.</s></p><p><s>Contributors aCt, Hp and Nuno oliveira participated in the treatment patient and continue to follow the patient.</s><s>Nuno oliveira performed the kidney biopsy.</s><s>CM, the pathologist, made the diagnosis based on the results of the biopsy and provided the images of the biopsy.</s><s>the bibliographical research, as well as the elaboration of the manuscript, was carried out by aCt.</s><s>Hp was responsible for the text formatting.</s><s>the review of the article was carried out by Nuno oliveira.</s></p><p><s>funding the authors have not declared a specific grant for this research from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</s></p><p><s>Competing interests None declared.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>figure 1 figure 2</head><label>12</label><figDesc><div><p><s>figure 1 Periodic acid Schiff (PAS) stain showing fibrocellular crescent with disruption of the Bowman's capsule.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,42.00,48.00,246.59,184.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>figure 3 Temporal evolution of therapy, proteinuria and serum albumin over time.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,85.00,48.00,425.28,230.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Copyright 2018 BMJ publishing Group.</s><s>all rights reserved.</s><s>For permission to reuse any of this content visit http://group.bmj.com/group/rights-licensing/permissions.</s><s>BMJ Case report Fellows may re-use this article for personal use and teaching without any further permission.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Become a Fellow of BMJ Case reports today and you can:</head><p><s>► submit as many cases as you like ► enjoy fast sympathetic peer review and rapid publication of accepted articles ► access all the published articles ► re-use any of the published material for personal use and teaching without further permission For information on Institutional Fellowships contact consortiasales@bmjgroup.com Visit casereports.bmj.com for more articles like this and to become a Fellow</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">the clinicopathologic characteristics and outcome of atypical anti-glomerular basement membrane nephritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Collins</forename><surname>Nasr Sh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ab</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Alexander Mp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.kint.2016.02.001</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Kidney Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="897" to="908" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glassock rJ. atypical anti-glomerular basement membrane disease: lessons learned</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ckj/sfw068</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Kidney J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="653" to="656" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular architecture of the Goodpasture autoantigen in anti-GBM nephritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Pedchenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bondar O</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Fogo Ab</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/NEJMoa0910500</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">363</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="343" to="354" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">Med2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">antiglomerular basement membrane disease with normal renal function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Singh Ak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/sj.ki.5002525</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Kidney Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1403" to="1408" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Goodpasture&apos;s disease in the absence of circulating anti-glomerular basement membrane antibodies as detected by standard techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Levy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1053/ajkd.2002.33385</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Kidney Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1162" to="1167" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circulating anti-glomerular basement membrane antibodies with predominance of subclass IgG4 and false-negative immunoassay test results in anti-glomerular basement membrane disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ohlsson S</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Herlitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lundberg S</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1053/j.ajkd.2013.08.032</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Kidney Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="289" to="293" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Frequently relapsing anti-glomerular basement membrane antibody disease with changing clinical phenotype and antibody characteristics over time</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Barbour Sj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ckj/sfw048</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Kidney J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="661" to="664" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple recurrences of anti-glomerular basement membrane disease with variable antibody detection: can the laboratory be trusted?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Liu P, Waheed S</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Boujelbane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ckj/sfw038</idno>
		<ptr target="https://academic.oup.com/ckj/article-lookup/doi/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Kidney</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="657" to="660" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">J2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glomerular disease with idiopathic linear immunoglobulin deposition: a rose by any other name would be atypical</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Colvin</forename><surname>Rosales Ia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.kint.2016.01.018</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Kidney Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="750" to="752" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jennette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Olson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Heptinstall&apos;s Pathology of the Kidney</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="657" to="685" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>7th edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">12/08/2016 treatment of antiGBM antibody (Goodpasture&apos;s) disease official reprint from UptoDate ® www. uptodate. com ©2016 UptoDate ®</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Appel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2016</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">anti-glomerular basement membrane antibody disease treated with rituximab: a case-based review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Syeda Ua</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Singer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Magrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.semarthrit.2012.10.007</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semin Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="567" to="572" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">rituximab for the treatment of refractory simultaneous anti-glomerular basement membrane (anti-GBM) and membranous nephropathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bandak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jones</forename><surname>Ba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ckj/sft152</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Kidney J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">an unusual case of anti-glomerular basement membrane disease presenting with nephrotic syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Okafor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bourne</forename><surname>Balogun Ra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Dt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s11255-010-9862-0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int Urol Nephrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1249" to="1253" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">anti-CD20 antibodies for Idiopathic Nephrotic syndrome in Children</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ravani P</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bonanni A</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Rossi R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.2215/CJN.08500815</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin J Am Soc Nephrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="710" to="720" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
