<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Apoptosis Susceptibility Prolongs the Lack of Memory B Cells in Acute Leukemic Patients After Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Angela</forename><surname>Mensen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Medical Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité University Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CVK</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Youngseong</forename><surname>Oh</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Medical Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité University Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CVK</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sonya</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Medical Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité University Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CVK</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Philipp</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hemmati</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Hematology, Oncology and Tumor Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité University Medicine CVK</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Christian</forename><surname>Jehn</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Hematology, Oncology and Tumor Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité University Medicine CVK</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jörg</forename><surname>Westermann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Hematology, Oncology and Tumor Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité University Medicine CVK</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Szyska</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Experimental and Clinical Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Henning</forename><surname>Göldner</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Hematology, Oncology and Tumor Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité University Medicine CVK</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bernd</forename><surname>Dörken</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Hematology, Oncology and Tumor Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité University Medicine CVK</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Max Delbrück Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Carmen</forename><surname>Scheibenbogen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Medical Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité University Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CVK</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Renate</forename><surname>Arnold</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Hematology, Oncology and Tumor Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité University Medicine CVK</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Il-Kang</forename><surname>Na</surname></persName>
							<email>il-kang.na@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Medical Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité University Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CVK</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Experimental and Clinical Research Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Il-Kang</forename><surname>Pd</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Hematology, Oncology and Tumor Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité University Medicine CVK</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Na</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Charité</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Onkologie und Tumor-immunologie</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Klinikum, Augustenburger Platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Hämatologie, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Apoptosis Susceptibility Prolongs the Lack of Memory B Cells in Acute Leukemic Patients After Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BA6A05D18D7E3A1DA0A1D350E940A580</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.bbmt.2015.08.008</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 11 June 2015 Accepted 4 August 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:31+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation B cell intrinsic and germinal center defects Long-term memory B cell paucity</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Long-term survival after allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation requires intact immunosurveillance, which is hampered by lymphoid organ damage associated with conditioning therapy, graftversus-host disease, and immunosuppression.</s><s>Our study aimed to identify the mechanisms contributing to sustained low memory B cell numbers after transplantation.</s><s>Peripheral B and T cell subset recovery and functional marker expression were investigated in 35 acute leukemic patients up to 1 year after transplantation.</s><s>Apoptosis of B cells after CD40/TLR-9, CD40/BCR, and CD40/BCR/TLR-9-dependent stimulation and drug efflux capacity were analyzed.</s><s>One half of the patients suffered from infections after day 180.</s><s>All patients had strongly diminished CD27 þ memory B cells despite already normalized total B cell numbers and fully recovered CD27 À IgD À memory B cells, putatively of extra-follicular origin.</s><s>Circulating memory follicular helper T cells were reduced in the majority of patients as well.</s><s>Naïve B cells exhibited a decreased expression of CXCR5, which mediates follicular B cell entry.</s><s>Additionally, a lower HLA-DR expression was found on naïve B cells, impairing antigen presentation.</s><s>Upon CD40/TLR-9edependent activation, B cells underwent significantly increased apoptosis paralleled by an aberrant up-regulation of Fas-L on activated T cells and Fas on resting B cells.</s><s>Significantly increased B cell apoptosis was also observed after CD40/BCR and CD40/BCR/TLR-9 edependent activation.</s><s>Drug efflux capacity of naïve B cells was diminished in cyclosporin Aetreated patients, additionally contributing to an apoptosis-prone phenotype.</s><s>We conclude that B cell survival and migration and T cell communication defects are contributing candidates for an impaired germinal center formation of memory B cells after allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation.</s><s>Follow-up studies should evaluate effectiveness of revaccinations on the cellular level and should address the long-term sequelae of B cell defects after transplantation.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p><s>Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (allo-HSCT) can cure leukemia; however, its success is limited by incidence of infections, high-grade graft-versus-host disease (GVHD), and relapse that contribute to morbidity and mortality after transplantation <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>.</s><s>The conditioning therapy before transplantation, occurrence of GVHD, and prolonged immunosuppressive treatment impair the immune reconstitution from bone marrow and thymus and the formation of adaptive immune responses in secondary lymphoid organs.</s><s>Mechanisms of long-term immune dysfunction remain to be resolved to enable therapeutic interventions.</s></p><p><s>A profound B and T cell paucity is found within the first months after allo-HSCT, which is prolonged by the presence of GVHD directly targeting the bone marrow and thymic stroma <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>.</s><s>The onset of B cell reconstitution is characterized by a strong increase in the number of transitional B cells, which leave the bone marrow first and further differentiate into recirculating naïve B cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s>We have shown in patients that a delayed onset of B cell reconstitution after allo-HSCT was significantly associated with the presence of systemic acute GVHD, a full-intensity conditioning regimen, and increased bone marrow T cell infiltration <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s>Although B cell numbers normalize within 1 year after allo-HSCT <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>, antigen-experienced B cell subsets, including CD27 þ IgD À switched and CD27 þ IgD þ IgM þ marginal zoneelike (MZ-like) memory B cells, remain profoundly diminished <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>.</s><s>Insufficient vaccination responses, as seen within the first year after transplantation <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, further hint at functional immune defects.</s><s>Thus, patients retain a dysfunctional humoral immune system.</s></p><p><s>Defects in the germinal center (GC) reaction are assumed to cause the slow recovery of B cell memory, but they are poorly characterized so far.</s><s>Deficient CD4 þ T cell help due to the slow recovery of CD4 þ T cells was proposed as 1 contributing mechanism <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</s><s>In addition, damage to splenic and lymph node architecture, particularly in GVHD patients, has been reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>.</s><s>This includes damage to follicular dendritic cells (FDCs), which are stromal cells that essentially support the formation of GCs within the B cell follicle by producing the CXCR5 chemokine CXCL13 and presenting opsonized antigens to the B cell receptor (BCR) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s>Although the immunoglobulin (Ig) repertoire is restricted during the first months and normalizes within 1 year after allo-HSCT <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, less diversity from somatic hypermutations remains, thus further suggesting defects in the GC reaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Because secondary lymphoid organs in the posttransplantation course are inaccessible, in depth in vivo analysis of GC defects is limited in patients.</s><s>In an attempt to complement the already existing data on GC defects and to get a better picture of B cell intrinsic and extrinsic mechanisms potentially contributing to sustained low memory B cell numbers in allo-HSCT patients, we performed immunological analyses of peripheral B and T cell subset recovery and their expression of functional markers.</s><s>Furthermore, we studied B cell apoptosis after CD40/TLR-9, CD40/BCR and CD40/BCR/TLR-9-dependent B cell activation and drug efflux capacity of B cells as an intrinsic contributor to B cell survival.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MATERIALS AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patients/Healthy Controls</head><p><s>The study included 35 adult patients diagnosed with acute leukemia.</s><s>They received allogeneic hematopoietic grafts obtained by apheresis from granulocyte colonyestimulating factoretreated HLA-matched related or unrelated donors.</s><s>Cyclosporine A (CsA)/methotrexate AE antithymoglobulin (ATG) was given as GVHD prophylaxis to patients with a full-intensity and CsA/mycophenolate mofetil/ATG to patients with reduced-intensity conditioning regimen.</s><s>Patients' characteristics are listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s><s>Blood samples were obtained at days 180 and 360 after allo-HSCT.</s><s>Ten patients died between days 180 and 360.</s><s>Because of the paucity of material, blood samples from additional acute leukemic patients were collected at days 120 to 180 for the analysis of drug efflux capacity (Supplementary Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S1</ref>).</s><s>The clinical characteristics of both patient cohorts were comparable.</s><s>The Charité local ethics committee approved this study (no.</s><s>EA4/128/09).</s><s>Patients gave their informed consent.</s><s>Healthy controls (HC) were Caucasians with no known immune deficiency and no ongoing infection.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Flow Cytometry</head><p><s>Peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) from patients and HC were freshly isolated by Ficoll density gradient centrifugation (Biocholl separating solution, Biochrom, Germany), and immediately used for the determination of absolute lymphocyte subsets counts, of functional marker expression, and of the drug efflux capacity by flow cytometry analysis.</s><s>Fluorochrome-conjugated anti-human monoclonal antibodies were used for staining at 4 C in PBS/2% Flebogamma (Biotest, Germany; Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S2</ref>).</s><s>Analyses were performed at a LSRII Fortessa Flow Cytometer (Becton Dickinson, Heidelberg, Germany).</s><s>Data evaluation was done with the FlowJo-9.5.2 software (TreeStar, Ashland, OR, USA).</s><s>Differential blood counts were used to determine absolute cell numbers.</s><s>To exclude differences in mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) expression levels related to machine settings, the same compensation setup was used for all measurements.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Apoptosis Staining</head><p><s>To perform functional analyses, we resorted to the backup of viable frozen PBMC samples from patients.</s><s>For better comparison, samples of HC were also viable frozen PBMC.</s><s>Median percentages of Fas-expressing B cells were comparable before and after freezing of patient PBMCs (before 17%; after 14%).</s><s>For CD40/TLR-9-dependent B cell activation, cells were thawed and stimulated with 10 mg/mL CpG (Invivogen, Toulouse, France) and 1 mg/ mL human recombinant CD40 L (CD40 ligand, R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, USA) in RPMI/10% FCS/1% penicillin/streptomycin (6 Â 10 6 cells/2 mL) for 48 hours at 37 C, 5% CO 2 .</s><s>For CD40/BCR and CD40/BCR/TLR-9-dependent activation, PBMCs were stimulated for 48 hours with 20 mg/mL F(ab')2 fragment goat antihuman IgM (Jackson Immunoresearch, Suffolk, UK) in combination with CD40 L or CD40 L and CpG.</s><s>Necrotic/apoptotic B cells were determined by Annexin-V FITC (BD Biosciences, Heidelberg, Germany) and propidium iodide (Biolegend, Fell, Germany) staining for 15 minutes, RT.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Drug Efflux Measurement</head><p><s>Freshly prepared PBMC were incubated overnight in Iscove's Modified Dulbecco's Media (IMDM)/10% human AB-serum/1% penicillin/streptomycin at 37 C, 5% CO 2 .</s><s>Then, 5 Â 10 6 cells/approach were incubated with 2.5 mg/mL rhodamine 123 (R123, Invitrogen, Darmstadt, Germany) in 1.5 mL IMDM/1% BSA for 20 minutes at 37 C. Next, 25 mM CsA (Sigma-Aldrich, Taufkirchen, Germany) was added after 10 minutes of incubation.</s><s>After centrifugation, cell pellets were resuspended in 6 mL IMDM medium only.</s><s>The 4 C approach was then immediately incubated on ice, whereas 2 incubation steps at 37 C (15 and 40 minutes) with medium exchange in between followed for the other approaches.</s><s>Finally, cells were stained for flow cytometry analysis at 4 C.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Luminex Multiplex Cytokine Assay</head><p><s>Plasma diluted with PBS 1:2 was collected from the Ficoll after PBMC isolation and frozen at À80 C until use.</s><s>Twenty-nine cytokines from the Milliplex Human Cytokine/Chemokine Magnetic Bead Panel (HCYTOMAG-60K, Merck Millipore, Darmstadt Deutschland) were simultaneously assayed with 25 mL of sample based on the Luminex xMAP technology according to the manufacturers' instructions (Luminex; Hertogenbusch, The Netherlands).</s><s>Quantification was performed at a Bio-Plex 200 system with the Bio-Plex Manager 6.0 software (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head><p><s>Sustained Low CD27 þ Memory B Cell and CD4 þ Memory T Follicular Helper Cell (T FH ) Numbers After Allo-HSCT Infections with clinical symptoms, typical morphology in radiological imaging, or pathogen detection were found in 49% of patients after day 180.</s><s>CD19 þ B cell numbers normalized in patients at day 360 when compared with agematched HC (n ¼ 12; 6 male, 6 female; median age, 53; range, 40 to 78) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>).</s><s>CD3 þ T cells in patients also reached levels of HC at day 360.</s></p><p><s>Among CD19 þ B cells, CD27 À IgD þ CD38 hi CD24 hi transitional and CD27 À IgD þ CD38 int CD24 int/À naïve B cells, which were the predominating B cell subsets after transplantation, reached levels of HC at day 360 (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1</ref>).</s><s>CD27 þ IgD þ MZ-like and CD27 þ IgD À switched memory  B cells remained significantly diminished in patients (median cell number/mL: MZ-like: HC, 6.7; allo-HSCT, 1.9; P .01;</s><s>switched memory: HC, 15.7; allo-HSCT, 1.3; P .001)</s><s>(Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>), whereas IgD À CD27 À double negative (DN) B cells fully recovered until day 360.</s><s>CD38 hi CD24 À plasmablasts normalized in the majority of patients at day 360.</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">CD19 þ B cell subsets (CD38 hi CD24 À plasmablasts, CD27 þ IgD À switched memory, CD27 þ IgD þ MZ-like, CD27 À IgD À DN B cells, B) and the gating of CD4 þ T cells within CD3 þ T cells (C) and CXCR5 þ T FH cells within CD3 þ CD4 þ T cells (D)</formula><p><s>CD3 þ CD4 þ T cells remained diminished at day 360 in patients (median cell number/mL: HC, 890; allo-HSCT, 271; P .001)</s><s>(Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref>).</s><s>CXCR5 þ -expressing cells within CD4 þ T cells, representing recirculating memory T FH cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref>, were significantly reduced in the majority of patients at day 360 when compared with those of HC (median %: HC, 9.5; allo-HSCT, 1.3; P .05)</s><s>(Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1D</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Numbers of MZ-like, switched memory, DN B cells, and plasmablasts as well as of CD3 þ CD4 þ T cells at day 360 after allo-HSCT were comparable in patients who had received full or reduced-intensity conditioning therapy, with no-ATG or ATG treatment, with presence or absence of chronic GVHD, and with no infectious or infectious complications between day 180 and day 360 (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2</ref>).</s><s>Only CD3 þ CD4 þ T cells were significantly decreased in patients with ATG treatment when compared with patients without ATG treatment.</s><s>Percentages of T FH cells were significantly reduced in patients with chronic GVHD compared with patients without chronic GVHD (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Migration and Communication Defects Might Contribute to Defective GC-Reactions</head><p><s>Decreased numbers of memory B and T FH cells but normalized DN B cells indicated defects in the GC reaction.</s><s>GC defects could be supported by the sustained and significantly reduced expression levels of the chemokine receptor CXCR5 on patients' naïve B cells at day 360 when compared with HC (median MFI: HC, 4,223; allo-HSCT, 3,223; P .001)</s><s>(Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>), possibly impeding the B cell follicle entry.</s><s>Memory B cell subsets also showed decreased CXCR5 expression levels at day 360 (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S3A</ref>).</s><s>The expression of CCR7 on naïve B cells was slightly but not significantly reduced.</s><s>The HLA-DR expression levels on naïve B cells were significantly lower in patients than those in HC, suggesting a reduced antigen-presenting function (median MFI: HC, 15,741; allo-HSCT, 6,116).</s><s>CXCR5, CCR7, and HLA-DR expression levels on naïve B cells at day 360 after allo-HSCT were comparable between patient groups with different clinical conditions (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S3B-E</ref>), except the CCR7 expression was significantly higher for patients with ATG treatment than for patients without ATG treatment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>High B Cell Apoptosis Rate After CD40/TLR-9edependent B Cell Activation</head><p><s>To investigate functional defects, we analyzed B cell apoptosis upon CD40/TLR-9-dependent B cell activation.</s></p><p><s>To distinguish different types/phases of cell death, we performed Annexin-V and propidium iodide staining (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3A</ref>).</s><s>Although there was no difference in T cell apoptosis/necrosis before stimulation, patients' B cells tended to more early apoptotic (Annexin-V þ PI À ) B cells compared with those of HC.</s><s>After stimulation, more T cells and significantly more B cells were found in the stage of late apoptosis (Annexin-V þ PI þ ) for patients at day 360 (B cells, median %: HC, 9; allo-HSCT, 37; P .05).</s><s>Three of the 7 investigated patients had chronic GVHD and all showed increased late apoptotic B cells when compared with HC, although clearly increased late apoptotic B cells were only found for 2 of 4 patients without chronic GVHD (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3B</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stimulation-Induced B Cell Apoptosis is Paralleled by an Aberrant Up-Regulation of Fas-L on T Cells and Fas on B Cells</head><p><s>To test for mechanisms of higher susceptibility to apoptosis, we investigated the expression of Fas and Fas-L on B and T cells (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4</ref>).</s><s>Patients B cell subsets at day 360 expressed significantly higher Fas ex vivo when compared with that of HC (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4A</ref>).</s><s>Plasmablasts, which showed a high percentage of Fas-expressing cells in HC, were not different in patients.</s><s>Fas expression on total B cells was comparable between HC and patients at day 360 (median %: 13 versus 15 respectively, data not shown), which can be attributed to different B cell subset compositions with predominating naïve and low numbers of memory B cells in patients.</s><s>Significantly higher Fas expression was found on MZ-like B cells from patients with a reduced-intensity conditioning therapy than on those from patients with a fullintensity conditioning therapy, as well as on transitional B cells in chronic GVHD patients compared with patients without chronic GVHD (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S4</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Fas expression on B cells stimulated in vitro with CpG/ CD40L significantly increased to a level as seen for HC (median %, HC: before,11; after, 40; P .001;</s><s>allo-HSCT: before, 15; after 40, P .05)</s><s>(Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4B</ref>).</s><s>Fas expression on CD4 þ but not on CD8 þ T cells was significantly higher before stimulation for patients than HC (median %: HC, 19; allo-HSCT.</s><s>63; P .05)</s><s>(Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4B</ref>), which was not changed upon stimulation.</s><s>Patient but not HC CD4 þ T cells up-regulated Fas-L significantly upon stimulation (median %, CD4 þ : before, 1.2; after, 3.0; P .05)</s><s>(Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4C</ref>).</s><s>No significant differences in Fas-L expression were seen on B cells.</s></p><p><s>High B Cell Apoptosis Rate after CD40/BCR and CD40/BCR/ TLR-9-dependent B Cell Activation CD40 and TLR-9 signaling pathways are important contributors to the T celledependent memory B and plasma cell formation of BCR-activated B cells within a GC reaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref>.</s><s>Therefore, we further investigated B cell apoptosis after PBMC stimulation with CpG/CD40L in combination with anti-IgM treatment as well as after CD40L/anti-IgM stimulation, for comparison, to mimic T celledependent B cell activation as occurs during the GC reaction.</s><s>For HC, anti-IgM/ CD40L stimulation resulted only marginally in increased percentages of early (median %: 3 before, 4 after) and late (3 before, 5 after) apoptotic B cells, which increased with addition of CpG (9 early, 14 late; Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5A</ref>).</s><s>Patients' B cells, in contrast, displayed significantly higher rates of cells in the stage of late apoptosis after CD40L/anti-IgM stimulation (median, 59%), and was even higher after CD40L/anti-IgM/ CpG stimulation (83%).</s><s>The percentage of late apoptotic B cells before stimulation was comparable to those of HC (median 3%).</s></p><p><s>Efficient B cell activation was verified by assessment of CD69 expression, which was found at median of 84% of B cells after CD40L/anti-IgM stimulation and 71% after CD40L/anti-IgM/CpG stimulation, but only on 4% on B cells before stimulation for HC (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5B</ref>).</s><s>A median of 84% and 56% of patient B cells expressed CD69 after CD40L/anti-IgM and CD40L/anti-IgM/CpG stimulation, respectively, which was not significantly different from those of HC.</s></p><p><s>We observed higher percentages of early apoptotic and CD69-expressing B cells for the patients with chronic GVHD than for those without chronic GVHD before stimulation (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5C,D</ref>).</s><s>After CD40L/anti-IgM and CD40L/anti-IgM/ CpG stimulation, there was a tendency towards higher percentages of late apoptotic B cells and lower percentages of CD69-expressing B cells for patients with chronic GVHD than for patients without chronic GVHD.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A Sustained Inflammatory Milieu is Present After Allo-HSCT</head><p><s>Increased Fas expression on B and CD4 þ T cells might result from a sustained inflammatory milieu upon cytotoxic treatment.</s><s>Accordingly, B cell subsets, except plasmablasts, displayed a more activated phenotype at day 180, characterized by significantly more CD86-expressing cells (median %: transitional: HC, 4; allo-HSCT, 15; naïve: HC, 2; allo-HSCT, 11; MZ-like: HC, 5; allo-HSCT, 14; switched memory: HC, 2; allo-HSCT, 20; DN: HC, 3; allo-HSCT, 20) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6A</ref>).</s><s>Significantly more cells expressing the activation/inflammationinduced chemokine receptor CXCR3 were seen for transitional (HC, 4; allo-HSCT, 8), naïve (HC, 2; allo-HSCT, 6), switched memory (HC, 9; allo-HSCT.</s><s>32), and DN B cells (HC, 9; allo-HSCT, 11) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6B</ref>).</s><s>CD86 and CXCR3 expression remained increased on switched memory (CD86: allo-HSCT, 30; CXCR3: allo-HSCT, 31) and DN B cells (CD86: allo-HSCT, 13; CXCR3: allo-HSCT, 11) at day 360.</s></p><p><s>The activated/inflammatory phenotype was accompanied by an inflammatory milieu.</s><s>The simultaneous analysis of 29 cytokines revealed significantly higher plasma levels of the cytokines granulocyte colonyestimulating factor, granulocyte macrophage colonyestimulating factor, IFNa2, and TNFa and of the chemokines IP-10, MCP-1, MIP-1b, and Eotaxin in allo-HSCT patients at day 180 (9 male, 7 female, median age, 48; range, 24 to 62) than in HC (5 male, 5 female, median age, 42; range, 30 to 59) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6C</ref>).</s><s>No differences were obtained for IFNg, IL-1ra, IL-7, and sCD40L.</s><s>IL-1a, IL-1b, IL-2, IL-3, IL-4, IL-6, IL-9, IL-10, IL-13, IL-15, IL17A, MIP-1a, MIP-1b, and TNFb were below the detection limit.</s><s>IL-5, IL-6, IL-12, and MCP-3 were detectable only in single patients, and IL-8 in 9 of 16 patients but in none of the HC (data not shown).</s><s>The expression of CD86 and CXCR3 on B cell subsets at day 360 after allo-HSCT as well as serum cytokine concentrations at day 180 after allo-HSCT were comparable between patients with different clinical conditions (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">S5</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Decreased Drug Efflux Capacity of Naive B Cells in CsA-Treated Patients</head><p><s>Cytotoxicity of post-transplantation treatments may contribute to increased susceptibility to apoptosis of B cells in addition to immunological mechanisms after transplantation.</s><s>Naïve B cells can extrude toxic substances via adenosine triphosphate (ATP)-binding cassette transporter <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>.</s><s>As CsA is an unspecific inhibitor of ATP-binding cassette  transporter, we wanted to determine whether decreased drug efflux capacity in CsA-treated patients might also contribute to apoptosis susceptibility of naïve B cells.</s><s>Therefore, we obtained blood from additional acute leukemia patients, who were under CsA-treatment, at days 120 to 180 and showed a notable presence of naïve B cells (clinical characteristics see Supplementary Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S1</ref>).</s><s>We observed a significantly decreased percentage of naïve B cells extruding the dye R123 for patients compared with those for HC (median percentage R123 À naïve B cells: HC, 51; allo-HSCT, 31, P .05)</s><s>(Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">7</ref>).</s><s>No drug efflux was seen at 4 C (negative control) and it was strongly diminished with addition of CsA in both groups.</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_1">L expression on CD3 þ , CD3 þ CD4 þ and CD3 þ CD8 þ T</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>In this study, we were interested in identifying mechanisms that could potentially contribute to sustained memory B cell paucity after allo-HSCT.</s><s>Because secondary lymphoid organs are inaccessible in the post-transplantation follow-up in surviving patients, and also few studies have demonstrated direct correlations between circulating cells and those found in lymphoid tissues based on microarray analyses of cell subsets with similar flow cytometric phenotypes <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19]</ref>, we analyzed peripheral blood B and T cell subset phenotypes and functionalities to identify clues about lymphocytic defects that might impair the GC reaction in allo-HSCT patients.</s><s>In accordance with previous studies, we observed a sustained peripheral CD4 þ T cell and CD27 þ memory B cell paucity up to 1 year after allo-HSCT <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">20]</ref>.</s><s>CD4 þ T cell paucity was even more pronounced in ATG-treated patients than in non-ATGetreated patients, in accordance with our previously published data <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[21]</ref>.</s><s>CD27 þ memory B cell paucity was comparable in both groups.</s><s>Prolonged low CD27 þ memory B cell numbers may simply result from a shorter history of antigen encounter in patients, but this appears unlikely, as donor B cells are constantly encountering alloantigen.</s><s>In addition to these findings, we found a rapid recovery of DN B cells.</s><s>In mice, DN B cells supposedly represent extra-follicularedeveloping progenitors of CD27 þ memory B cells that fail to go through a GC reaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[24]</ref>.</s><s>Thus, the normalization of DN B cells in our patients could indicate an intact extra-follicular differentiation pathway, partly replenishing the B cell memory after transplantation.</s><s>Normal numbers of plasmablasts, which derive from GC reactions, like the deficient CD27 þ memory B cells, might argue for a specific defect only in the pathway towards memory B cell generation.</s><s>Alternatively, these might also derive from extrafollicular B cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Decreased memory and increased plasmablast compartment in patients with chronic GVHD have been previously shown by de Masson et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref>.</s><s>This we could not observe, which might possibly be attributed to the much later time point of analysis (mean follow-up, 41 months after HSCT in patients without chronic GVHD and 44 months in patients with chronic GVHD).</s><s>In accordance with our results, Sarantopoulos et al. observed no significant differences in absolute numbers of CD27 þ B cells in patients with and without chronic GVHD <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[27]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Activated T FH cells were shown in mice to support GC formation by producing cytokines such as IL-21, which mediate class-switch recombination and somatic hypermutation of GC B cells and their differentiation into memory B cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[28]</ref>.</s><s>For the majority of patients and in particular for chronic GVHD patients, we observed decreased frequencies of CXCR5 þ cells within CD4 þ T cells, which supposedly represents a circulating memory compartment of T FH cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref>.</s><s>This indicates that not only quantitatively reduced CD4 þ T cells but also reduced formation of T FH cells after GC defects may account for reduced memory B cell formation in patients.</s><s>To our knowledge, the frequency of recirculating memory T FH cells has not been investigated in allo-HSCT patients before.</s></p><p><s>Murine T FH and B cells migrate via CXCR5 towards CXCL13-producing FDCs into the B cell follicle to take part in the GC reaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30]</ref>.</s><s>Although the CXCR5 level appeared normal on T FH cells, we observed significantly reduced CXCR5 levels on naïve and memory B cell in subsets of patients.</s><s>CCR7 expression, important for the B cell entry into the T cell zone of secondary lymphoid organs, was slightly reduced on naïve B cells.</s><s>Because decreased levels of CXCR5 and CCR7 on B cells have been associated with reduced migration capacity towards the respective ligands CXCL13 and CCL21 in humans <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref>, lower CXCR5 expression on naïve B cells in our patients could suggest an impaired migration capacity into the B cell follicle and consequently reduced participation in GC reactions.</s></p><p><s>In mice, the interaction of naïve CD4 þ T cells with antigen-presenting B cells contributes to priming of T FH cells and maintains T FH cell responses and, thereby, GC formation of memory B cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[33]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34]</ref>.</s><s>We observed significantly reduced HLA-DR expression on naïve B cells, which could impair B-T cell interaction within a GC reaction because of a reduced antigen-presenting function towards CD4 þ T cells.</s><s>This could further contribute to the lower number of memory T FH cells in our patients.</s></p><p><s>Strikingly, patients' B cells at day 360 displayed a 3-fold higher apoptosis rate compared with those of HC when stimulating PBMCs with CD40 L and CpG.</s><s>Additionally, T cells also displayed increased apoptosis in this stimulation setting, hinting at multiple survival defects that could possibly impair the GC reaction of patients.</s><s>Increased B cell apoptosis may be attributed to increased numbers of immature transitional B cells, which are likely more prone to apoptosis than mature B cells are.</s><s>However, at day 360, mature naïve B cells were predominating in all patients so that differences in apoptosis rates between HC and patients are unlikely to be caused by an immature B cell state in patients only.</s><s>Importantly, we observed profoundly increased apoptosis of patient B cells after CD40L/anti-IgM stimulation, which was further increased by addition of CpG.</s><s>These stimulations mimic the T celledependent B cell activation as occurring during the GC reaction.</s><s>CD40 signaling has been shown in mice deficient for CD40 or CD40L to be critical for T celledependent Ig class switching, GC differentiation, and formation of memory B cells and long-lived plasma cells of BCR-activated B cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">15]</ref>.</s><s>TLR-9 signaling enhances T celledependent antibody responses of BCR-activated B cells at multiple stages of the GC reaction, such as by increasing the number of T FH cells and GC B cells and by augmenting class switch to IgG2a, affinity maturation, and memory antibody responses <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>CD40/TLR-9, CD40/BCR, and CD40/BCR/TLR-9 stimulatione induced death of B cells was even more pronounced in patients with chronic GVHD than in those without chronic GVHD.</s><s>Allen et al. has shown increased survival rates and an increased metabolic state of B cells in patients with active chronic GVHD compared with in patients without chronic GVHD <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[35]</ref>.</s><s>However, these authors only investigated spontaneous apoptosis but not B cell activationeinduced cell death.</s><s>Whether the increased activation-induced cell death, which we observed, is associated with a hyperactivated state of B cells in chronic GVHD patients remains to be elucidated.</s><s>Increased CD69 expression on B cells from chronic GVHD patients before stimulation might support an increased activation status of B cells in chronic GVHD patients, whereas decreased percentages of CD69-expressing B cells after stimulation could be explained by rapid apoptosis of activated B cells.</s></p><p><s>To better understand the higher susceptibility to apoptosis, we determined Fas/Fas-L expression on B and T cells during stimulation with CpG/CD40L.</s><s>In mice, Fas expression on activated GC B cells is an important negative regulator of B and T cell survival <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[36]</ref>.</s><s>High expression of Fas on murine GC B cells has been shown to be associated with susceptibility to Fas-mediated apoptosis in vitro <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[37]</ref>.</s><s>In line with that, Fas ablation in murine GC B cells resulted in fatal B and T cell proliferation and increased memory B cell formation, which was prevented by blocking B-T cell interaction and GC formation <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[36]</ref>.</s><s>We observed significantly increased Fas expression on B and CD4 þ T cells ex vivo, suggesting a higher susceptibility of both subsets to apoptosis.</s><s>For B cells, higher Fas expression might further indicate an increased activation status, as Fas was significantly up-regulated upon stimulation, which is known to occur after T celledependent activation via CD40 signaling.</s><s>Although we observed a strong Fas up-regulation on B cells from patients and HC, Fas-L was significantly up-regulated only on CD4 þ T cells of the patients.</s><s>Together with an increased Fas expression on B cell subsets before stimulation, this could explain the increased apoptosis susceptibility of patient B cells.</s><s>BCR and TLR-9 signaling have been shown to collaborate in rescuing B cells from Fas-induced apoptosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[38]</ref>.</s><s>Whether patient B cells differ in Fas-induced pro-apoptotic or BCR/TLR-9 induces anti-apoptotic signaling events might be an important indication for future investigations.</s><s>Increased Fas-FasL interaction during T celledependent B cell activation could potentially contribute to decreased GC memory B cell formation in allo-HSCT patients.</s><s>This is in line with a previous study, showing decreased Ig-production after in vitro stimulation of B cells in the presence of T cells, suggesting defects in T cell helper or T cell suppressor activity in allo-HSCT patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[39]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In a murine allogeneic transplantation model, B cell paucity was significantly reduced in recipients of Fas-Ledeficient donor T cells, suggesting a role of the Fas-FasL system in lymphoid hypoplasia <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[40]</ref>.</s><s>Inflammatory cytokines, such as IFNg and TNFa, are increased after allo-HSCT in patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[41]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[42]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[43]</ref> and contribute to the up-regulation of Fas on lymphocyte progenitors in bone marrow <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">45]</ref>.</s><s>One half of a year after transplantation, we could still detect elevated plasma levels of inflammatory cytokines and chemokines, including TNFa, MCP-1, and IP-10.</s><s>These had been shown before to be elevated within the first 100 days after allo-HSCT but have not been investigated at later time points <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">46]</ref>.</s><s>Thus, a sustained inflammatory status might support Fas-L expression on (allo)-activated T cells and Fas expression on B cells, rendering them more susceptible to apoptosis.</s><s>Interestingly, we further found that naïve B cells in CsA-treated patients displayed decreased drug efflux capacity.</s><s>This might suggest that not on only immunological mechanisms but also treatmentassociated cytotoxicity after inhibition of drug efflux capacity by immunosuppressive treatment might render naive B cells intrinsically more "fragile" and more susceptible to apoptosis.</s><s>This, in turn, could reduce the number of naïve B cells potentially participating in the GC reaction.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p><s>The results of our analyses on peripheral B and T cell phenotypes and functionalities reveal multiple lymphocytic defects that could, if similarly found within secondary lymphoid organs, impair the GC-dependent generation of memory B cells at different stages in patients who have undergone transplantation, thus providing a basis for investigation in murine transplantation models.</s><s>We propose the following model (Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref>).</s><s>B cells in a more apoptosis-prone state and functional defects in the GCreaction cause persistent memory B cell paucity and, thus, susceptibility to infections 1 year after HSCT.</s><s>Our data emphasize the careful consideration of comprehensive anti-infectious prophylactic treatment even 1 year after allo-HSCT, a control of vaccination responses at immune cell level, and the assessment of adoptive memory B cell transfer as a treatment strategy to support the immune function after transplantation.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Sustained low CD27 þ memory B cell and CD4 þ T FH cell numbers after allo-HSCT.</s><s>PBMCs (HC, n ¼ 12; patients at day 180, n ¼ 33, and day 360, n ¼ 21) were analyzed for the number of (A) CD19 þ B and CD3 þ T cells, (B) within CD19 þ B cells for the number of marginal zone-like (MZ-like), switched memory, double negative (DN) B cells and plasmablasts and (C) within CD3 þ T cells for the number of CD4 þ T helper cells.</s><s>Cells/ml blood and median values for HC (squares) and patients (black dots) are given.</s><s>(D) The percentage of memory CXCR5 þ T FH cells within CD3 þ CD4 þ T cells was determined (HC n ¼ 11, patients at day 360, n ¼ 12).</s><s>Dot plots show representative examples for the gating of CD19 þ B cell subsets (CD38 hi CD24 À plasmablasts, CD27 þ IgD À switched memory, CD27 þ IgD þ MZ-like, CD27 À IgD À DN B cells, B) and the gating of CD4 þ T cells within CD3 þ T cells (C) and CXCR5 þ T FH cells within CD3 þ CD4 þ T cells (D) for a HC and an allo-HSCT patient at day 360.</s><s>Statistical significant differences between HC and patients are depicted.</s><s>*P .05,</s><s>**P .001.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,66.27,184.14,447.35,484.38" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Sustained low CD27 þ memory B cell and CD4 þ T FH cell numbers after allo-HSCT.</s><s>PBMCs (HC, n ¼ 12; patients at day 180, n ¼ 33, and day 360, n ¼ 21) were analyzed for the number of (A) CD19 þ B and CD3 þ T cells, (B) within CD19 þ B cells for the number of marginal zone-like (MZ-like), switched memory, double negative (DN) B cells and plasmablasts and (C) within CD3 þ T cells for the number of CD4 þ T helper cells.</s><s>Cells/ml blood and median values for HC (squares) and patients (black dots) are given.</s><s>(D) The percentage of memory CXCR5 þ T FH cells within CD3 þ CD4 þ T cells was determined (HC n ¼ 11, patients at day 360, n ¼ 12).</s><s>Dot plots show representative examples for the gating of CD19 þ B cell subsets (CD38 hi CD24 À plasmablasts, CD27 þ IgD À switched memory, CD27 þ IgD þ MZ-like, CD27 À IgD À DN B cells, B) and the gating of CD4 þ T cells within CD3 þ T cells (C) and CXCR5 þ T FH cells within CD3 þ CD4 þ T cells (D) for a HC and an allo-HSCT patient at day 360.</s><s>Statistical significant differences between HC and patients are depicted.</s><s>*P .05,</s><s>**P .001.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Migration and antigen-presenting defects might impair the GC reaction.</s><s>The mean fluorescent intensity (MFI) and median values are shown for the expression of CXCR5, CCR7, and HLA-DR on naïve B cells (HC, n ¼ 11, squares; patients at day 180, n ¼ 27, circles, and day 360, n ¼ 20, triangles).</s><s>Significant differences between HC and patients are depicted.</s><s>*P .05.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,317.88,59.75,223.68,101.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. High CD40L/CpG stimulationeinduced apoptosis of B cells.</s><s>PBMCs were stimulated with CpG/CD40L.</s><s>(A) Shown is the percentage of propidium iodide (PI) À AnnexinV þ early apoptotic, PI þ AnnexinV þ late apoptotic and PI þ AnnexinV À necrotic B (upper graphs) and T (lower graphs) cells (HC, n ¼ 7, black; patients at day 360, n ¼ 7, white) before and after stimulation.</s><s>(B) B cell apoptosis/necrosis before and after stimulation is given for patients without chronic GVHD (white dots) and patients with chronic GVHD (grey dots).</s><s>Lines indicate median values.</s><s>Dot plots depict representative examples for a HC and a patient after stimulation.</s><s>Significant differences between HC and patients are given.</s><s>*P .05,</s><s>**P .001.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,65.82,59.76,448.29,398.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. Stimulation-induced B cell apoptosis is paralleled by aberrant Fas/FasL expression.</s><s>Shown are the percentages and median values of (A) the Fas expression on CD19 þ B cell subsets (HC, n ¼ 12, squares; patients at day 180, n ¼ 27, circles and day 360, n ¼ 21, triangles) and (B,C) the Fas and Fas-L expression on CD3 þ , CD3 þ CD4 þ and CD3 þ CD8 þ Tcells and B cells (HC, n ¼ 7, patients day 360, n ¼ 7) before (black) and after (white) PBMC stimulation with CpG/CD40L.</s><s>Dot plots show representative examples for the gating of Fas-expressing CD19 þ B cells (B) and Fas-L expressing CD3 þ CD4 þ T cells (C) before and after stimulation for a HC and an allo-HSCT patient at day 360.</s><s>Significant differences between HC and patients and between values before and after stimulation are given.</s><s>*P .05,</s><s>**P .001.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,76.59,59.76,455.02,459.21" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. Stimulation-induced B cell apoptosis is paralleled by aberrant Fas/FasL expression.</s><s>Shown are the percentages and median values of (A) the Fas expression on CD19 þ B cell subsets (HC, n ¼ 12, squares; patients at day 180, n ¼ 27, circles and day 360, n ¼ 21, triangles) and (B,C) the Fas and Fas-L expression on CD3 þ , CD3 þ CD4 þ and CD3 þ CD8 þ Tcells and B cells (HC, n ¼ 7, patients day 360, n ¼ 7) before (black) and after (white) PBMC stimulation with CpG/CD40L.</s><s>Dot plots show representative examples for the gating of Fas-expressing CD19 þ B cells (B) and Fas-L expressing CD3 þ CD4 þ T cells (C) before and after stimulation for a HC and an allo-HSCT patient at day 360.</s><s>Significant differences between HC and patients and between values before and after stimulation are given.</s><s>*P .05,</s><s>**P .001.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. Increased CD40/BCR and CD40/BCR/TLR-9-induced B cell apoptosis in allo-HSCT patients.</s><s>PBMCs were stimulated with anti-IgM/CD40L (upper graphs) or with anti-IgM/CD40L/CpG (lower graphs).</s><s>(A) The percentages of propidium iodide (PI) À AnnexinV þ early apoptotic, PI þ AnnexinV þ late apoptotic, and PI þ AnnexinV À necrotic B cells and (B) the percentage of CD69-expressing B cells before and after stimulation are given (HC, n ¼ 4, black dots; patients at day 360, n ¼ 7, white dots).</s><s>(C,D) Shown are the results of A and B for patients without chronic GVHD (white dots) and with chronic GVHD (grey dots).</s><s>Lines indicate median values.</s><s>Significant differences between HC and patients are given.</s><s>**P .001.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,66.27,59.76,447.35,517.78" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6.</s><s>Increased activated B cell phenotype and inflammatory serum cytokines.</s><s>(A,B) The percentages of CD86-and CXCR3-expressing B cell subsets with median values are shown (HC, n ¼ 12, squares; patients at day 180, n ¼ 27, circles, and day 360, n ¼ 21, triangles).</s><s>(C) Levels of indicated inflammatory cytokines (upper row) and chemokines (lower row) in plasma and median values are depicted (HC, n ¼ 10; patients at day 180, n ¼ 16).</s><s>Statistical significant differences between HC and patients are given.</s><s>*P .05,</s><s>**P .001.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,100.40,59.75,407.48,579.86" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Decreased naïve B cell drug efflux capacity as a result of immunosuppression and increased Fas expression on naïve B and CD4 þ T cells due to persistent inflammation renders both participants of GC-reactions pro-apoptotic.</s><s>Within secondary lymphoid organs, decreased CXCR5 levels on B cells impair proper migration into the B cell follicle towards CXCL13-producing antigen-presenting FDCs, thus effectively impairing GC induction.</s><s>As a consequence of low CD4 þ T cell numbers due to impaired thymic activity, CD4 þ T cell priming by dendritic cells and formation of effector T helper and pre-GC T FH cells occur less frequently.</s><s>Pre-GC T FH cells normally migrate to the T-B cell border to interact with antigen-activated B cells.</s><s>Furthermore, decreased HLA-DRedependent antigen presentation by B cells impairs the maintenance of T FH cells.</s><s>Increased BCR/ CD40/TLR-9 signalingeinduced apoptosis of B cells during T celledependent B cell activation leads to reduced GC formation of memory B cells and might potentially be attributed to an aberrant up-regulation of Fas-L on activated CD4 þ T cells The extra-follicular non-GC differentiation of DN B cells may be not affected.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 7. Decreased B cell drug efflux capacity in CsA-treated patients.</s><s>Representative examples for R123 À -(effluxing) naïve B cells at 4 C (negative control), 37 C, and 37 C þ CsA are shown for an HC and patient at D120.</s><s>Below, the percentages of R123 À naïve B cells and median values are depicted (HC, n ¼ 9, squares; patients at D120-180, n ¼ 6, dots).</s><s>Statistical significant differences between HC and patients are given.</s><s>*P .05.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,317.25,59.75,224.83,440.16" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="11,52.61,59.76,474.67,342.43" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>StatisticsScatter plot depictions with median values are shown.</s><s>The 2-sided Mann-Whitney U-test was used for comparisons between 2 groups and was performed with the GraphPad Prism-v5.0.</s><s>P values of .05 were considered statistically significant.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Patients' Clinical Characteristics</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Characteristic</cell><cell>n ¼ 35</cell></row><row><cell>Median age, yr</cell><cell>57</cell></row><row><cell>&lt;50</cell><cell>14</cell></row><row><cell>!50</cell><cell>21</cell></row><row><cell>Sex</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>17</cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell>18</cell></row><row><cell>Diagnosis</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>AML</cell><cell>33</cell></row><row><cell>ALL</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>Donor</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>MRD</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>MUD</cell><cell>25</cell></row><row><cell>Conditioning therapy</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Full-intensity</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>Reduced-intensity</cell><cell>27</cell></row><row><cell>ATG</cell><cell>30</cell></row><row><cell>Chronic GVHD after d 100</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>No</cell><cell>23</cell></row><row><cell>Grade 1-3</cell><cell>12</cell></row><row><cell>Viral reactivation</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CMV</cell><cell>14</cell></row><row><cell>EBV</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">AML, acute myeloid leukemia; ALL, acute lymphoblastic leukemia; MUD,</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">matched unrelated donor; MRD, matched related donor; CMV, cytomega-</cell></row><row><cell>lovirus; EBV, Epstein-Barr virus.</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>The authors thank Sabine Diehl und Doreen Uhlenbroch for providing us necessary transplantation-related information.</s><s>All the physicians and nurses from the Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Department of Hematology, Oncology and Tumorimmunology are thanked for their care of patients and assistance in obtaining blood samples.</s></p><p><s>Financial disclosure statement: The authors declare that there are no financial disclosures.</s></p><p><s>Conflicts of interests: None.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</head><p><s>Supplementary data related to this article can be found online at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.bbmt.2015.08.008.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reconstitution of the immune system after hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Storek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Geddes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semin Immunopathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="425" to="437" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immune reconstitution after hematopoietic cell transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bosch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Storek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Hematol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="324" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bone marrow T-cell infiltration during acute GVHD is associated with delayed B cell recovery and function after HSCT</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Johrens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Anagnostopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="963" to="972" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The cytolytic molecules Fas ligand and TRAIL are required for murine thymic graft-versus-host disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Na</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Yim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="343" to="356" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transitional B cells in humans: characterization and insight from B lymphocyte reconstitution after hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Marie-Cardine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Divay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Dutot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">127</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="25" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation recipients have defects of both switched and IgM memory B cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>D'orsogna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Krueger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol Blood Marrow Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="795" to="803" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">B lymphocyte reconstitution after hematopoietic stem cell transplantation: functional immaturity and slow recovery of memory CD27þ B cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Avanzini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Locatelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dos</forename><surname>Santos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp Hematol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="480" to="486" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">White pulp reconstitution after human bone marrow transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nakayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hirabayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ito</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Pathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">143</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1111" to="1120" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Abnormal CD4:CD8 ratios and delayed germinal center reconstitution in lymph nodes of human graft recipients with graft-versus-host disease (GVHD): an immunohistological study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Sale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alavaikko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Schaefers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp Hematol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1017" to="1021" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Follicular dendritic cells help establish follicle identity and promote B cell retention in germinal centers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Exp Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">208</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2497" to="2510" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ig heavy chain third complementarity determining regions (H CDR3s) after stem cell transplantation do not resemble the developing human fetal H CDR3s in size distribution and Ig gene utilization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gokmen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Raaphorst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Boldt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Teale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2802" to="2814" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immunoglobulin heavy chain variable region gene usage in bone marrow transplant recipients: lack of somatic mutation indicates a maturational arrest</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Milner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Glas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1873" to="1880" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Proposed model of defects contributing to sustained memory B cell paucity. On the left, homeostatic condition without presence of an antigen and on the right in presence of an appropriate antigen</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Figure 8. By Demski Design</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human blood CXCR5(þ) CD4(þ) T cells are counterparts of T follicular cells and contain specific subsets that differentially support antibody secretion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Morita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Schmitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bentebibel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="108" to="121" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The immune responses in CD40-deficient mice: impaired immunoglobulin class switching and germinal center formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kawabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Naka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yoshida</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="178" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mice deficient for the CD40 ligand</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Foy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Laman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="431" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toll-like receptor 9 signaling acts on multiple elements of the germinal center to enhance antibody responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Rookhuizen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Defranco</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="E3224" to="E3233" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ABCB1 transporter discriminates human resting naive B cells from cycling transitional and memory B cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wirths</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lanzavecchia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3433" to="3441" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human circulating PD-1þCXCR3-CXCR5þ memory Tfh cells are highly functional and correlate with broadly neutralizing HIV antibody responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Locci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Havenar-Daughton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Landais</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="758" to="769" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human blood IgM &quot;memory&quot; B cells are circulating splenic marginal zone B cells harboring a prediversified immunoglobulin repertoire</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Weller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3647" to="3654" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinctions between CD8þ and CD4þ T-cell regenerative pathways result in prolonged T-cell subset imbalance after intensive chemotherapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mackall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fleisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3700" to="3707" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rabbit antithymocyte globulin (thymoglobulin) impairs the thymic output of both conventional and regulatory CD4þ T cells after allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in adult patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Na</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wittenbecher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dziubianau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Haematologica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="30" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rituximab improves peripheral B cell abnormalities in human systemic lupus erythematosus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Anolik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Barnard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cappione</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3580" to="3590" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new population of cells lacking expression of CD27 represents a notable component of the B cell memory compartment in systemic lupus erythematosus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Anolik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cappione</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">178</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6624" to="6633" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phenotypic and functional heterogeneity of human memory B cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sanz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Anolik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extrafollicular plasmablast B cells play a key role in carrying retroviral infection to peripheral organs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Finke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Baribaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Diggelmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Acha-Orbea</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">166</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6266" to="6275" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CD24(hi)CD27(þ) and plasmablast-like regulatory B cells in human chronic graft-versus-host disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>De Masson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bouaziz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Le</forename><surname>Buanec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1830" to="1839" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Altered B cell homeostasis and excess BAFF in human chronic graft-versus-host disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sarantopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Stevenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3865" to="3874" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">T follicular helper (TFH) cells in normal and dysregulated immune responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>King</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tangye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mackay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu Rev Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="741" to="766" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phenotype and functions of memory Tfh cells in human blood</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Schmitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bentebibel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ueno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="436" to="442" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finding the right niche: B cell migration in the early phases of T-dependent antibody responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Pereira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cyster</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="413" to="419" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Expansion of functionally immature transitional B cells is associated with humanimmunodeficient states characterized by impaired humoral immunity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Cuss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Avery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Cannons</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">176</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1506" to="1516" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ICOS receptor instructs T follicular helper cell versus effector cell differentiation via induction of the transcriptional repressor Bcl6</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kageyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Eto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="932" to="946" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Follicular helper T cell differentiation requires continuous antigen presentation that is independent of unique B cell signaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Deenick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="253" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cutting edge: dendritic cellrestricted antigen presentation initiates the follicular helper T cell program but cannot complete ultimate effector differentiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Goenka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Barnett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Silver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">187</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1091" to="1095" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">B cells from patients with chronic GVHD are activated and primed for survival via BAFF-mediated pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Fore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wooten</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2529" to="2536" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fas receptor expression in germinalcenter B cells is essential for T and B lymphocyte homeostasis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Hao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Duncan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Seagal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunity</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="615" to="627" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FLICE-inhibitory protein is a key regulator of germinal center B cell apoptosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hennino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Berard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Krammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Defrance</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Exp Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">193</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="447" to="458" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">TLR9-mediated signals rescue B cells from Fas-induced apoptosis via inactivation of caspases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hancz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Koncz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Szili</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sarmay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunol Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">143</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="77" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">B cell, helper T cell, and suppressor T cell abnormalities contribute to disordered immunoglobulin synthesis in patients following bone marrow transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Korsmeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Elfenbein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Goldman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transplantation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="184" to="190" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graft-versus-host-diseaseassociated lymphoid hypoplasia and B cell dysfunction is dependent upon donor T cell-mediated Fas-ligand function, but not perforin function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Riley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Podack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Levy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1366" to="1371" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increased serum levels of tumor necrosis factor alpha precede major complications of bone marrow transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Holler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kolb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Moller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1011" to="1016" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cytopenia and leukocyte recovery shape cytokine fluctuations after myeloablative allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Melenhorst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Haematologica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="867" to="873" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of serum levels of interferon and interferon-dependent secondary messages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Niederwieser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Herold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Woloszczuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transplantation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="620" to="625" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Endogenous IFNgamma during human bone marrow transplantation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional expression of Fas antigen (CD95) on hematopoietic progenitor cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nagafuji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Shibuya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Harada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="883" to="889" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fas antigen expression on CD34þ human marrow cells is induced by interferon gamma and tumor necrosis factor alpha and potentiates cytokine-mediated hematopoietic suppression in vitro</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Maciejewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Selleri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3183" to="3190" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cytokine and chemokine patterns across 100 days after hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in children</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dicarlo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Agarwal-Hashmi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol Blood Marrow Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="361" to="369" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
