<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Two Severe Cases of Tungiasis in Goat Kids in Uganda</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Francis</forename><surname>Mutebi</surname></persName>
							<email>francmutebi10@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Veterinary Medicine, Animal Resources and Biosecurity</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Makerere University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 7062</postBox>
									<settlement>Kampala</settlement>
									<country key="UG">Uganda</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J€</forename><surname>Urgen Kr€</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Parasitology and Tropical Veterinary Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Freie Universit€ at Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Robert-von-Ostertag Street 7-13</addrLine>
									<postCode>14163</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Norbert</forename><surname>Mencke</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Bayer Animal Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>51368</postCode>
									<settlement>Leverkusen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hermann</forename><surname>Feldmeier</surname></persName>
							<email>feldmeier.fuberlin@t-online.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Microbiology and Hygiene</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charit e University Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Benjamin Franklin, Hindenburgdamm 30</addrLine>
									<postCode>12203</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Georg</forename><surname>Von Samson-Himmelstjerna</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Parasitology and Tropical Veterinary Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Freie Universit€ at Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Robert-von-Ostertag Street 7-13</addrLine>
									<postCode>14163</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Charles</forename><surname>Waiswa</surname></persName>
							<email>cwaiswa@covab.mak.ac.ug</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">College of Veterinary Medicine, Animal Resources and Biosecurity</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Makerere University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 7062</postBox>
									<settlement>Kampala</settlement>
									<country key="UG">Uganda</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Two Severe Cases of Tungiasis in Goat Kids in Uganda</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">07458E871924EA4793CB7ED8662C2DC4</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/jisesa/iew016</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 11 December 2015; Accepted 9 February 2016</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:47+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>clinical presentation</term>
					<term>goat</term>
					<term>Tunga penetrans</term>
					<term>Uganda</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Tungiasis ensues from the penetration and burrowing of female sand fleas (Tunga spp.; Siphonaptera: Tungidae) in the skin of mammals.</s><s>There are few case reports of severe tungiasis in goats and in these cases the Tunga species were not in most cases clearly identified.</s><s>Two cases of severe tungiasis caused by Tunga penetrans in goat kids from tungiasis-endemic rural Uganda are reported.</s><s>These are the first severe cases of tungiasis in goats reported from outside South America.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Tungiasis is caused by female sand fleas (Tunga spp.) burrowing in the skin of mammals including humans.</s><s>Although to date 14 species have been characterized in the genus Tunga, only three species, Tunga penetrans, Tunga trimamillata, and Tunga hexalobulata, are known to parasitize domestic animals <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(De Avelar et al. 2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">, Linardi and Avelar 2014</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">, Ezquiaga et al. 2015)</ref>.</s><s>Of the three species, only T. penetrans has been reported in Africa.</s><s>In sub-Saharan Africa, the pathogen parasitizes humans and a wide range of animals <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Ugbomoiko et al. 2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">, Mutebi et al. 2015)</ref>.</s><s>T. trimamillata and T. hexalobulata, which have been reported only in South America, are the main sand flea species affecting domestic ruminants <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Fioravanti et al. 2003</ref><ref type="bibr">, De Avelar et al. 2013</ref><ref type="bibr">, Linardi et al. 2013)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Principally, the life cycle of the T. penetrans consists of broadly two phases; off host development as well as the in situ development in the skin of homeothermic vertebrate hosts.</s><s>In a suitable environment, off-host development progresses through eggs, larvae, pupae before adults emerge in about 17 d <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Nagy et al. 2007</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">, Pampiglione et al. 2009)</ref>.</s><s>A suitable environment has been characterized as one with dry and sandy soils containing some organic matter and away from direct sunlight with a temperature range of 20-31 C <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Linardi et al. 2010)</ref>.</s><s>While both male and female adult fleas are hematophagous, only the females embed in the skin of a wide range of suitable homeothermic hosts, develop by neosomy, lay eggs, and eventually die in situ in about 30 d after penetration <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Eisele et al. 2003</ref><ref type="bibr">, Feldmeier et al. 2007</ref>).</s><s>Nevertheless, abnormal on-host metamorphosis has been reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Thielecke and Feldmeier 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Normally, shortly after penetration, female sand fleas hypertrophy and increase in size by 2000 times within 2 wk <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Eisele et al. 2003)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>During its development in host skin, T. penetrans evokes a severe inflammatory response which is often complicated by bacterial super infections which intensify the inflammation to cause severe morbidity.</s></p><p><s>There are few reported cases of goats infected by T. penetrans, of which, very few have presented with severe morbidity <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Pampiglione et al. 2009</ref>) and all are exclusively from South America <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Trentini et al. 2000</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">, Gustinelli et al. 2006)</ref>.</s><s>This short communication presents two cases of severe manifestations of T. penetrans infection in goat kids detected during an epidemiological survey in rural impoverished communities in Busoga, Uganda <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Mutebi et al. 2015)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case Reports</head><p><s>Case 1</s></p><p><s>A 3-wk-old female goat kid with a history of weakness and inappetence was detected in Masolya Village, Bugiri District, Busoga, Uganda, where tungiasis is highly prevalent among humans.</s><s>It was under free range management and neither anthelminthic nor ectoparasitic treatment had ever been administered.</s><s>The kid was clinically anemic (pale mucous membranes), had a starry hair coat, and was also infested with Ctenocephalides canis.</s><s>A total of 34 sand flea lesions were detected on the four limbs.</s><s>According to the Fortaleza staging system <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Eisele et al. 2003)</ref>, 21 were viable (Stages IIa to IIIb) and 13 were dead (Stage IV).</s><s>On the limbs, sand fleas were localized mainly on the coronary band of the claws but some were embedded on the soles of the hooves (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A and B</ref>).</s><s>The affected hoof wall was necrotic and had peeled off from the sole to expose the underlying soft tissue (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Sites with viable lesions were painful on palpation and the kid exhibited shifting limb lameness while moving (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref>).</s><s>It spent most of the time lying down but its body temperature was within the normal range (38.9 C).</s><s>The household also had a mature goat (dam to the affected kid), a sow, a dog, and a cat.</s><s>The sow, the dog, and all four household members were infected by T. penetrans but the mature goat and the cat did not have any sand flea lesions.</s><s>Goats were housed in a kitchen with earthen floor and the homestead was generally of poor sanitation with household waste being disposed off in the garden close to the compound.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case 2</head><p><s>A 3-wk-old male goat kid was detected from Busindha Village, Bugiri District in which human tungiasis is endemic.</s><s>It was kept under free range management and had no history of ectoparasite or helminth control measures.</s><s>It had six viable (Stages IIa to IIIb) embedded sand fleas which were exclusively on the right hind leg at the coronary band of both hooves and the accessory digits.</s><s>The kid was neither anemic (as per the physical examination) nor was it pyrexic (body temperature 38.4 C).</s><s>The area around the attachment sites of Stage III lesions on the coronary band of the dew claws was edematous (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>, arrows) and very painful on touch as evidenced by limb retraction and bleating on touch.</s></p><p><s>The affected limb was raised off the ground when the kid was moving (swinging lameness; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>).</s><s>On the same compound, there were three adult goats (1 yr), one sow, one cat, and eight chickens.</s><s>The other goats, the four examined chickens, and a cat were not affected but 12 out of 13 household members had tungiasis.</s><s>The affected goat kid was roaming on the compound during day time whereas other goats were tethered in bushes.</s><s>However, it was housed during the night with other goats in a goat shade on the compound which had a dusty floor.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Intervention</head><p><s>Affected kids were dewormed with Wormicid 150 (levamisole 150 mg; Cosmos Limited, Nairobi City, Kenya) and Supona aerosol (chlorfenvinphos 4.8%, dichlorphos 0.75%, and gentian violet 0.145%; Pfizer Laboratories (Pty) Limited, Sandton, 2196, South Africa) was applied on the affected sites to kill the embedded sand fleas and control secondary bacterial infections.</s><s>One viable sand flea (Stage III) was extracted from each of the goats, fixed in 70% ethanol, and transported to the laboratory at the College of Veterinary Medicine, Animal Resources and Bio-security, Makerere University and the Freie Universit€ at, Berlin, Germany, for morphological identification based on features described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(De Avelar et al. 2012</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">, Ezquiaga et al. 2015)</ref>.</s><s>The chitin of the anterior hypertrophic abdominal segment of the gravid fleas had an appearance reminiscent of a clover leaf on light and electron microscopy hence identified as T. penetrans <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Mutebi et al. 2015)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In a follow-up 1 wk after the treatment, the kid in Case 1 was reported to have died 4 d after treatment following a short-clinical course of illness characterized by anorexia and a mucoid nasal discharge.</s><s>No viable sand fleas were detected and healing by re-epithelialization had taken place when the kid in Case 2 was re-examined 1 wk post-treatment.</s><s>The kid had also regained a normal gait.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Data on tungiasis-associated morbidity in animals is scarce.</s><s>Regarding goats, only a few cases have been described in South America <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Trentini et al. 2000</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">, Gustinelli et al. 2006</ref>).</s><s>Most of these were attributed to T. trimamillata, which was initially misidentified as T. penetrans <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Linardi et al. 2013</ref>).</s><s>An epidemiological study in Uganda during which these two cases were identified, detected tungiasis in only two goat kids from two villages out of 848 goats examined from 10 villages <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Mutebi et al. 2015)</ref>.</s><s>In general, it appears that goats represent rather uncommon hosts of T. penetrans in sub-Saharan Africa.</s><s>This may be attributed to the tough horny hoof wall and thick skin which increase as the goats mature and move on rough surfaces resulting into a considerable barrier for penetrating sand fleas.</s><s>This may explain why mature goats on the same compound were not infected.</s><s>However, goat kids still have soft hoof walls and thinner stratum corneum.</s><s>In this case, the affected kids were the only young goats (5 mo) on the compounds on which they were detected.</s></p><p><s>Necrosis of the hoof wall in one kid could be attributed to a dense cluster of sand fleas exerting pressure on tissues at the site of penetration.</s><s>In addition, the goat kid may have rubbed the itchy lesions against hard surfaces further aggravating the necrosis.</s><s>The site of extensive necrosis (soles of the hooves, Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A and B</ref>) further supports this assertion since the sole of the hoof is the area that goats can easily rub against hard surfaces.</s></p><p><s>In humans and pigs, the degree of morbidity parallels the intensity of infection <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Feldmeier et al. 2004</ref>).</s><s>From the cases presented it appears that in young goats, even a few lesions can induce severe morbidity as indicated by severe inflammation, tissue necrosis, and lameness.</s><s>Therefore, tungiasis should be included among the differential diagnoses whenever hoof necrosis and lameness are detected in goats in endemic areas.</s><s>The cause of death of one of the kids was not ascertained.</s><s>However, from the clinical history obtained, respiratory complications such as pneumonia are implicated.</s></p><p><s>As demonstrated in this article, animal tungiasis can cause severe morbidity.</s><s>It is also an important epidemiological factor in human tungiasis in sub-Saharan Africa <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Mutebi et al. 2015)</ref>.</s><s>Therefore, ectoparasite control should be encouraged among animal owners.</s><s>However, an effective compound is yet to be identified.</s><s>The chlorfenvinphos and dichlorphos in the Supona wound spray appeared to be tungicidal at least in one kid and the antibacterial effects of gentian violet presumably helped to curb super infections thus facilitating healing.</s><s>However, these effects need to be validated through controlled studies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>Tungiasis can cause severe morbidity in goats especially kids manifesting with variable degrees of lameness.</s><s>Therefore, tungiasis should be considered a differential diagnosis when lameness and hoof lesions are detected in goats in endemic areas.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1.</s><s>Tungiasis in Case 1. Stage III lesions on coronary band of the dew claw (arrows) and bilateral hoof wall loss of the front limb (A).</s><s>Dead sand fleas, necrosis, and loss of hoof wall tissues of the hind leg (B).</s><s>Infected goat kid with lameness (C).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,124.67,59.47,363.23,195.14" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 2. Tungiasis in Case 2. Right hind leg of a goat kid with viable sand fleas (A) surrounded by edematous zones at the coronary band of claws (arrows).</s><s>Goat kid with swinging lameness (B).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,126.26,59.47,359.96,128.58" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p><s>The Management of High Heights Initiatives and the goat owners are appreciated for their support.</s><s>No specific funding was received for this study.</s><s>The cases described were detected during an epidemiological survey of animal tungiasis which was supported by Bayer Animal Health, Leverkusen, German and the German Academic Exchange Service (DAAD).</s><s>Data are part of Francis Mutebi s thesis.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new species of Tunga (Siphonaptera: Tungidae) from Brazil with a key to the adult species and neosomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>De Avelar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Linhares</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Linardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Med. Entomol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new species of tunga (siphonaptera: Tungidae) parasitizing cattle from Brazil</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>De Avelar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J F</forename><surname>Filho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Linardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Med. Entomol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="679" to="684" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigations on the biology, epidemiology, pathology and control of Tunga penetrans in Brazil: I. Natural history of tungiasis in man</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eisele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heukelbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Marck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mehlhorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Meckes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Franck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Feldmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Parasitol. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new species of Tunga perforating the osteoderms of its armadillo host in Argentina and redescription of the male of Tunga penetrans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ezquiaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Linardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>De Avelar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lareschi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med. Vet. Entomol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="196" to="204" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigations on the biology, epidemiology, pathology and control of Tunga penetrans in Brazil: IV. Clinical and histopathology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Feldmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eisele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Marck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mehlhorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ribeiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heukelbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Parasitol. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigations on the biology, epidemiology, pathology and control of Tunga penetrans in Brazil. VI. Natural history of the infestation in laboratory-raised Wistar rats</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Feldmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Witt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schwalfenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Linardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ribeiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A C</forename><surname>Capaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Marck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Meckes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mehlhorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mencke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heukelbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Parasitol. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A second species of Tunga (Insecta, Siphonaptera) infecting man; Tunga trimamillata</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fioravanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pampiglione</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Trentini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Parasite</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="282" to="283" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathology of Tunga trimamillata (Siphonaptera, Tungidae) in animals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gustinelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fioravanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Fabbri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Trentini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Onore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Caffara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pampiglione</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ICOPA XI</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006. 2006</date>
			<publisher>Glagow</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neosomes of tungid fleas on wild and domestic animals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Linardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M D</forename><surname>Avelar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Parasitol. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3517" to="3533" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Establishment of Tunga trimamillata (Siphonaptera: Tungidae) in Brazil</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Linardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>De Avelar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Facury Filho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Parasitol. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3239" to="3242" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Occurence of off-host stages of Tunga penetrans (Siphonaptera) in various environments in Brazil</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Linardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M L</forename><surname>Calheiros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Campelo-Junior</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Duarte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heukelbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Feldmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann. Trop. Med. Parasit</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="345" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Animal reservoirs of zoonotic tungiasis in endemic rural villages of Uganda</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mutebi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kr€ Ucken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Feldmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Waiswa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mencke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sentongo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Von-Samson-Himmelstjerna</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Negl. Trop. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e0004126</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Investigations on the life cycle and morphology of Tunga penetrans in Brazil</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Nagy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Abari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>D'haese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Calheiros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heukelbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mencke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Feldmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Parasitol. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="S233" to="S242" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sand flea (Tunga spp.) infections in man and domestic animals: state of the art</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pampiglione</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fioravanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gustinelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Onore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Montovani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Luchetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Trentini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med. Vet. Entomol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="172" to="186" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The fate of the embedded virgin sand flea Tunga penetrans: hypothesis, self-experimentation and photographic sequence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Thielecke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Feldmeier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Travel. Med. Infect. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="440" to="443" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Observations about specimens of Tunga spp. (Siphonaptera: Tungidae) extracted from goats in Ecuador</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Trentini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pampiglione</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gianneto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Finocchiaro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Parassitologia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">65</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pigs are the most important animal reservoirs for Tunga penetrans (jigger flea) in rural Nigeria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ugbomoiko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ariza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heukelbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trop. Doct</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="226" to="227" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
