<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">DIETS OF GIANTS: THE NUTRITIONAL VALUE OF SAUROPOD DIET DURING THE MESOZOIC</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Fiona</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gill</surname></persName>
							<email>f.gill@leeds.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">School of Earth &amp; Environment</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leeds</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>LS2 9JT</postCode>
									<settlement>Leeds</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">€ Urgen</forename><surname>Hummel</surname></persName>
							<email>jhummel@gwdg.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Animal Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Goettingen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Goettingen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Reza</forename><surname>Sharifi</surname></persName>
							<email>rsharif@gwdg.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Animal Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Goettingen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Goettingen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexandra</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
							<email>alexandra.lee@live.co.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">The School of Biosciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Nottingham</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Sutton Bonington Campus, Sutton Bonington</addrLine>
									<postCode>LE12 5RD</postCode>
									<settlement>Leicestershire</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Barry</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lomax</surname></persName>
							<email>barry.lomax@nottingham.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">The School of Biosciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Nottingham</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Sutton Bonington Campus, Sutton Bonington</addrLine>
									<postCode>LE12 5RD</postCode>
									<settlement>Leicestershire</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">DIETS OF GIANTS: THE NUTRITIONAL VALUE OF SAUROPOD DIET DURING THE MESOZOIC</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">048857BB65FF8AA280F04D28AAF49F81</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/pala.12385</idno>
					<note type="submission">received 27 July 2017; accepted in revised form 12 June 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:47+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Mesozoic</term>
					<term>sauropod</term>
					<term>diet</term>
					<term>atmospheric CO 2</term>
					<term>metabolizable energy</term>
					<term>carrying capacity</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>A major uncertainty in estimating energy budgets and population densities of extinct animals is the carrying capacity of their ecosystems, constrained by net primary productivity (NPP) and its digestible energy content.</s><s>The hypothesis that increases in NPP due to elevated atmospheric CO 2 contributed to the unparalleled size of the sauropods has recently been rejected, based on modern studies on herbivorous insects that imply a general, negative correlation of diet quality and increasing CO 2 .</s><s>However, the nutritional value of plants grown under elevated CO 2 levels might be very different for vertebrate megaherbivores than for insects.</s></p><p><s>Here we show plant species-specific responses in metabolizable energy and nitrogen content, equivalent to a two-fold variation in daily food intake estimates for a typical sauropod, for dinosaur food plant analogues grown under CO 2 concentrations spanning estimates for Mesozoic atmospheric concentrations.</s><s>Our results potentially rebut the hypothesis that constraints on sauropod diet quality were driven by Mesozoic CO 2 concentration.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>M A N Y Mesozoic terrestrial ecosystems were dominated by sauropod dinosaurs <ref type="bibr">(Farlow et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sander et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Barrett 2014</ref>) some of which reached over 50 metric tons in body mass during the Jurassic and Cretaceous <ref type="bibr">(Sander et al. 2011)</ref>.</s><s>Global Mesozoic climate was very different to that of the present day, with equable temperatures, a low tropic to pole heat gradient with little polar ice (Frakes &amp; Krassay 1992) and elevated atmospheric CO 2 concentrations.</s><s>A recent compilation of CO 2 estimates <ref type="bibr">(Foster et al. 2017)</ref> based on data from palaeosol, stomata, liverwort and alkenone proxies estimated Mesozoic carbon dioxide levels of between 229 (Late Cretaceous) and 2132 ppm (Late Triassic) compared to the present (~400 ppm) <ref type="bibr">(Cerling 1991</ref><ref type="bibr">(Cerling , 1992;;</ref><ref type="bibr">Andrews et al. 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ghosh et al. 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr">Beerling et al. 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr">McElwain 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ekart et al. 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lee 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Lee &amp; Hisada 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">McElwain et al. 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Chen et al. 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ghosh et al. 2001</ref><ref type="bibr">Ghosh et al. , 2005;;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tanner et al. 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr">Beerling &amp; Royer 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Nordt et al. 2002</ref><ref type="bibr">Nordt et al. , 2003;;</ref><ref type="bibr">Robinson et al. 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Greenwood et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tabor et al. 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Haworth et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">McElwain et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Prochnow et al. 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sandler 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sun et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Cleveland et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fletcher et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">Beerling et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Leier et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Passalia 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Quan et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Retallack 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Yan et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Barclay et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Bonis et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Doria et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Schaller et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Steinthorsdottir et al. 2011</ref><ref type="bibr">Steinthorsdottir et al. , 2016;;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wan et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Gutierrez &amp; Sheldon 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hong &amp; Lee 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Huang et al. 2012</ref><ref type="bibr">Huang et al. , 2013;;</ref><ref type="bibr">Schaller et al. 2012</ref><ref type="bibr">Schaller et al. , 2015;;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mortazavi et al. 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Franks et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Li et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ludvigson et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mays et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Nordt et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Steinthorsdottir &amp; Vajda 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Whiteside et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Du et al. 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Naafs et al. 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wu et al. 2016)</ref>.</s><s>Both temperature and atmospheric CO 2 can have a profound effect on vegetation and net primary productivity <ref type="bibr">(Beerling &amp; Woodward 2001)</ref>, although other authors have questioned the assumption that CO 2 is the most important driver of plant growth (e.g.</s><s>K€ orner 2015).</s><s>It has been postulated that sauropod gigantism was related to food availability and quality during the Mesozoic, but the nature of this relationship has been disputed.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Burness et al. (2001)</ref> speculated that increases in net primary production (NPP) as a function of elevated Mesozoic atmospheric CO 2 levels was an enabling factor allowing sauropods to achieve their unprecedented size.</s><s>This hypothesis was rejected by <ref type="bibr">Midgley et al. (2002)</ref>, who posited that light, water and nutrients would be limiting factors to increasing NPP even under high atmospheric CO 2 concentrations.</s><s>Outside of direct effects of CO 2 on plant growth (i.e.</s><s>NPP) there are thought to be indirect CO 2 effects on the digestibility and nutritional value of plant material and it is this latter hypothesis we explicitly test in this study.</s><s>This is because numerous authors (e.g.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Midgley et al. 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sander et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wilkinson &amp; Ruxton 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Barrett 2014)</ref> have suggested that even if NPP did increase under elevated atmospheric CO 2 levels, the poor nutritional quality of Mesozoic fodder, either as an inherent trait of non-angiosperm plants <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Weaver 1983)</ref> or due to low nitrogen content as a result of growth under elevated CO 2 <ref type="bibr">(Midgley et al. 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wilkinson &amp; Ruxton 2013)</ref>, may have resulted in sauropods being obliged to consume vast quantities of food, necessitating large body size.</s><s>Much evidence cited by those authors focuses on the response of angiosperms to CO 2 growth concentrations up to twice current ambient levels and the effect on associated insect herbivores (e.g.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Roth &amp; Lindroth 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr">Curtis 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wand et al. 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ehleringer et al. 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">K€ orner 2004)</ref>.</s><s>However, nonangiosperm flora formed the bulk of sauropod diet; Mesozoic atmospheric concentrations of CO 2 at times significantly exceeded twice current ambient levels, and the physiology, digestive processes and metabolism of vertebrate megaherbivores differ greatly from those of insects <ref type="bibr">(Karasov &amp; Douglas 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Consequently, the results of these insect feeding trials may not be directly transferable to understanding food quality for sauropods.</s></p><p><s>Alongside higher nitrogen:energy requirements, a critical difference between insects and sauropods is that the majority of insect herbivores use cell contents, including non-structural carbohydrates such as starches and sugars, as their primary food source, whereas vertebrate megaherbivores utilize cell wall material (i.e.</s><s>structural carbohydrates such as cellulose) as a food source, via fermentation by gut microbes <ref type="bibr">(Karasov &amp; Douglas 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Multiple lines of evidence indicate that sauropod dinosaurs also depended on gut microbes for fermentation of plant material in their diet <ref type="bibr">(Farlow 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hummel &amp; Clauss 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sander et al. 2011</ref>) therefore in vitro fermentation experiments represent an alternative approach to investigating food quality for plants grown under elevated CO 2 <ref type="bibr">(Akin et al. 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr">Carter et al. 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Morgan et al. 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Muntifering et al. 2006)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Combining in vitro fermentation experiments with plant growth experiments at CO 2 concentrations representing Mesozoic atmospheric estimates provides a novel mechanistic framework to evaluate the nutritional value of sauropod food plants and test the competing theories of food quality and sauropod gigantism <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Weaver 1983;</ref><ref type="bibr">Burness et al. 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr">Midgley et al. 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sander et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wilkinson &amp; Ruxton 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Barrett 2014)</ref>.</s><s>We emphasize that the experiments reported here were designed to address the knowledge gaps mentioned above, specifically in the plant species selected (dinosaur food plant analogues, predominantly gymnosperms and monilophytes rather than angiosperms), in the range of CO 2 growth concentrations used, reflecting current consensus on Mesozoic atmospheric CO 2 concentration estimates, and in the method of evaluating nutritional value, here represented by metabolizable energy and nitrogen content.</s><s>Inevitably, our experiments have inherent limitations and represent a gross simplification of reality, but we believe that they can still contribute to the understanding of sauropod food quality during the Mesozoic.</s><s>All experiments were conducted in two walk-in growth room chambers (UNIGRO, UK) meaning two [CO 2 ] treatments could be run concurrently.</s><s>Complete air exchange within each cabinet occurred three times per hour ensuring a fully mixed atmosphere.</s><s>The first sets of experiments were conducted on the three understorey species, the angiosperm R. acris and the monilophytes P. vulgare and E. hyemale.</s><s>The understorey species were grown for three months under treatment.</s><s>Firstly, these species were grown at 400 and 1200 ppm CO 2 for three months (May-August 2012).</s><s>R. acris was grown from seed that germinated under treatment; P. vulgare and E. hyemale were placed under treatment as 3-4 month old plants.</s><s>Secondly the growth chambers were reprogrammed to 800 and 2000 ppm CO 2 and the process repeated with fresh plants (August-November 2012).</s><s>All canopy species were placed under treatment as small 3-5 month old seedlings for a period of 6 months.</s><s>The potting medium used for all plants was Levington M3.</s><s>The canopy species were initially grown at 800 and 2000 ppm CO 2 (July-December 2013) and then new plants were sourced and the process repeated with the growth rooms reprogrammed to 400 and 1200 ppm (January-July 2014).</s><s>All other growth conditions remained constant.</s><s>Plants received 10 hours of light (300 lmol/m 2 /s) per day in a simulated day/night program.</s><s>Night temperature was set at a high of 17°C and daytime temperature peaked at 20°C for the understory and 22°C for the canopy species.</s><s>Relative humidity was set at 70%.</s><s>Throughout the experimental programme set points were monitored and there was minimal deviation from these set points.</s><s>In all cases plants were kept well-watered throughout their experiment and no additional fertilizer was applied due to the relatively short growth period of the experiment.</s><s>Visual inspection of the plants throughout the experimental treatment indicated that plants were not under nutrient stress.</s><s>Extensive ecophysiological measurements taken throughout the experiment and prior to harvest (Lee 2015) also showed no evidence of plant stress.</s><s>In all cases plant material harvested and used in the analysis had developed in the target CO 2 atmosphere.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MATERIAL AND METHOD</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Plant growth experiments</head><p><s>Work in growth chambers is by necessity a trade-off between facilities and time available to undertake the experiments.</s><s>Ideally CO 2 treatments would be repeated or run in parallel in a number of different chambers to fully test for chamber effects; effects driven entirely by the chamber which are independent of growth conditions <ref type="bibr">(Porter et al. 2015)</ref>.</s><s>Whilst this approach is feasible when comparing two different CO 2 concentrations this approach would quickly become untenable when comparing multiple species across multiple CO 2 treatments.</s><s>As an alternative, we have focused on within-chamber plant replication and switching chambers for CO 2 treatments.</s><s>An additional limitation is the relatively short duration of the experiments, which we have acknowledged in the interpretation of our results.</s></p><p><s>At the end of the experimental run (three months for understory plants and six months for canopy species) leaves of the experimental plant material that had developed in the target CO 2 concentration were harvested and then dried at 60°C.</s><s>The duration of the understory versus the canopy experiments was different due to understory plants reaching maturity (either the production of flowers in the case of R. acris or spore production in P. vulgare; E. hyemale was also harvested at this time to allow for comparison) sooner than the canopy plants.</s></p><p><s>Leaves from individual plants (five plants per species per CO 2 treatment) under investigation were harvested, pooled and after drying were milled to ~1 mm.</s><s>From this bulk sample three aliquots were taken for the in vitro fermentation experiments described below.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>In vitro fermentation experiments</head><p><s>Hohenheim Gas Test equipment was used for in vitro evaluation of the digestibility of plant samples.</s><s>Briefly, milled plant samples were incubated with cattle rumen fluid in gas-tight syringes at 37°C <ref type="bibr">(Menke &amp; Steingass 1988)</ref>.</s><s>Gas production techniques are widely applied in agricultural feed evaluation and the strong relationship between digestibility and gas production is due to the direct stoichiometric linking of the production of gas and short chain fatty acids (SCFA) <ref type="bibr">(Bl€ ummel et al. 1999)</ref>.</s><s>The latter are the major end products of gut microbial fermentation and represent the major energy source for the host animal.</s><s>The experiments were conducted over 72 h in order to reliably estimate the fermentation parameters (a + b; k).</s><s>The length of the experiment also reflects the long ingesta retention time inferred for sauropod dinosaurs <ref type="bibr">(Sander et al. 2011)</ref>.</s><s>Gas readings were taken at 4, 8, 12, 24, 32, 48, 56 and 72 h.</s></p><p><s>The fermentation parameters a + b (maximal gas production) and c (fractional fermentation rate) were estimated using the model:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">GP ¼ a þ b Â ð1 À e ÀcÂt Þ</formula><p><s>with GP being gas production at time t, a + b being maximal gas production (mL/200 mg DM) and c being the fractional fermentation rate (per h) <ref type="bibr">(Bl€ ummel &amp; Oerskov 1993)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Metabolizable energy estimation</head><p><s>Metabolizable energy (ME) was estimated from a linear regression set up from a data set of 24 h GP and ME contents of 24 feeds, based on data from (Menke &amp; Huss 1987):</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_1">ME ½MJ=kg DM ¼ 0:1474 Â 24 h GP½mL=200 mg DM þ 2:6412ðR 2 ¼ 0:8154Þ</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Nutrient analyses</head><p><s>Neutral detergent fibre (NDF) and acid detergent lignin (ADL) analyses were done according to official German recommendations (values expressed without residual ash) (VDLUFA 2012).</s><s>Both NDF and ADL were analysed using the Ankom fibre bag technique (Ankom Technology, Macedon, NY, USA).</s></p><p><s>Carbon and nitrogen analysis was carried out using a FLASH EA1121 CNS analyser (Thermo Scientific; https:// www.thermofisher.com).</s><s>Three ~20 mg subsamples of the pooled leaf material were analysed per species per CO 2 treatment.</s><s>Percentages of carbon and nitrogen were determined for each treatment and C:N ratio was calculated from these values.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical analyses</head><p><s>Effects of plant type and CO 2 concentration on fermentation parameters (a + b; c) were evaluated via a two-factorial ANOVA <ref type="bibr">(Gill et al. 2018</ref>, SI 2.1) followed by comparison of means by the Tukey-Kramer method, using SAS software <ref type="bibr">(Gill et al. 2018, SI 3-5)</ref>.</s><s>The Tukey-Kramer method was also applied to evaluate differences in mean % N within taxa <ref type="bibr">(Gill et al. 2018, SI 6)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>To estimate ME of individual taxa grown under estimated Mesozoic atmospheric CO 2 concentrations <ref type="bibr">(Foster et al. 2017)</ref>, polynomial regression equations were applied to the data <ref type="bibr">(Gill et al. 2018, SI 7)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>NITROGEN</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Changes in nitrogen content for the six species investigated did not show any clear trends with increasing CO 2 growth concentration (Fig. <ref type="figure">1A</ref>; <ref type="bibr">Gill et al. 2018, SI 6)</ref>.</s><s>When comparing plants grown at 400 ppm CO 2 and 800 ppm CO 2 (comparable to the modern ambient and twice-ambient values used in the majority of published studies) two of the six experimental taxa, R. acris and G. biloba, showed a significant reduction in % N content;</s></p><p><s>A. araucana and P. vulgare showed a significant increase in % N; and the % N content of E. hyemale and M. glyptostroboides was not significantly different between the two treatments (Fig. <ref type="figure">1A</ref>; <ref type="bibr">Gill et al. 2018, SI 6)</ref>.</s><s>When comparing N content between 'ambient' (i.e.</s><s>400 ppm) and CO 2 growth concentrations higher than twice-ambient (i.e.</s><s>our 1200 and 2000 ppm growth treatments), differences were observed for some taxa.</s><s>Metasequoia glyptostroboides showed a notable decrease in % N at higher CO 2 growth concentrations <ref type="bibr">(Gill et al. 2018, SI 6</ref>) and a two-fold increase in C:N ratio for the 1200 ppm treatment compared to the 400 ppm and 800 ppm CO 2 treatments (Fig. <ref type="figure">1B</ref>).</s><s>The % N value for E. hyemale was significantly higher for plants grown under 2000 ppm CO 2 than for all other CO 2 concentrations.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Few published data exist on carbon and nitrogen content under ambient or elevated CO 2 growth conditions for our experimental species.</s><s>Hummel et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(2008)</ref> measured crude protein content of a number of plant species from ambient conditions, including G. biloba and Equisetum spp., from which % N can be derived (crude protein is calculated as % N 9 6.25).</s><s>Our results for plants grown under the ambient-equivalent treatment (i.e.</s><s>400 ppm CO 2 ) are similar to those of Hummel et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(2008)</ref>, with our G. biloba leaves having 2.14% N vs 2.5% N for those of Hummel et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(2008)</ref> and our E. hyemale having 1.80% N vs 1.9% N for Equisetum spp.</s><s>from Hummel et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(2008)</ref>.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Similarly, Decherd (2006)</ref>  The assumption that leaf % N content of Mesozoic flora would have been reduced and C:N ratios increased by elevated atmospheric CO 2 concentrations <ref type="bibr">(Midgley et al. 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sander et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wilkinson &amp; Ruxton 2013)</ref> is based on studies that focused largely on angiosperms <ref type="bibr">(Roth &amp; Lindroth 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr">Curtis 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wand et al. 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ehleringer et al. 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">K€ orner 2004)</ref> with nitrogen data from only two non-angiosperm species (Pinus ponderosa and Pinus taeda; Curtis 1996).</s><s>These and other studies (e.g.</s><s>Stiling &amp; Cornelissen 2007) undoubtedly show an overall trend towards reduced leaf % N with elevated CO 2 growth concentration, including the majority of the limited number of gymnosperm taxa studied, but some species deviate from this trend.</s><s>For example, leaf nitrogen content was reduced in the angiosperm Betula papyrifera but not the gymnosperm Pinus strobus for plants grown at elevated (650 ppm) versus ambient (350 ppm) CO 2 concentrations <ref type="bibr">(Roth &amp; Lindroth 1994)</ref>.</s><s>Similarly, a recent study investigating the effects of simulated palaeoatmospheres on non-angiosperm plant growth <ref type="bibr">(Bacon et al. 2016)</ref> found that one of the six species studied, Nageia nagi, had a lower C:N ratio and higher % N for plants grown under 1500 ppm CO 2, compared to those grown under ambient CO 2 concentrations.</s><s>These findings are consistent with our results and together these examples indicate that a reduction in leaf % N is not a universal consequence of growth under elevated CO 2 , at least for gymnosperms, but may be taxon-specific.</s><s>Our results also reinforce previous findings (e.g.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Kaplan et al. 2012</ref>) that plant responses to moderately elevated CO 2 may be different under superelevated CO 2 concentrations.</s><s>However, an important caveat when interpreting nitrogen data from both our study and those cited, is that all were based on growth experiments of relatively short duration: 35 days for <ref type="bibr">Decherd (2006)</ref>; 53 days for Roth &amp; Lindroth (1994); 3 months for our understory plants; 6 months for our canopy plants; and 18 months for Bacon et al. (2016) (K.</s><s>Bacon, pers.</s><s>comm.</s><s>November 2017).</s><s>The short durations of these experiments mean that nitrogen in the growth medium is unlikely to be significantly depleted and become a limiting factor for growth, which may be the case in natural environments (e.g.</s><s>K€ orner 2015).</s></p><p><s>As discussed above, changes in leaf nitrogen content or C:N values are not inevitable for plants grown under elevated CO 2 concentrations, but if they did occur, sauropods may have responded differently to modern insect herbivores.</s><s>The most fundamental difference between the insects in the studies cited <ref type="bibr">(Roth &amp; Lindroth 1994</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">, 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ehleringer et al. 2002)</ref>  Megaherbivores have high absolute energy demands, which can be met by fermentation of abundant cell wall material, and may have metabolic (e.g.</s><s>lower metabolic rates), physiological (e.g.</s><s>larger body size) or behavioural (e.g.</s><s>lower activity levels) adaptations to accommodate food resources with low leaf % N or high C:N ratio (e.g.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Grubb 1992;</ref><ref type="bibr">Midgley 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hummel et al. 2008)</ref>.</s><s>The few published studies applying the feeding trial approach to vertebrates <ref type="bibr">(Wroblewitz et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">Habeck &amp; Lindroth 2013)</ref>, albeit with a limited number of taxa and CO 2 concentrations, have shown no negative impact of food plant growth under elevated CO 2 .</s></p><p><s>The evidence presented here indicates that nitrogen content of food plants may not necessarily have been a limiting factor in sauropods' use of plant resources during the Mesozoic.</s><s>This does not exclude the possibility that it may have been a limiting factor for some taxa, but strongly suggests that the effect may be species-specific.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METABOLIZABLE ENERGY</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> summarizes ME (estimated from gas production (GP) as described in Material and Method, above), neutral detergent fibre (NDF) and acid detergent lignin (ADL) values for each experimental taxon, under each CO 2 growth concentration.</s></p><p><s>Plant species and CO 2 growth concentration both significantly affected the rate and extent of GP (Gill et al. 2018, SI 2.1, 2.2) and hence ME content (Fig. <ref type="figure">2A</ref>).</s><s>E. hyemale had the maximum GP of the taxa investigated and A. araucana had the lowest overall cumulative GP (Gill et al. 2018, SI 2.1, 3.1).</s><s>When comparing the mean GP across all taxa, the highest overall GP was associated with growth under 1200 ppm CO 2 <ref type="bibr">(Gill et al. 2018, SI 4)</ref>.</s><s>GP also varied significantly between plants of the same taxon grown at different CO 2 concentrations for all experimental taxa except E. hyemale (although not necessarily between every CO 2 growth concentration for each species) <ref type="bibr">(Gill et al. 2018, SI 5</ref>).</s><s>These results demonstrate the impact of taxon and CO 2 growth concentration on the digestibility of plant matter by digestive tract microbes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Our results show that the GP, and therefore ME content, of the two monilophyte species and one of the gymnosperm species tested (M.</s><s>glyptostroboides) is comparable to (or exceeds in the case of E. hyemale) that of the angiosperm species evaluated, when comparing mean values across all CO 2 treatments <ref type="bibr">(Gill et al. 2018, SI 3)</ref>.</s><s>This is consistent with previous findings, albeit on plants grown under modern ambient CO 2 , demonstrating that the ME content of some potential dinosaur food plant analogues is not intrinsically low, but is comparable to angiosperm ME values in some cases <ref type="bibr">(Hummel et al. 2008)</ref>.</s><s>Looking at each taxon individually, maximum ME (Fig. <ref type="figure">2A</ref>) was estimated in plants grown at a CO 2 concentration of 1200 ppm, for five of the six taxa evaluated, although this difference was statistically significant (based on measured gas production) only for G. biloba <ref type="bibr">(Gill et al. 2018, SI 5)</ref>.</s><s>A corresponding decrease in NDF (i.e.</s><s>hemicellulose, cellulose and lignin, also referred to as structural carbohydrates) and ADL at this CO 2 concentration was observed (Fig. <ref type="figure">2B, C</ref>), which may be due to increased production of easily-fermented non-structural carbohydrates, such as sugars, at the expense of structural carbohydrates.</s><s>Metasequoia glyptostroboides exhibited a different response, with ME decreasing and ADL increasing with increasing CO 2 growth concentrations.</s><s>The negative correlation between ME and ADL has been observed in previous studies <ref type="bibr">(Hummel et al. 2006)</ref>, and is attributed to the fact that lignin is not only not fermentable by gut microbes in anaerobic environments, but also forms linkages to normally digestible structural carbohydrates, especially hemicelluloses, rendering them completely indigestible <ref type="bibr">(Van Soest 1994)</ref>.</s><s>The same reasoning may also explain why E. hyemale has the highest overall ME, since it has very low ADL content, implying that the majority of structural carbohydrates are available for fermentation.</s><s>The low lignin content of E. hymale may be due to use of silica as an alternative structural element, which has also been reported for Mesozoic examples of the genus (e.g.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Channing et al. 2011)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Our experiments have demonstrated species-specific responses, in terms of ME content, to growth under elevated CO 2 concentrations (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>), which may have had significant implications for the amount of plant biomass needed to sustain terrestrial herbivores during the Mesozoic.</s><s>We have modelled the effect of differing food ME content on estimated sauropod daily intake requirements for a range of sauropod body sizes and metabolic rates corresponding a typical modern reptile (55 kJ ME/kg BW 0.75 /day), a typical modern mammal (550 kJ ME/kg BW 0.75 /day) and two intermediate metabolic rates <ref type="bibr">(Hummel et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fig. 3;</ref><ref type="bibr">Gill et al. 2018, SI 8.1)</ref>.</s><s>Using our experimental results, we estimate that a hypothetical 30 t sauropod with an energy requirement of 280 kJ ME/kg BW 0.75 /day (i.e. with a metabolism intermediate between modern lizards and mammals; <ref type="bibr">Hummel et al. 2008)</ref> would need to eat 110 kg per day (all food intake estimates are reported on a dry matter (DM) basis for ease of comparison) of A. araucana grown under atmospheric CO 2 concentrations of 2000 ppm, whereas an identical animal would need to eat less than half that amount, i.e. 51 kg/day, if feeding exclusively on E. hyemale grown under CO 2 levels of 1200 ppm <ref type="bibr">(Gill et al. 2018, SI 8.2)</ref>.</s><s>Extending this approach, we have modelled (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>) expected changes in ME as CO 2 concentrations fluctuated through the Mesozoic (Fig. <ref type="figure">4A</ref>; Foster et al. 2017).</s><s>Figure <ref type="figure">4B-C</ref> shows estimates of ME for the experimental taxa and Figure <ref type="figure">4D</ref> indicates how broad resolution modelled variation in atmospheric CO 2 may have impacted food intake for browsing/canopy-feeding sauropods versus understory-consuming sauropods throughout the Mesozoic <ref type="bibr">(Gill et al. 2018, SI 8.3</ref>).</s><s>Food intake estimates are higher for browsing/canopy feeding sauropods than for understory-consuming sauropods throughout the Mesozoic, but the intake estimates for these two broad diet categories during the Mesozoic run largely in parallel, until the Late Cretaceous, when browser/canopy-feeding intake estimates are substantially reduced, although still considerably higher than for understory eaters.</s><s><ref type="bibr">2002)</ref>.</s><s>At best, ME values from dinosaur food plant analogues grown at ambient CO 2 concentration are used <ref type="bibr">(Hummel et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">Farlow et al. 2010)</ref>.</s><s>However, we have demonstrated that ME varies with CO 2 growth concentration for the majority of our experimental species and that the response to growth in varying levels of CO 2 differs between species.</s><s>Therefore, incorporating these factors into calculations may improve estimates.</s><s>Returning to the Morrison formation and substituting our experimentally derived maximum (based on E. hyemale) and minimum (based on A. araucana) ME values for the Late Jurassic results in an estimated increase in carrying capacity from a maximum of 54 800 000 kJ/km 2 /day according to <ref type="bibr">Farlow et al. (2010)</ref> to 68 500 000 kJ/km 2 /day <ref type="bibr">(Gill et al. 2018, SI 8.5)</ref>.</s><s>Assuming that Morrison Formation herbivores found 50% of the plant matter available and palatable <ref type="bibr">(Farlow et al. 2010)</ref>, this results in a change in estimated population density of approximately 20%: from 6.4-1566 (Farlow et al. 2010) to 6.5-1954 individuals per km 2 of landscape <ref type="bibr">(Gill et al. 2018, SI 8.5)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p><s>This study has employed a novel experimental approach towards estimating the nutritional value of dinosaur food plants during the Mesozoic, challenging existing assumptions about the relationship between CO 2 levels, food quality and sauropod gigantism.</s><s>In particular, our data clearly challenge a view of a constant and linear decrease of diet quality with increasing atmospheric CO 2 , which has previously been suggested as a driver for sauropod gigantism <ref type="bibr">(Midgley et al. 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wilkinson &amp; Ruxton 2013)</ref>.</s><s>The mechanistic approach employed in this study could equally well be applied to other ecosystems and megaherbivore groups, for example, Miocene mammals <ref type="bibr">(Janis et al. 2000)</ref>.</s><s>PhD thesis, University of Nottingham, UK.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Understory plants were chosen as models representative of the Mesozoic community (Gill et al. 2018, SI 1.1) with Polypodium vulgare (a fern) and Equisetum hyemale (a horsetail) representing a pre-Cretaceous monilophyte flora (Pryer et al. 2004) and Ranunculus acris used as an analogue to some of the earliest Cretaceous herbaceous angiosperms, due to the antiquity of the family (Crane et al. 2000; Friis et al. 2010).</s><s>Canopy plants are living examples of plants from groups with a well characterized fossil record, namely the gymnosperms Metasequoia glyptostroboides, Gingko biloba and Araucaria araucana (Lu et al. 2014).</s><s>The CO 2 growth concentrations were selected to span the range of recent estimated CO 2 values for the Mesozoic (Foster et al. 2017).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>and sauropods, is the reliance of the former on cell contents (Abe &amp; Higashi 1991) and the presumed reliance of the latter on microbial fermentation of cell walls (Farlow 1987; Hummel &amp; Clauss 2011; Sander et al. 2011) to meet their nutritional needs.</s><s>Phytophagous (sensu Abe &amp; Higashi 1991) insects have low absolute energy requirements and high nitrogen requirements, which are met by cell contents (Karasov &amp; Douglas 2013).</s><s>They may therefore be particularly sensitive to decreases in leaf % N or increases in leaf C:N ratio.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>A K I N , D. E., K I M B A L L , B. A., W I N D H A M , W. R., P I N -T E R , P. J. Jr, W A L L , G. W., G A R C I A , R. L., L A M O R T E , R. L. and M O R R I S O N , W. H. III 1995.</s><s>Effect of free-air CO 2 enrichment (FACE) on forage quality of wheat.</s><s>Animal Feed Science &amp; Technology, 53, 29-43.</s><s>A N D R E W S , J. E., T A N D O N , S. K. and D E N N I S , P. F. 1995.</s><s>Concentration of carbon dioxide in the Late Cretaceous atmosphere.</s><s>Journal of the Geological Society, 152, 1-3.</s><s>B A C O N , K. L., H A W O R T H , M., C O N R O Y , E. and M c E L W A I N , J. C. 2016.</s><s>Can atmospheric composition influence plant fossil preservation potential via changes in leaf mass per area?</s><s>A new hypothesis based on simulated palaeoatmosphere experiments.</s><s>Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology, 464, 51-64.</s><s>B A R C L A Y , R. S., M c E L W A I N , J. C. and S A G E M A N , B. B. 2010.</s><s>Carbon sequestration activated by a volcanic CO 2 pulse during Ocean Anoxic Event 2. Nature Geoscience, 3, 205-208.</s><s>B A R R E T T , P. M. 2014.</s><s>Paleobiology of herbivorous dinosaurs.</s><s>Annual Review of Earth &amp; Planetary Sciences, 42, 207-230.</s><s>B E E R L I N G , D. J. and R O Y E R , D. L. 2002.</s><s>Fossil plants as indicators of the Phanerozoic global carbon cycle.</s><s>Annual Review of Earth &amp; Planetary Sciences, 30, 527-556.</s><s>B E E R L I N G , D. and W O O D W A R D , F. I. 2001.</s><s>Vegetation and the terrestrial carbon cycle: the first 400 million years.</s><s>Cambridge University Press, 405 pp.</s><s>B E E R L I N G , D. J., M c E L W A I N , J. C. and O S B O R N E , C. P. 1998.</s><s>Stomatal responses of the 'living fossil' Ginkgo biloba to changes in atmospheric CO 2 concentrations.</s><s>Journal of Experimental Botany, 49, 1603-1607.</s><s>-F O X , A. and A N D E R S O N , C. W. 2009.</s><s>Quantitative uncertainty analyses of ancient atmospheric CO 2 estimates from fossil leaves.</s><s>American Journal of Science, 309, 775-787.</s><s>BL € UM M E L , M. and O E R S K O V , E. R. 1993.</s><s>Comparison of in vitro gas production and nylon bag degradability of roughages in predicting feed intake in cattle.</s><s>Animal Feed Science &amp; Technology, 40, 109-119.</s><s>-A I P L E , K.-P., S T E I N G A S S , H. and B E C K E R , K. 1999.</s><s>A note on the stoichiometrical relationship of short chain fatty acid production in vitro in feedstuffs of widely differing quality.</s><s>Journal of Animal Physiology &amp; Animal Nutrition, 81, 157-167.</s><s>B O N I S , N. R., K O N I J N E N B U R G -V A N C I T T E R T , J. H. A. VAN and K € UR S C H N E R , W. M. 2010.</s><s>Changing CO 2 conditions during the end-Triassic inferred from stomatal frequency analysis on Lepidopteris ottonis (Goeppert) Schimper and Ginkgoites taeniatus (Braun) Harris.</s><s>Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology, 295, 146-161.</s><s>B U R N E S S , G. P., D I A M O N D , J. and F L A N N E R Y , T. 2001.</s><s>Dinosaurs, dragons, and dwarfs: the evolution of maximal body size.</s><s>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 98, 14518-14523.</s><s>B U T T O N , D. J., R A Y F I E L D , E. J. and B A R R E T , P. M. 2014.</s><s>Cranial biomechanics underpins high sauropod diversity in resource-poor environments.</s><s>Proceedings of the Royal Society B, 281, 20142114.</s><s>C A R T E R , E. B., T H E O D O R O U , M. K. and M O R R I S , P. 1999.</s><s>Responses of Lotus corniculatus to environmental change.</s><s>2. Effect of elevated CO 2 , temperature and drought on tissue digestion in relation to condensed tannin and carbohydrate accumulation.</s><s>Journal of the Science of Food &amp; Agriculture, 79, 1431-1440.</s><s>C E R L I N G , T. E. 1991.</s><s>Carbon dioxide in the atmosphere: evidence from Cenozoic and Mesozoic palaeosols.</s><s>American Journal of Science, 291, 377-400. -199</s><s>2.</s><s>Use of carbon isotopes in paleosols as an indicator of the P(CO 2 ) of the paleoatmosphere.</s><s>Global Biogeochemical Cycles, 6, 307-314.</s><s>C H A N N I N G , A., Z A M U N E R , A., E D W A R D S , D. and G U I D O , D. 2011.</s><s>Equisetum thermale sp.</s><s>nov.</s><s>(Equisetales) from the Jurassic San Agust ın hot spring deposit, Patagonia: anatomy, paleoecology, and inferred paleoecophysiology.</s><s>American Journal of Botany, 98, 680-697.</s><s>C H E N , L.-Q., L I , C.-S., C H A L O N E R , W. G., B E E R L I N G , D. J., S U N , Q.-G., C O L L I N O N , M. E. and M I T C H E L L , P. L. 2001.</s><s>Assessing the potential for the stomatal characters of extant and fossil Ginkgo leaves to signal atmospheric CO 2 change.</s><s>American Journal of Botany, 88, 1309-1315.</s><s>C L E V E L A N D , D. M., N O R D T , L. C., D W O R K I N , S. I. and A T C H L E Y , S. C. 2008.</s><s>Pedogenic carbonate isotopes as evidence for extreme climatic events preceding the Triassic-Jurassic boundary: implications for the biotic crisis?</s><s>Geological Society of America Bulletin, 120, 1408-1415.</s><s>C R A N E , P. R., F R I I S , E. M. and P E D E R S E N , K. R. 2000.</s><s>The origin and early diversification of angiosperms.</s><s>In G E E , H. (ed.) Shaking the tree: readings from Nature in the history of life.</s><s>University of Chicago Press, 418 pp.</s><s>C U R T I S , P. S. 1996.</s><s>A meta-analysis of leaf gas exchange and nitrogen in trees grown under elevated carbon dioxide.</s><s>Plant, Cell &amp; Environment, 19, 127-137.</s><s>D ' E M I C , M. D., W H I T L O C K , J. A., S M I T H , K. M., F I S H E R , D. C. and W I L S O N , J. A. 2013.</s><s>Evolution of high tooth replacement rates in sauropod dinosaurs.</s><s>PLoS One, 8, e69235.</s><s>D E C H E R D , S. M. 2006.</s><s>Primary productivity and forage quality of Ginkgo biloba in response to elevated carbon dioxide and oxygenan experimental approach to mid-Mesozoic palaeoecology.</s><s>PhD thesis, North Carolina State University, USA.</s><s>D O R I A , G., R O Y E R , D. L., W O L F E , A. P., F O X , A., W E S T G A T E , J. A. and B E E R L I N G , D. J. 2011.</s><s>Declining atmospheric CO 2 during the late Middle Eocene climate transition.</s><s>American Journal of Science, 311, 63-75.</s><s>D U , B., S U N , B., Z H A N G , M., Y A N G , G., X I N G , L., T A N G , F. and B A I , Y. 2016.</s><s>Atmospheric palaeo-CO 2 estimates based on the carbon isotope and stomatal data of Cheirolepidiaceae from the Lower Cretaceous of the Jiuquan Basin, Gansu Province.</s><s>Cretaceous Research, 62, 142-153.</s><s>E H L E R I N G E R , J. R., C E R L I N G , T. E. and D E A R I N G , M. D. 2002.</s><s>Atmospheric CO 2 as a global change driver influencing plant-animal interactions.</s><s>Integrative &amp; Comparative Biology, 42, 424-430.</s><s>E K A R T , D. D., C E R L I N G , T. E., M O N T A ÑE Z , I. P. and T A B O R , N. J. 1999.</s><s>A 400 million year carbon isotope record of pedogenic carbonate: implications for paleoatmospheric carbon dioxide.</s><s>American Journal of Science, 299, 805-827.</s><s>F A R L O W , J. O. 1976.</s><s>A consideration of the trophic dynamics of a Late Cretaceous large-dinosaur community (Oldman Formation).</s><s>Ecology, 57, 841-857. -198</s><s>7.</s><s>Speculations about the diet and digestive physiology of herbivorous dinosaurs.</s><s>Paleobiology, 13, 60-72.</s><s>-C O R O I A N , I. D. and F O S T E R , J. R. 2010.</s><s>Giants on the landscape: modelling the abundance of megaherbivorous dinosaurs of the Morrison Formation (Late Jurassic, western USA).</s><s>Historical Biology, 22, 403-429.</s><s>F L E T C H E R , B. J., B R E N T N A L L , S. J., A N D E R S O N , C. W., B E R N E R , R. A. and B E E R L I N G , D. J. 2008.</s><s>Atmospheric carbon dioxide linked with Mesozoic and early Cenozoic climate change.</s><s>Nature Geoscience, 1, 43-48.</s><s>F O S T E R , G. L., R O Y E R , D. L. and L U N T , D. J. 2017.</s><s>Future climate forcing potentially without precedent in the last 420 million years.</s><s>Nature Communications, 8, 14845.</s><s>F R A K E S , L. A. and K R A S S A Y , A. A. 1992.</s><s>Discovery of probable ice-rafting in the Late Mesozoic of the Northern Territory and Queensland.</s><s>Australian Journal of Earth Sciences, 39, 115-119.</s><s>F R A N K S , P. J., R O Y E R , D. L., B E E R L I N G , D. J., W A T E R , P. K. VAN DE, C A N T R I L L , D. J., B A R B O U R , M. M. and B E R R Y , J. A. 2014.</s><s>New constraints on atmospheric CO 2 concentration for the Phanerozoic.</s><s>Geophysical Research Letters, 41, 4685-4694.</s><s>F R I I S , E. M., P E D E R S E N , K. R. and C R A N E , P. R. 2010.</s><s>Diversity in obscurity: fossil flowers and the early history of angiosperms.</s><s>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B, 365, 369-382.</s><s>G H O S H , P., B H A T T A C H A R Y A R A , S. K. and J A N I , R. A. 1995.</s><s>Palaeoclimate and palaeovegetation in central India during the Upper Cretaceous based on stable isotope composition of the palaeosol carbonates.</s><s>Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology, 114, 285-296.</s><s>-G H O S H , P. and B H A T T A C H A R Y A , S. K. 2001.</s><s>CO 2 levels in the Late Palaeozoic and Mesozoic atmosphere from soil carbonate and organic matter, Satpura basin, Central India.</s><s>Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology, 170, 219-236.</s><s>-B H A T T A C H A R Y A , S. K. and G H O S H , P. 2005.</s><s>Atmospheric CO 2 during the Late Paleozoic and Mesozoic: estimates from Indian soils.</s><s>8-34.</s><s>In E H L E R I N G E R , J. R., C E R L I N G , T. E. and D E A R I N G , M. D. (eds).</s><s>A history of atmospheric CO 2 and its effects on plants, animals, and ecosystems.</s><s>Springer.</s><s>G I L L , F. L., H U M M E L , J., S H A R I F I , A. R., L E E , A. P. and L O M A X , B. H. 2018.</s><s>Data from: Diets of giants the nutritional value of sauropod diet during the Mesozoic.</s><s>Dryad Digital Repository.</s><s>https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.9j92p2b</s><s>G R E E N W O O D , D. R., S C A R R , M. J. and C H R I S T O -P H E L , D. C. 2003.</s><s>Leaf stomatal frequency in the Australian tropical rainforest tree Neolitsea dealbata (Lauraceae) as a proxy measure of atmospheric pCO 2 .</s><s>Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology, 196, 375-393.</s><s>G R U B B , P. J. 1992.</s><s>Presidential address: a positive distrust in simplicitylessons from plant defences and from competition among plants and among animals.</s><s>Journal of Ecology, 80, 585-610.</s><s>G U T I E R R E Z , K. and S H E L D O N , N. D. 2012.</s><s>Paleoenvironmental reconstruction of Jurassic dinosaur habitats of the Vega Formation, Asturias, Spain.</s><s>GSA Bulletin, 124, 596-610.</s><s>H A B E C K , C. W. and L I N D R O T H , R. L. 2013.</s><s>Influence of global atmospheric change on the feeding behavior and growth performance of a mammalian herbivore, Microtus ochrogaster.</s><s>PLoS One, 8, e72717.</s><s>H A W O R T H , M., H E S S E L B O , S. P., M c E L W A I N , J. C. and R O B I N S O N , S. A. 2005.</s><s>Mid Cretaceous pCO 2 based on stomata of the extinct conifer Pseudofrenelopsis.</s><s>Geology, 33, 749-752.</s><s>H O N G , S. K. and L E E , Y. I. 2012.</s><s>Evaluation of atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations during the Cretaceous.</s><s>Earth &amp; Planetary Science Letters, 327-328, 23-28.</s><s>H U A N G , C. M., R E T A L L A C K , G. J. and W A N G , S. C. 2012.</s><s>Early Cretaceous pCO 2 levels recorded from pedogenic carbonates in China.</s><s>Cretaceous Research, 33, 42-49.</s><s>--W A N G , C. and H U A N G , Q. 2013.</s><s>Paleoatmospheric pCO 2 fluctuations across the Cretaceous-Tertiary boundary recorded from paleosol carbonates in NE China.</s><s>Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology, 385, 95-105.</s><s>H U M M E L , J. and C L A U S S , M. 2011.</s><s>Sauropod feeding and digestive physiology.</s><s>In K L E I N , N., R E M E S , K., G E E , C. T. and S A N D E R , P. M. (eds).</s><s>Biology of the sauropod dinosaurs: understanding the life of giants.</s><s>Indiana University Press, 344 pp.</s><s>-S € UD E K U M , K.-H., S T R E I C H , W. J. and C L A U S S , M. 2006.</s><s>Forage fermentation patterns and their implications for herbivore ingesta retention times.</s><s>Functional Ecology, 20, 989-1002.</s><s>-G E E , C. T., S € UD E K U M , K.-H., S A N D E R , P. M., N O G G E , G. and C L A U S S , M. 2008.</s><s>In vitro digestibility of fern and gymnosperm foliage: implications for sauropod feeding ecology and diet selection.</s><s>Proceedings of the Royal Society B, 275, 1015-1021.</s><s>J A N I S , C. M., D A M U T H , J. and T H E O D O R , J. M. 2000.</s><s>Miocene ungulates and terrestrial primary productivity: where have all the browsers gone?</s><s>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 97, 7899-7904.</s><s>K A P L A N , F., Z H A O , W., R I C H A R D S , J. T., W H E E L E R , R. M., G U Y , C. L. and L E V I N E , L. H. 2012.</s><s>Transcriptional and metabolic insights into the differential physiological responses of Arabidopsis to optimal and supraoptimal atmospheric CO 2 .</s><s>PLoS One, 7, e45383.</s><s>K A R A S O V , W. H. and D O U G L A S , A. E. 2013.</s><s>Comparative digestive physiology.</s><s>Comprehensive.</s><s>Physiology, 3, 741-783.</s><s>K € OR N E R , C. 2004.</s><s>Through enhanced tree dynamics carbon dioxide enrichment may cause tropical forests to lose carbon.</s><s>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B, 359, 493-498.</s><s>-2015.</s><s>Paradigm shift in plant growth control.</s><s>Current Opinion in Plant Biology, 25, 107-114.</s><s>L E E , Y. I. 1999.</s><s>Stable isotopic composition of calcic paleosols of the Early Cretaceous Hasandong Formation, southeastern Korea.</s><s>Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology, 150, 123-133.</s><s>L E E , A. P. 2015.</s><s>CO 2 decline and the rise of the angiosperms.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,52.89,372.91,223.94,275.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,73.30,76.49,224.01,425.89" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>low browsers, with a diet based on consuming monilophytes such as ferns and Equisetum sp., whereas Morrison Formation Camarasaurus sp.</s><s>show evidence for higher browsing and a more mixed diet, with a higher proportion of woody, probably coniferous material (Button et al.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>14 A</cell></row><row><cell>DM)</cell><cell>12</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">ME 2014; T€ utken 2011). Combining this palaeontological evi--1 10 (MJ kg 8 dence with our experimental data allows us to estimate</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">food intake for these two Morrison Formation sauropods, 6 although we acknowledge the simplification inherent in</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Acid detergent using our limited range of relevant experimental species, lignin (ADL; % DM) 16 B in contrast to the known diversity of the Morrison For-14 mation flora (Farlow et al. 2010). Again assuming an 12 energy requirement of 280 kJ ME/kg BW 0.75 /day, a 10.8 t 10 (Farlow et al. 2010) Morrison Formation Diplodocus sp. 8 feeding exclusively on ferns would need to eat 33.2 kg per 6 day (based on ME values derived from P. vulgare). The 4 same animal feeding exclusively on Equisetum sp. would 2 need to consume 23.8 kg/day (based on values derived 0 Neutral detergent 25 30 35 40 45 50 55 from E. hyemale) or 27.7 kg/day of a 50:50 mixture of C the two plant groups. Under the same assumptions, a 12.6 t (Farlow et al. 2010) Camarasaurus sp. with a mixed diet consisting of equal proportions of monilophyte understory and canopy plants (using values derived from P. vulgare, E. hyemale, A. araucana, G. biloba and M. glyptostroboides) would need to eat 34.2 kg/day. For fibre ( NDF; % DM) 15 comparison, a typical modern elephant, weighing 7 t, 20 with an energy requirement of 550 kJ ME/kg BW 0.75 /day</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">400 would need to eat 47.0 kg/day of P. vulgare, 33.7 kg/day 800 1200 1600 2000</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">E. hyemale sp., 39.3 kg/day of a 50:50 mixture of these CO 2 (ppm) two species or 48.4 kg/day of a diet consisting of equal</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">R. acris parts of P. vulgare, E. hyemale, A. araucana, G. biloba and G. biloba</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">E. hyemale P. vulgare M. glyptostroboides. See Gill et al. (2018), SI 8.4 for details M. glyptostroboides A. araucana of calculations in this section.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">F I G . 2 . A, metabolizable energy (ME) content; B, acid deter-Models of dinosaur biomass and population density</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">gent lignin (ADL) content; C, neutral detergent fibre (NDF) usually do not consider variation in metabolizable energy</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">content of experimental taxa at experimental CO 2 growth con-content between different dinosaur food plants, and</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">centrations. between the same taxa growing under different CO 2 con-</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">centrations (e.g. Farlow 1976; McNab 2009; Trammer</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">2011) or, if they do, consider it at an extremely broad</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">level, e.g. gymnosperms versus angiosperms (Midgley et al.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>allowing us to translate and apply our theoretical</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>approach to the fossil record. Niche partitioning between</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>sauropod species in the formation has been suggested</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">REVISED SAUROPOD DINOSAUR</cell><cell>based on multiple lines of evidence (Farlow et al. 2010),</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">BIOMASS AND POPULATION DENSITY</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">IN THE MORRISON FORMATION</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">The Late Jurassic Morrison Formation is one of the most</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">well-known and widely studied dinosaur deposits,</cell></row></table><note><p><s>including (but not restricted to) skull functional morphology(Button et al. 2014), carbon stable isotopic analysis of bones and teeth (T€ utken 2011) and tooth replacement rates(D'Emic et al. 2013).For example, Morrison Formation Diplodocus sp. have been interpretedF I G . 3 .Daily food intake estimates at variable metabolizable energy content of food for: A, 10 t sauropod; B, 30 t sauropod; C, 70 t sauropod; assuming a metabolic rate of: 55 kJ ME/kg body weight 0.75 (red, equivalent to modern day reptiles); 280 kJ ME/kg body weight 0.75 (blue); 410 kJ ME/kg body weight 0.75 (black); 550 kJ ME/kg body weight 0.75 (grey, equivalent to modern day mammals) (Hummel et al. 2008).Body sizes were chosen to represent small, average and maximal sauropod body size illustrated in: A, by Diplodocus sp.; B, by Brachiosaurus sp.; C, by Dreadnoughtus sp.See Gill et al. (2018, S. I. 8.1) for details of calculations.A B C D F I G . 4 .A, atmospheric CO 2 estimates through the Mesozoic (Foster et al. 2017).B, estimated ME values for canopy experimental taxa throughout the Mesozoic.C, estimated ME values for understory experimental taxa throughout the Mesozoic.D, daily food intake estimates for hypothetical 30 t sauropod with a metabolic rate of 280 kJ ME/kg body weight 0.75 during the Mesozoic with browsing (A.araucana + M. glyptostroboides + G. biloba) vs understory (E.hyemale + R. acris + P. vulgare) diet.See Gill et al. (2018, SI 8.3) for details of calculation.as</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6">4 8 P A L A E O N T O L O G Y , V O L U M E 6 1</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">F I G . 1 . A, % N content; B, C:N content of experimental taxa at experimental CO 2 growth concentrations. Note symbols for E. hyemale and P. vulgare are of a different size to enable all data points to be displayed. C:N ratio data for A. araucana not available. Where error bars are not shown, error is within the display of the symbol.6 5 0 P A L A E O N T O L O G Y , V O L U M E 6 1</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">G I L L E T A L . : D I E T S O F G I A N T S 6 5 1</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6">5 4 P A L A E O N T O L O G Y , V O L U M E 6 1</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6">5 6 P A L A E O N T O L O G Y , V O L U M E 6 1</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6">5 8 P A L A E O N T O L O G Y , V O L U M E 6 1</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Acknowledgements.</s><s>We thank Darren Hepworth and Saul Vazquez (University of Nottingham) and Rolf Jeronim and Anke von Gaza (University of Goettingen) for technical support, and James McKay for producing the dinosaur images for Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>.</s><s>This work was supported by the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council [grant number BB/F017014/1] awarded to BHL and supporting APL and a Royal Society research award (RG110322) and Dorothy Hodgkin Fellowship both awarded to FLG.</s></p><p><s>We also thank Jennifer McElwain, Paul Barrett, Sally Thomas and an anonymous reviewer for their helpful comments on an earlier draft of this paper.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Author contributions.</s><s>FLG and BHL developed the research outlined in this paper, FLG wrote the manuscript and BHL produced the figures.</s><s>APL with BHL developed and delivered the experimental plant material.</s><s>JH with FLG conducted the in vitro fermentation experiments.</s><s>ARS with JH conducted the statistical analysis.</s><s>All authors commented on the manuscript.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DATA ARCHIVING STATEMENT</head><p><s>Data for this study are available in the Dryad Digital Repository: https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.9j92p2b</s></p><p><s>Editor.</s><s>Leyla Seyfullah</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>REFERENCES</head><p><s>A B E , T. and H I G A S H I , M. 1991.</s><s>Cellulose-centered perspective on terrestrial community structure.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Elevated atmospheric CO 2 : effects on phytochemistry, insect performance and insect-parasitoid interactions</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Change Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="182" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>S A N D E R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>C H R I S T I A N</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>C L A U S S</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>F E C H -N E R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>G E E</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E.-M</forename><surname>G R I E B E L E R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-C</forename><surname>G U N G A</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>H U M M E L</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>M A L L I S O N</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>P E R R Y</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>P R E -U S C H O F T</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">M W</forename><surname>R A U H U T</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>R E M E S</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>T € Ut K E N</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>W I N G S</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W I T Z E L</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biological Reviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Biology of the sauropod dinosaurs: the evolution of gigantism</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Estimates of atmospheric CO 2 levels during the mid-Turonian derived from stable isotope composition of paleosol calcite from Israel</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>S A N D L E R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Paleoenvironmental record and applications of Calcretes and Palustrine carbonates</title>
				<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ons O -Z Arz A</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T A N N E R</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Boulder, Colorado</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Geological Society of America Special Paper</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">416</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="88" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Myr record of Late Triassic atmospheric pCO 2 variation reflects a fundamental control of the carbon cycle by changes in continental weathering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>S C H A L L E R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>W R I G H T</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K E N T</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">V E</forename><surname>. ; O L S E N P</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>27-39. ---2015. A 30</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geological Society of America Bulletin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">331</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="661" to="671" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Earth &amp; Planetary Science Letters</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Early Jurassic (late Pliensbachian) CO 2 concentrations based on stomatal analysis of fossil conifer leaves from eastern Australia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>S T E I N T H O R S D O T T I R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V A J D A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gondwana Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="932" to="939" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global trends of pCO 2 across the Cretaceous-Paleogene boundary supported by the first Southern Hemisphere stomatal proxy-based pCO 2 reconstruction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">-J E R A M</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E L W A I N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>; V A J D A</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P O L E</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">308</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="143" to="152" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Palaeogeography, Palaeoclimatology, Palaeoecology</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How does elevated carbon dioxide (CO 2 ) affect plant-herbivore interactions? A field experiment and meta-analysis of CO 2 -mediated changes on plant chemistry and herbivore performance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>S T I L I N G</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>O R N E L I S S E N</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Change Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1823" to="1842" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative analysis of paleoatmospheric CO 2 level based on stomatal characters of fossil Ginkgo from Jurassic to Cretaceous in China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>S U N</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>X I A O</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>X I E</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>D E N G</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>W A N G</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>J I A</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>T U R N E R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Geologica Sinica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">81</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="931" to="939" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Goethite, calcite and organic matter from Permian and Triassic soils: carbon isotopes and CO 2 concentrations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>T A B O R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Y A P P</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M O N T A Ñe Z</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1503" to="1517" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stability of atmospheric CO 2 levels across the Triassic/Jurassic boundary</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>T A N N E R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>H U B E R T</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>O F F E Y</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I -N E R N Y</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">411</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="675" to="677" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differences in global biomass and energy use between dinosaurs and mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>T R A M M E R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Geologica Polonica</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="132" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The diet of sauropod dinosaurs: implications of carbon isotope analysis on teeth, bones, and plants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T € Ut K E N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>; K L E I N</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>R E M E S</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>G E E</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>A N D E R</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Biology of the sauropod dinosaurs: understanding the life of giants</title>
				<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Indiana University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">344</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">pp</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nutritional ecology of the ruminant</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>V A N S O E S T</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
			<publisher>Cornell University Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>2nd edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Handbuch der landwirtschaftlichen Versuchsund Untersuchungsmethodik (VDLUFA-Methodenbuch)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>V D L U F A</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Das VDLUFA Methodenbuch. 3. Die chemische Untersuchung von Futtermitteln. Verband deutscher landwirtschaftlicher Untersuchungs-und Forschungsanstalten</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Darmstadt, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trend of Santonian (Late Cretaceous) atmospheric CO 2 and global mean land surface temperature: evidence from plant fossils</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W A N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>W A N G</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Z H U</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q U A N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science China Earth Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1338" to="1345" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Responses of wild C4 and C3 grass (Poaceae) species to elevated atmospheric CO 2 concentration: a meta-analytic test of current theories and perceptions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W A N D</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J E</forename><surname>M I D G L E Y</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>O N E S</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C U R T I S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Global Change Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="723" to="741" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The improbable endotherm: the energetics of the sauropod dinosaur Brachiosaurus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Weaver</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Paleobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="182" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>W H I T E S I D E</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>L I I N D S T R € Om</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>I R M I S</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extreme ecosystem instability suppressed tropical dinosaur dominance for 30 million years</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>G L A S S P O O L</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>S C H A L L E R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>D U N L A V E Y</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>N E S B I T T</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>S M I T H</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>U R N E R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7909" to="7913" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High C/N ratio (not low-energy content) of vegetation may have driven gigantism in sauropod dinosaurs and perhaps omnivory and/ or endothermy in their juveniles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>W I L K I N S O N</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R U X T O N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Functional Ecology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="135" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ro B L Ew It Z</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>H € Ut H E R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>B E R K</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>L E B -</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z I E N A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>K L U T H</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>M A N D E R S C H E I D</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>E R B S</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>W E I G E L</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H.-J</forename><surname>W € At Z I G D</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D € An I C K E</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The impact of free air carbon dioxide enrichment (FACE) on nutrient digestibility of maize grains in pigs and broiler chickens and on ruminal in sacco degradability</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Animal Feed Science &amp; Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">196</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="128" to="138" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reconstructing paleoatmospheric CO 2 levels based on fossil Ginkgoites from the Upper Triassic and Middle Jurassic in Northwest China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-Y</forename><surname>W U</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-T</forename><surname>D I N G</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q.-J</forename><surname>L I</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B.-N</forename><surname>S U N</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W A N G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y.-D</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pal€ aontologische Zeitschrift</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="377" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Response to paleoatmospheric CO 2 concentration of Solenites vimineus (Phillips) Harris (Ginkgophyta) from the Middle Jurassic of the Yaojie Basin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y A N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>S U N</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>X I E</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>L I</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W E N</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science in China Series D: Earth Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2029" to="2039" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
