<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A hypomorphic Cbx3 allele causes prenatal growth restriction and perinatal energy homeostasis defects</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-04-27">27 April 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ebru</forename><surname>Aydin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Sub-department of Evolution &amp; Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Evolutionary Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Uppsala University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>18A, S-75236</postCode>
									<settlement>Norbyvägen, Uppsala</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Dick-Paul</forename><surname>Kloos</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Proteomics and Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Leiden University Medical Center (LUMC)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Albinusdreef 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>2300 RC</postCode>
									<settlement>Leiden</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Emmanuel</forename><surname>Gay</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Proteomics and Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Leiden University Medical Center (LUMC)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Albinusdreef 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>2300 RC</postCode>
									<settlement>Leiden</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Willem</forename><surname>Jonker</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Proteomics and Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Leiden University Medical Center (LUMC)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Albinusdreef 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>2300 RC</postCode>
									<settlement>Leiden</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lijuan</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Sub-department of Evolution &amp; Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Evolutionary Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Uppsala University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>18A, S-75236</postCode>
									<settlement>Norbyvägen, Uppsala</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jörn</forename><surname>Bullwinkel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Immunoepigenetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Immunology and Cell Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Research Center Borstel</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>D-23845</postCode>
									<settlement>Borstel</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jeremy</forename><surname>Pbrown</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Immunoepigenetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Immunology and Cell Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Research Center Borstel</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>D-23845</postCode>
									<settlement>Borstel</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Cell Biology and Neurobiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Anatomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><surname>Manukyan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Albert-Ludwigs-Universität Freiburg</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">BIOSS Centre for Biological Signalling Studies</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Schänzlestrasse 18</addrLine>
									<postCode>79104</postCode>
									<settlement>Freiburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Giera</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Proteomics and Metabolomics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Leiden University Medical Center (LUMC)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Albinusdreef 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>2300 RC</postCode>
									<settlement>Leiden</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Immunoepigenetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Immunology and Cell Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Research Center Borstel</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>D-23845</postCode>
									<settlement>Borstel</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Cell Biology and Neurobiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Anatomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">School of Natural Sciences and Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Liverpool John Moores University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Byrom Street</addrLine>
									<postCode>L3 3AF</postCode>
									<settlement>Liverpool</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Reinald</forename><surname>Fundele</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Sub-department of Evolution &amp; Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Center for Evolutionary Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Uppsala University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>18A, S-75236</postCode>
									<settlement>Norbyvägen, Uppsala</settlement>
									<country key="SE">Sweden</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A hypomorphic Cbx3 allele causes prenatal growth restriction and perinatal energy homeostasis defects</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-04-27">27 April 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">8461E9F50DD6422FD98E301AC25AF1FE</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s12038-015-9520-x</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Brown adipose tissue</term>
					<term>HP1</term>
					<term>Igf2P0</term>
					<term>placental development</term>
					<term>Upc1</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Mammals have three HP1 protein isotypes HP1β (CBX1), HP1γ (CBX3) and HP1α (CBX5) that are encoded by the corresponding genes Cbx1, Cbx3 and Cbx5.</s><s>Recent work has shown that reduction of CBX3 protein in homozygotes for a hypomorphic allele (Cbx3 hypo ) causes a severe postnatal mortality with around 99% of the homozygotes dying before weaning.</s><s>It is not known what the causes of the postnatal mortality are.</s><s>Here we show that Cbx3 hypo/hypo conceptuses are significantly reduced in size and the placentas exhibit a haplo-insufficiency.</s><s>Late gestation Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas have reduced mRNA transcripts for genes involved in growth regulation, amino acid and glucose transport.</s><s>Blood vessels within the Cbx3 hypo/hypo placental labyrinth are narrower than wild-type.</s><s>Newborn Cbx3 hypo/hypo pups are hypoglycemic, the livers are depleted of glycogen reserves and there is almost complete loss of stored lipid in brown adipose tissue (BAT).</s><s>There is a 10-fold reduction in expression of the BAT-specific Ucp1 gene, whose product is responsible for nonshivering themogenesis.</s><s>We suggest that it is the small size of the Cbx3 hypo/hypo neonates, a likely consequence of placental growth and transport defects, combined with a possible inability to thermoregulate that causes the severe postnatal mortality.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p><s>HP1 proteins are small adapter proteins that are constituents of larger complexes involved in a variety of nuclear functions <ref type="bibr">(Canzio et al. 2014)</ref>.</s><s>These include roles in heterochromatin formation, positive and negative transcriptional regulation, DNA repair, chromosome segregation and replication of heterochromatin (reviewed in <ref type="bibr">Grewal and Elgin 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Billur et al. 2010)</ref>.</s><s>In mammals, there are three HP1 isotypes, HP1β (CBX1), HP1γ (CBX3) and HP1α (CBX5), that are encoded by distinct genes, chromobox homolog 1 (Cbx1), Cbx3 and Cbx5, respectively <ref type="bibr">(Jones et al. 2000)</ref>.</s><s>The three HP1 isotypes possess extensive sequence similarity, but this similarity belies their nonredundant functions.</s><s>The suggestion that the mammalian HP1 isotypes are likely to possess non-redundant functions came first from immunolocalization studies using isotypespecific antibodies.</s><s>CBX1 and CBX5 proteins were found to be concentrated at sites of constitutive heterochromatin <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Saunders et al. 1993;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Wreggett et al. 1994)</ref>, while CBX3 was shown to have a more euchromatic distribution <ref type="bibr">(Horsley et al. 1996)</ref>.</s><s>It was suggested that its euchromatic distribution reflected the acquisition of new functions by CBX3 and subsequently it was shown that CBX3 is associated with euchromatic genes and is involved in elongation and processing of their mRNA transcripts <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Vakoc et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hediger and Gasser 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Smallwood et al. 2012)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Proof that HP1 isotypes were non-redundant came from mutational analyses.</s><s>It was demonstrated that loss of CBX1 protein cannot be compensated by <ref type="bibr">CBX3 and CBX5 proteins (Aucott et al. 2008)</ref> because the murine Cbx1 −/− mutation is perinatal lethal.</s><s>Mortality is caused by respiratory failure due to defective post-synaptic differentiation in the diaphragm <ref type="bibr">(Aucott et al. 2008)</ref>.</s><s>In addition, while other organ systems seemed intact, Cbx1 −/− mutants exhibited defective development of the central nervous system that was associated with a profound genomic instability <ref type="bibr">(Aucott et al. 2008)</ref>.</s><s>Deletion of the CBX5 protein had no obvious effect.</s><s>Cbx5 −/− mice are fully viable and fertile (cited in <ref type="bibr">Aucott et al. 2008)</ref>, indicating a redundancy, most likely with CBX1.</s><s>However, a recent study has shown that Cbx5 −/− mice exhibit a specific defect in the silencing of T H 1 expression in T H 2 cells <ref type="bibr">(Allan et al. 2012)</ref>.</s><s>These data show that CBX protein function(s) are likely to be overlapping, but there are non-redundant functions peculiar to each isotype that cannot be compensated and some of these functions may be quite specific in character.</s></p><p><s>Ablation of Cbx3 expression causes infertility in both sexes and a severe neonatal mortality <ref type="bibr">(Brown et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Abe et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Takada et al. 2011</ref>).</s><s>In one study, which used a hypomorphic Cbx3 allele (Cbx3 hypo ), roughly 99% of the homozygous mutants died before weaning, whereas on day 19 of fetal development (E19) normal Mendelian ratios of wild-type to targeted alleles were observed <ref type="bibr">(Brown et al. 2010)</ref>.</s><s>In all Cbx3 hypo/hypo tissues examined the levels of CBX3 protein were barely detectable <ref type="bibr">(Brown et al. 2010)</ref>.</s><s>The causes for the neonatal demise of Cbx3 hypo/hypo homozygotes are not known.</s><s>Here we describe the cellular and molecular changes that take place in Cbx3 hypo/hypo conceptuses and newborns.</s><s>Our findings indicate that the Cbx3 hypo/hypo mutation is pleiotropic and causes generalized defects in placental development and energy homeostasis that are together responsible for the postnatal mortality of Cbx3 hypo/hypo homozygotes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Materials and methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Mice and mouse tissues</head><p><s>All experiments with mice were conducted according to the guidelines issued by Uppsala University.</s><s>The Cbx3 hypo allele, which has been described in detail in <ref type="bibr">Brown et al. (2010)</ref>, was propagated as heterozygote in a mixed C57BL6/129 genetic background at the Borstel Research Center and subsequently at the animal facilities at the Biomedical Center, Uppsala, where the allele was crossed into a BALB/c background to backcross 3.</s><s>No obvious differences could be observed between fetuses from matings with different strain combinations and consequently results are pooled.</s><s>Pregnant females were killed by cervical dislocation, with the day of vaginal plug being counted as day 1.</s><s>Fetuses and placentas were weighed.</s><s>Placentas were halved, one half was frozen on dry ice for nucleic acid or protein extraction, while the other half was either fixed in Carnoy's fixative and later processed for paraffin histology, or embedded directly in Tissue-Tek O.C.T. Compound (Sakura) and used for cryo-sectioning.</s><s>For determination of blood glucose levels, newborn mice were decapitated and blood glucose determined with a OneTouch UltraEasy glucose meter.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">BrdU cell proliferation assay</head><p><s>Cellular proliferation in placental and fetal tissues was determined using the BrdU assay according to <ref type="bibr">Jägerbauer et al. (1992)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Staining of sections</head><p><s>Antibodies used were against smooth muscle actin (DAKO M0851) and BrdU (DAKO M0744), isolectin B4 was obtained from Vector laboratories (B-1205).</s><s>Horseradish peroxidase-labelled secondary antibodies were obtained from DAKO and Vector laboratories.</s><s>IHC was carried out according to standard procedures.</s><s>Antigen retrieval was performed in a microwave at 480 W for 10 min in 10 mM citrate, 0.05% Tween20, pH 6.0.</s><s>Frozen, 10% PFA postfixed sections were stained with Oil red O. Carnoy's fixed paraffin sections were stained with PAS.</s><s>For counting of nuclei, pictures were taken at 40× magnification and quantified on a screen.</s><s>Three randomly selected areas from at least 3 different fetuses were analysed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">DNA extraction and genotyping PCR</head><p><s>Genomic DNA was extracted from tissues using the Promega Wizard genomic DNA extraction kit.</s><s>The following primers were used to genotype Cbx3 mutant mice: forward: 5′-AGTCCCAGTACTGAGAGTTC-3′ and reverse: 5′-CTCTACCTCCTGAGTACTAG-3′.</s><s>Reaction conditions have been described previously <ref type="bibr">(Brown et al. 2010)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Lipid extraction and analysis</head><p><s>For placental transport analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Wu et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">Yuet al. 2008)</ref>, total lipid was extracted and purified from Cbx3 hypo/hypo and Cbx3 +/+ E13 and E18 fetuses and their placentas and the ratios of EFAs (20:4; 18:2; 22:6) to NEFAs (16:0; 18:0) were determined.</s><s>BSTFA containing 1% TMCS was from Thermo (Runcorn, UK).</s><s>All other chemicals were from Sigma Aldrich (Schnelldorf, Germany).</s><s>A Scion TQ GC-MS system from Bruker (Bremen, Germany) equipped with a Bruker BR5-MS 15 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 μm column was used.</s><s>The injector was operated in splitless mode, held at 280°C.</s><s>The injection volume was 1 μL and the oven program started and kept for 0.5 min at 90°C, ramped to 180 with 30°C/min, then to 250°C with 10°C/ min, then to 266°C with 2°C/min, and finally to 300°C with 120°C/min.</s><s>Helium (99.9990%) was used as carrier gas at a flow rate of 1.2 mL/min.</s><s>The retention times of all analytes were determined, so the selected ion monitoring (SIM) method could be programmed with a 0.30 min window for each compound.</s></p><p><s>For the analysis of the total lipid content, to ~1 mL sample, 3 mL of methanol and 1 mL of 10 M NaOH were pipetted into a pre-cleaned glass 10 mL test-tube.</s><s>Before closing the tube, the atmosphere in the vial was flushed with argon.</s><s>The tube was placed in an oven for 1 h at 90°C.</s><s>After cooling, 2 mL of 6 N of HCl were added, subsequently 10 μL internal standard (C16:0 d31) was added.</s><s>Extraction was carried out by adding 3 mL of n-hexane.</s><s>After shaking, the n-hexane layer was transferred to another tube.</s><s>This was done three times, to ensure an optimal extraction.</s><s>n-Hexane was added to the extract to 10 mL.</s><s>50 μL were taken from the extract and dried in an autosampler vial.</s></p><p><s>Dried samples were derivatized by 25 μL of MtBSTFA for 10 min at room temperature and subsequently 25 μLo f BSTFA and 2.5 μL of pyridine were added before putting the sample in an oven for 15 min at 50°C.</s><s>947.5 μLo f n-hexane, containing 10 μg/mL octadecane (C18) internal standard, was used to dilute the sample, prior to injection.</s></p><p><s>2.6 Quantitative real-time RT-PCR (qRT-PCR) Gene expression levels were analysed by quantitative real time PCR (Corbett Research RG-3000 thermo-cycler) for the growth regulatory genes (Grb10, Igf2, H19), the placentaspecific transcript of Igf2 (Igf2P0), the placental transporter genes of the system A family of amino acid transporters (Slc38a1, Slc38a2, Slc38a4), the predominant placental glucose transporters (Slc2a1, Slc2a3), the prolactin family genes (Prl, Prlr, Prl7b1, Prl3c1, Prl4a1, Prl8a9, Prl7c1), the key enzymes in glucose homeostasis (G6pc, Pck1, Gys2), and the genes related to lipid and mitochondrial metabolism (Pparg2, Srebp1, Pgc1a, Ucp1, Cs, Hmgcs).</s><s>Total RNA was extracted from snap-frozen tissues with TRIzol reagent (Ambion Life Technologies) according to manufacturer's guide.</s><s>DNase treatment was performed prior to cDNA synthesis with Promega's RQ1 RNase-Free Dnase Kit. cDNA was synthesized using high-capacity cDNA Reverse Transcription Kit of AppiledBiosystems.</s><s>PowerSYBR® Green PCR Master Mix (Life Technologies) was used for real time PCR quantification of transcripts.</s><s>All samples were analysed in triplicates and data were normalized using Delta Delta CT method <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Livak and Schmittgen, 2001)</ref>.</s><s>Accordingly, the amplification efficiency of the constitutively expressed reference genes, Tubb, Actb and 28s rRNA, were compared of the amplification of the target genes of interest (given above) in order to find the optimal combination of reference gene and target gene for calculation of normalized expression as described by <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Livak and Schmittgen (2001)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Conditions and primer sequences used in qRT-PCR are shown in the table below.</s><s>3. Results</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Effect of the Cbx3 hypo allele on placental and fetal growth</head><p><s>Placental and fetal weights were determined between E12 and E19 (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>At E12 Cbx3 hypo/hypo homozygous placentas exhibited a tendency for reduced weight, compared to both Cbx3 hypo/+ and Cbx3 +/+ placentas (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>).</s><s>From day 13 onwards weight differences between Cbx3 hypo/hypo and Cbx3 +/+ placentas were statistically highly significant (P&lt;0.001;</s><s>figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>), with the mean relative weight of the Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas reaching a minimum at E14 and E16, with 62.1% and 62.0% of wild-type weights respectively.</s><s>There was some catch-up on E18 and E19 where mean relative weights of Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas reached 70.4% and 74.8% of wild-type placentas respectively.</s><s>Notably, Cbx3 hypo/+ placenta weights were consistently intermediate between Cbx3 hypo/hypo and Cbx3 +/+ (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>), indicating that the Cbx3 hypo allele is haplo-insufficient with regard to placental weight.</s><s>Specifically, the weight differences between Cbx3 hypo/hypo and Cbx3 hypo/+ placentas were significant at all stages except E12 (P&lt;0.05 for E13, P&lt;0.001 for all other stages); between Cbx3 hypo/+ and wild-type placentas, weight differences were significant on E13 (P&lt;0.005),</s><s>E18 (P&lt;0.01), and E19 (P&lt;0.01).</s><s>With regard to fetal weights, the weights of Cbx3 hypo/hypo fetuses were significantly reduced compared with both Cbx3 hypo/+ and Cbx3 +/+ fetuses from day 16 onwards (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1d</ref>).</s><s>These data indicate that the reduced placental weights we observed from day 13 (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>) could cause or contribute to the fetal growth restriction that follows.</s><s>Cbx3 hypo/hypo fetuses showed no catch-up growth during late gestation unlike Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas.</s><s>Neither was there any significant weight difference between Cbx3 hypo/+ and Cbx3 +/+ fetuses at any stage (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1d</ref>), showing that the Cbx3 haplo-insufficiency was only in the placenta.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Effect of the Cbx3 hypo allele on proliferation in placental and fetal tissues</head><p><s>It is known that differential cell proliferation is sufficient to explain growth phenotypes <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Zechner et al. 2002)</ref>.</s><s>To determine if reduced fetal and placental weights were caused by decreased cell proliferation, we performed anti-BrdU immunohistochemistry (IHC) and calculated the percentage of BrdU-positive nuclei.</s><s>With regard to fetuses there was clear evidence for decreased proliferation in Cbx3 hypo/hypo vs. Cbx3 +/+ tissues at E13, with 18.5±3.0%</s><s>vs. 32.9±4.1% BrdU-positive nuclei in heart (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a and b</ref>; P=0.001), 38.9±3.7% vs. 47.2±4.9%</s><s>BrdU-positive nuclei in lung (P=0.001), and 27.7±2.9%</s><s>vs. 31.2±1.6% in tongue (P&lt;0.002).</s><s>On E18 no significant difference could be observed between hearts of Cbx3 hypo/hypo and wild-type fetuses (22.5±0.76 vs. 23.0±0.99;</s><s>P=0.57).</s><s>Notably, at E18 the brown adipose tissue (BAT) of Cbx3 hypo/hypo fetuses exhibited significantly increased BrdU-incorporation compared to wild-type BAT (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2c and d</ref>; 16.7±5.3%</s><s>vs. 6.8±4.7%;</s><s>P&lt;0.001).</s></p><p><s>With regard to the placenta, decreased proliferation was observed in the E13 Cbx3 hypo/hypo labyrinth, which had 38.7±5.1% BrdU-positive nuclei as compared to 51.5±10.8% in wild-type labyrinth (P&lt;0.001).</s><s>The E13 spongiotrophoblast, the supporting structure of the developing labyrinthine layer, showed no significant differences in cell proliferation (8.7±4.3 wt vs. 11.5±3.3</s><s>Cbx3 hypo/hypo ; P=0.09).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Placental morphology and function</head><p><s>Prompted by the observation that placental growth restriction presaged the onset of fetal growth restriction (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>) and may thus cause the fetal growth restriction, we decided to investigate placental morphology and function in more detail.</s><s>We compared the placental morphology of Cbx3 hypo/hypo and wild-type placentas between E12 and E19 of gestation using hematoxylin and eosin (HE), an anti-smooth muscle actin (SMA) antibody and isolectin-B4 (BSB4) that marks the matrix surrounding fetal blood vessels <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Wood et al. 1979</ref>;K u r zet al. 1999).</s></p><p><s>We did not observe any consistent alterations of placental morphology in early post-mid gestation Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas, but we did observe some changes in late gestation Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas.</s><s>First, as shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3a to d,w</ref> e observed increased staining, both in terms of the numbers of cells and staining intensity, of the SMA-positive pericytes.</s><s>Apart from this enhanced staining of pericytes smooth muscle differentiation looked normal in late gestation Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas.</s><s>Second, there was decreased BSB4-staining (C.f.</s><s>figure 3e with 3f) that was associated with decreased width of blood vessels.</s><s>Third, we observed increased numbers of nuclei per given area in sections of late gestation Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas compared to wild-type placentas.</s><s>E18 and E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo placental sections showed significantly higher nuclear density in the labyrinth compared to wild-type placentas (E18: 291±35.3 vs. 257±35.6;</s><s>E19: 315±51 vs. 206±42; P&lt;0.001; C.f. figure 3i with 3j).</s><s>This contrasted to the situation found at E12 where nuclear density in the labyrinth was reduced in Cbx3 hypo/hypo compared to wild-type placentas (231±16 vs. 273±17; P=0.02; C.f. figure 3g with 3h); analysis of intervening stages showed that the tendency for reduced nuclear density in Cbx3 hypo/hypo labyrinth persisted until E14.</s><s>These findings indicate that after E14 the Cbx3 hypo/ hypo placentas compensate by increasing cell number and thus the surface area for exchange of nutrient, gas and waste exchange between the fetal and maternal blood supplies.</s></p><p><s>We next measured changes in mRNA transcripts of genes whose expression is known to change during the placental growth restriction that results from undernourishment of dams <ref type="bibr">(Coan et al. 2010)</ref>.</s><s>They included placental growth regulators, amino acid and glucose transporters (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3k</ref>).</s><s>In E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas expression of the placentaspecific transcript of Igf2, Igf2P0, and of Grb10 are reduced  The nuclei of E12 to E19 placental sections from Cbx3 hypo/hypo and Cbx3 +/+ littermates were stained and counted.</s><s>Comparing the number of nuclei in E12 Cbx3 hypo/hypo (g) placentas to that of Cbx3 +/+ (h) littermates showed that the nuclear density was reduced in E12 Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas (number of placentas counted: hypo/hypo=2; +/+=2; 3 areas were analysed from each placenta).</s><s>By contrast, E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas shown in (i) exhibited higher nuclear density in the labyrinth than Cbx3 +/+ littermates shown in (j) (number of placentas analysed: hypo/hypo=4; +/+=2; 3 areas were analysed from each placenta).</s><s>to 78%and 70% of wild-type respectively.</s><s>There was no significant change in expression of the growth regulator H19.</s><s>E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas showed significantly reduced expression of mRNA transcripts in two of the three members of the system A amino acid transporter family, Slc38a1 (down to 80% of wt) and Slc38a2 (down to 78% of wt).</s><s>There was no significant change in the expression of the Slc38a4 gene.There was a dramatic reduction in the mRNA transcript of placental glucose transporter gene, Slc2a3, to 58% of wild-type levels.</s><s>The Slc2a1 mRNA transcript was also reduced to 83% of wild-type levels.</s></p><p><s>To directly test placental transport function we determined essential fatty acid (EFA) transport across the placenta.</s><s>We used the method detailed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Wu et al. (2003)</ref>a n dY uet al. <ref type="bibr">(2008)</ref> and measured fetal and placental ratios of EFAs: non-essential FAs (NEFAs) in Cbx3 hypo/hypo and wild-type littermates at E13 and E18.</s><s>At E13 there was no significant difference in placental EFA:NEFA ratios in two litters that were investigated.</s><s>In one of the E13 litters there was a significantly reduced EFA:NEFA ratio in the fetuses, with values of 1.67±0.21 in Cbx3 hypo/hypo (N=2) vs. 2.44±0.21 in wild-type and heterozygous (N=3; P&lt;0.05).</s><s>However, fetuses of the second E13 litter showed no significant differences, with EFA:NEFA ratios of 3.23±0.04 in Cbx3 hypo/hypo (N=2) vs. 2.98±0.21 in control littermates (N=2).</s><s>Examination of an E18 litter, which comprised two Cbx3 hypo/hypo fetuses and four wild-type and heterozygous controls, showed that the EFA:NEFA ratios were significantly reduced in the heads of the Cbx3 hypo/hypo fetuses (1.83±0.12 vs. 2.51±0.14;</s><s>P=0.02), but not in the rest of the bodies (2.15±0.21 vs. 2.65±0.69;</s><s>P=0.16) or in the placentas.</s><s><ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1d</ref>).</s><s>When a PP8 litter consisting of four pups was analysed, body weights were 3,805 and 3,288 mg for Cbx3 hypo/hypo and 5,657 mg and 5,756 mg in a Cbx3 +/+ and a Cbx3 hypo/+ , respectively; Cbx3 hypo/hypo weights were 62% of wild-type.</s><s>Reduced body weight had also been observed in the adult Cbx3 hypo/hypo mice described previously (Brown and Singh, unpublished).</s><s>Stomachs of PP1 Cbx3 hypo/hypo pups frequently contained no milk (C.f.</s><s>figure 4a with 4d)a n dm o s t were found dead or dying at around noon of PP1at the periphery of the group/huddle of littermates.</s><s>Death also occurred when competing wild-type and heterozygous littermates had been removed.</s><s>Only three Cbx3 hypo/hypo pups survived beyond PP1: one pup died on PP2, and two pups from one litter were sacrificed on PP8 for analysis.</s><s>The mortality of the Cbx3 hypo/hypo homozygotes was too early to be explained by non-feeding alone because non-feeding mice that do not suckle die within a time window of 12-2 4ha f t e rb i r t h( T u r g e o na n d Meloche 2009).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Newborn Cbx3</head><p><s>External examination of Cbx3 hypo/hypo pups provided no explanation for the severe neonatal mortality.</s><s>Cbx3 hypo/hypo newborns possessed neither the characteristic Cbx1 −/− hunch-back phenotype <ref type="bibr">(Aucott et al. 2008)</ref>, nor any cyanosis.</s><s>They also exhibited a normal righting reflex and were not anosmic.</s><s>Internal examination of Cbx3 hypo/hypo , Cbx3 hypo/+ and control wild-type PP1 pups revealed no obvious malformation of organ systems necessary for postnatal survival, such as heart and kidneys.</s><s>However, we consistently observed reduced vascularization of the intestines and the intrascapular BAT in Cbx3 hypo/hypo pups (not shown).</s><s>Vascularization of the intestines largely occurs postnatally and is induced by milk uptake; notably, as shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4a and d</ref>, milk was frequently absent from the stomachs of PP1 Cbx3 hypo/hypo pups.</s><s>BAT is the main site of thermogenesis in neonatal mice and vascularization of this tissue is required because of the high oxygen demands of this process <ref type="bibr">(Crandall et al. 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr">L i met al. 2012)</ref>.</s><s>The changes in vascularization of the intestines and BAT prompted us to examine defects in metabolism and energy homeostasis as the cause of the neonatal mortality because such defects may result in neonatal mortality in the absence of overt morphological abnormalities <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Turgeon and Meloche 2009)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5">Cbx3 hypo/hypo neonates are hypoglycemic and have reduced amounts of glycogen</head><p><s>Blood glucose measurements showed that PP1 Cbx3 hypo/hypo neonates had significantly lower blood glucose levels than wild-type or heterozygous pups, with concentrations of 2.1±0.6 mmol/L (N=9; range 3.1-&lt;1.1 ) as compared to 3.1±0.5 mmol/L (N=17; range 3.8-2.1;</s><s>P&lt;0.006) respectively.</s><s>In two of the PP1 Cbx3 hypo/hypo pups glucose levels were below the detection limit of 1.1 mmol/L.</s><s>Moderately reduced blood glucose levels were also observed in the two PP8 Cbx3 hypo/hypo pups, even though they were found to have full stomachs upon dissection, with 5.6 and 5.7 mmol/L (two Cbx3 hypo/hypo pups) comp a r e dt o6 .</s><s>8( Cbx3 +/+ ) and 7.5 mmol/L (Cbx3 hypo/+ )i n control littermates.</s></p><p><s>Staining of livers for PAS showed that there was reduced glycogen in newborn (PP1) Cbx3 hypo/hypo (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4b</ref>) (N= 6) livers compared to wild-type (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4e</ref>) (N=6).</s><s>There was no difference in PAS staining of PP1 hearts (not shown) indicating that the depletion of liver glycogen is likely to be a secondary consequence to the inability of Cbx3 hypo/hypo newborns to suckle and take on carbohydrate in the milk (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a and d</ref>), which would be transported back to the liver via the intestines.</s><s>This would also be consistent with the observation that depleted glycogen reserves were limited to postnatal livers because fetal (E19) Cbx3 hypo/hypo (N=6) and wild-type (N=6) livers showed no difference in PAS staining (C.f.</s><s>figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4c with 4f</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Given the hypoglycemia and reduction in glycogen deposits in PP1 Cbx3 hypo/hypo livers we investigated mRNA transcript levels of three genes coding for enzymes active in glucose/ glycogen metabolism by qRT-PCR on days E19 and PP1.</s><s>The genes were glycogen synthase (Gys2), glucose-6-phosphatase (G6pc)a n dphosphoenolpyruvate carboxykinase (Pck1).</s><s>As shown in figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4k</ref> Pck1 was up-regulated in Cbx3 hypo/hypo mutants at both E19 and PP1 by 1.4-and 2.3-fold respectively.</s><s>G6pc transcript levels were also up-regulated 2.4-fold on PP1, but showed a moderate 0.8-fold down-regulation on E19 (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4k</ref>).</s><s>There were no significant changes in expression of Gys2 (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4k</ref>).</s></p><p><s>3.6 Cbx3 hypo/hypo homozygotes are deficient in BAT lipid deposits</s></p><p><s>The finding that BAT vascularization is reduced in Cbx3 hypo/hypo homozygotes indicated that the function of this tissue might be impaired.</s><s>We therefore decided to examine the histology and lipid content by HE and Oil red O staining of BAT from PP1 Cbx3 hypo/hypo and wild-type pups.</s><s>HE revealed that BAT of Cbx3 hypo/hypo mutants exhibited a higher nuclear density that was likely due to reduced cell volume (C.f.</s><s>figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4g with 4h</ref>).</s><s>The difference in Oil Red O staining of PP1 Cbx3 hypo/hypo (N=9) BAT compared to wildtype or Cbx3 hypo/+ controls (N=9) was striking.</s><s>Lipid was either absent or strongly reduced in Cbx3 hypo/hypo BAT (C.f.</s><s>figure 4g with 4h); this strong reduction in lipid content could explain the decreased cell volume in Cbx3 hypo/hypo BAT.</s><s>We next asked whether the reduction of lipid was also found prenatally.</s><s>Accordingly, we stained BAT of E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo fetuses with Oil Red O and showed that the lipid was also reduced in the BAT of E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo fetuses (9 mutant vs. 7 wild-type or heterozygous) (C.f.</s><s>figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4i</ref> with figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4j</ref>).</s><s>The prenatal depletion of lipid Cbx3 hypo/hypo BAT indicates that the depletion was not caused solely by the inability to suckle.</s></p><p><s>The abnormal development of BAT prompted us to investigate real time mRNA transcription of genes involved in lipid metabolism and BAT differentiation in Cbx3 hypo/hypo BAT.</s><s>We measured mRNA transcripts of three genes involved in lipid metabolism, Pparg2 (Jones et al. 2005), Srebf1 (Eberlé et al. 2004)a n dHmgcs <ref type="bibr">(Goldstein and Brown 1990)</ref>.</s><s>For BAT differentiation we measured mRNA transcripts for Prlr (Budge et al. 2002), Igf2, Pgc1a <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Wu et al. 1999)</ref>, C i t r a t es y n t h a s e( C s ) (Kloosterboer et al. 1979) and Ucp1.</s><s>We observed similar levels of mRNA transcripts for Pparg2 and Hmgcs while Sreb1 transcription was elevated in Cbx3 hypo/hypo BAT (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4k</ref>).</s><s>Hmgcs is a target gene of SREBF1 protein <ref type="bibr">(Horton et al. 2003)</ref>.</s><s>The lack of any change in Hmgcs expression indicates that Hmgcs may be regulated independently of SREBF1 in BAT.</s><s>Cs is a quantitative marker for mitochondria <ref type="bibr">(Kloosterboer et al. 1979)</ref> indicating that the number of mitochondria is unlikely to be changed in Cbx3 hypo/hypo BAT.</s><s>Prlr showed no change in expression but there was up-regulation of Igf2 in Cbx3 hypo/hypo BAT onE19 but not on PP1 (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4k</ref>).</s><s>Notably, mRNA transcripts of BAT-specific thermogenic genes Pgc1a and Ucp1 were significantly reduced on both E19 and PP1 (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4k</ref>), with Ucp1 showing a marked 10-fold down-regulation on E19.</s></p><p><s>In addition to measuring specific transcripts in BAT we also investigated whether there was any effect of the Cbx3 hypo/hypo mutation on placental prolactin (Prl) mRNA levels.</s><s>We were prompted to do this because the placenta expresses Prl and prolactin is known to be involved in BAT development <ref type="bibr">(Budge et al. 2002)</ref>, so it was possible that changes in placental Prl expression could cause the changes in BAT.</s><s>We also extended our investigation to measuring transcript levels of several members of the prolactin gene family <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Wiemers et al. 2003)</ref>, including Prl3c1, Prl4a1, Prl7b1, Prl7c1 and Prl8a9.</s><s>qRT-PCR showed that mRNA transcripts from the Prl gene were expressed at similar levels in E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo and wild-type placentas (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4k</ref>).</s><s>Expression of mRNAs from all other family members was significantly up-regulated in E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">4k</ref>).</s><s>The up-regulation ranged from around a 2-fold increase for Prl4a1, Prl7c1 and Prl8a9 to 3-fold for Prl7b1 and 6-fold for Prl3c1.</s><s><ref type="bibr">et al. 2008</ref>).</s><s>Here we show that the severe neonatal attrition seen in Cbx3 hypo/hypo mutants likely results from an accumulation of deleterious lesions that begin during development in utero.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mammalian</head><p><s>4.1 Cbx3 hypo/hypo mutants are at a disadvantage at birth compared to wild-type Depletion of CBX3 protein impedes fetal and placental growth.</s><s>Placental growth restriction in Cbx3 hypo/hypo conceptuses starts before the observed fetal growth restriction; Cbx3 hypo/+ placentas are intermediate in size between Cbx3 hypo/hypo and wild-type placentas indicating a haploinsufficiency and that placental growth is exquisitely sensitive to depletion of CBX3 protein.</s><s>The first sign that Cbx3 hypo/hypo placental weights were statistically smaller than wild-type was on E13 and correlates with both reduced cell proliferation and nuclear density within the labyrinth of the placenta, which is the site of nutrient, gas and waste exchange between the fetal and maternal blood supplies <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Watson and Cross 2005)</ref>.</s><s>The weight disparity between Cbx3 hypo/hypo and wild-type was greatest between E14 and E16, thereafter the placenta appears to compensate for its small size; the disparity was narrowed but was never closed.</s><s>One compensatory mechanism that began at around E14 was an increase in nuclear density within the labyrinth of Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas.</s><s>The increase in nuclear density was still manifested in E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas and might provide a compensatory mechanism to increase interface between the fetal and maternal blood supplies.</s><s>The 'catch-up' in Cbx3 hypo/hypo placental weight was not reflected in the trajectory of Cbx3 hypo/hypo fetal weights during development: there is no 'catch-up' in the weight of Cbx3 hypo/hypo fetuses during development.</s><s>We did not find an increase in cell proliferation in Cbx3 hypo/hypo heart, lung or tongue.</s><s>There was one exception in that Cbx3 hypo/hypo BAT exhibited increased cell proliferation compared to wildtype.</s><s>Although unlikely to contribute significantly to overall fetal weight because of its small size the increased cell proliferation in Cbx3 hypo/hypo BAT may represent a compensatory mechanism in an organ that is important for early postnatal life: BAT is responsible for the rapid production of heat at birth <ref type="bibr">(Cannon and Nedergaard 2004)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Nutrient supply from the placenta to the fetus is not only dependent on the size of the placenta but also on its morphology, blood flow and the abundance of the various transport mechanisms.</s><s>All three of these characteristics appear to be compromised in the Cbx3 hypo/hypo mutant placentas.</s><s>We observed a morphological narrowing of the placental blood vessels in late gestation Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas that is likely due to a reduction of the intracellular matrix surrounding the vessels; the smooth muscle appeared normal.</s><s>Narrowing of placental blood vessels would reduce blood flow and thus nutrient exchange and exacerbate any problems in transport across the placenta.</s><s>Our investigation of transport mechanisms was revealing.</s><s>In E19 placentas there was downregulation of genes that promote placental growth such as the placenta-specific transcript of Igf2, Igf2P0, and Grb10.</s><s>The reduced expression of Igf2P0 is of interest because it is known to be important for placental growth <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Constancia et al. 2002)</ref> and placental transport through regulation of genes such as Slc38a2 that encode transporter proteins <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Sferruzzi-Perri et al. 2011)</ref>.</s><s>Notably, the mRNA transcripts of both glucose (Slc2a1 and Slc2a3) and amino-acid (Slc38a1 and Slc38a2) transporters were significantly reduced showing that placental transport function is likely to be compromised in Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas.</s><s>We directly tested transport capacity by measuring the cumulative transport of EFAs across Cbx3 hypo/hypo and wild-type placentas.</s><s>EFA transport is strictly regulated and involves several protein classes, such as FA translocases and FA transport proteins (Duttaroy 2009).</s><s>Our results indicated that there was likely to be a defect in placental transport in Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas.</s><s>Specifically, we found that Cbx3 hypo/hypo fetuses in one of two E13 litters showed a significant reduction in the EFA:NEFA ratio and the Cbx3 hypo/hypo heads of an E18 litter showed a reduced EFA:NEFA ratio.</s></p><p><s>The picture that emerges is that Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas are affected first, with abnormalities observed in placental morphology, blood supply and transport.</s><s>These defects are likely to contribute to the fetal growth restriction that follows.</s><s>An important player is, we suggest, the placentaspecific Igf2P0 transcript.</s><s>Down-regulation of the Igf2P0 transcript could set in motion the growth and transport defects we observe in the Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas.</s><s>A key experiment will be to test whether CBX3 protein binds the Igf2P0 gene, which would support a role for CBX3 in facilitating proper elongation of Igf2P0 transcript.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Loss of energy homeostasis in Cbx3 hypo/hypo neonates</head><p><s>The small Cbx3 hypo/hypo neonates show no overt morphological abnormalities.</s><s>Reduced size cannot alone explain the severe postnatal mortality.</s><s>For example, ablation of the Igf2P0 transcript is not associated with postnatal mortality despite Igf2P0 null newborns being even smaller than Cbx3 hypo/hypo newborns -69% (Igf2P0 null mutant) <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Constancia et al. 2002)</ref> vs. 78% (Cbx3 hypo/hypo mutant).</s><s>Other defects in Cbx3 hypo/hypo mutants must be involved in the postnatal mortality.</s><s>From our results there are good candidates that could contribute to the postnatal mortality of Cbx3 hypo/hypo newborns.</s></p><p><s>One of the observations was that there was a likely disruption of glucose/glycogen metabolism in Cbx3 hypo/hypo mutants.</s><s>Any hypoglycemia would have been compounded by the lack of suckling of PP1 Cbx3 hypo/hypo pups that would in turn lead to depletion of liver glycogen reserves.</s><s>The compensatory upregulation of G6pc on PP1was ineffectual because there were little glycogen reserves upon which the enzyme could act.</s><s>The up-regulation of liver Pck1, whose product is the rate limiting step of gluconeogenesis from non-carbohydrate sources <ref type="bibr">(Chakravarty et al. 2005)</ref>, on E19 and PP1 was also insufficient to alleviate the hypoglycemia.</s><s>We also observed a dramatic depletion of lipid stores in BAT and the reduced expression of two BAT-specific thermogenic genes, Pgc1a and Ucp1.</s><s>Pgc1a is involved in activation of the Ucp1gene in BAT <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Puigserver et al. 1998</ref>) and, importantly, the UCP1 protein is responsible for non-shivering thermogenesis in BAT <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Matthias et al. 2000)</ref>.</s><s>We did not observe any changes in expression of the prolactin (Prl) gene in the placenta or of the gene encoding its cognate receptor (Prlr)i nB A T ,b o t ho f which are involved BAT differentiation <ref type="bibr">(Budge et al. 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Viengchareun et al. 2008)</ref>.</s><s>We did observe changes in placental expression in other members of the prolactin gene family but it is unclear what this means for BAT differentiation.</s></p><p><s>Given the broad euchromatic distribution of CBX3 <ref type="bibr">(Horsley et al. 1996)</ref> and its role in transcriptional elongation of mRNA transcripts <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Vakoc et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hediger and Gasser 2006)</ref>, depletion of CBX3 is likely to have widespread effects on decreasing transcriptional elongation of many genes.</s><s>Accordingly, CBX3 depletion may explain the down-regulation of mRNAs for growth regulators, Igf2P0 and Grb10, glucose (Slc2a1 and Slc2a3) and amino-acid (Slc38a1 and Slc38a2) transporters in the placenta.</s><s>The dramatic reduction of the Ucp1 mRNA transcripts in BAT is of particular significance, especially in the context of the depleted lipid stores.</s><s>This is because UCP1 protein is responsible for non-shivering thermogenesis in BAT <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Matthias et al. 2000)</ref>.</s><s>UCP1 increases the conductance of the inner mitochondrial membrane so that BAT mitochondria generate heat instead of ATP <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Nicholls and Locke 1984)</ref>.</s><s>There is also an essential requirement of long chain fatty acids (LCFA) in this process.</s><s>UCP1 is a LCFA anion/H + symporter and has an absolute requirement for LCFA in order to function <ref type="bibr">(Fedorenko et al. 2012)</ref>.</s><s>Thus the dramatic decrease in transcription of Ucp1 and the almost complete loss of lipid stores would render the heat-generating capacity of Cbx3 hypo/hypo BAT practically negligible.</s></p><p><s>The mechanism by which CBX3 protein activates Ucp1 expression may be as a constituent of the PRDM16 transcriptional complex <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Seale et al. 2008)</ref>, which contains the histone H3K9 methyltransferase EHMT1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Ohno et al. 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Depletion of CBX3 could destabilize the PRDM16 transcriptional complex in a manner that has already been described after loss of EHMT1 protein <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Ohno et al. 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Loss of PRDM16 or EHMT1 activity decreases Upc1 expression to 50% and 33% of wild-type levels respectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Seale et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Ohno et al. 2013)</ref>.</s><s>By contrast Upc1 expression is reduced 10-fold in E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo BAT indicating that defects in other regulatory mechanism(s) reduce Ucp1 expression.</s><s>We suggest that inhibition of transcriptional elongation of Ucp1 and its activator, Pgc1a, might also contribute to the decrease of Ucp1 mRNA transcripts in Cbx3 hypo/hypo BAT.</s><s>4.3 A scenario for the severe attrition of Cbx3 hypo/hypo neonates</s></p><p><s>The severe postnatal mortality of Cbx3 hypo/hypo homozygotes is similar to that observed in newborn rats that have been subjected to experimental fetal growth restriction (FGR) <ref type="bibr">(Cogneville et al. 1975)</ref>.</s><s>Cogneville and colleagues generated unilateral FGR by clamping the uterine artery of one uterine horn.</s><s>Just as we observed for Cbx3 hypo/hypo mutants, the growth-restricted fetuses and newborn rats exhibited both reduced lipid stores in BAT and a severe postnatal mortality <ref type="bibr">(Cogneville et al. 1975)</ref>.</s><s>It was argued that since BAT is essential for non-shivering thermogenesis in altricial newborn rodents, the postnatal depletion of lipids in BAT would lead to rapid hypothermia, inability to suckle, hypoglycemia, followed by death.</s><s>However, work on mice deleted for Prlr (prolactin receptor gene), which causes reduced formation of BAT <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Viengchareun et al. 2008)</ref>, indicates that there is little requirement for BAT in postnatal survival in the mouse (Nadine Binart, personal communication), although, as expected, Prlr −/− pups do succumb more rapidly to cold exposure than wild-type mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Viengchareun et al. 2008)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Notwithstanding the observations with Prlr −/− mice, we are persuaded that the scenario for neonatal death described by <ref type="bibr">Cogneville et al. (1975)</ref> is similar to that which brings about the death of Cbx3 hypo/hypo homozygotes.</s><s>This is because Prlr −/− newborns are of normal size <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Viengchareun et al. 2008)</ref>, unlike the Cbx3 hypo/hypo pups and FGR neonates <ref type="bibr">(Cogneville et al. 1975)</ref>.</s><s>The smaller Cbx3 hypo/hypo newborns would lose heat more rapidly compared to Prlr −/− newborns because of the former's greater surface-to-volume ratio (the 'square-cube law'; Haldane 1926).</s><s>Moreover, heat loss may be further compounded because, in addition to thermoregulation via BAT, thermoregulation in newborn altricial rodents has a behavioural component termed huddling <ref type="bibr">(Alberts 1978;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Sokoloff and Blumberg 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr">Harshaw and Alberts 2012)</ref>.</s><s>Huddling close to littermates is protective against the rapid heat loss that occurs during the brief exposure to cool ambient temperatures that isolated pups experience when the dam leaves the nest (Harshaw and Alberts 2012).</s><s>Notably, in a huddle of newborns there is competition between pups and pups with functional BAT thermogenesis tend to avoid contact with pups whose BAT thermogenesis is blocked <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Sokoloff and Blumberg 2001)</ref>.</s><s>Given that BAT development is abnormal in the smaller-than-normal Cbx3 hypo/hypo newborns, heat loss is likely to be further exacerbated by the mutants being pushed to the periphery of the nest where they do not experience the thermoregulatory benefit of huddling.</s></p><p><s>A scenario for the postnatal mortality is that Cbx3 hypo/hypo mutants are born small and hypoglycemic, largely due to abnormalities in placental morphology, blood supply and transport.</s><s>After birth, hypothermia sets in due to defective BAT-dependent non-shivering thermogenesis and the lack of huddling.</s><s>The hypoglycemia is further compounded by an inability to suckle and depletion of glycogen reserves.</s><s>These defects reinforce each other and are severally necessary and jointly sufficient in bringing about the demise of the majority of Cbx3 hypo/hypo newborns.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Homozygosity for Cbx3 hypo/hypo causes placental and fetal growth restriction.</s><s>(a) An E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo conceptus whose placental and fetal weights were 84.1 and 752 mg respectively.</s><s>(b) An E19 Cbx3 hypo/+ conceptus whose placental and fetal weights were 107 and 1095 mg respectively.</s><s>We have shown the comparison of the Cbx3 hypo/hypo conceptus in (a) with the E19 Cbx3 hypo/+ conceptus in (b)so that the similarity in size of the placentas can be seen, which is where the haplo-insufficiency for Cbx3 hypo is observed.</s><s>By contrast there is an obvious difference in size of the fetuses.</s><s>(c) Diagram of the weight increase of Cbx3 hypo/hypo , Cbx3 +/− and Cbx3 +/+ placentas between E12 and E19 of gestation; values are shown as x±S.D. (d) Diagram of the weight increase of Cbx3 hypo/hypo , Cbx3 +/− and Cbx3 +/+ fetuses between E12 and E19 of gestation and for post partum day 1 (PP1) newborn mice; values are shown as x±S.D. Statisticalsignificance was assessed by unpaired t-test.</s><s>Number of conceptuses: E12 -hypo/hypo=4; hypo/+=7; +/+=5; E13 -hypo/hypo= 16; hypo/+=53; +/+=25; E14 -hypo/hypo= 9; hypo/+=18; +/+=8; E16 -hypo/hypo=8; hypo/+=18; +/+=9; E18 -hypo/hypo= 10; hypo/+=23; +/+=12; E19 -hypo/hypo=25; hypo/+=61; +/+=22; PP1 -hypo/hypo= 13; hypo/+=24; +/+=15; hypo/hypo=Cbx3 hypo/hypo ; hypo/+=Cbx3 +/hypo ;+/+=Cbx3 +/+ ;greenbars=Cbx3 hypo/hypo ; red bars=Cbx3 hypo/+ ; blue bars=Cbx3 +/+ .</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,86.12,72.85,425.95,425.54" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Cellular proliferation in Cbx3 hypo/hypo and Cbx3 +/+ fetal tissues.</s><s>Cellular proliferation was determined by BrdU-IHC.</s><s>(a) BrdU-IHC on a section of E13 Cbx3 hypo/hypo heart.</s><s>(b) BrdU-IHC on a section of E13 Cbx3 +/+ heart that is a littermate of the fetus in (a).</s><s>Comparison of (a) with (b) shows that there is reduced BrdU incorporation in the Cbx3 hypo/hypo heart.</s><s>(c) BrdU-IHC on a section of E18 Cbx3 hypo/hypo BAT.</s><s>(d) BrdU-IHC on a section of E18 Cbx3 +/+ BAT that is a littermate of the fetus in (c).</s><s>Comparison of (c) with (d) shows that there is increased BrdU incorporation in the Cbx3 hypo/hypo BAT.</s><s>Number of tissues counted: hypo/hypo=4; +/+=4; three areas were analysed from each tissue.</s><s>Magnifications are ×40 of the original.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,118.77,72.85,354.91,284.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. Altered placental morphology of Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas.</s><s>Morphology of placentas was investigated using anti-smooth muscle actin (SMA) and Isolectin BSB4 IHC.</s><s>(a, c) Anti-SMA IHC on placental sections of E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo .(b,</s><s>d) Anti-SMA IHC on placental sections of E19 Cbx3 +/+ that is a littermate of the animal in (a, c).</s><s>Comparison of (a, c) with (b, d) shows that there both an increase in the number and in the intensity of staining of the SMA-positive pericytes in Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas.</s><s>(e) Isolectin BSB4-staining of E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo placenta.</s><s>(f) Isolectin BSB4-staining of E19 Cbx3 +/+ placenta.</s><s>Comparison of (e) and (f) shows decreased width of blood vessels in Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas.</s><s>Number of placentas analysed: hypo/hypo=6; +/+=6.</s><s>(g to j)The nuclei of E12 to E19 placental sections from Cbx3 hypo/hypo and Cbx3 +/+ littermates were stained and counted.</s><s>Comparing the number of nuclei in E12 Cbx3 hypo/hypo (g) placentas to that of Cbx3 +/+ (h) littermates showed that the nuclear density was reduced in E12 Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas (number of placentas counted: hypo/hypo=2; +/+=2; 3 areas were analysed from each placenta).</s><s>By contrast, E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas shown in (i) exhibited higher nuclear density in the labyrinth than Cbx3 +/+ littermates shown in (j) (number of placentas analysed: hypo/hypo=4; +/+=2; 3 areas were analysed from each placenta).</s><s>(k) Normalized real time PCR transcripts of genes relevant to placental growth and transport function.</s><s>mRNA transcripts in Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas were measured on E19 (black, filled bars) and compared to Cbx3 +/+ transcript levels that were normalized to 1.0 (empty bars).</s><s>Significant expression changes are indicated by asterisks (*p&lt; 0.05; **p&lt;0.01).</s><s>Statistical significance was assessed by unpaired t-test.</s><s>Cbx3 hypo/hypo gene expression levels are indicated by filled bars, Cbx3 +/+ levels, normalized to 1.0, by empty bars (number of placentas analysed: hypo/hypo=3; +/+=3).</s><s>Magnification in (a, b) is ×10 and (c to j) is ×40 of the original.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,124.50,74.16,349.13,457.28" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. Altered placental morphology of Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas.</s><s>Morphology of placentas was investigated using anti-smooth muscle actin (SMA) and Isolectin BSB4 IHC.</s><s>(a, c) Anti-SMA IHC on placental sections of E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo .(b,</s><s>d) Anti-SMA IHC on placental sections of E19 Cbx3 +/+ that is a littermate of the animal in (a, c).</s><s>Comparison of (a, c) with (b, d) shows that there both an increase in the number and in the intensity of staining of the SMA-positive pericytes in Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas.</s><s>(e) Isolectin BSB4-staining of E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo placenta.</s><s>(f) Isolectin BSB4-staining of E19 Cbx3 +/+ placenta.</s><s>Comparison of (e) and (f) shows decreased width of blood vessels in Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas.</s><s>Number of placentas analysed: hypo/hypo=6; +/+=6.</s><s>(g to j)The nuclei of E12 to E19 placental sections from Cbx3 hypo/hypo and Cbx3 +/+ littermates were stained and counted.</s><s>Comparing the number of nuclei in E12 Cbx3 hypo/hypo (g) placentas to that of Cbx3 +/+ (h) littermates showed that the nuclear density was reduced in E12 Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas (number of placentas counted: hypo/hypo=2; +/+=2; 3 areas were analysed from each placenta).</s><s>By contrast, E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas shown in (i) exhibited higher nuclear density in the labyrinth than Cbx3 +/+ littermates shown in (j) (number of placentas analysed: hypo/hypo=4; +/+=2; 3 areas were analysed from each placenta).</s><s>(k) Normalized real time PCR transcripts of genes relevant to placental growth and transport function.</s><s>mRNA transcripts in Cbx3 hypo/hypo placentas were measured on E19 (black, filled bars) and compared to Cbx3 +/+ transcript levels that were normalized to 1.0 (empty bars).</s><s>Significant expression changes are indicated by asterisks (*p&lt; 0.05; **p&lt;0.01).</s><s>Statistical significance was assessed by unpaired t-test.</s><s>Cbx3 hypo/hypo gene expression levels are indicated by filled bars, Cbx3 +/+ levels, normalized to 1.0, by empty bars (number of placentas analysed: hypo/hypo=3; +/+=3).</s><s>Magnification in (a, b) is ×10 and (c to j) is ×40 of the original.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. Cbx3 hypo/hypo neonates exhibit symptoms of defective energy homeostasis.</s><s>(a)ACbx3 hypo/hypo newborn approximately 4 h after birth.</s><s>Comparison of the Cbx3hypo/hypo newborn with its Cbx3 +/+ littermate in (d) shows that the stomach of the Cbx3 +/+ pup is filled with milk, as marked by the white arrow.</s><s>The Cbx3 hypo/hypo newborn's stomach is empty (see white arrow).</s><s>(b to f) Liver glycogen was stained with PAS in PP1 and E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo and Cbx3 +/+ livers.</s><s>Comparing the PAS-staining of the PP1 Cbx3 hypo/hypo liver section in (b) with its PP1 Cbx3 +/+ littermate in (e) shows a dramatic reduction of glycogen in the PP1 Cbx3 hypo/hypo liver.</s><s>There was no difference in PASstaining between staining between E19 Cbx3 hypo/hypo liver sections given in (c) with its E19 Cbx3 +/+ littermate in (f).</s><s>(g to j) BAT sections from E19 and PP1 Cbx3 hypo/hypo and Cbx3 +/+ littermates were stained with lipid-specific stain Oil Red O (ORO).</s><s>Comparison of OROstained BAT sections showed either complete absence or strong reduction of lipid in BAT sections of Cbx3 hypo/hypo both at E19 (i) and PP1 (g) as compared to E19 (j) and PP1 (h) Cbx3 +/+ littermates.</s><s>(k) Normalized real time PCR transcripts of genes expressed in Cbx3 hypo/hypo BAT, placenta and liver.</s><s>mRNA transcripts were measured on E19 (black, filled bars) and PP1 (cross-hatched) and compared to Cbx3 +/+ transcript levels that were normalized to 1.0 (empty bars).</s><s>Significant expression changes are indicated by asterisks (*p&lt;0.05;</s><s>**p&lt;0.01).</s><s>Statistical significance was assessed by unpaired t-test.</s><s>Number of animals analysed: BAT for ORO -hypo/hypo=6; +/+=6; BAT for gene expression -hypo/hypo=5; +/+=5 for E19 and hypo/hypo=3; +/+=4 for PP1; liver for PAS -hypo/hypo=6; +/+=6; liver for gene expression hypo/hypo=3; +/+=3 for E19 and hypo/hypo=4; +/+=2 for PP1; placenta for gene expression hypo/hypo=3; +/+=3.</s><s>PCRs were repeated 3 times.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,135.10,74.15,328.03,458.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Cbx genes have non-redundant functions (reviewed in Singh 2010).</s><s>This was first shown for the Cbx1 gene where the proximate cause of the neonatal lethality of Cbx1 −/− mice was the inability of the lungs to inflate because of defective innervations of the diaphragm (Aucott et al. 2008).</s><s>Ablation of the Cbx5 gene results in a specific silencing defect within the T-cell lineage (Allan et al. 2012) although Cbx5 −/− mice are viable and fertile (cited in Aucott</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>hypo/hypo mutants do not exhibit major morphological abnormalities</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>We have previously shown that roughly 99% of</cell></row><row><cell>Cbx3 hypo/hypo homozygotes on a mixed 129/Sv-C57BL/6</cell></row><row><cell>genetic background die before weaning, whereas during</cell></row><row><cell>prenatal development normal Mendelian ratios of Cbx3 hypo</cell></row><row><cell>to wild-type alleles were observed (Brown et al. 2010). The</cell></row><row><cell>nature and the timing of the postnatal attrition of Cbx3 hypo/hypo</cell></row><row><cell>homozygotes was not determined (Brown et al. 2010). A</cell></row><row><cell>number (N=10) of post-partum (PP1) day 1 litters from</cell></row><row><cell>Cbx3 hypo/+ × Cbx3 hypo/+ matings were analysed. The pre-</cell></row><row><cell>natal fetal weight restriction (figure 1) persisted in post-</cell></row><row><cell>natal Cbx3 hypo/hypo pups. At PP1 Cbx3 hypo/hypo body</cell></row><row><cell>weights were 79% of Cbx3 hypo/+ and Cbx3 +/+ combined</cell></row><row><cell>(P&lt;0.001; figure</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">J. Biosci. 40(2), June 2015</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>We are grateful to Drs Nadine Binart, Miguel Constância and Mike Soares for critically reading the manuscript, and to Drs Irene and Kenneth Söderhäll for their help and support.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <ref type="bibr">Symonds ME and Stephenson T 2002</ref> <p><s>The effect of maternal prolactin infusion during pregnancy on fetal adipose tissue development.</s><s>J. <ref type="bibr">Endocrinol. 174 427-433 Cannon B and Nedergaard J 2004</ref></s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biol. Neonate</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="112" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lack of correlation between placenta and offspring size in mouse interspecific crosses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kurz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Zechner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Orth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fundele</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Anat. Embryol. (Berl)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">200</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="335" to="343" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cold-induced activation of brown adipose tissue and adipose angiogenesis in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Honek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Xue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Seki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hosaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Protoc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="606" to="615" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Livak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Schmittgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="402" to="408" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermogenic responses in brown fat cells are fully UCP1-dependent. UCP2 or UCP3 do not substitute for UCP1 in adrenergically or fatty scid-induced thermogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Matthias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ohlson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fredriksson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jacobsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nedergaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">275</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25073" to="25081" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thermogenic mechanisms in brown fat</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Nicholls</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Locke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiol Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="64" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">EHMT1 controls brown adipose cell fate and thermogenesis through the PRDM16 complex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ohno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Shinoda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ohyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Sharp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kajimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">504</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="167" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A cold-inducible coactivator of nuclear receptors linked to adaptive thermogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Puigserver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Graves</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wright</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Spiegelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="829" to="839" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular cloning of a human homologue of Drosophila heterochromatin protein HP1 using anti-centromere autoantibodies with anti-chromo specificity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Saunders</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goebl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Craig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Powers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Eissenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Elgin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="573" to="582" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PRDM16 controls a brown fat/ skeletal muscle switch</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Seale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bjyork</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kajimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Scimè</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Devarakonda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">454</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="961" to="967" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Placentalspecific Igf2 deficiency alters developmental adaptations to undernutrition in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Sferruzzi-Perri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Vaughan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Coan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Suciu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Darbyshire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Constancia</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Burton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fowden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Endocrinology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">152</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3202" to="3212" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What is the essential interaction of HP1?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genetika</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">CBX3 regulates efficient RNA processing genome-wide</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Smallwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jin</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Espinosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Genome. Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1426" to="1436" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Competition and cooperation among huddling infant rats</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sokoloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Blumberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Psychobiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HP1gamma links histone methylation marks to meiotic synapsis in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Takada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Naruse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Shirakawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tachibana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sharif</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Kezuka-Shiotani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4207" to="4217" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interpreting neonatal lethal phenotypes in mouse mutants: insights into gene function and human diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Turgeon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Meloche</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiol. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="117" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Vakoc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mandat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Olenchock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Blobel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Histone H3 lysine 9 methylation and HP1gamma are associated with transcription elongation through mammalian chromatin</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="381" to="391" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prolactin receptor signaling is essential for perinatal brown adipocyte function: a role for insulin-like growth factor-2</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Viengchareun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Servel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Feve</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Freemark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lombes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Binart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">E1535</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development of structures and transport in the mouse placenta</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Watson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cross</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="180" to="193" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mouse prolactin gene family</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Wiemers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Soares</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">locus. Endochronolgy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">144</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="313" to="325" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immunochemical studies of the combining sites of the two isolectins, A4 and B4, isolated from Bandeiraea simplicifolia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kabat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Goldstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch. Biochem. Biophys</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">198</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="1979">1979</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A mammalian homologue of Drosophila heterochromatin protein 1 (HP1) is a component of constitutive heterochromatin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wreggett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>James</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hutchings</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Butcher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cytogenet. Cell. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="103" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Extra-embryonic function of Rb is essential for embryonic development and viability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>De Bruin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Saavedra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Starovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Trimboli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Opavska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">421</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="942" to="947" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanisms controlling mitochondrial biogenesis and respiration through the thermogenic coactivator PGC-1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Puigserver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Andersson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Adelmant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Mootha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Troy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cinti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">98</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influence of murine maternal diabetes on placental morphology, gene expression, and function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Shi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Konno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Soares</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Geyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fundele</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch. Physiol. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proliferation and growth factor expression in abnormally enlarged placentas of mouse interspecific hybrids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Zechner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hemberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Constancia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Orth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Dragatsis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Luttges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hameister</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fundele</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Dyn</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">224</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="125" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">MS received</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>SANJEEV KHOSLA</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014-11-11">11 November 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>accepted 16 March 2015 Corresponding editor</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
