<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Attenuated bidirectional short-term synaptic plasticity in the dentate gyrus of Schnurri-2 knockout mice, a model of schizophrenia</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Katsunori</forename><surname>Kobayashi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Graduate School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nippon Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1-1-5 Sendagi, Bunkyo-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>113-8602</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Graduate School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nippon Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1-1-5 Sendagi, Bunkyo-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>113-8602</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tsuyoshi</forename><surname>Takagi</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0001-8537-8448</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute for Developmental Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Aichi Human Service Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Kasugai</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">RIKEN Tsukuba Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tsukuba</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Shunsuke</forename><surname>Ishii</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">RIKEN Tsukuba Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Tsukuba</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hidenori</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Graduate School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nippon Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1-1-5 Sendagi, Bunkyo-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>113-8602</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Graduate School of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nippon Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>1-1-5 Sendagi, Bunkyo-ku</addrLine>
									<postCode>113-8602</postCode>
									<settlement>Tokyo</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tsuyoshi</forename><surname>Miyakawa</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Systems Medical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute for Comprehensive Medical Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Fujita Health University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Toyoake</settlement>
									<country key="JP">Japan</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Attenuated bidirectional short-term synaptic plasticity in the dentate gyrus of Schnurri-2 knockout mice, a model of schizophrenia</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B6F20C3A56B01A8315BC65228FEDAFC4</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s13041-018-0400-9</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 24 August 2018 Accepted: 26 September 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Short-term plasticity</term>
					<term>Perforant path</term>
					<term>Dentate gyrus</term>
					<term>Schizophrenia</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>The dentate gyrus of the hippocampus has been implicated in the pathophysiological basis of neuropsychiatric disorders including schizophrenia.</s><s>We have identified several mouse models of neuropsychiatric disorders with robust molecular and functional defects in the dentate gyrus.</s><s>Among them, mice lacking Schnurri-2 (Shn2 or HIVEP2) have been proposed as a model of schizophrenia and intellectual disability.</s><s>Shn2 knockout mice exhibit behavioral abnormalities resembling symptoms of schizophrenia and HIVEP2-related intellectual disability as well as marked functional alterations in the soma and output synapse of the dentate granule cells (GCs).</s><s>Although robust abnormalities were also observed in the dendritic spine morphology in the GCs, their functional correlates remain unknown.</s><s>In the present study, we performed electrophysiological analyses of synaptic transmission at the medial perforant path (MPP) input onto the GCs in Shn2 knockout mice.</s><s>While the basal synaptic efficacy was preserved, short-term synaptic depression induced by paired-pulse or low-frequency stimulation was reduced in the mutant mice.</s><s>High-frequency tetanic stimulation induced lasting synaptic potentiation in both wild-type and mutant mice.</s><s>However, the decaying synaptic potentiation shortly after the tetanic stimulation was significantly reduced in the mutant mice.</s><s>These results indicate that the Shn2 deficiency attenuates bidirectional short-term synaptic plasticity at the MPP-GC synapse, thereby rendering the synapse more static.</s><s>Our finding further supports a possible role of the dentate gyrus dysfunction in pathophysiology of schizophrenia and may also provide important information in interpreting morphology changes of the brain synapses in neuropsychiatric disorders.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>The hippocampal dentate gyrus has been implicated in the pathophysiology of neuropsychiatric disorders including schizophrenia <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>.</s><s>In several mouse models of neuropsychiatric disorders, we have demonstrated shared molecular and functional defects in the dentate granule cells (GCs), characterized as the immature-like phenotype <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</s><s>Among them, mice lacking Schnurri-2 (Shn2; also called major histocompatibility complex [MHC]-binding protein 2 [MBP-2], or human immunodeficiency virus type I enhancer binding protein 2 [HIVEP2]) have been proposed as a model for schizophrenia and HIVEP2-related intellectual disability with good face and construct validity <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>.</s><s>Shn2 knockout mice exhibit behavioral abnormalities resembling symptoms of these disorders, mild brain inflammation, and transcriptome/proteome changes similar to those in the brain of schizophrenia <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>At cellular levels, Shn2 knockout mice show marked changes in somatic firing properties of the GCs and greatly reduced activity-dependent facilitation at their output synapses <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>We have recently examined subcellular-scale structures of the GCs of Shn2 knockout mice and revealed immature filopodia-like dendritic spines characterized by increased spine length and decreased neck diameter <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, suggesting possible functional changes in the excitatory synaptic input.</s><s>Given potential importance of spine pathology in neuropsychiatric disorders <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, it would be important to examine functional correlates of altered spine morphology in these mice.</s><s>Therefore, in the present study, we performed electrophysiological analyses of synaptic transmission at the medial perforant path (MPP) input onto the GCs in Shn2 knockout mice.</s></p><p><s>Transverse hippocampal slices were prepared from adult mice, and field excitatory postsynaptic potentials (EPSPs) were recorded at the MPP-GC synapse (see Additional file 1 for the detailed method).</s><s>We first examined the input-output relationship of MPP-GC synaptic transmission by changing the intensity of stimulation.</s><s>The presynaptic fiber volley amplitude was reduced in the mutant mice, and the EPSP slope showed a trend toward reduction (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a and b</ref>).</s><s>The relationship between fiber volley amplitude and EPSP slope was similar between wild-type and mutant mice (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>).</s><s>These results suggest that the presynaptic fiber, MPP, is less excitable in the mutant mice, while the basal synaptic efficacy at the MPP-GC synapse is unaffected.</s><s>Next we examined several forms of activity-dependent synaptic plasticity.</s><s>Paired-pulse stimulation induces short-term synaptic depression at this synapse <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s>The mutant mice showed smaller paired-pulse depression at stimulus intervals shorter than 1 s (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1c</ref>).</s><s>Similarly, synaptic depression during repetitive stimulation was significantly reduced in the mutant mice at 5 Hz, but not at 1 Hz (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1d</ref>).</s><s>Then we examined the effect of short high-frequency stimulation (HFS).</s><s>In both wild-type and mutant mice, HFS induced long-term potentiation (LTP) of synaptic transmission.</s><s>However, initial short-term potentiation (STP) decaying after HFS was significantly smaller in the mutant mice (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1e</ref>).</s><s>The excitability of MPP during HFS was not significantly changed in the mutant mice (see Supplementary Discussion).</s><s>Taken together, our results indicate that activity-dependent bidirectional short-term plasticity is attenuated at the MPP-GC synapse in Shn2 knockout mice.</s><s>The present study demonstrated that the MPP-GC synaptic efficacy is intact at the basal condition, but less sensitive to neuronal activity in Shn2 knockout mice.</s><s>We have previously shown that synaptic facilitation during 1 Hz stimulation is strongly reduced at the GC output mossy fiber to CA3 synapse in these mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>Therefore, activity-dependent short-term regulation is impaired at both input and output synapses in the GCs of Shn2 knockout mice, which may underlie impaired hippocampus-dependent cognitive functions in these mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Paired-pulse depression or facilitation is generally thought to be mediated by presynaptic mechanisms.</s><s>However, it has been reported that desensitization of α-Amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazolepropionic acid (AMPA) receptors also contributes to paired-pulse depression at the MPP-GC synapse <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, which raises a possibility that the reduced synaptic depression observed here represents altered functions of the postsynaptic GCs.</s><s>LTP at the MPP synapse is induced in an N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptor-dependent manner <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> and shares expression mechanisms with the well-characterized Schaffer collateral/commissural fiber-CA1 LTP <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s><s>Since the STP phase also largely depends on the NMDA receptor-dependent postsynaptic processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, the reduced STP may be due to weaker activation of NMDA receptors in Shn2 knockout mice.</s><s>However, partial block of NMDA receptors is supposed to reduce LTP more severely than STP <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>, which is opposite to our present observation.</s><s>Although a possibility of presynaptic changes cannot be excluded (see Supplementary Discussion), the result of our previous morphological study implies possible postsynaptic mechanisms underlying the reduced STP.</s><s>We have shown that the dendritic spine neck of the GCs is longer and thinner in Shn2 knockout mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s><s>In CA1, the STP phase has been shown to require lateral diffusion of AMPA receptors from a pre-existing extra-synaptic surface pool <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</s><s>The abnormal spine morphology of GCs may hamper rapid lateral diffusion of AMPA receptors shortly after HFS, thereby preferentially reducing STP.</s><s>In addition, an immunofluorescent analysis revealed an approximately 50% decrease in expression of the AMPA receptor subunit GluA1 in the dentate molecular layer of Shn2 knockout mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s><s>Given the intact basal transmission at the MPP-GC synapse in these mice, the reduced GluA1 expression may mostly represent a reduced surface pool of extra-synaptic AMPA receptors, which could also contribute to impaired STP.</s><s>A similar reduction of STP has been demonstrated in the CA1 region of mice with Disc1 mutation that modeled a risk allele for schizophrenia <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, suggesting that reduced STP could be common synapse pathology in schizophrenia.</s></p><p><s>The present study has demonstrated the functional defects at the MPP-GC synapse of Shn2 knockout mice that appeared to be in good agreement in part with altered spine morphology previously demonstrated in these mice.</s><s>These morpho-functional analyses of model mice would provide crucial information in interpreting altered spine morphology in patients with schizophrenia, intellectual disability and other related neuropsychiatric disorders and eventually in understanding essential synapse pathology in these disorders.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1 Impaired activity-dependent short-term synaptic plasticity in dentate granule cells of Shn2 knockout mice.</s><s>a Medical perforant path (MPP) synaptic potentials evoked at the stimulus intensities of 1.5, 2, 3, 4 and 5 V in wild-type (+/+) and Shn2 knockout (−/−) mice.</s><s>Scale bar: 10 ms, 1 mV.</s><s>b Dependence of fiber volley amplitude (left) and EPSP slope (center) on stimulus intensity, and the relationship between fiber volley and EPSP (right).</s><s>The mutant showed smaller fiber volley amplitude (repeated measure two-way ANOVA: genotype effect, F 1,28 = 7.995, P = 0.0086, n = 15 each; Sidak's test: *P &lt; 0.05, ***P &lt; 0.001).</s><s>c Reduced paired-pulse depression in the mutant mice (repeated measure two-way ANOVA: genotype effect, F 1,12 = 22.15, P = 0.0005, n = 7 each; Sidak's test: ****P &lt; 0.0001).</s><s>Sample traces show EPSPs evoked by paired stimulation at the 50 ms interval.</s><s>Scale bar: 20 ms, 0.2 mV.</s><s>d Significant reduction in the magnitude of synaptic depression during 5 Hz stimulation in the mutant mice (t 8 = 2.651, P = 0.0292, n = 5 each), but no significant change at 1 Hz (n = 5 each).</s><s>Sixty pulses were delivered at 1 or 5 Hz, and the depression ratio was measured for the last 15 pulses.</s><s>Sample traces are averages of 15 consecutive EPSPs during baseline and 5 Hz stimulation.</s><s>Scale bar: 10 ms, 0.4 mV. e Reduced short-term potentiation after high-frequency tetanic stimulation in the mutant mice (repeated measure two-way ANOVA: genotype × time interaction, F 7,63 = 11.69,</s><s>P &lt; 0.0001; Sidak's test: **P = 0.0051; +/+: n = 5, −/− n = 6).</s><s>Tetanic stimulation (100 Hz, 0.5 s repeated three times) was delivered at time 0. EPSP slopes were averaged at 5 min bin for statistical analysis.</s><s>Sample traces are averages of 15 consecutive EPSPs during baseline, immediately after tetanus and 35 to 40 min after tetanus.</s><s>Scale bar: 10 ms, 0.5 mV</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,127.28,325.76,340.76,267.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional file</head><p><s>Additional file 1: Materials and Methods.</s><s>Supplementary Discussion.</s><s>(DOCX 24 kb) Abbreviations AMPA: α-Amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazolepropionic acid; EPSP: Excitatory postsynaptic potential; GC: Granule cell; HFS: High-frequency stimulation; HIVEP2: Human immunodeficiency virus type I enhancer binding protein 2; LTP: Long-term potentiation; MPP: Medial perforant path; NMDA: N-methyl-D-aspartate; Shn2: Schnurri-2; STP: Short-term potentiation Funding This work was supported by JSPS KAKENHI Grant Number 17H05964 (to K.K.).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Availability of data and materials</head><p><s>The datasets used and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</s></p><p><s>Authors' contributions KK, HS, and TM conceived the study.</s><s>KK performed experiments, analyzed the data, and wrote the manuscript.</s><s>TT and SI provided Shn2 knockout mice.</s><s>All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethics approval</head><p><s>All procedures were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Nippon Medical School.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Consent for publication</head><p><s>Not applicable.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Competing interests</head><p><s>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Publisher's Note</head><p><s>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Targeting the hippocampal mossy fiber synapse for the treatment of psychiatric disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kobayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Neurobiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hippocampal neurogenesis as a target for the treatment of mental illness: a critical evaluation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Decarolis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Eisch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuropharmacology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="884" to="893" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alpha-CaMKII deficiency causes immature dentate gyrus, a novel candidate endophenotype of psychiatric disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Yamasaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maekawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kobayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Maeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Soma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Brain</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deficiency of Schnurri-2, an MHC enhancer binding protein, induces mild chronic inflammation in the brain and confers molecular, neuronal, and behavioral phenotypes related to schizophrenia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Takao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kobayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hagihara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ohira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Shoji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hattori</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuropsychopharmacology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1409" to="1425" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synaptosomal-associated protein 25 mutation induces immaturity of the dentate granule cells of adult mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ohira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kobayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Toyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Nakamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Shoji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Takao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Brain</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The immature dentate gyrus represents a shared phenotype of mouse models of epilepsy and psychiatric disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kobayashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hagihara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kogan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Miyake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tajinda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bipolar Disord</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="405" to="421" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immature morphological properties in subcellular-scale structures in the dentate gyrus of Schnurri-2 knockout mice: a model for schizophrenia and intellectual disability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nakao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Miyazaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ohira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hagihara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Takagi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Usuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Brain</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">60</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lossof-function variants in HIVEP2 are a cause of intellectual disability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Srivastava</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Engels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Schanze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Cremer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wieland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Menzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Hum Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="556" to="561" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dendritic spine pathology in neuropsychiatric disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Penzes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cahill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-E</forename><surname>Vanleeuwen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Woolfrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="293" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanisms underlying induction of long-term potentiation in rat medial and lateral perforant paths in vitro</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Colino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Malenka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurophysiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1150" to="1159" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CKAMP44: a brain-specific protein attenuating short-term synaptic plasticity in the dentate gyrus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Von Engelhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Mack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sprengel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kavenstock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Stern-Bach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">327</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1518" to="1522" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Postsynaptic conversion of silent synapses during LTP affects synaptic gain and transmission dynamics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Poncer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Malinow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="989" to="996" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Postsynaptic factors control the duration of synaptic enhancement in area CA1 of the hippocampus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Malenka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="53" to="60" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hippocampal LTP and contextual learning require surface diffusion of AMPA receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Penn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Georges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Royer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Breillat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hosy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">549</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="384" to="388" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A mutation in mouse Disc1 that models a schizophrenia risk allele leads to specific alterations in neuronal architecture and cognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kvajo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Mckellar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Arguello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Drew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Moore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Macdermott</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7076" to="7081" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
