<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Short Lives with Long-Lasting Effects: Filopodia Protrusions in Neuronal Branching Morphogenesis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-09-03">September 3, 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">George</forename><surname>Leondaritis</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Pharmacology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Medical School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Ioannina</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ioannina</settlement>
									<country key="GR">Greece</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Britta</forename><forename type="middle">Johanna</forename><surname>Eickholt</surname></persName>
							<email>britta.eickholt@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biochemistry &amp; Neuro Cure Cluster of Excellence</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Short Lives with Long-Lasting Effects: Filopodia Protrusions in Neuronal Branching Morphogenesis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-09-03">September 3, 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">C1FAED4AB10A415F480AB75001020CF6</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pbio.1002241</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Arp2/3, Actin-related proteins 2/3</term>
					<term>BAR, Bin-Amphiphysin-Rvs</term>
					<term>CaM, Calmodulin</term>
					<term>Cobl, Cordon-Bleu WH2 repeat protein</term>
					<term>mDia1-3, Mammalian Diaphanous-related 1-3</term>
					<term>NMDA, N-Methyl-D-aspartate</term>
					<term>N-WASP, Neural Wiskott-Aldrich Syndrome Protein</term>
					<term>PIP2, Phosphatidylinositol-4,5bisphosphate</term>
					<term>PIP3, Phosphatidylinositol-3,4,5trisphosphate</term>
					<term>WAVE-1, WASP-family Verprolinhomologous protein</term>
					<term>WH2, WASP Homology 2</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>The branching behaviors of both dendrites and axons are part of a neuronal maturation process initiated by the generation of small and transient membrane protrusions.</s><s>These are highly dynamic, actin-enriched structures, collectively called filopodia, which can mature in neurons to form stable branches.</s><s>Consequently, the generation of filopodia protrusions is crucial during the formation of neuronal circuits and involves the precise control of an interplay between the plasma membrane and actin dynamics.</s><s>In this issue of PLOS Biology, Hou and colleagues identify a Ca 2+ /CaM-dependent molecular machinery in dendrites that ensures proper targeting of branch formation by activation of the actin nucleator Cobl.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Thin, finger-like, dynamic membrane protrusions, filopodia, extending from the plasma membrane of cells were first described some 100 years ago and, since then, their definition is still largely based on morphological criteria.</s><s>Structurally, classical filopodia are composed of unbranched, bundled actin filaments, which are polarized towards the tip of the filopodial membrane.</s><s>As the actin filaments grow at their rapidly polymerizing barbed ends, protrusions of finger-like membrane domains occur.</s><s>Whilst filopodia of different cell types or distinct specialized cellular compartments show a remarkably similar macroscopic appearance, they may nevertheless differ substantially in their ultrastructure, molecular composition, motility and functionality <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>In the interest of simplicity, however, we would like to emphasize that we use here the term "filopodia" or "filopodia protrusions" throughout to collectively describe finger-like membrane protrusions as precursors of axon or dendrite branches, or dendritic spines.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dendritic Membrane Filopodia-like Protrusions as Precursors of Branches or Spines</head><p><s>In neurons, it has long been argued that filopodia originating from dendrite shafts are different to classical filopodia originating in the growth cones of dendrites and axons.</s><s>For example, dendritic shaft filopodia are composed of actin filaments that are not as tightly bundled as those found in classical filopodia <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s>Dendrite filopodia also contain actin filaments of mixed polarity, which suggests that they can extend at the filopodia tip as well as at the filopodia root <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s>This further implies that actin-dependent motor proteins, like myosin II, can induce contractility of these structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s>As well as long actin filament bundles, dendritic filopodia contain branched actin filaments that derive from a specific set of actin nucleators.</s><s>This characteristic specific to dendrites is thought to provide further structural plasticity to the nascent filopodium, which is essential for the transition of the filopodium into a dendritic spine or a dendrite branch <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>A wealth of studies directly links the generation of filopodia-like protrusions to dendritic branching, arborization, and spine formation during morphogenesis and establishment of synaptic contacts in the developing brain <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>.</s><s>Defects in these processes are believed to contribute to specific neurological diseases in the adult brain <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s><s>Considering the timing and control of these processes, both intrinsic and extrinsic signals are instrumental.</s><s>Extrinsic signals such as neurotrophic factors, adhesion molecules, presynaptic neurotransmitter cues, and neuronal activity are particularly important, and all contribute to this highly dynamic process <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>How Are Filopodia Protrusions</head><p><s>Filopodia formation can be seen as a sequence of three interconnected phases: (a) the phase of actin nucleation, (b) the phase of rapid elongation of an actin filament through barbed-end polymerization, and (c) the bundling of actin filaments (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>An increasing list of filopodia regulators have been identified and characterized in recent years <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>.</s><s>Among them, the actin nucleators take on specific importance during the formation of filopodia protrusions, and they do so for several reasons.</s><s>For example, actin nucleation is the first, and rate-limiting, step Actin nucleators are classified in three classes depending on their mode of action.</s><s>Class I nucleators include the first nucleator identified, the Actin-related proteins 2/3 (Arp2/3) complex, and its accessory nucleation-promoting factors such as Neural Wiskott-Aldrich Syndrome Protein (N-WASP) and WASP-family Verprolin-homologous protein (WAVE-1).</s><s>The regulation of Arp2/3 complex is intricate, but consensus has it that stimulation of the small GTPases Rac1 and Cdc42 by membrane the phosphoinositides PIP2 and PIP3 is an essential component of the Arp2/3 upstream activation machinery.</s><s>Following filopodia formation, Arp2/3 then creates branched actin filaments and functions as the major actin nucleator responsible for the formation of lamellipodia at the leading edge of migrating cells and neuronal growth cones <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14]</ref>.</s><s>Class II nucleators include formins, such as Mammalian Diaphanous-related 1-3 (mDia1-3), which can function as elongators of actin filaments frequently found at the tip of a filopodium.</s><s>Formins are recruited to the plasma membrane by interactions with acidic phospholipids and the GTPase Rif <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>.</s><s>In the case of dendrite filopodia, for example, the formin mDia2 and Rif, in combination with Cdc42 and the Arp2/3 complex, act in a concerted manner during the transition from a nascent filopodium into a spine <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>.</s><s>Class III nucleators include a set of newly identified diverse proteins such as the Cordon-Bleu WH2 repeat protein (Cobl), Spire, and Leiomodin, all of which share a common Wasp Homology 2 (WH2) domain to achieve nucleation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref>.</s><s>To date, candidate upstream regulators or signals that induce the activity of these class III nucleators are not well described.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A Novel Mechanism for Signal-Induced Formation of Actin Patches and Dendrite Branches</head><p><s>What is exciting about the contribution made by Hou et al. in PLOS Biology is that their paper delineates a novel regulatory mechanism for the formation of dendritic filopodia and dendrite arborization by class III nucleators <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>.</s><s>The authors studied the class III actin nucleator Cobl, which had previously been identified as an important mediator of dendritic branch formation <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</s><s>By using a variety of cellular and molecular approaches, the authors demonstrate that Cobl connects localized raises in Ca 2+ in dendrites to the initiation of dendritic protrusion and branches.</s><s>Live cell imaging reveals a correlation of local Ca 2+ increases, Cobl accumulation, and F-actin patches at sites of dendrite branching.</s><s>Interestingly, whilst increases in Ca 2+ either preceded or followed the formation of actin patches, the maximum of Cobl accumulation appeared prior to the formation of actin patches at sites of extending filopodia protrusions.</s><s>Cobl recruitment to the initiated protrusion required calmodulin (CaM), and live cell imaging indicated a timed correlation between local Ca 2+ increases, CaM, and Cobl recruitment to sites along the dendritic membrane with somewhat protrusive morphology.</s><s>Given that overexpression of Cobl has been shown to increase the number of dendrites and dendritic branches in hippocampal neurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, the authors went on to investigate if the activity of Ca 2+ /CaM is necessary for this phenotype.</s><s>Indeed, CaM inhibitors suppressed Cobl-induced dendritic arborization and, furthermore, they produced a rapid shutdown of filopodia dynamics and gradual loss of Cobl from putative initiation sites.</s><s>Conversely, Cobl mutants unable to bind to Ca 2+ /CaM failed to increase dendritic numbers and branches and were unable to rescue the phenotype of Cobl-silenced branching in cerebellar Purkinje neurons.</s></p><p><s>A crucial aspect of the initial phases of actin nucleation and filopodia initiation is the association of the regulators to the plasma membrane.</s><s>In some cases, reorientation of actin filaments towards membranes by actin nucleators is ensured and guided by membrane phospholipids such as PIP2 or PIP3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref>.</s><s>In some instances, localized increases in actin dynamics and the formation of actin patches have been shown to correlate with accumulations of factorinduced PIP3 in membrane microdomains <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>In a well-described model for initiation of axonal filopodia, for example, PIP3 microdomains provide a signal for recruitment of actin nucleators such as the Arp2/3 complex and its associated promoting factors and activating GTPases to the membrane.</s><s>This sequence of events then increases the probability of generating an actin patch, which may develop into a membrane filopodium upon further expansion and elongation <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21]</ref>.</s><s>Alternatively, proteins that interact specifically with membranes, such as proteins of the F-Bin-Amphiphysin-Rvs (BAR) and I-BAR subfamilies involved in sensing membrane curvature, may control both actin nucleation activity of Cobl and membrane association.</s><s>The authors probed for the effects of Ca 2+ and Ca 2+ /CaM on known interactions of Cobl with actin and the F-BAR protein syndapin.</s><s>Collectively, the results of these experiments demonstrate that local and transient raises in Ca 2+ induce a net increase of both the actin-binding and syndapin-binding properties of Cobl.</s><s>Cobl may be able to respond to transient, but not long-lasting, Ca 2+ /CaM signaling.</s><s>This correlates well with previous observations that provided a link between local Ca 2+ transients and filopodia outgrowth, whilst high levels of Ca 2+ inhibited the formation of filopodia <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>The work by Hou et al. establishes Cobl΄s role as a Ca 2+ sensor that can induce the initiation of filopodia-like protrusions on dendrites in a Ca 2+ /CaM-dependent manner.</s><s>The question then arises what the source or the initial signal for this Ca 2+ increase in the brain may be.</s><s>Many studies have suggested that spontaneous release of neurotrasmitters from axons occurs before the establishment of functional presynaptic terminals in developing neurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s>Spontaneous glutamate release from growing axons exerts a specific role prior to synapse formation to control dendritic arbor formation by signaling via "long-range" activation of N-Methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptors on dendrites <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[23]</ref>.</s><s>The activation of NMDA receptors could therefore conceivably provide one of the initial local Ca 2+ raises to induce Cobl-mediated actin nucleation and filopodia initiation coupled to extensive branching on dendrites.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig 1. Filopodia formation in five steps.</s><s>1.</s><s>Under resting conditions, actin nucleators (blue and green crosses), filament bundling and crosslinking proteins (grey crosses), and membrane curvature-sensing proteins (purple and orange curved lines) reside in the cytosol and preserve a base-line level of filamentous (F-) actin (red lines).</s><s>Black dots denote plasma membrane microdomains rich in specific lipids and transmembrane proteins.</s><s>2. Upon signaling (e.g., increases in Ca 2+ in the cytosol or activation of growth factor induced Phosphatidylinositol-4,5-bisphosphate (PIP2)-Phosphatidylinositol-3,4,5-trisphosphate (PIP3) turnover), nucleators are activated and, together with elongation factors, promote rapid actin polymerization and actin patch formation.</s><s>3. Filaments extend rapidly towards the membrane, and changes in membrane curvature are sensed and/or induced by curvature-sensing proteins.</s><s>4. A growing filopodium has established a mixture of unbundled and bundled or crosslinked actin filaments.</s><s>It is conceivable that different sets of nucleators and elongators may contribute to increased actin polymerization.</s><s>Other proteins that uncap or cap barbed ends or proteins that sever filaments at the root of filopodia may regulate filament turnover during this process.</s><s>5.</s><s>In a "mature" filopodium, additional signals may guide microtubule invasion in order to stabilize the nascent filopodium into a branch.</s><s>doi:10.1371/journal.pbio.1002241.g001</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,36.00,359.21,413.24,238.51" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">PLOS Biology | DOI:10.1371/journal.pbio.1002241 September 3, 2015</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Activity-regulated dynamic behavior of early dendritic protrusions: evidence for different types of dendritic filopodia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Portera-Cailliau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yuste</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">12904473</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7129" to="7142" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular architecture of synaptic actin cytoskeleton in hippocampal neurons reveals a mechanism of dendritic spine morphogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Korobova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Svitkina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1091/mbc.E09-07-0596</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">19889835</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Biol Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="165" to="176" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Actin in dendritic spines: connecting dynamics to function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hotulainen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hoogenraad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1083/jcb.201003008</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">20457765</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">189</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="619" to="629" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanisms underlying the initiation and dynamics of neuronal filopodia: from neurite formation to synaptogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gallo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/B978-0-12-407704-1.00003-8</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">23317818</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int Rev Cell Mol Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">301</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="156" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defining mechanisms of actin polymerization and depolymerization during dendritic spine morphogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Hotulainen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Llano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Smirnov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tanhuanpää</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Faix</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rivera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1083/jcb.200809046</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">19380880</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">185</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="323" to="339" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Twigs into branches: how a filopodium becomes a dendrite</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Heiman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shaham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.conb.2009.10.016</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">19939665</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Neurobiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="91" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The dendritic tree and brain disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kulkarni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Firestein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.mcn.2012.03.005</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22465229</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Cell Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vivo imaging of synapse formation on a growing dendritic arbor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Niell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">14758365</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="254" to="260" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intrinsic and extrinsic mechanisms of dendritic morphogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bülow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1146/annurev-physiol-021014-071746</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">25386991</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu Rev Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of neuronal and transmitter release on synapse formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Andreae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Burrone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.conb.2014.02.008</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">24632375</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Neurobiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New players in actin polymerization-WH2-domain-containing actin nucleators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Qualmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.tcb.2009.03.004</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">19406642</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="276" to="285" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">mDia1-3 in mammalian filopodia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Goh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ahmed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4161/cib.20214</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">23060957</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Commun Integr Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="340" to="344" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Actin nucleation and elongation factors: mechanisms and interplay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Chesarone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Goode</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="37" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A nucleator arms race: cellular control of actin assembly</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kg1</forename><surname>Campellone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Welch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nrm2867</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">20237478</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="251" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanisms of plasma membrane targeting of formin mDia2 through its amino terminal domains</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gorelik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kameswaran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dominguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Svitkina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1091/mbc.E10-03-0256</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">21119010</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Biol Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="201" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cordon-bleu is an actin nucleation factor and controls neuronal morphology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ahuja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pinyol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Reichenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Custer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Klingensmith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">17956734</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="350" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The actin nucleator Cobl is controlled by calcium and calmodulin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Izadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nemitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Haag</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Qualmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pbio.1002233</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1002233</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Self-assembly of filopodia-like structures on supported lipid bilayers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Gallop</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Rambani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kirschner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/science.1191710</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">20829485</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">329</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1341" to="1345" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of phosphoinositide-regulated actin reorganization in chemotaxis and cell migration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/bph.12777</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">25420930</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">171</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5541" to="5554" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nerve growth factor induces axonal filopodia through localized microdomains of phosphoinositide 3-kinase activity that drive the formation of cytoskeletal precursors to filopodia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ketschek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gallo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1740-10.2010</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">20826681</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12185" to="12197" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The actin nucleating Arp2/3 complex contributes to the formation of axonal filopodia and branches through the regulation of actin patch precursors to filopodia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Spillane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ketschek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Korobova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Marsick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lanier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/dneu.20907</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">21557512</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev Neurobiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="747" to="758" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Local calcium transients regulate the spontaneous motility of dendritic filopodia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lohmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Finski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bonhoeffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">15711541</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="312" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spontaneous Neurotransmitter Release Shapes Dendritic Arbors via Long-Range Activation of NMDA Receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Andreae</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Burrone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="873" to="882" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
