<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Biological characterization and pluripotent identification of ovine amniotic fluid stem cells</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-03-03">3 March 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wenhua</forename><forename type="middle">Pei</forename><surname>Tengfei</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lu</forename><surname>Kunfu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wang</forename><surname>Meng</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ji</forename><surname>Shuang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zhang</forename><surname>Fenghao</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Li</forename><surname>Xiangchen</surname></persName>
							<email>lixiangchen@caas.cn</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Li</forename><forename type="middle">Weijun</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wenhua</forename><surname>Pei</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tengfei</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Á</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Á</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ji</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Á</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Á</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Animal Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Yuanmingyuan West road, haidian district</addrLine>
									<postCode>100193</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">College of Wildlife Resources</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Northeast Forestry University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150040</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Research Center for Sports Scientific Experiment</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Sport University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country>People&apos;s Republic of China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">College of Human Movement Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Harbin Sport University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>150040</postCode>
									<settlement>Harbin</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">College of Animal Science and Technology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Agricultural University of Hebei</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>071000</postCode>
									<settlement>Baoding</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Biological characterization and pluripotent identification of ovine amniotic fluid stem cells</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-03-03">3 March 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">400A0A0D0246782848125E86D4935F56</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s10616-017-0115-2</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 11 December 2016 / Accepted: 21 March 2017 /</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Ovine</term>
					<term>Amniotic fluid</term>
					<term>Stem cell</term>
					<term>Differentiation</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Mesenchymal stem cells derived from amniotic fluid have become one of the most potential stem cell source for cell-based therapy for the reason they can be harvested at low cost and without ethical problems.</s><s>Here, we obtained amniotic fluid stem cells (AFSCs) from ovine amniotic fluid and studied the expansion capacity, cell markers expression, karyotype, and multilineage differentiation ability.</s><s>In our work, AFSCs were subcultured to passage 62.</s><s>The cell markers, CD29, CD44, CD73 and OCT4 which analyzed by RT-PCR were positive; CD44, CD73, CD90, CD105, NANOG, OCT4 analyzed by immunofluorescence and flow cytometry were also positive.</s><s>The growth curves of different passages were all typically sigmoidal.</s><s>The different passages cells took on a normal karyotype.</s><s>In addition, AFSCs were successfully induced to differentiate into adipocytes, osteoblasts and chondrocytes.</s><s>The results suggested that the AFSCs isolated from ovine maintained normal biological characteristics and their multilineage differentiation potential provides many potential applications in cell-based therapies and tissue engineering.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) originate from mesoderm and ectoderm in the early development of embryo.</s><s>They widely exist in the matrix of various tissues and organs <ref type="bibr">(Bobis et al. 2006)</ref>.</s><s>For the reason that MSCs have a good ability of self-renewal and multiple differentiation potential, they became one of the most promising cell populations for tissue engineering and regenerative medicine <ref type="bibr">(Parekkadan and Milwid 2010)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Amniotic fluid (AF) is a kind of mixed liquid, providing nutrition for the fetus, promoting the growth of the fetus and providing buffer and protection for the fetus <ref type="bibr">(In 'tAnker et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">Antonucci et al. 2011)</ref>.</s><s>A number of studies have proven that stem cells exist in the AF and these cells have the same abilities as MSCs <ref type="bibr">(In 'tAnker et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">Antonucci et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kaviani et al. 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr">Da Sacco et al. 2011)</ref>.</s><s>Researchers began to study AFSCs in the early twenty first century and discovered that these cells possess the ability to extend in vitro <ref type="bibr">(Peister et al. 2009)</ref>.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Priest et al. (1984)</ref> found multiple types of cells in the AF.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Subsequently, Prusa et al. (2003)</ref> discovered that amniotic fluid contained ample stem cells.</s><s>Amniotic fluid derived cells were named AFSCs by De <ref type="bibr">Coppi et al. (2007)</ref> and these cells have properties similar to ES cells.</s><s>AFSCs were first reported to have the ability of forming embryoid bodies like ES cells and primordial germ cells (PGCs) <ref type="bibr">(Galende et al. 2010)</ref>.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Kim et al. (2014)</ref> made use of AFSCs for treatment of neuronal degenerative diseases.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Wang et al. (2016)</ref> used AFSCs to protect the heart against the ischemiareperfusion.</s><s>Recently, AFSCs has become a hotspot in the research of stem cells <ref type="bibr">(Prusa et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">De Coppi et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tsai et al. 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Joo et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Gao et al. 2014)</ref>.</s><s>AFSCs have been used as seed cells to treat skin wounds, bone defects and breast cancer and so on <ref type="bibr">(Ghafarzadeh et al. 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Rota et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Da Sacco et al. 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Skardal et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zavatti et al. 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr">Young et al. 2016)</ref>, mainly due to the following reasons: Compared with other stem cells, AFSCs will not cause injury to the donor <ref type="bibr">(Antonucci et al. 2011)</ref>.</s><s>It is easy to obtain AFSCs.</s><s>Furthermore, AFSCs are widely multipotent, express some embryonic stem (ES) cells markers, such as OCT4 and SSEA4 <ref type="bibr">(Tsai et al. 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kim et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Pappa and Anagnou 2009)</ref>.</s><s>Compared with ES cells, the cultivation of AFSCs does not need feeder layer and the ethical problems are avoided <ref type="bibr">(Delo et al. 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">De Coppi et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Roubelakis et al. 2007)</ref>.</s><s>It is a good choice to substitute AFSCs for ES cells.</s><s>In addition, AFSCs also possess many other properties, such as low immunogenicity <ref type="bibr">(Di Trapani et al. 2015)</ref>, easy accessibility and inability of form tumors <ref type="bibr">(De Coppi et al. 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tsai et al. 2004</ref>).</s><s>These are the reasons why these cells are considered a candidate for regenerative medicine and tumor targeted therapy.</s></p><p><s>The ovine is a kind of main livestock and has biological characteristics similar to human.</s><s>Besides, the ovine is easy to obtain and raise.</s><s>Moreover, the use of the ovine as experimental animal costs a minimum price.</s><s>That's the reason why it widely be used in the clinical evaluation and the development of biotechnology.</s><s>The purpose of this work was to investigate the isolation and culture process of AFSCs in vitro.</s><s>And exploring the biological characteristics in terms of morphology, growth kinetics, karyotype, cell markers and differentiation potential.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials and Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental materials</head><p><s>4-week-old ovine embryo was provided by the livestock and poultry Experimental Base Institute of Animal Sciences (Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing).</s><s>All animal procedures were in accordance with the guidelines established by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at the Chinese Academy of Agriculture Sciences.</s><s>Statistical analysis: The statistical software SAS was used for ANOVA variance analysis and variance homogeneity test based on the experimental data.</s><s>P \ 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</s></p><p><s>Isolation and culture of AFSCs 10 mL amniotic fluid samples were extracted with sterile syringes.</s><s>The sample appeared clear and transparency.</s><s>If the sample mixed with other impurity in the process of extraction, it will present a faint yellow.</s><s>The AFSCs isolated from this sample took unnormal karyotype.</s><s>Then the samples were centrifuged at 5009g for 30 min.</s><s>The supernatant was discarded and 0.5 mL amniotic fluid at the bottom of the centrifugation tube was retained.</s><s>The cells were plated in 6 well plates with DF/12 (Gibco Scotland), 10% (v/v) fetal bovine serum (FBS) (Gibco Australia), 10 ng/ml basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF) (Pe-proTech USA) and 1% (v/v) GlutaMAX (Gibco New York, USA).</s><s>Subsequently the cells were incubated at 37 °C, 5% CO 2 .</s><s>About 7 days later, the cell population reached 80% confluence, 0.25% (w/v) trypsin were added to trypsinized cells.</s><s>The cells were passaged according to the proportion of 1:2.</s><s>The medium was refreshed every 2 days.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Kinetics</head><p><s>In order to establish growth characteristics, the ovine AFSCs from passages 5, 20 and 40 were harvested by 0.25% (w/v) trypsin and resuspended in DF/12, 10% (v/v) fetal bovine serum (FBS), 10 ng/ml basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF) and 1% (v/v) Glu-taMAX.</s><s>Then the cells were plated into a 24-well plate with a density of 10 4 /mL, respectively, and three random wells were counted each day for 8 days.</s><s>The population doubling time was calculated according to the following formula: PDT = (t -t0) lg2/ (lgNt -lgN0), t0: starting time of culture; t: termination time of culture; N0: initial cell number of culture; Nt: ultimate cell number of culture.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Karyotype analysis</head><p><s>Standard protocols were used to investigate the chromosomal profiles of the cells.</s><s>The passage 5 ovine AFSCs were incubated in 0.4 lg/mL colcemid (Baomanbio shanghai, China) for 4 h at 37.5 °C, then the cells were dispersed by 0.25% trypsin.</s><s>Next, the harvested cells were centrifuged at 2009g for 8 min.</s><s>The pellet was re-suspended in 0.075 M KCL solution and incubated at 37 °C for 30 min.</s><s>Finally, the cells were fixed in methanol/glacial acetic acid (3:1) and dropped on the prechilled glass slides, stained with Giemsa stain (Baomanbio shanghai, China).</s><s>The chromosome numbers were observed under an oil immersion objective.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Immunofluorescent detection of cell markers</head><p><s>When AFSCs reached 60-80% confluence, it could be used for immunofluorescent detection.</s><s>Firstly, the cells were washed with PBS and fixed with 4% paraphormaldehyde (PFA) (Sigma) for 15 min.</s><s>Then the cells were permeabilized with 0.25% Triton X-100 for 10 min in order to exclude false positive staining and were washed three times with PBS.</s><s>Next, The cells were blocked with blocking solution (1% BSA (Biovision USA) in PBS) for 30 min and incubated overnight with primary antibodies at 4 °C.</s><s>The antibody details are as follows: rabbit anti-CD44 (BIOSS ANTIBODIES, Beijing, China), rabbit anti-CD73 (BIOSS ANTIBODIES), rabbit anti-CD90 (BIOSS ANTIBODIES), and rabbit anti-CD105 (BIOSS ANTI-BODIES), rabbit anti-NANOG (BIOSS ANTIBO-DIES), rabbit anti-OCT4 (BIOSS ANTIBODIES).</s><s>All of the antibody were diluted with PBS according to the proportion of 1:100.</s><s>The next day, cells were incubated with FITC-conjugated goat anti-rabbit (BIOSS ANTI-BODIES) for 1 h in dark place.</s><s>Finally, the cells were counterstained with 4 0 ,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI) (Beyotime beijing, China).</s><s>Nikon TE-2000-E confocal microscope (Nikon, Tokyo, Japan) was used to take photomicrographs.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RT-PCR assay</head><p><s>Passage 5, passage 20 and passage 40 cells were chosen as the low, middle and high passages for RT-PCR analysis.</s><s>The total RNA was extracted with Trizol reagent from 1 9 10 6 cells.</s><s>The Trizol extract was transferred to 1.5 mL EP tube and mixed with 200 lL chloroform.</s><s>Then the compound was centrifuged at 12,0009g for 15 min.</s><s>After centrifugation, the supernatant was mixed with isopropanol and centrifuged at 12,0009g for another 10 min.</s><s>Next, the RNA pellet was washed with 70% DEPC-ethanol and dried at room temperature.</s><s>Finally, the RNA concentration was measured by spectrophotometer.</s><s>The extracted RNA was reverse transcribed to cDNA using an RNA PCR kit version 3.0 (Takara, Shiga, Japan).</s><s>PCR reaction was conducted by the PCR master Mix Kit (Takara) in a 20 lL mixture that contains 1 lL template cDNA, 0.5 lL each of forward and reverse primers, 8 lL ddH 2 O and 10 lL 2 9 PCR Mix.</s><s>The primers which were designed by NCBI primer-blast are listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s><s>A thermal cycler was programmed for 35 cycles as follows: 1 cycle at 94 °C for 5 min; 35 cycles including denaturation step at 94 °C for 30 s, annealing step at 50-60 °C for 30 s and elongation step at 72 °C for 30 s; finally 1 cycle at 72 °C for 8 min.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Flow cytometry</head><p><s>According to previously reports, the International Society for Cytotherapy declared that human MSCs must be CD73, CD90 and CD105 positive and CD14, CD34 and CD45 negative <ref type="bibr">(Alsalameh et al. 2004</ref>).</s><s>Flow cytometry analysis was performed to detect the markers of AFSCs including CD44, CD73, CD90, CD105, NANOG and OCT4.</s><s>The cells were harvested by treatment with 0.25% (w/v) trypsin and collected in the FACS tubes at a density of 1 9 10 6 cells per tube.</s><s>Then the cells were centrifuged at 2009g for 8 min and the pellet was fixed by 70% ethanol at 4 °C overnight.</s><s>Next, the cells were blocked by 1% BSA after another centrifugation at 2009g for 8 min.</s><s>The cells were incubated with primary antibodies at 4 °C overnight.</s><s>The antibodies are as follows: rabbit anti-CD44 (BIOSS ANTIBODIES), rabbit anti-CD73 (BIOSS ANTIBODIES), rabbit anti-CD90 (BIOSS ANTIBODIES), and rabbit anti-CD105 (BIOSS ANTIBODIES), rabbit anti-NANOG (BIOSS ANTI-BODIES), and rabbit anti-OCT4 (BIOSS ANTIBO-DIES).</s><s>All antibodies were diluted with PBS according to the proportion of 1:100.</s><s>Finally, the cells were washed twice in PBS and subjected to single channel fluorescently activated cell sorting (FACS) analysis.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>In vitro differentiation of AFSCs</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adipocytic differentiation</head><p><s>In order to verify the ability to differentiate into adipocytes, passage 5 AFSCs were cultured in DMEM/F12, 10% FBS, 0.5 mM dexamethasone, 200 lM indomethacin, 0.5 mM IBMX, and 10 lM insulin <ref type="bibr">(Alsalameh et al. 2004</ref>).</s><s>To test adipogentic differentiation, Oil Red O staining was peformed.</s><s>Briefly, the cells were washed with PBS for three times and fixed with 4% PFA for 15 min.</s><s>Then the cells were incubated with Oil Red O for 30 min at room temperature.</s><s>After that, the cells were rinsed with distilled water.</s><s>The lipid droplets were observed under an inverted microscope.</s><s>RT-PCR was used to identify adipocyte specific markers such as proliferator-activated receptor c (PPAR-c) and lipoprotein lipase (LPL).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Osteogenic differentiation</head><p><s>The ability of AFSCs to differentiate into osteoblasts was demonstrated by using alizarin red staining and RT-PCR assay.</s><s>Firstly, the culture medium was replaced with induction medium that consisted of DMEM/F12, 10%FBS, 10 mM b-glycerophosphate, 1 lM dexamethasone, and 0.1 mM L-ascorbic-acid-2-phosphate and the medium was changed every 3 days for 21 days.</s><s>Then, the cells were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) and stained with Alizarin Red.</s><s>Finally, the calcium nodules were observed by an</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">F:5 0 -GGCAGGCCGAGAAGGATATTA-3 0 R: 5 0 -GGCTCCCCTGATCGTAACTG-3 0 61 CD44 F: 5 0 -GACCATGGGGCAAACACAAC-3 0 R: 5 0 -TCCGCTAGGCTTTCTCTCCT-3 0 60 CD73 F: 5 0 -AAGGGGCCTCTAGCGTCTAA-3 0 R: 5 0 -AAAGCATAGGCCTGGACCAC-3 0 60 OCT4 F: 5 0 -CCGCCCTATGACTTGTGTGG-3 0 R: 5 0 -CGGTTCTCGATACTCGTCCG-3 0 62 GAPDH F: 5 0 -GTCAAGGCAGAGAACGGGAA-3 0 R: 5 0 -GGTTCACGCCCATCACAAAC-3 0 60 ATF4 F: 5 0 -AGGAGGATGCCCACTCAGAT-3 0 R: 5 0 -GGCCAAGGAATCTGCCTTCT-3 0 60 OPN F: 5 0 -GAGTTGCCACTGCAAACCTG-3 0 R: 5 0 -CTGATCGCCATGCTGCTTTC-3 0 60 LPL F: 5 0 -CAGGACTCCCGAAGACACAG-3 0 R: 5 0 -CCACGATGACGTTGGAGTCT-3 0 60 PPAR-c F: 5 0 -AAAATACGGCGTGCACGAGA-3 0 R: 5 0 -GAGGACTCGGGGTGGTTCAG-3 0 60 ACAN F: 5 0 -AGAGGCGCGTCTAGAAATCG-3 0 59</formula><p><s>inverted microscope and the specific genes were analyzed by RT-PCR assay.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chondrogenesis differentiation</head><p><s>The passage 5 AFSCs were induced to differentiate into chondrocytes.</s><s>After the cells have achieved confluency of 80%, the culture medium was replaced with induction medium that contains 10% FBS, 10 ng/mL transforming growth factor-beta 3 (TGF-b3) and 5 ng/mL bFGF.</s><s>The cells were cultured under the conditions of 38.5 °C and 5% CO 2 while the medium was refreshed every 3 days.</s><s>About 3 weeks later, Alcian blue staining was conducted to detect whether chondrocytes were present.</s><s>RT-PCR was used to analyze the expression of specific genes.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Isolation, culture, and morphology of AFSCs</head><p><s>We successfully isolated AFSCs from a 4 weeks old embryo and subcultured them to passage 62.</s><s>In primary culture, a few cells were observed in the first three days.</s><s>About 7 days later, cells spread to more than 80% of 6 well plate.</s><s>The cell layers were digested by 0.25% trypsin and 0.02% EDTA and the cells were distributed to 60 mm Petri dishes.</s><s>After passage 3, the AFSCs took on a typical long spindle shape which resembled bone marrow mesenchymal stem cells.</s><s>After passage 58, cells began to change, cell body increased, cell edge turned burr shaped and they detached from Petri dishes eventually (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Growth kinetics</head><p><s>The growth curves of AFSCs from P5, P20 and P40 are displayed in Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>. They took on a typical ''S'' shape.</s><s>AFSCs entered into logarithmic phase after 3 days, followed by plateau phase after 6 days, and the decline phase took place about 7 days later.</s><s>The population doubling time (PDT) was calculated with the following PDT formula: PDT = (t -t0) lg2/(lgNt -lgN0).</s></p><p><s>The PDT was 33.9, 37.7 and 41.4 h, respectively, for passage 5, passage 20 and passage 40.</s><s>As the passage numbers increased, the ability of proliferation declined for the cells.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Karyotype analysis</head><p><s>The chromosome number of ovine is 2n = 54, including 26 pairs of euchromosomes and one pair of sex chromosomes, XX.</s><s>Normal chromosome number and morphology showed that the cells had normal function.</s><s>The chromosome numbers per spread were counted for 100 spreads of the passage 5, passage 30, and passage 60, and the ratio of cells with 2n = 54 was 96.3, 95.1, and 92.7%, respectively.</s><s>Chromosomal karyotype of ovine AFSCs is shown in Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Detection of AFSCs markers</head><p><s>Cell antigen markers of AFSCs were detected by immunofluorescence and RT-PCR.</s><s>Experimental immunofluorescence results showed that AFSCs were positive for CD44, CD73, CD90, CD105, NANOG and OCT4 (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>).</s><s>The result of RT-PCR demonstrated that AFSCs were positive for CD29, CD44, CD73 and OCT4 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">5</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>FACS analysis</head><p><s>Fluorescent activated cell sorting (FACS) was used for analyzing AFSCs for a series of putative cell antigen markers.</s><s>Analyses of AFSCs for CD44 (b), CD73 (c), CD90 (d), CD105 (e), NANOG (f) and OCT4 (g) showed that positive rate over 99% of the viable cell population (Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Differentiation of AFSCs</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adipogenic differentiation of the AFSCs</head><p><s>When AFSCs were cultured in adipogenic induction medium, the morphology of cells changed slowly from fibroblast-like to oblate and the cytoplasm contained many tiny lipid droplets after 7 days.</s><s>With the induction time increasing, the tiny lipid droplets aggregated to larger ones.</s><s>Adipogenic differentiation of AFSCs was detected by oil red O staining and RT-PCR assay.</s><s>The differentiated cells were stained with red while the undifferentiated cells were non-stained (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">7</ref>).</s><s>The RT-PCR results showed that differentiated cells expressed adipocyte-specific genes peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma (PPARc) and lipoprotein lipase (LPL) (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">7e</ref>).</s><s>By comparing the AFSCs with bovine CSPCs, the lipid droplets from CSPCs (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">7b, d</ref>) are present at higher numbers and have a larger size.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Osteogenic differentiation of AFSCs</head><p><s>After incubating in osteogenic medium for 3 weeks, morphology of AFSCs changed and calcium nodules were visible.</s><s>With the increasing induction time, the nodules increased in size and number.</s><s>The nodules were positive for the alizarin red staining (Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>).</s><s>RT-PCR assay was used for analyzing the osteogenic differentiation of the AFSCs (Fig. <ref type="figure">8e</ref>).</s><s>The results showed that differentiated cells expressed osteoblast specific genes osteopontin (OPN) and Activating transcription factor 4 (ATF4).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chondrogenesis differentiation of AFSCs</head><p><s>AFSCs showed obvious morphological changes after culture in chondrogenic medium for 14 days.</s><s>After 20 days, the colonies increased in number and size.</s><s>Then they were stained with Alcian blue (Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref>).</s><s>RT-PCR assay was used for analyzing the chondrogenic differentiation of AFSCs (Fig. <ref type="figure">9</ref>).</s><s>The results showed that cartilage-specific genes ACAN and VIM were expressed in the differentiated cells.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Amniotic fluid contains at least three types of cells, amniotic fluid specific (AF-type) cells, epitheloid (Etype) cells and fibroblastic (F-type) cells <ref type="bibr">(Miki and Strom 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr">Antonucci et al. 2012)</ref>.</s><s>The E-type cells and AF-type cells can form colonies.</s><s>As the passages increased, E-type gradually disappeared and AF-type became dominant.</s><s>Thus, we isolated AF-type cells from amniotic fluid and identified the biological characteristics.</s><s>The AFSCs were differentiate into adipocytes, osteoblasts and chondrocytes in vitro.</s><s>They were positive for the cell markers CD44, CD73, CD90, CD105, NANOG and OCT4 analyzed by immunofluorescence and flow cytometry.</s><s>In addition, karyotype analysis and cell growth curve have proven that AFSCs possessed the ability of self-renewal and normal function.</s><s>The results demonstrated that the biological characteristics of AFSCs were stable.</s></p><p><s>To date, AFSCs become a suitable candidate for regenerative medicine compared with other stem cells <ref type="bibr">(Bollini et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Kang et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Cananzi et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Rennie et al. 2012)</ref>.</s><s>Firstly, the isolation of amniotic fluid stem cells will not cause much damage to the donor <ref type="bibr">(Antonucci et al. 2011</ref>).</s><s>The AFSCs were harvested from amniotic fluid which otherwise will be  Attributed by the ability of self-renewal, multiple differentiation and low immunogenicity, AFSCs have been used in regenerative medicine and cell-based therapy <ref type="bibr">(Wang et al. 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ghafarzadeh et al. 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr">Skardal et al. 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Zavatti et al. 2015)</ref>.</s><s>However, there are still many problems to be solved.</s><s>We have not a clear understanding about AFSCs how to realize the function.</s><s>For example, AFSCs how to grow under the condition of lacking of feeder layer; What is the regulatory mechanism of AFSCs; How to solve the immune rejection in clinical treatment.</s><s>If the above problems can be solved, AFSCs could be play an</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>In conclusion, AFSCs were isolated from amniotic fluid of a 4-week-old embryo.</s><s>We also evaluated the multipotency of AFSCs that they could be induced to differentiate into adipocytes, osteoblasts and chondrocytes.</s><s>These results not only provide a technological platform for the establishment of an ovine AFSCs line, but also provide new and abundant seeding cells for cell-based therapy and regenerative medicine.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1 Morphology of different passages of AFSCs.</s><s>a Ovine cells began to adhere to the Petri dishes after 3 days of cultivation and had a variety of forms.</s><s>b AF-type cells got clustered and there still existed other types of cells.</s><s>c Primary cultured AFSCs covered the Petri dishes.</s><s>d-k AFSCs at P5, P15,</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,49.65,59.25,447.84,292.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 3 Fig. 4</head><label>34</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 3 Karyotype of ovine AFSCs ($) XX type.</s><s>The diploid chromosome number of ovine AFSCs was 2n = 54, consisting of 26 pairs of euchromosomes and one pair of sex chromosomes type XX ($)</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,49.65,59.24,447.84,239.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 5 Detection of AFSCs markers by RT-PCR.</s><s>The RT-PCR assay also demonstrated that AFSCs were positive both for the mesenchymal stem cell markers and ES cells markers.</s><s>Lane1 Marker 600 bp.</s><s>Lane 2 CD29; Lane 3 CD44; lane 4 CD73; lane 5 OCT4; lane 6 GAPDH</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,165.92,59.25,334.56,126.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 7 Adipogenic differentiation of ovine AFSCs and bovine cartilage-derived stem/ progenitor cells (CSPCs).</s><s>a, c stand for AFSCs while b, d stand for CSPCs.</s><s>a, b The lipid droplets formed after 3 weeks of culture in induction medium.</s><s>c, d Oil red O was used to detect the adipocyte.</s><s>After 21 days induced, AFSCs induced into adipocyte and turn into red after reaction with oil red O. e RT-PCR detection of the adipogenic markers LPL and PPAR-c expression.</s><s>Scale bar = 100 lm</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,165.92,59.25,334.56,331.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="11,166.20,59.25,334.32,334.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="11,165.92,413.96,334.56,203.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Primer sequences used in RT-PCR assay</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Gene name</cell><cell>Primer sequences</cell><cell>Product length (bp)</cell><cell>Tm (°C)</cell></row><row><cell>CD29</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Acknowledgements This research was supported by the Project supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant Nos.</s><s>31472099, 31672404).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Compliance with ethical standards</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p><s>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>References</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
