<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Enhancing Bioethanol Productivity Using Alkali-Pretreated Empty Palm Fruit Bunch Fiber Hydrolysate</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-09-05">5 September 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Seonghun</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
							<email>seonghun@kribb.re.kr</email>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0001-7567-8244</idno>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Bioscience and Biotechnology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jeonbuk Branch Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>181 Ipsin-gil</addrLine>
									<postCode>56212</postCode>
									<settlement>Jeongeup</settlement>
									<country>Korea Research, Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Enhancing Bioethanol Productivity Using Alkali-Pretreated Empty Palm Fruit Bunch Fiber Hydrolysate</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-09-05">5 September 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">68C3EB1408DA9140D473C4AD5F499564</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1155/2018/5272935</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 30 April 2018; Revised 25 July 2018; Accepted 26 August 2018;</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:34+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Empty palm fruit bunch fiber (EPFBF) is a renewable resource in oil palm plantations that can be used for lignocellulosic bioethanol production.</s><s>To enhance ethanol productivity with high-lignin-content EPFBF, the biomass was prepared with an alkali-thermal pretreatment (sodium hydroxide, 121 ∘ C, 60 min).</s><s>The delignification yield was 55.4-56.9%, in proportion to the amount of sodium hydroxide, from 0.5 to 2.0 M. The lignin and hemicellulose contents of EPFBF were reduced by the pretreatment process, whereas the proportion of cellulose was increased.</s><s>During enzymatic saccharification using Celluclast 1.5L and Novozyme 188 enzyme cocktails, about 62% of glucan was converted to a fermentable sugar.</s><s>In simultaneous saccharification and fermentation, comparison among three ethanologenic yeast strains showed Saccharomyces cerevisiae W303-1A to be a candidate for maximum ethanol yield.</s><s>In a batch fermentation with alkali-pretreated EPFBF hydrolysate, 21 g/L ethanol was obtained within 28 h, for a production yield of 0.102 g ethanol/g dry EPFBF or 0.458 g ethanol/g glucose.</s><s>Moreover, a fed-batch fermentation produced 33.8±0.5 g/L ethanol with 1.57 g/L/h productivity in 20 h.</s><s>These results show that the combination of alkaline pretreatment and biomass hydrolysate is useful for enhancing bioethanol productivity using delignified EPFBF.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p><s>Lignocellulosic biomass is a renewable bioresource for second-generation bioethanol production.</s><s>Lignocellulosic biomass is composed primarily of cellulose, hemicellulose, and lignin.</s><s>Cellulose and hemicellulose can be hydrolyzed or degraded enzymatically to glucose and a variety of pentose and hexose sugars, respectively, which can then be fermented to produce bioethanol <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>However, the rigid cellulose structure, combined with the amorphous hemicellulose and lignin cross-linked structure, is chemically complex and resistant to degradation <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s>Thus, physical, chemical, and biological methods are needed to convert the complex structures of lignocellulose into fermentable sugars <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>.</s><s>The production of bioethanol from lignocellulosic biomass requires four main steps: physical and chemical pretreatment of the lignocellulosic biomass, enzymatic hydrolysis of the lignocellulosic biomass, fermentation of the resulting sugars, and finally distillation of the ethanol <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>Of these processes, pretreatment of the biomass is the most important step in saccharification efficiency, determining the ultimate bioethanol production yield <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>.</s><s>The selection of the pretreatment procedure depends on the proportions of cellulose, hemicellulose, and lignin in the biomass and removing interfering materials from the biological steps that affect the overall bioprocess <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The palm oil industries in Indonesia and Malaysia generate ∼8.2 million tons of lignocellulosic agricultural waste and byproducts per year <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>.</s><s>An abundant byproduct in the palm oil industry is empty palm fruit bunch fiber (EPFBF), which consists of 27.6-32.5% lignin, 41.3-46.5% cellulose, and 25.3-33.8%</s><s>hemicellulose <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10]</ref>.</s><s>EPFBF contains a relatively higher lignin content rather than other agriculture residual biomasses and feedstocks as a comparison of per gram of biomass (% lignin: % cellulose: % hemicellulose); soybean straw (19.2:44.2:5.9);</s><s>wheat straw (23.4:38.2:21.2);</s><s>corn stover <ref type="bibr">(17.6:37.5:22.4)</ref>;</s><s>and switch grass <ref type="bibr">(17.6</ref>:31.0:20.4)</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</s><s>Lignocellulosic EPFBF is potentially a low-cost material and an alternative renewable bioresource, instead of food sources, such as corn, sugar cane, and other food stocks, for the production of bioethanol <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>EPFBF contains relatively high levels of hemicellulose and lignin per gram biomass, compared with other lignocellulosic biomasses <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s>Thus, pretreatment is needed to reduce the hemicellulose and lignin contents before bioethanol fermentation.</s><s>The pretreatment processes should enhance the proportion of cellulose in the EPFBF <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s>Acidic, alkali, and sequential acidic-alkali pretreatments, combined with high temperature or high pressure, have been applied in "conventional" chemical treatment processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>.</s><s>Acidic pretreatments are known to be effective with lignocellulosic biomasses in reducing the hemicellulose content.</s><s>Similarly, alkali pretreatments have been reported as simple processes for the delignification of biomass under mild conditions with minimal sugar degradation and without the formation of inhibitory compounds <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s><s>Thus, both acid and alkali pretreatments can reduce hemicellulose and lignin together to enhance the cellulose content of a biomass <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In this study, to increase the cellulose content of EPFBF, the alkali pretreatment was applied and the effects of this pretreatment were evaluated on reducing nonfermentable components in a lignocellulosic biomass for bioethanol production and productivity with the enzymatic biomass hydrolysate.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Materials.</head><p><s>Empty palm fruit bunch fiber (EPFBF) was obtained from a local oil processing company in Malaysia.</s><s>It was washed with tap water to remove soil and other particles and then dried at 105 ∘ C for 24 h.</s><s>Celluclast 1.5L and Novozyme 188 were obtained from Novozymes Korea (Seoul, South Korea).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Chemical Pretreatment of EPFBF.</head><p><s>Dried EPFBF (20% w/v) with no physical treatment was soaked in sodium hydroxide (NaOH) solution in the concentration range of 0.5-3 M and heated in an autoclave (121 ∘ C, 15 psi, 60 min).</s><s>The physical reaction conditions were determined by pretest (Supplementary Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S1</ref>).</s><s>The thermal-alkali-pretreated biomasses were removed from the black alkali solution and then washed with flowing tap water to remove NaOH from the biomass.</s><s>This washing step was repeated several times until the washed water appeared a pale brown color.</s><s>The alkali-pretreated EPFBF was dried at 105 ∘ C for 24 h and then kept under anhydrous conditions.</s><s>The composition of the pretreated biomass was analyzed based on the NREL chemical analysis and testing laboratory analytical procedures (LAPs) of the US Department of Energy (DOE).</s><s>The lignin content of the biomass was analyzed according to the LAPs of the DOE (LAP-003 and LAP-004).</s><s>The biomass pretreatment with different NaOH concentration was performed in triplicate.</s><s>The physical morphologies of the native and pretreated biomass materials were analyzed by scanning electron microscopy (SEM) using the previous method <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Enzymatic Hydrolysis of EPFBF.</head><p><s>Enzymatic hydrolysis of the alkali-pretreated EPFBF (1 M NOH-treated biomass) was performed in a 50-mL cap-tube with a 10-mL working volume.</s><s>EPFBF (10% w/v) was soaked in phosphate buffer (pH 6.0) and then the cellulase cocktails with the different concentration Celluclast 1.5L ranging from 20 to 100 filter paper units (FPU)) and the fixed concentration of Novozyme 188 (40 cellobiase units (CBU) of per gram cellulose) was added.</s><s>The initial activities of Celluclast 1.5L and Novozyme 188 were 60 FPU per ml and 250 CBU per gram protein.</s><s>60 FPU of Celluclast 1.5L corresponds to 700 endoglucanase unit (EGU) per gram protein.</s><s>One unit of endoglucanase activity corresponds to 1 mol of glucose released from carboxymethyl cellulose as the substrate per minute at 40 ∘ C and pH 6.0.</s><s>One unit of cellobiase activity (CBU) is defined as 2 mole of glucose produced per minute at 40 ∘ C, pH 5. The enzymatic saccharification was carried out in a shaking incubator (42 ∘ C, 200 rpm, 72 h).</s><s>Samples were withdrawn at each time point and then centrifuged (13,000 rpm, 10 min).</s><s>The supernatant was removed and analyzed by HPLC to determine the amount of reducing sugars produced in the enzymatic reaction.</s><s>All enzymatic saccharification of the biomass was performed in triplicate and repeated three times.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Microorganisms, Growth Conditions, and Cultivation.</head><p><s>Saccharomyces cerevisiae W303-1A <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref>, Kluyveromyces marxianus CBS1555 <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref>, and Scheffersomyces stipitis (Pichia stipitis) CBS5776 <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> were used as ethanol fermentation strains.</s><s>Each yeast strain was cultivated in YPD medium (1% Bacto yeast extract, 2% Bacto peptone, and 2% glucose) at 30 ∘ C and 200 rpm for 24 h.</s><s>For the batch flask cultures, 10% (w/v) EPFBF was prehydrolyzed with 100 FPU Celluclast 1.5L and 40 CBU Novozyme 188 cocktail for 12 h and then the 5% (v/v) seed culture with an initial optical density (OD600 nm) of ∼5.0 was inoculated in the enzymatic saccharification solution containing 1% Bacto yeast extract and 2% Bacto peptone.</s><s>Yeast cells were cultured further (30 ∘ C, 200 rpm, 24 h) for ethanol fermentation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.">Batch and Fed-Batch Cultivation for Separated Saccharification and Fermentation (SHF).</head><p><s>For ethanol fermentation, 20% (w/v) alkali-pretreated EPFBF was hydrolyzed completely with 100 FPU Celluclast 1.5L and 40 CBU Novozyme 188 cocktail under the enzyme reaction conditions described above.</s><s>After digestion, the enzymatic hydrolysate was centrifuged (20,000 rpm, 1 h) and the supernatant was filtered through a 0.22-m pore filter membrane system (Corning, Corning, NY, USA).</s><s>For batch culture for SHF, 5% (v/v) preculture of S. cerevisiae strain was inoculated into a 1-L fermentor FMT ST-S (Fermentec, Cheongju, South Korea) with a 0.5 L working volume containing the filtered enzymatic hydrolysate of the biomass supplemented with 1% Bacto yeast extract and 2% Bacto peptone.</s><s>The initial glucose concentration was 45.9 g/L.</s><s>The fermentor was operated at 30 ∘ C with stirring at 200 rpm/min.</s><s>For fed-batch cultivation, the filtrated enzymatic hydrolysate was added by step-feeding into the fermentor at the time point when the concentration of glucose was below 1 g/L.</s><s>The other nutrient supplementation and the operation condition for the fed-batch fermentation except the feeding were the same to batch cultivation.</s><s>The ethanol fermentation were performed in triplicate.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.">Analytical Procedures.</head><p><s>Cell growth was monitored by measuring the optical density at 600 nm (OD600 nm) using a spectrophotometer.</s><s>Total reducing sugars in the enzymatic saccharification reaction were measured using the 3,5dinitrosalicylic acid method.</s><s>The amounts of the released sugars in the enzymatic saccharification and the metabolites in fermentation were determined with a high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) system (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA), equipped with a refractive index detector, an autosampler, and an Aminex HPX-87P column (7.8 × 300 mm; BioRad, Hercules, CA, USA) for monosaccharide analysis or a Rezex ROA-Organic Acid H + column (7.8 × 300 mm; Phenomenex, Torrance, CA, USA) for organic acid analysis as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</s><s>All samples were clarified by filtration with a 0.20-m filter (Acrodisc LC PVDF Minispike; Pall Life Sciences, Ann Arbor, MI, USA) and then injected into the analytical HPLC column.</s><s>The column temperature was kept at 65 ∘ C. The mobile phase was distilled water for monosaccharides and 2.5 mM sulfuric acid for organic acids, with a flow rate of 0.5 mL/min under isocratic conditions.</s><s>All analyses were performed in triplicate.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results and Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Alkali Treatment of EPFBF and Its Composition.</head><p><s>To determine the composition of the EPFBF raw material prior to alkali pretreatment, the cellulose, hemicellulose, and lignin contents were analyzed using the analytical procedures of the US DOE.</s><s>Dried EPFBF (100 g) consisted of 39% cellulose, 17% hemicellulose, and 28.8% lignin.</s><s>Compared with previous data <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, the EPFBF used in this study contained a relatively high amount of lignin.</s><s>Lignin interacts strongly with cellulose in biomass.</s><s>It needs to be reduced or eliminated to enhance the enzymatic digestibility of the cellulose, to generate glucose, a fermentable sugar, and to increase bioethanol fermentation yield using yeast strains (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To prepare a high-cellulose-content biomass, alkali pretreatment was performed to reduce lignin in the EPFBF.</s><s>After the biomass had dried completely, the change in the chemical composition in alkali-pretreated EPFBF was analyzed (Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>).</s><s>The concentration of sodium hydroxide affected the solubility of the biomass and the loss of cellulose, hemicellulose, and lignin contents (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S2</ref>).</s><s>Alkalithermal treatment within sodium hydroxide extracted up to 38.5-51.9% of the biomass into the soluble fraction.</s><s>With 3 M sodium hydroxide pretreatment, the insoluble residue fraction contained 34.2 g cellulose, 4.9 g hemicellulose, and 9.0 g lignin per gram of the residual biomass.</s><s>After alkali treatment, 10.2±0.5 % lignin and 18.9±1.2%</s><s>hemicellulose were left in the residual biomass and the removal yields were ∼ 71.1% and ∼18.9%, respectively.</s><s>Under high sodium hydroxide concentration from 2.5 M to 3.0 M, the half of the biomass was extracted as soluble fractions.</s><s>On the other hand, the pretreated biomass did not lose much cellulose content, from 36.8 g to 34.2 g per gram of the residual EPFBF, with an increase in the sodium hydroxide concentration ranging from 0.5 to 2.0 M. The delignification yield with the alkali-thermal pretreatment was 55.4-56.9%, in proportion to the amount of sodium hydroxide.</s><s>However, &gt; 57% of the lignin could not be removed from the biomass under the alkali-thermal pretreatment conditions, even with a high concentration of sodium hydroxide.</s><s>The alkali-thermal treatment of the biomass demonstrated that sodium hydroxide can extract hemicellulose and lignin effectively and increase the cellulose content per gram biomass.</s></p><p><s>Sodium hydroxide treatment was effective for delignification of the biomass.</s><s>The main advantage is that the alkali process condition is relatively mild <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref>.</s><s>These mild conditions prevent condensation of lignin, resulting in a high lignin solubility.</s><s>Due to the mild conditions, degradation of sugars to furfural, HMF, and organic acids, considering potential inhibitors for enzymatic saccharification as well as ethanol fermentation, is prevented.</s><s>Moreover, the sodium hydroxide solution could be reused several times.</s><s>In addition, to compare with other chemical pretreatment processes using aqueous ammonia, organosolv, and ionic liquids, the alkali treatment does not need the special equipment and the reactor.</s><s>The cost of sodium hydroxide and of the alkali recovery is cheaper rather than the other chemical catalysts.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Enzymatic Hydrolysis of EPFBF.</head><p><s>To assess the enzymatic hydrolysis of alkali-thermal-pretreated EPFBF with 1 M sodium hydroxide, 10% (w/v) of the biomass, which contained 35.1% cellulose, 12.1% hemicellulose, and 8.8% lignin per 100 g dry biomass, was digested with different concentrations of cellulase (Celluclast 1.5L), from <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">20</ref>  of glucose generated by enzymatic saccharification increased with increasing amounts of cellulase per unit pretreated EPFBF (Figure <ref type="figure">3(a)</ref>).</s><s>At 72 h, the cellulose-degrading enzyme cocktail generated 23.6-34.6 g/L glucose and 14.1-14.6</s><s>g/L xylose.</s><s>At enzyme loading ratios of 0.5 to 2.5 Celluclast 1.5L per Novozyme 188, the enzymatic digestibility efficiency at 72 h ranged from 42.3% to 62% with the pretreated biomass.</s><s>At a ratio of 2.5 FPU/g cellulose to 1 CBU/g cellulose, 34.6 g/L glucose and 14.6 g/L xylose were obtained from the pretreated biomass.</s><s>However, the untreated biomass saccharification with equal amount of cellulase cocktail dose produced 7.1-10.4</s><s>g/L glucose and 4.2-4.5 g/L xylose under equal enzyme dose (data not shown).</s><s>Compared with untreated biomass, the alkali-thermal-pretreated EPFBF produced 2-3 times higher amounts of fermentable sugars in the enzymatic hydrolysis.</s><s>The chemical pretreatment could extract lignin from the biomass and reduce the strong interactions in cellulose-hemicellulose-lignin complexes in the biomass structure, enhancing the enzyme reaction efficiency <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</s><s>Moreover, the morphological analysis of the untreated and the alkaline-treated biomass by scanning electron microscopy (SEM) showed clearly that the alkaline pretreatment made the biomass surface many cracks, porous, and rough structures.</s><s>These morphological changes in the pretreated biomass might be for the cellulase to enhance accessibility as well as enzymatic hydrolysis of the polysaccharide structures (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Nevertheless, an increase in enzyme dose did not significantly affect the amount of fermentable sugar generation.</s><s>At the final reaction time point, the amount of glucose increased up to a 1.5 enzyme loading ratio of Celluclast51.5/Novozyme</s><s>188, whereas the sugar concentrations decreased at 2.0 and 2.5 enzyme cocktail ratios (data not shown).</s><s>It would be a product inhibition for the cellulase: the monosaccharides, disaccharides, and oligosaccharides generated by enzymatic hydrolysis might inhibit cellulase cocktails as a product inhibition.</s><s>High concentration sugars produced by the cellulase could decrease further hydrolysis reaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Additionally, sugar production increased time-dependently, whereas enzymatic hydrolysis rates decreased exponentially due to product inhibition (Figure <ref type="figure">3(b)</ref>).</s><s>The generated glucose, xylose, and incompletely digested cellobiose may inhibit the hydrolysis reactions of the cellulase cocktail enzymes.</s></p><p><s>The amount of xylose hydrolyzed from xylan in the biomass showed a near-constant value of ∼14 g/L, even when the enzyme loading ratio was changed.</s><s>The constant amount of xylose with enzyme supplementation was probably due to the -xylosidase activity present in Novozyme188, which was loaded at a fixed concentration (40 CBU).</s><s>All of the data presented for the enzymatic saccharification showed that pretreated EPFBF could be used to generate high concentrations of glucose, rather than xylose and other sugars, for bioethanol production.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Simultaneous Saccharification and Fermentation of</head><p><s>Alkali-Pretreated EPFBF.</s><s>To test ethanol production with the enzymatic hydrolysis of alkali-pretreated EPFBF, three yeast strains, Saccharomyces cerevisiae W303-1A <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref>, Kluyveromyces marxianus CBS1555 <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16]</ref>, and Scheffersomyces stipitis (Pichia stipitis) CBS5776 <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>, were used as ethanol producers.</s><s>Batch cultivation of each yeast strain was performed in a 50-mL culture volume in a 250-mL Erlenmeyer flask with 5 g of alkali-pretreated EPFBF, supplemented with a 100 FPU Celluclast 1.5L and 40 CBU Novozyme 188 cocktail.</s><s>Before cell inoculation, prehydrolysis was performed at 42 ∘ C for 12 h.</s><s>Then, 5% (v/v) yeast inoculum (5 OD600 nm) was added and cultured further (30 ∘ C, 200 rpm, 18 h) for ethanol fermentation.</s><s>The prehydrolysis step generated ∼12.3±1.5 g/L glucose in each flask for yeast cell growth with no lag phase.</s><s>The ethanol productivity of each yeast strain under these culture conditions is summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s></p><p><s>With simultaneous saccharification and fermentation (SSF), S. cerevisiae W303-1A was the "best" strain for maximum ethanol concentration and production yield: 10% (w/v) alkali-pretreated EPFBF was converted to 14.5 g/L ethanol with 0.14 g ethanol/g dried biomass.</s><s>The yeast used 82.2% of the fermentable sugars for ethanol production, and no reduction in ethanol concentration was observed in culturing for 18 h.</s><s>On the other hand, K. marxianus CBS1555 and Scheffersomyces stipitis CBS5776 produced 10.6 g/L ethanol with 0.11 g ethanol/g dried biomass and 10.1 g/L ethanol with 0.10 ethanol/g dried biomass, respectively.</s><s>These yeast strains converted 60.1% and 57.2% glucose, respectively, in the biomass hydrolysate to ethanol.</s></p><p><s>In SSF, among the yeast strains tested, S. cerevisiae W303-1A had maximum ethanol productivity and yield (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>Although inoculum size and initial glucose concentration were almost equal amounts in culture broth, the ethanol productivity of S. cerevisiae W303-1A was about 1.4-fold higher than those of K. marxianus CBS1555 and Scheffersomyces stipitis CBS5776 strains.</s><s>These different productivities among the ethanologenic yeast might be due to the individual strain characteristics such as glucose uptake and metabolism, stress responsibility, and redox balance in the biomass hydrolysate <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Batch Fermentation Supplemented with Alkali-Pretreated</head><p><s>EPFBF Hydrolysate.</s><s>To assess the fermentability of the alkali-pretreated EPFBF hydrolysate, separate hydrolysis and fermentation reactions were performed using S. cerevisiae W303-1A in a 1 L jar fermentor.</s><s>The enzymatic hydrolysate was prepared as described in Methods.</s><s>The initial concentrations of glucose and xylose in the hydrolysate of alkali-pretreated EPFBF were 47.4±2.5 g/L and 19.0±1.2 g/L, respectively.</s><s>After yeast inoculation, ethanol fermentation proceeded gradually for 30 h (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4</ref> was slow until 4.5 h in a lag phase, increased exponentially, and entered a stationary phase between 16 and 24 h (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4(b)</ref>).</s><s>The concentration of glucose decreased gradually due to cell growth.</s><s>All of the glucose in the culture broth was depleted at 28 h.</s><s>The amount of xylose, which is a nonfermentable sugar, did not decrease.</s></p><p><s>The highest ethanol concentration was 21 g/L at 28 h, giving an ethanol yield of 0.102 g ethanol/g dry EPFBF and 0.458 g ethanol/g glucose at 28 h.</s><s>Ultimately, 85.4% of the fermentable sugar was used by the yeast for ethanol fermentation.</s><s>No reduction in ethanol concentration was observed until glucose depletion.</s><s>Cell growth and ethanol production in the separate hydrolysis and fermentation (SHF) were faster than those in the simultaneous saccharification and fermentation (SSF) (Supplementary Fig. <ref type="figure">S2</ref>).</s><s>Ethanol fermentation of the alkali-pretreated EPFBF by S. cerevisiae W303-1A produced several metabolites, including acetic acid, lactic acid, succinic acid, and glycerol (data not shown).</s><s>All metabolites produced by the yeast were at concentrations &gt; 1 g/L, lower than that of the ethanol.</s><s>In addition, these metabolites accumulated with no consumption in the fermentation broth.</s><s>These metabolites did not appear to affect cell growth or ethanol productivity during the fermentation.</s><s>Levels of these byproduct metabolites were probably too low to have any negative effects on cell metabolism due to the short fermentation time in the SHF process.</s><s>These results indicated that SHF produced large amounts of ethanol with less byproducts and no inhibition by metabolites in the short fermentation time.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.">Fed-Batch Fermentation Supplemented with Alkali-Pretreated EPFBF Hydrolysate.</head><p><s>To increase ethanol production and yield, separate hydrolysis and fermentation in a fed-batch were performed using the alkali-pretreated EPFBF hydrolysate.</s><s>When the residual glucose concentration fell below 0.5 g/L during the fermentation, the filtered enzymatic hydrolysate was fed into the fermentor to maintain ∼10.0±1.5 g/L glucose.</s><s>By 20 h, 33.8±0.5 g/L ethanol was produced (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref>(a)), and the residual glucose concentration was completely depleted.</s><s>The productivity of ethanol was 1.57 g/L/h, and the production yield was 0.102 g per g EPFBF and 0.465 g per g glucose, with 91.2% sugar conversion efficiency.</s></p><p><s>The yeast strain grew exponentially with no lag phase for 4 h and then entered a stationary phase at 8 h (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5(b)</ref>).</s><s>The cell density was maintained until the culture end time with no growth decrease.</s><s>The initial glucose was consumed rapidly by the yeast by 8 h.</s><s>In addition, the fed sugar in each 2-h period was also taken up rapidly by the viable yeast cells until the fermentation end point.</s><s>Xylose could not be fermented by the yeast and thus accumulated in the fermentor (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5(a)</ref>).</s><s>Total reducing sugar decreased markedly until 8 h in the fermentation, and then the nonfermentable sugar increased gradually (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5(b)</ref>).</s></p><p><s>In the fed-batch cultivation, byproduct metabolites, such as organic acids and glycerol, were produced, but at &lt; 0.53±0.12</s><s>g/L by the end of fermentation (data not shown).</s><s>The cultivation time for ethanol production was only 20 h until the glucose was completely depleted.</s><s>It may be that the byproducts did not accumulate in the fed-batch culture due to the short fermentation time.</s><s>These results showed that separate hydrolysis and fermentation in a fed-batch using the alkali-pretreated EPFBF hydrolysate could produce bioethanol with high productivity in a short operation time.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusions</head><p><s>Alkali-thermal pretreatment of EPFBF with sodium hydroxide was effective in reducing hemicellulose and lignin contents and enhancing the enzymatic digestibility and fermentability of the biomass.</s><s>The alkali-pretreated EPFBF showed ∼55.4% delignification efficiency.</s><s>In the pretreated Cell growth (closed square) was monitored by measuring the absorbance at 600 nm using a spectrophotometer.</s><s>Total reducing sugar (open triangle) was measured using the 3,5-dinitrosalicylic acid method.</s><s>All analyses were performed in triplicate.</s><s>The data are expressed as mean ± SEM, n = 3. biomass, 62% of the cellulose was hydrolyzed by the Celluclast 1.5L/Novozyme 188 enzyme cocktail and was converted to fermentable sugars during enzymatic saccharification.</s><s>In a small-scale culture of simultaneous saccharification and fermentation supplemented with the pretreated biomass, S. cerevisiae, the best ethanol producer among the three yeast strains tested, produced 14.5 g/L ethanol with 0.14 g ethanol/g biomass and 82.2% fermentable sugar conversion.</s><s>In a batch involving separate hydrolysis and fermentation supplemented with the alkali-pretreated EPFBF hydrolysate, 21 g/L ethanol was obtained within 28 h for a production yield of 0.102 g ethanol/g dry EPFBF or 0.458 g ethanol/g glucose.</s><s>In addition, a fed-batch involving separate hydrolysis and fermentation could produce 33.8±0.5 g/L ethanol with 1.57 g/L/h productivity in only 20 h.</s><s>These results confirm that alkali-pretreated EPFBF effectively reduced the hemicellulose and lignin components.</s><s>Moreover, separate hydrolysis and fermentation using biomass hydrolysate may be useful for producing bioethanol with high productivity.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1: Overall scheme for bioethanol production from empty palm fruit bunch fiber (EPFBF).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,329.76,73.76,193.54,216.16" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :Figure 3 :</head><label>23</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2: Composition of empty palm fruit bunch fiber (EPFBF) after pretreatment with different concentrations of NaOH at 121 ∘ C for 1 h.</s><s>(a) Proportion of insoluble solids in alkali-pretreated EPFBF and delignification efficiency (close circles).</s><s>(b) Contents of cellulose, hemicellulose, and lignin in EPFBF after NaOH pretreatment.</s><s>All experiments were performed in triplicate.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4: Batch fermentation of enzymatically hydrolyzed EPFBF by S. cerevisiae W303-1A in a 1 L jar fermentor.</s><s>(a) The amounts of glucose (closed circle), xylose (closed triangle), and ethanol (open circle) were analyzed by HPLC.</s><s>(b) Cell growth (closed square) was monitored by measuring the absorbance at 600 nm using a spectrophotometer.</s><s>All analyses were performed in triplicate.</s><s>The data are expressed as mean ± SEM, n = 3.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>FermentationFigure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5: Fed-batch separate hydrolysis and fermentation using the alkali-pretreated EPFBF hydrolysate with S. cerevisiae W303-1A in a 1 L jar fermentor.</s><s>(a) The amounts of glucose (closed circle), xylose (closed triangle), and ethanol (open circle) were analyzed by HPLC.</s><s>(b)Cell growth (closed square) was monitored by measuring the absorbance at 600 nm using a spectrophotometer.</s><s>Total reducing sugar (open triangle) was measured using the 3,5-dinitrosalicylic acid method.</s><s>All analyses were performed in triplicate.</s><s>The data are expressed as mean ± SEM, n = 3.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Comparison of ethanol production among three yeast strains.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Yeast strain</cell><cell>Saccharomyces cerevisiae W303-1A</cell><cell>Kluyveromyces marxianus CBS1555</cell><cell>Scheffersomyces stipites CBS5776</cell></row><row><cell>Max. ethanol (g/L)</cell><cell>14.5±0.2</cell><cell>10.6±0.1</cell><cell>10.1±0.2</cell></row><row><cell>Ethanol yield (EtOH g/ g EPFBFs)</cell><cell>0.14±0.01</cell><cell>0.11±0.01</cell><cell>0.10±0.01</cell></row><row><cell>Ethanol productivity (g/L/h)</cell><cell>0.81±0.01</cell><cell>0.59±0.01</cell><cell>0.56±0.01</cell></row><row><cell>Inoculation (OD 600nm )</cell><cell>5.3±0.1</cell><cell>5.2±0.1</cell><cell>5.4±0.1</cell></row><row><cell>Initial glucose (g/L)</cell><cell>12.3±1.5</cell><cell>12.3±1.5</cell><cell>12.3±1.5</cell></row><row><cell>Residual xylose (g/L)</cell><cell>7.3±0.1</cell><cell>6.2±0.1</cell><cell>5.4±0.1</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Availability</head><p><s>The data used to support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon request.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflicts of Interest</head><p><s>The author declares no conflicts of interest regarding the publication of this article.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary Materials</head><p><s>Table <ref type="table">S</ref> .</s><s>Comparison of the contents of cellulose, hemicellulose, and lignin in the thermal-alkaline-pretreated EPFBFs under different temperatures (the alkaline pretreatment of EPFBFs was performed with 0.5 M NaOH at each temperature for 60 min).</s><s>Table <ref type="table">S</ref> .</s><s>The composition of cellulose, hemicellulose, and lignin in the EPFBF biomass before and after the treatment.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biochemical conversion processes of lignocellulosic biomass to fuels and chemicals -A review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brethauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Studer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chimia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="572" to="581" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mechanisms employed by cellulase systems to gain access through the complex architecture of lignocellulosic substrates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Donohoe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Resch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Opinion in Chemical Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="100" to="107" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Current Pretreatment Technologies for the Development of Cellulosic Ethanol and Biorefineries</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H L</forename><surname>Silveira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R C</forename><surname>Morais</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Da Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lopes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ChemSusChem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3366" to="3390" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Green methods of lignocellulose pretreatment for biorefinery development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Capolupo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Faraco</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9451" to="9467" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A thermochemicalbiochemical hybrid processing of lignocellulosic biomass for producing fuels and chemicals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Jarboe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechnology Advances</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1799" to="1813" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of hydrotropic pretreatment on lignocellulosic biomass</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Devendra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Kiran</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pandey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioresource Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">213</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="350" to="358" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Techno-economic analysis of lignocellulosic ethanol: A review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gnansounou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dauriat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioresource Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4980" to="4991" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ethanol and lignin production from Brazilian empty fruit bunch biomass</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Raman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gnansounou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioresource Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">172</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="241" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Production of cellulase enzymes during the solid-state fermentation of empty palm fruit bunch fiber</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioprocess and Biosystems Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bioethanol production using the sequential acid/alkali-pretreated empty palm fruit bunch fiber</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Renewable Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="155" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Empty fruit bunches from oil palm as a potential raw material for fuel ethanol production</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Piarpuzán</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Quintero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cardona</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biomass &amp; Bioenergy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1130" to="1137" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pretreatment technologies for an efficient bioethanol production process based on enzymatic hydrolysis: a review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Alvira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tomás-Pejó</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ballesteros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Negro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioresource Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4851" to="4861" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sequential acid-/alkali-pretreatment of empty palm fruit bunch fiber</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-W</forename><surname>Seo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioresource Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of Alkali-Pretreated Soybean Straw for Lignocellulosic Bioethanol Production</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ID 5241748</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Polymer Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2018</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ethanol production using whole plant biomass of jerusalem artichoke by Kluyveromyces marxianus CBS1555</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Applied Biochemistry and Biotechnology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">169</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1531" to="1545" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of whole Jerusalem artichoke (Helianthustuberosus L.) for consolidated bioprocessing ethanol production</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Renewable Energy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="91" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selection of non-Saccharomyces yeast strains for reducing alcohol levels in wine by sugar respiration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Quirós</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Rojas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gonzalez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Morales</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Food Microbiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">181</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="91" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A biorefinery processing perspective: treatment of lignocellulosic materials for the production of value-added products</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fitzpatrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Champagne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Cunningham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Whitney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioresource Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8915" to="8922" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cradle-to-grave&apos; assessment of existing lignocellulose pretreatment technologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Da Costa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Sousa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Chundawat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Balan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Dale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current Opinion in Biotechnology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="339" to="347" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cellulase inhibition by high concentrations of monosaccharides</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hsieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cannella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jørgensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Felby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Thygesen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3800" to="3805" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Looking beyond Saccharomyces: The potential of non-conventional yeast species for desirable traits in bioethanol fermentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Radecka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Mukherjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Mateo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stojiljkovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Foulquié-Moreno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Thevelein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>ID fov053</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FEMS Yeast Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
