<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Consensus of German Transplant Centers on Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation in Fanconi Anemia Konsensus Empfehlungen Deutscher Transplantationszentren zur hamatopoetischen Stammzelltransplantation bei Fanconi Anamie</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Stammzelltransplantation</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Konsensus</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Em</forename><surname>Pfehlungen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Prof</roleName><surname>Karl-Wolter</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Syfcora</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chao'</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ebell</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Baderl</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Beie R'</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Burkhardt</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">'</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Feuchtlnge</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ha</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hanen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Koehjj</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kratz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kremens</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Meisel</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Mueller</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Roesslg</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">'</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sauer</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">'</forename><forename type="middle">P G</forename><surname>Sch Legel'</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schulz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Strahm</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Thol' S</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Syko Ra'</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">CC&gt; Georg Thieme Verlag KG</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Stuttgart • New York</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Pediatric Hematology/ Oncology Hannover Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Carl-Neuberg-StraBe 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>30625</postCode>
									<settlement>Hannover</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<address>
									<settlement>Cl •~</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Consensus of German Transplant Centers on Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation in Fanconi Anemia Konsensus Empfehlungen Deutscher Transplantationszentren zur hamatopoetischen Stammzelltransplantation bei Fanconi Anamie</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">0300-8630</idno>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5A28E2AF2BA962EA4021FC8F6A816D29</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:34+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation ( HSCT) is currently the only curative therapy for the severe hematopoietic complications associated with Fanconi anemia ( FA).</s><s>In Germany, it is estimated that 10-15 transplants are performed annually for FA.</s><s>However, because FA is a DNA repair disorder, standard conditioning regimens confer a high risk of excessive regimen -related toxicities and mortality, and reduced intensity regimens are linked with graft fai lure in some FA patients.</s><s>Moreover.</s><s>development of graft-versus-host disease is a major contributing factor for secondary solid tumors.</s><s>The relative rarity of the disorder limits HSCT experience at any single center.</s><s>Consensus meetings were convened to develop a national approach for HSCT in FA.</s><s>This manuscript outlines current experience and knowledge about HSCT in FA and, based on this analysis, general recommendations reached at these meetings.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>T</head><p><s>Fanconi anemia ( FA) is a ra re inherited genomic instability disorder associated with congenital abnormalities, progressive bone marrow failure (BMF).</s><s>and a predisposition to develop malignancies including myelodysp lastic syndrome (MDS )/ acute myeloid leukemia (AML) and squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">41 ]</ref>.</s><s>Although there is phenotypic variability among FA individuals.</s><s>hematologic abnormalities arise in the majority of patients and represent a significant clinical feature of the disorder.</s><s>Some FA patients have mild hematologic changes and do not require thera-Zusammenfassung T Die allogene Stammzelltransplantation ( HSCT) ist zurzeit die einzige kurative Therapie der schweren hamatopoetischen Komplikationen der Fanconi-Anamie ( FA).</s><s>In Deutsch land werden etwa 10-15 Trans plantationen pro Jahr bei Patienten m it FA durchgefiih rt.</s><s>Da die FA auf einem Defekt der DNA-Reparatur beruht, ,konnen Standard-Konditionierun gsprotokolle zu hoher Toxizitat und Mortalitat fiihren, wa hrend Regime mit reduzierter lntensi tat ein Risiko fiir Transplantatversagen in sich tragen.</s><s>Hinzu kommt, dass die Entwicklung der Transplantat-gegen-Empfanger-Erkrankung ein wichtiger Risikofaktor fiir die Entwicklu ng von sekundaren soliden Tumoren ist.</s><s>Die relative Seltenheit der Erkrankung fiihrt dazu, dass die Erfahrung jedes einzelnen Transplantationszentrums mit der Erkrankung begrenzt ist.</s><s>Konsensus-Treffen mit dem Ziel de r Entwicklung eines bundesweiten Vorgehens bei der Transplantation der FA w urden abgehalten.</s><s>Dieses Manuskript beschre ibt die langjahrige Erfahrung und den aktuellen Kenntnisstand zur Transplantation bei FA sowie den darauf basierenden Konse ns, der auf diesen Treffen erzielt w urde.</s><s>peutic intervention.</s><s>Others have moderate to severe BMF that improves with androgen therapy <ref type="bibr" target="#b55">(60]</ref>.</s><s>In patients with BMF who fail to respond to androgens or w ho develop myeloid neoplasia, allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplan tation (HSCT) can restore normal hematopoiesis.</s><s>Unfortunately, early FA HSCT preparative regimens (cyclophosphamide±radiation) based on HSCT for patients w ith acquired severe aplastic anemia (SAA) were fraught w ith severe complications <ref type="bibr">(25, 27 ,28, 31, 32,45 ]</ref>.</s><s>Excessive regimenrelated toxicities ( RRT), high rates of graft failure, graft-versus-host-disease ( GVHD), secondary cancers, and poor survival outcomes were ob-.</s><s>R e p o r t served.</s><s>These were attributed to underlying congenital abnormalities, hypersensitivity to DNA damaging agents and putatively radiotherapy.</s><s>delayed or absent tissue repair after GVHD induced injury, and/or presence ofT cell mosaicism in some FA individuals.125,</s><s><ref type="bibr">27,28, 31.32.45 ]</ref>.</s><s>Over the past 3 decades.</s><s>modifications to FA HSCT condition ing regimens together with advances in transplant medicine (e.g. more accurate HLA typing.</s><s>better supportive care.</s><s>graft processing, etc.) have dramatically improved the prognosis of FA HSCT 120].</s><s>Reduction of chemotherapy and radiation doses (reduced intensity conditioning) lessened RRTs 127,63 J. Incor poration of nudarabine to preparative regimens enhanced immunosuppression and engraftment without adding toxicity l8.29.39,68J.</s><s>In vivo and/or ex vivo T cell depletion of allografts decreased the incidence and severity of GVHD 18. 17J.</s><s>Radiation was eliminated in some conditioning regimens with excellent results 148.</s><s>54 J.</s><s>For some FA HSCTs, particularly in HLA matched si bling donor (MSD) trans plants.</s><s>survival now ranges from 70-100 % with low graft failure and GVHD rates l48J.</s><s>Challenges.</s><s>however.</s><s>remain.</s><s>For FA patients who do not have a MSD and receive transplants from either mismatched related or unrelated donors, collectively termed alternative donor (AD).</s><s>the outcomes of HSCT are less encouraging, albeit improving l68J.</s><s>FA patients with advanced MOS or AML have a poorer prognosis 12).</s><s>Post-transplant infections represent a leading cause of transplant related morbidity and mortality I 1 OJ <ref type="bibr">(Chao et</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Overview of FA HSCT nationally and internationally</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>,,</head><p><s>The first HSCTs for FA in Germany were completed at the University of Ulm in the mid-1980s.</s><s>Whereas the initial conditioning regimens included total body irradiation (TBI ) or total lymphoid irradiation (TLI ), since 1991, radiation has been eliminated.</s><s>To date.</s><s>14patients 16 matched unrelated (MUD).</s><s>5 MSD. 2 matched related trans plants (MRD).</s><s>and one haploidentical transplant! have received a cyclophosphamide fludarabine based regime n without radiation at the University of Ulm.</s><s>Busulfan was a lso administered in patients with clonal disease and in the haploidentical transplant and anti-lymphocyte therapy with alemtuzumab (Campath-lH ) or anti-thymocyte globulin (ATC) was applied in all patients except in those receiving MSD transplants.10 of the 14 patients are alive.</s><s>but unfortunately. 2 of the surviving patients are suffering from carcinomas.</s><s>Between October 1999 and April 2014.</s><s>the Pediatric Blood and Marrow Transplantation Department at Cha rite University Medicine Berlin completed 39 consecutive MSD (n • 4 ) and AD (n =35) HSCTs for FA.</s><s>These transplants account for the majority of FA HSCTs performed in Germany.</s><s>HSCT regimens titled German Fanconi Anemia 02 (GEFA02) (n = 18) and German Fanconi Anemia 03 (GEFA03) (Chao et a l. in press) (n = 2 1 ).</s><s>consisting of fludarabine based non-radiation conditioning.</s><s>were utilized.</s><s>The GEFA02 preparative regimen included fludarabine 30 mg/ m 2 /day IV x 6 days, busulfan 1 mg/kg/day in 2 divided doses POx2 days, ATC -Fresenius 20mg/kg/day 1Vx3 days, and Muromonab-CD3 (OKT3, Orthoclone OKT3) 0.1 mg/kg/day IV x 12 days and was employed from 1999 to 2005.</s><s>Since 2005 to the present time, the GEFA03 regimen which includes fludarabine 30mg/ m 2 /day JVx 6 days, busulfan 1 mg/kg/day in 2 divided doses PO x 2 days, cyclophosphamide 20 mg/kg/day IV x 2 days, and alemtuzumab 5mg/m 2 /dayxl day fo llowed by 10mg/ m 2 /day IV x 3 days has been used.</s><s>Patients received Cyclosporine A (CSA) for GVHD prophylaxis.</s><s>In this series.</s><s>all but one patient experienced neutrophil engraftment.</s><s>Mixed chimerism was observed in 4 patients who all converted to full donor chi merism after stem cell boost(s), and 4 second transplants were undertaken for graft failure.</s><s>Approximately 38 % of patients developed grade I acute GVHD (aGVHD).</s><s>10 % grade II aGVHD, and no grade Ill-IV aGVHD was observed.</s><s>Among the eva luable patients.</s><s>17% developed mild chronic GVHD (cGVHD ) and no patient experienced moderate or severe cGVHD.</s><s>11 patients died: 8 from viral infection.</s><s>2 from AML disease progression.</s><s>and one from SCC.</s><s>The 2-year probability of survival was 76% (SE 7%) with a median followup of 5. 7 years.</s><s>A sub-analys is of GEFA03 patients showed a 2-year probability of survival of 90%, 100 % neutrophil engraftment.</s><s>38% grade I aGVHD and no grade 11-IV aGVHD.</s><s>and no mode rate or severe cGVHD.</s><s>At Eberhard Karl University in Tuebingen.</s><s>7 pediatric patients were transplanted for FA in more recent years.</s><s>There were 4 MUD. 2 MSD. and one haploidentical donor transplants.</s><s>The conditioning regimen included fludarabi n e 40 mg/m 2 /dose x4 doses, cyclophosphamide 300mg/m 2 /dose x4 doses.</s><s>and ATG Thymoglobulin 4.5 mg/kg total dose (0.5-2-2 mg/ kg).</s><s>For MUD transplants the dose of ATG was increased to 10mg/ kg (1-3-3-3 mg/ kg).</s><s>For the haploidentical transplant, 15 mg/kg ATG-Fresenius ( 1-4-5-5 mg/kg) was used and 4 Cy TBI.</s><s>followed by a TCRa~/CDl 9 negative depleted allograft of PBSCs.</s><s>For MSD and MUD transplants.</s><s>the GVHD prophylaxis included CSA and mycophenolate mofetil ( MMF) and for the haploidentical transplant the patient received only MMF.</s><s>All patients engrafted.</s><s>3 patients experienced aGVHD and among these patients.</s><s>2 developed grade I aGVHD and one grade Ill aGVHD.</s><s>To date, only one patient has developed mild cGVHD.</s><s>The overall survival was 100 %.</s><s>The German experiences recapitulate worldwide FA HSCT experiences (e.g. a retreat from radiation based conditioning, utilization of fludarabine and anti-lymphocyte antibodies.</s><s>and use of new stem cell sources such as haploidentical donors ).</s><s>Current conditioning regimens used in Germany are comparable to preparative regimens employed by others elsewhere and confer good outcomes.</s><s>FA HSCT results publis hed in the past 5 years are detailed in o Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Radiation vs. n o rad iation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>,,</head><p><s>Historically, radiation was used in FA HSCT preparative regimens to facilitate engraftment.</s><s>Yet, the early use of sta ndard dose radiation was associated w ith severe adverse side e ffects and initial studies suggesting a marked hypersensitivity of FA patients towards radiation led to significant reduction of th e radiation dose 125,27].</s><s>Elimination of the modality proved successful in MSD t ransplants.</s><s>Here, graft failu re was less problematic and radiation was omitted without comprom ising engraftment.</s><s>In mismatched and unrelated donor FA HSCTs.</s><s>radiation was replaced by busulfan in some centers with good results 112].</s><s>Other ce nters have continued to employ radiation at lower doses for mismatched and unrelated donor transplants, arguing that single fraction low-dose radiation confers minimal toxicities not exceeding busulfan related toxicities 147,48].</s><s>In Germany, radia-   <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(49)</ref>.</s><s>A newer study demonstrated that primary fibroblasts from patients with mutations in FANCA.</s><s>FANCD2.</s><s>and FANCG are not pa rticularly sensitive for either ionizing or UV radiation <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[37)</ref>.</s><s>Moreover, older studies clearly implicated radiation in t he development of post-transplant head and neck sec in FA patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(15)</ref>, but more recent studies have not identified this link <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(55,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b54">59)</ref>.</s><s>The consensus group addressed the question whether radiation might be reintroduced in future German FA transplant protocols  The difference in survival outcomes between alemtuzumab and T cell replete groups was not statistically significant but the difference between ATG and unmanipulated T cell replete grafts was significant (p =0.008 ) <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">[64]</ref>.</s><s>Lower incidences of CVHD and RRTs and their sequelae related with alemtuzumab administration may explain the improved survival rates [ 4 7] .</s><s>Of significance for FA patients is the lower rate ofCVHD afforded by alemtuzumab.</s><s>since its development is associated with a higher risk for secondary malignancy IS91 and a negative impact on the quality of life.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Other GVHD prophylaxis</head><p><s>,,</s></p><p><s>In a retrospective review of patients with FA (n =37) or acquired aplastic anemia (n = 73) following MSD HSCT, FA patients had double the relative risk of grades II-IV aGVHD (p = 0.021 ), and in younger patients.</s><s>the relative risk was 7.93 (p= 0.014 ) <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[32]</ref>.</s><s>Moreover.</s><s>the risk of requiring systemic corticosteroids and experiencing steroid-resistant aGVHD was higher in FA patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[32]</ref>.</s><s>Increased cellular apoptosis in FA individuals has been linked to the higher severity of aGVHD l69J.</s><s>Wang et al. assessed epithelial cell apoptosis and studied TP53 and miR-34a expression in the skin and gut biopsies from S non-transplanted FA patients, 20 FA patients with aCVHD, and 25 acquired aplastic anemia patients.</s><s>Although FA and aplastic anemia patients received similar preparative regimens, epithelial apoptosis was higher in FA specimens than in samples from patients with acquired aplastic anemia patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[69]</ref>.</s><s>Further studies of gut biopsies from FA patients showed that this delete rious effect was not related to TPS3 gene overexpression but rather miR-34a which mimics pS3 apoptotic effects in response to DNA damage <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">[69]</ref>.</s><s>In a large analysis of 795 FA HSCTs between 1972 and 2009, the incidence of cCVHD was 14% at 1 year and 19% at S years IS5].</s><s>Older age at transplant and history of aCVHD were independent predictors of cCVHD <ref type="bibr">[SS]</ref>.</s><s>The development of cCVHD correlated with an increased risk of developing head and neck SCC [S9[.</s><s>A principal goal in FA HSCT has been to reduce the incidence and severity of CVHD in order to abolish any of its potential shortand long-term complications.</s><s>In addition to anti-lymphocyte antibody to reduce the incidence and severity ofCVHD.</s><s>the consensus group advises CSA as CVHD prophylaxis, with the addition of M MF for unrelated donors.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Immune reconstitution</head><p><s>,,</s></p><p><s>Allogeneic HSCT is associated with profound immune deficiency owing to a multitude of factors including underlying disease, transplant conditioning regimen, ste m cell source, degree of HLA matching.</s><s>graft manipulation, development ofCVHD, immunosuppressive medications for CVHD prophylaxis/therapy, and others.</s><s>However, the speed of immune recovery has important repercussions regarding infectious complications and relapse following allogeneic HSCT 121,401.</s><s>The consensus group addressed post-transplant immune reconstitution as related to the</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(ij •c: &lt;I&gt; ro E 'O</formula><p><s>Report.</s></p><p><s>anti-lymphocyte antibody utilized in the preparative regimen.</s></p><p><s>The focus was on alemtuzumab since the antibody is proposed for future studies.</s></p><p><s>There is evidence that alemtuzumab is more immunosuppressive than ATC because the former is directed against a variety of immune cells including T and B cells, macrophages, monocytes, and NK cells and the latter targets mainly T lymphocytes l57j.</s><s>In a comparison of immune reconstitution following alemtuzumab (n=14) or ATC (n= 13) in pediatric unrelated transplants, patients who received alemtuzumab demonstrated significantly slower immune recovery (61 j.</s><s>The presence of peripheral blood CD3 +T cells ( &gt; 30cells/µL) <ref type="bibr">(</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[ 13]</ref>.</s><s>The 20 mg total dose of alemtuzumab was associated with a greater risk of grade Ill-IV aCVHD and severe cCVHD in comparison with doses &gt; 20mg.</s><s>A total dose of 20 mg or lower was linked with incomplete saturation of CD52 binding sites.</s><s>more rapid clearance, and greater risk of severe acute and chronic CVHD <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">57]</ref>.</s><s>A total dose of 30 mg or lower was associated with a significant decrease in alemtuzumab levels by day 28 [13.57j.</s><s>The 30mg dose resulted in comparable CVHD outcomes but better lymphocyte recovery at one year post-transplantation than the 40 mg or 60 mg dose groups <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[ 13 ]</ref>.</s><s>However, improved lymphocyte counts were not associated with lower rates of infections <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(13)</ref> ).</s><s>Other reduced intensity conditioning regimens for HSCT in patients with chronic granulomatous disease or DNA breakage repair disorder use alemtuzumab doses ranging from 0.5 mg/kg to 1 mg/kg <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">33]</ref>.</s><s>The consensus group agreed to an alemtuzumab dose of 30mg/ m 2 ( 1 mg/kg), since further dose reductions appear not to provide anti-infection benefits and may increase the risk of GVHD.</s></p><p><s>A decreased alemtuzumab dose of 20mg/m 2 may be employed in patients with MSD allografts ( 10/10, genotypically identical).</s><s>only of BM is used as stem cell graft.</s><s>In patients with MSD allografts ( ~9/10 ) and PBSC grafts, total alemtuzumab dose should remain 30mg/m 2 , due to increased risk ofCVHD.</s><s>The group also advocates prophylaxis and strict surveillance of infections, preemptive therapy and aggressive early treatment.</s></p><p><s>Selective allodepletion of the graft may be one method to improve immune reconstitution following allogeneic HSCT. .</s><s>R e p o r t grafts.</s><s>Within the first month post-transplantation, rapid imm une reconstitution with good levels of CD3 + T cells, CD3+CD4+T cells, and CD56+NK cells was observed <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(42)</ref>.</s><s>In addition, expansion of TCRyo + T cells occurred faster than TCRap+ T cells in the early post-transplant period and may contribute to anti-infectious and anti-tumor immunity <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[42,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">53)</ref>.</s><s>Graft engineering technologies may benefit FA patients, especially if they receive a mismatched PBSC allograft.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Haploidentical transplantation</head><p><s>...</s></p><p><s>In patients who lack an HLA matched related or unrelated donor, haploidentical stem cell transplantation is a feasible alternative.</s></p><p><s>The immediate availa bility of a haploidentical donor in most families and the possibility for post-transplant cellular therapies either in the prevention of relapse or treatment of viral infections by adoptive T cell transfer are advantages of this type of transplantation (52(.</s><s>Haploidentical HSCTs have been undertaken for both malignant and nonmalignant disorders since the late 1970s [6, <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">58)</ref>.</s><s>In a recent publication, Zecca et al. reported on 12 FA patients who were given T cell depleted.</s><s>CD34 + positively selected cells from a haploidentical related donor after a reduced intensity conditioning regimen including fludarabine (120mg/m 2 ).</s><s>cyclophosphamide (1 200 mg/m 2 ), ATC-Fresenius (40mg/kg) with and without radiation (2Gy TBI) [72).</s><s>Engraftment was achieved in 9of12 patients (75 %) and the cumulative incidence of graft rejection was 17% (95 % confidence interval [Cl), 5-59%).</s><s>The frequencies of grades II-IV aGVHD and cGVHD were 17% (95 % Cl, 5-59%) and 35% (95% Cl, 14-89%), respectively.</s><s>The cumulative incidence of transplant-related mortality was 17% (95 % Cl, 5-59%).</s><s>The 5-year overall survival, event-free survival (probability of survival from time of transplant to occurrence of any event-graft failure, rejection or death from any cause-or the date of last follow up ), and disease-free s urvival (probability of survival without evidence of disease at anytime after transplantation) were 83% (95 %CI.</s><s>62-100%).</s><s>67%(95 % Cl.</s></p><p><s>40-93 %), and 83 % (95% Cl, 62-100%), respectively [72).</s><s>Another group published their experience with 3 FA haploidentical HSCTs <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[66)</ref>.</s><s>The patients received cyclophosphamide, fludarabine, and radiation.</s><s>All 3 patients engrafted.</s><s>One patient died from infection on day + 37. Of the 2 remaining patients, both developed~grade II aGVHD and one patient developed mild cG-VHD <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">[66)</ref>.</s><s>Dufort et al. also reported on 3 FA patients who were given fludarabine.</s><s>cyclophosphamide, ATG, and TLI prior to haploidentical transplantation <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[ 18)</ref>.</s><s>The patients engrafted, did not experience GVHD.</s><s>and are alive at last follow-up (5.</s><s>6, and 16 months ) <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[18)</ref>.</s><s>Charite University Medicine Berlin performed one haploidentical transplant for FA using the GEFA03 conditioning regimen.</s></p><p><s>The patient had MOS classified as refractory anemia with 7 % blasts and complex karyotype including a chromosome 3 abnormality.</s><s>He received CD34 +positively selected PBSC from a paternal uncle and engrafted neutrophils and platelets.</s><s>The patient did not experience any aGVHD, but did develop mild cGVHD.</s><s>Approximately 18 months post-transplantation. the marrow showed recipient marrow reconstitution and progression to AML.</s><s>The patient subsequently received multiple donor lymphocyte infusions, reinduction chemotherapy, and a second haploidentical transplant from his 'father.</s><s>•Omit busulfan for low risk patients defined as cytopenia without evidence of leukemia or cytogenetic aber• rations and with HLA ident ical donor (i.e.</s><s>"'9/10 MSD.</s><s>MRD. or MUD).</s><s>Busulfan levels recommended.</s><s>#Decrease alemtuzumab dose to 20mg/m2 in patients with MSD allografts (10/10) and only if BM is used as stem cell source.</s><s>In patients with MSD ( S9/l 0), unrelated donor, or PBSC grafts.</s><s>total ale mtuzumab dose should remain 30mg/m 2 • The total dose of conditioning drugs Is: fiudarabine l 80 mg/m 2 • IV busul• fan (Busilvex®) 1.6mg/kg.</s><s>cyclophosphamide40mg/kg. and alemtuzum• ab 30 mg/m 2 for MUD.</s><s>MMRD.</s><s>or PBSC (5 mg/m 2 days• 7 and• 6 followed by 10mg/m 2 days -5 and • 4) reduced to 20mg/m 2 for MSD (5mg/m 2 days• 7 and •6 followed by 10mg/m 2 day -5).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions and recommendations y</head><p><s>HSCT represents a curative option for the severe hematological complications associated with FA.</s><s>The therapeutic procedure is, however.</s><s>characterized by unique challenges in this patient population.</s><s>The consensus meetings on HSCT in FA aims to build upon previous German and international experiences and incorporate new data and technologies to improve outcomes.</s><s>The current conclusions and recommendations are as follows: 1. Chemotherapy-only conditioning regimens resulted in equal or better outcomes than regimens that included radiotherapy.</s><s>also in patients with MDS/AML.</s><s>There is no reason to reintroduce radiotherapy into conditioning regimens for FA. 2. The chemotherapeutic backbone in the German GEFA03 study, the ESID-EBMT recommendations.</s><s>and other modern conditioning therapies consist offludarabine and cyclophosphamide <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[30]</ref>.</s><s>This combination also forms the basis of the current recommendation.</s><s>o Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">1</ref> illustrates the preparative regimen.</s><s>3. The addition of busulfan to the fludarabine cyclophosphamide backbone is probably not necessary in patients transplanted for BMF without blood cell clonal aberration(s) and/ or MDS/AML, if transplanted from a ' ?:. 9/10 HLA matched related or unrelated donor.</s><s>4. Busulfan is recommended to facilitate engraftment in patients with mismatched/haploidentical allografts ( &lt;9/10) and as anti-leukemic agent in patients with bone marrow clonal aberrations and/or MDS/AML.</s><s>The intravenous formulation is prefe rred due to more consistent blood levels.</s><s>To gain more knowledge about the pharmacology ofbusulfan in FA, pharmacological monitoring of bus ulfan levels is recommended.</s><s>5. To prevent GVHD. in vivo T eel! depletion is recommended in all FA patients, including patients transplanted from an MSD.</s></p><p><s>Report.</s></p><p><s>6. Alemtuzumab is considered s uperior to ATC in FA patients because of its better GVHD prophylactic effect.</s><s>7.</s><s>In addition to anti-T cell antibody, CSA (day -1 until day + 100.</s><s>then taper ) is employed for GVHD prophylaxis.</s><s>MMF (day -1 to day+ 28. then taper ) is added to CSA in unrelated donors only.</s><s>Continuation or tapering of CSA and MMF is dependent on the presence or absence of GVHD.</s><s>8. Bone marrow is preferred as a stem cell source over PBSC because of its lower risk for GVHD.</s><s>9.</s><s>For matched ("?:9/1 O) PBSC grafts, lim itation of the total Teel! dose of the unmanipulated graft or exvivo reduction of the T cell dose may be considered to avoid GVH D. For m ismatched/ haploidentical (&lt;9/10) transplants.</s><s>for T cell depletion is mandatory.</s><s>10.</s><s>Haploidentical transplantation concepts in FA are under development; no specific concept can be favored over another at this time.</s><s>11.</s><s>Because CBT in FA is still evolving, unrelated cord blood as a stem cell source is not generally recommended for transplantation of FA patients at this time.</s><s>12.</s><s>Although most transplant experience stems from HSCTs conducted in children with FA. these recommendations are inte nded for pediatric and adult patients with the condition.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>al. in press ).</s><s>Long-term follow-up of FA patients indicate a 4.4 fold increased risk of developing head and neck sec after HSCT l59J.</s><s>associated with GVHD development and debatably radiation exposure I 15, 32,59J.</s><s>These challenges provide incentive for further improvements in FA HSCT.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>. The group agreed to continue with non-radiation protocols based on (a) established experience with non-radiation FA HSCT protocols.</s><s>(b) good results achieved with these protocols.</s><s>(c) potential to eliminate any possible short-and long-term toxicities associated with radiation, and (d) recent large FA HSCT reviews suggesting inferior survival for FA patients treated with radiationcontaining prepa rative regimens (3,55 ).</s><s>The backbone ~ Early FA HSCT conditioning regimens consisted of cyclophosphamide (200mg/kg) and radiation.</s><s>With increasing experience, there have been refinements to the conditioning regimens.</s><s>A 5-10 fold reduction in the cyclophosphamide dose was instituted.</s><s>Likewise, radiation was decreased in dose or eliminated.</s><s>Kapelushnik et al. were the first to report the use of fludarabine in FA HSCT (391.</s><s>Subsequently, numerous studies demonstrated that fludarabine accorded engraftment and survival benefits.</s><s>Currently, fludarabine based regimens are regarded as sta ndard in FA HSCTs [8, 14.65].</s><s>Dose reduction of fludarabine, however, is warranted in FA patients with renal compromise (personal communication with W. Ebell ).</s><s>Might there be additional modification(s) to the FA HSCT preparative regimens to further reduce RRTs?</s><s>In 2007.</s><s>Bonfim et al. reported on 43 FA patients who received transplants from HLA-matched related donors<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(11 )</ref>.</s><s>The conditioning regimen consisted of cyclophosphamide alone ( total dose 60mg/kg).</s><s>40 patients (93%) were alive with a median follow-up of 3.7 years.</s><s>One patient experienced primary graft failure and 4 patients developed late graft failure.</s><s>Grade 11-111 aGVHD and cGVHD were noted in 17 and 28.5 % of patients.</s><s>respectively<ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[ 11 )</ref>.</s><s>A recently completed phase I/ II study at Baylor College of Medicine in Houston.</s><s>Texas, USA examined alemtuzumab and anti-CD45 antibodies (YTH-24 and YTH-54) ( 10/ 10 HLA matched) or alemtuzumab, anti-CD45 antibodies, and fludarabine (9/10 HLA matched) conditioning in 5 pediatric patients with FA or other DNA breakage/chromosomal instability syndromes (5 I).</s><s>For HLA mismatched donors.</s><s>harvested peri pheral blood stem cells (PBSC) were enriched for CD34+cells<ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(51 )</ref>. 2 of the 5 participants showed donor engraftment at day + 100.</s><s>Median time to ANC &gt;500/mm 3 was 15 days.</s><s>No aGVHD grade II -IV or cGVHD was observed and all patients are alive at oneChao MM et al.</s><s>Consensus of German Transplant ... Klin Padiatr 2015; 227: 157-165 iii transplantation 151 ].</s><s>At Boston Children's Hospital.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig.1Recommended allogeneic he matopoietic stem cell transplanta • tion schema based on GEFA03.</s><s>•Omit busulfan for low risk patients defined as cytopenia without evidence of leukemia or cytogenetic aber• rations and with HLA ident ical donor (i.e.</s><s>"'9/10 MSD.</s><s>MRD. or MUD).</s><s>Busulfan levels recommended.</s><s>#Decrease alemtuzumab dose to 20mg/m2 in patients with MSD allografts (10/10) and only if BM is used as stem cell source.</s><s>In patients with MSD ( S9/l 0), unrelated donor, or PBSC grafts.</s><s>total ale mtuzumab dose should remain 30mg/m 2 • The total dose of conditioning drugs Is: fiudarabine l 80 mg/m 2 • IV busul• fan (Busilvex®) 1.6mg/kg.</s><s>cyclophosphamide40mg/kg. and alemtuzum• ab 30 mg/m 2 for MUD.</s><s>MMRD.</s><s>or PBSC (5 mg/m 2 days• 7 and• 6 followed by 10mg/m 2 days -5 and • 4) reduced to 20mg/m 2 for MSD (5mg/m 2 days• 7 and •6 followed by 10mg/m 2 day -5).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Spyridonidis A. Wascl1 R et al.</s><s>A novel GVHD-prophylaxis with low-dose alemtuzumab in allogeneic sibling or unrelated donor hematopoetic cell transplantation: the feasibility of deescalation.</s><s>Biology of blood and marrow transplantation: journal of the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation 2009; 15: 1563-1570 8 Bican M. Or R. Shapiro MY et al.</s><s>Fludarabine-based reduced intensity conditioning for stem cell transplantation of Fanconi anemia patients from fully matched related and unrelated donors.</s><s>Biology of blood and marrow transplantation: journal of the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation 2006; 12: 712-718 9 Bokhari S. Das-Gupta E. Russell Net al. Post-transplant lymphoproliferative disease following reduced intensity conditioning transplants incorporating alemtuzumab.</s><s>Bone marrow trans plantation 2008: 42: 281-282 10 Bonfim C. Ribeiro LL, Bitencourt Met al.</s><s>Long Term Follow up After with fludarabine based conditioning in multitransfused fanconi anemia patients w ho underwent peripheral blood stem cell transplantation.</s><s>journal of pediatric hematology/oncology 2009; 31: 5 12-515 72 Zecca M, Stroccl1io L, Pagliaro D era/.</s><s>HLA-haploidentical Tcell-depleted allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in children with Fanconi anemia.</s><s>Biology of blood and marrow transplantation: journal of the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation 2014; 20: 57 1-576 Chao MM et al.</s><s>Consensus of Ge rman Transplant ... Klin Padiatr 2015: 227: 157</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>11.4.12.</s><s>19, 34,46-48, 62,65, 67.70.71 ).</s></p></div></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 FA</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>HSCT results published over last S years.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>R~erence</cell><cell>Condit ioning</cell><cell>GVHO Proph y</cell><cell>No. of Cases</cell><cell>Med ian</cell><cell>Eng raft-</cell><cell>aGVHO</cell><cell>cGVHD</cell><cell>Survival</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Regi men</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Age</cell><cell>m ent'</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ayas et al. 201211 I</cell><cell>Cy, Flu, ATG</cell><cell>CSA</cell><cell>26 (19 MRD, 7 UCB)</cell><cell>7.8yrs</cell><cell>19/19.</cell><cell>1/19.</cell><cell>1/19.</cell><cell>100%,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2/7</cell><cell>1/7</cell><cell>1/7</cell><cell>43%0S</cell></row><row><cell>Shimada et al.</cell><cell>Cy, Flu, ATG</cell><cell>CSA, MTX;</cell><cell>8 (3 MSD, 1 MRD,</cell><cell>4.Syrs</cell><cell>8/8</cell><cell>1/8</cell><cell>0/8</cell><cell>100%0S</cell></row><row><cell>20121621</cell><cell></cell><cell>FK506, MTX</cell><cell>2 MUD, 2 MMUD)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Yabeetal. 20121701</cell><cell>Cy, ATG, TAl/TBI;</cell><cell>CSA, MTX</cell><cell>15(MSD)</cell><cell>8yrs</cell><cell>14/15</cell><cell>1/ 15</cell><cell>3/14</cell><cell>80%0S</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Cy, Flu, ATG</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Boulad et al.</cell><cell>Cy, Bu, Flu, ATG</cell><cell></cell><cell>27(AD)</cell><cell></cell><cell>27/27</cell><cell>3/27</cell><cell></cell><cell>83%0S</cell></row><row><cell>20121121</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>MacMillan et al.</cell><cell>Cy, ATG. TBI. ±Flu</cell><cell></cell><cell>127(AD)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>18-50%</cell><cell>9-25%</cell><cell>61% 1 yr</cell></row><row><cell>20121461</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>grade</cell><cell></cell><cell>POS; 54%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>II-IV</cell><cell></cell><cell>Syrs POS</cell></row><row><cell>Thaker et al. 2011 [671</cell><cell>Flu, TBI</cell><cell>CSA, MMF</cell><cell>6(AD)</cell><cell></cell><cell>5/6</cell><cell>4/6</cell><cell>3/5</cell><cell>50%0S</cell></row><row><cell>Stepensky et al.</cell><cell>Cy, ±TAI/</cell><cell>CSA; CSA. MMF;</cell><cell>41 (MSD,AD;</cell><cell>10.3yrs</cell><cell>17/17,</cell><cell>14/17,</cell><cell>4/17,</cell><cell>35%, 83%</cell></row><row><cell>2011 [651</cell><cell>TU, ±Bu, ±ATG;</cell><cell>Dae; CSA, Dae;</cell><cell>17 w/o Flu, 24 w/ Flu)</cell><cell></cell><cell>22/24</cell><cell>11/24</cell><cell>8/24</cell><cell>OS</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Flu ±Cy, ±Bu,</cell><cell>FK506, MMF,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>±ATG/Atgam, ±TBI</cell><cell>Dae</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Hamidieh et al.</cell><cell>Cy, Bu, ±ATG; Cy,</cell><cell>CSA±MTX</cell><cell>53 (MSD, MRD, MMRD;</cell><cell>9yrs</cell><cell>49/53</cell><cell>79%,</cell><cell>17%,</cell><cell>61%05</cell></row><row><cell>2011 [341</cell><cell>Flu,ATG</cell><cell></cell><cell>42 w/o Flu, 11 w/ Flu)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>45%</cell><cell>36%</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>MacMillan et al.</cell><cell>Cy. Flu. ATG</cell><cell></cell><cell>22 (MSD)</cell><cell>8.Syrs</cell><cell>22/22</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>0%</cell><cell>82%0$</cell></row><row><cell>2010 [48)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>MacMillan et al.</cell><cell>Cy, Flu, TBI, ATG</cell><cell>CSA</cell><cell>24 (AD; 22 w/ 3 Gy TBI,</cell><cell>8.Byrs</cell><cell>22/ 22,</cell><cell>3/22.</cell><cell></cell><cell>86%,</cell></row><row><cell>2009 [47 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2 w/ l.5GyTBI)</cell><cell></cell><cell>0/2</cell><cell>0/2</cell><cell></cell><cell>100%0$</cell></row><row><cell>Ertem et al. 2009 [ 191</cell><cell>Cy, Bu; Cy, Au, ATG</cell><cell>CSA, MTX</cell><cell>8(MSD)</cell><cell>12 yrs</cell><cell>8/8</cell><cell>0/8</cell><cell>1/8</cell><cell>87.5% OS</cell></row><row><cell>Baker et al. 2009141</cell><cell>Cy, Flu, ATG, ±Bu</cell><cell>CSA, MP</cell><cell>5(MRD. MUD)</cell><cell></cell><cell>4 /5</cell><cell>2/5</cell><cell>0/5</cell><cell>80%05</cell></row><row><cell>Yesilipek et al.</cell><cell>Cy. TAI, ATG; Cy,</cell><cell>CSA±MMF</cell><cell>16 (MRD. MUD;</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>50%. 90%</cell></row><row><cell>2009 (71)</cell><cell>Flu, ATG</cell><cell></cell><cell>6 TBI, 10 Flu)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>OS</cell></row></table><note><p><s>•. primary stable engraftment: Cy, cydophosphamide: Flu, fludarabine: ATG, anti•thymocyte globulin; CSA, cyclosporine A: MRD.</s><s>matched related donor: UCB, unrelated cord blood: OS. overall survival: POS.</s><s>probability of survival: MTX, methotrexate: MSD.</s><s>matched sibling donor; MUD, matched unrelated donor: MMUO.</s><s>mismatched unrelated donor: TAI.</s><s>total abdominal irradiation; TBI, total body irradiation; MMF, mycophenolate mofetil; TU, total lymphoid irradiation; Bu. busulfan; Dae.</s><s>daclizumab: MP: methylprednisolone tion has been omitted for MSD.</s><s>MUD, and mismatched unrelated donor FA HSCTs (excluding some haploidentical transplants).</s><s>In terestingly.</s><s>conflicting experimental and clinical data regarding the radiosensitivity of FA has emerged.</s><s>While Marcou et al. demonstrated normal colony survival assays in irradiated fibroblasts from a FA patient, Djuzenova et al. using the same patient's fibroblasts showed increased DNA damage after radiation exposure [ 16,49 I.</s><s>The patient experienced severe toxicities after radiotherapy for tonsillar carcinoma</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Boston.</s><s>Massachusetts.</s><s>USA 4 patients with dyskeratosis congenita were successfully transplanted with matched unrelated donor allografts ( ~ 9/10 HLA matched) using nudarabine and alemtuzumab 143).</s><s>All patients engrafted neutrophils by day + 30, and are alive and transfusion independent with a follow-up ranging from 6 months ( 1 patient) to 2 years (3 patients) 143].</s><s>All patients showed full donor myeloid chimerism by day +60.</s><s>3 of the 4 patients s howed full donor lymphoid chimerism by year 2, and the fourth patient has high and increasing mixed donor lymphoid chimerism at day + 180.</s><s>There was no aGVHD and only one patient developed limited cGVHD of the skin 143).</s><s>Whether nudarabine and alemtuzumab only preparative regimen might be effective in FA HSCT is yet to be established.</s><s>Based on these and other published data and the German experience.</s><s>particularly GEFA03, the consensus group agreed that nudarabine, cyclophosphamide.</s><s>and busulfan will continue as the backbone agents: however.</s><s>busulfan may be excluded in some transplants.</s><s>Busulfan is unlikely to be necessary for "low risk" transplants (i.e.</s><s>Relapse was more frequent with alemtuzumab and ATC ( 49 and 51 %, respectively, vs. 38 % unmanipulated, p &lt;0.001 ).</s><s>The 3-year probability of survival after adjusting for age, performance status, disease, disease status, CVHD prophylaxis, and donor source were SO% for alemtuzumab, 46% for T cell replete, and 38 % for ATC containing regimens.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>senius with OKT3 in the GEFA02 protocol and alemtuzumab in</cell></row><row><cell>the GEFA03 protocol. Comparison ofGEFA02 and GEFA03 results.</cell></row><row><cell>with the caveat that the backbone agents were not identical,</cell></row><row><cell>demonstrated more stable engraftment (5/18 vs. 0/21 graft fail-</cell></row><row><cell>ure or mixed chimerism requiring stem cell boost s), less fatal</cell></row><row><cell>viral infections (6/18 vs. 2/21 ), and a higher overall survival rate</cell></row><row><cell>(10/18 vs. 18/21) with GEFA03. Moreover, published reports in</cell></row><row><cell>other diseases and adult patients suggest superior outcomes</cell></row><row><cell>with alemtuzumab. Marsh et al. retrospectively compared pa-</cell></row><row><cell>tients with acquired SAA who were conditioned for allogeneic</cell></row><row><cell>HSCT with regimens including alemtuzumab (n = 100) or ATG</cell></row><row><cell>(n =55) [50]. Engraftment failure occurred in 9 and 11 % of pa-</cell></row><row><cell>tients in the alemtuzumab and ATG groups, respectively. The</cell></row><row><cell>5-year survival rate was 90% for alemtuzumab and 79% for ATG.</cell></row><row><cell>Overall survival was significantly better when using alemtu-</cell></row><row><cell>zumab (88 %) compared with ATG (57%, p =0.026) for unrelated</cell></row><row><cell>donor transplants. The risk for cGVHD was lower in the alemtu-</cell></row><row><cell>zumab group (11 vs. 26%, p =0.03 1) [50]. Similarly. Soiffer et al.</cell></row><row><cell>examined the outcomes of reduced intensity conditioning trans-</cell></row></table><note><p><s>~9/ 10 HLA matched related or unrelated HSCTs with BMF).Busulfan may be beneficial in FA patients with mismatched allografts to assist engraftment.and</s><s>as an anti-leukemic agent in FA patients with bone marrow clonal aberration(s) and/or MDS/AML.Intravenous busulfan is preferred over oral busulfan due to its more consistent pharmacokinetics.In vivo T cell depletion: Anti-thymocyte globulins vs. alemtuzumab ,, Both ATG(s) and alemtuzumab have been applied as in vivo T cell depleting agents in FA HSCTs to aid engraftment and to reduce the incidence and severity of GVHD.</s><s>Whether one lymphocyte-depleting antibody may be advocated over the other is difficult to answer, as there are no prospective direct comparison studies in FA.</s><s>Charite University Medicine Berlin used ATC-Freplants according to the use of in vivo T cell depletion with ATG (n=584).</s><s>alemtuzumab (n=213).</s><s>or no antibody therapy (n =879) in patients with hematopoietic malignancies 164 J.</s><s>Both grade 11-IV aGVHD and cCVHD incidences were lower with alemtuzumab compared with ATC and unmanipulated grafts (19 vs. 38 % for ATC and 40% for unmanipulated grafts.</s><s>p &lt;0.0001 and 24 vs. 40 % for ATG and 52 % for unmanipulated grafts, p&lt;0.0001.</s><s>respectively) 164].</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>-lOmg total dose) of alemtuzumab has been employed in allogeneic HSCT [3S.57].</s><s>Chakraverty et al. examined de-escalating doses of alemtuzumab in reduced intensity conditioning regimen with fludarabine and melphalan in 106 adult MSD transplants</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>64.5 vs. 27 days). the median time to</cell></row><row><cell>normal phytohemagglutinin response (2S3 vs. SS days). and the</cell></row><row><cell>median time to an antigen specific response (365 vs. 150 days )</cell></row><row><cell>occurred later in those receiving alemtuzumab in comparison to</cell></row><row><cell>patients given ATC [61 j. Despite these delays in immune recov-</cell></row><row><cell>ery, there was no increase in infectious complications in recipi-</cell></row><row><cell>ents of alemtuzumab 161 ].</cell></row><row><cell>Total lymphocyte and lymphocyte subset counts in peripheral</cell></row><row><cell>blood were evaluated in the 39 patients who received CEFA02</cell></row><row><cell>(ATC/OKT3) and CEFA03 (alemtuzumab) preparative regimens.</cell></row><row><cell>There was large patient-to-patient variability related to the clin-</cell></row><row><cell>ical circumstance of the patient: however, as a group, total lym-</cell></row><row><cell>phocyte counts steadily rose and by day + 100 the mean value</cell></row><row><cell>was 1166/µL NK cells were present at normal numbers immedi-</cell></row><row><cell>ately following transplantation and accounted for the majority</cell></row><row><cell>of lymphoid cells during the early post-transplant period. B cells</cell></row><row><cell>reached normal levels by day + 60. CDS+ cells recovered by 3</cell></row><row><cell>months. CD4+T cells were considerably slower to recover and</cell></row><row><cell>the CD4 +to CDS+ ratio remained &lt; 1 in the majority of patients</cell></row><row><cell>during the first year following transplantation. CD4 +reached</cell></row><row><cell>normal levels by day +365. Memory (CD45RO+) helper (CD4+)</cell></row><row><cell>and cytotoxic (CDS+ )Tcells predominated over nalve(CD45RA+)</cell></row><row><cell>T cells during the one-year analysis period. Comparison of</cell></row><row><cell>CEFA02 and CEFA03 immune reconstitution data showed mod-</cell></row><row><cell>estly higher lymphocyte values for CEFA03 patients that were</cell></row><row><cell>not statistically significant for most of the analyzed time points.</cell></row><row><cell>This pattern of post-transplantation immune reconstitution is</cell></row><row><cell>similar but not identical to reports by others [24, 56 ]. In FA pa-</cell></row><row><cell>tients following HSCT, Perlingeiro et al. found a slightly different</cell></row><row><cell>kinetic of recovery in the major lymphocyte subsets in 23 pa-</cell></row><row><cell>tients conditioned with one of 3 regimens (fludarabine. cyclo-</cell></row><row><cell>phosphamide and ATC, cyclophosphamide alone, or fludarabine</cell></row><row><cell>and irradiation) for related and unrelated donor transplants [56j.</cell></row><row><cell>NK cells were the first to recover, followed by cytotoxic CDS+ T</cell></row><row><cell>cells and B cells, and finally CD4+T cells. Early lymphocyte re-</cell></row><row><cell>covery consisted of memory cells potentially derived from the</cell></row><row><cell>graft. New thymic emigrant (CD31 +CD45RA+) and naive</cell></row><row><cell>CD4+or CDS+T cells rose only at 6 months after HSCT. Only</cell></row><row><cell>marginal differences were observed in the early recovery of</cell></row><row><cell>CDS+ T cells among those receiving a graft from a related donor</cell></row><row><cell>versus an unrelated donor. Patients with CVHD displayed a</cell></row><row><cell>markedly delayed recovery of NK cells and B cells as well as of</cell></row><row><cell>regulatory T cells and both early thymic emigrant and total</cell></row><row><cell>CD4 + T cells [56 ]. Nonetheless. viral infection represented a ma-</cell></row></table><note><p><s>jor complication following FA allogeneic transplantation [ 10j.</s><s>Indeed, in the Charite University Medicine Berlin cohort (n=39), viral reactivation/infection involving CMV.</s><s>human herpes virus 6, Epstein-Barr virus (EBV), adenovirus, and combined viral infections.</s><s>were the leading causes of death (8/11 ).</s><s>A logical response to improve post-transplant immune recovery may be to decrease the dose of alemtuzumab.</s><s>A wide range of doses (100</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>[57]rtz et al. reported no difference in grade Ill -IV aCVHD and extensive cCVHD or graft failure in 127 patients who received 10, 20, or 40mg (total dose) alemtuzumab for unrelated transplants[7].There was a significant difference in grade II-IV aCVHD incidence between the 20 and 40 mg dose cohorts[7].In summary, the standard total dose of 100 mg appears more than is required in most transplant settings.Doses of less than 30 mg may be insufficient and predispose to increased risks of CVHD[57], however, comparative analyses of data from published literature are difficult due to differences in patient populations.</s><s>diseases treated, and preparative regimens.</s><s>Still more, the clinical benefit (i.e.</s><s>decreased infections) is unclear.</s></p></div></figDesc><table /><note><p><s>Finally, Bokhari et al. reported increased incidence of EBV induced post-transplant lymphoproliferative disease (PTLD) following a reduction in alemtuzumab dose from 50 to 30mg [9].</s><s>For comparison, the alemtuzumab dose of 35 mg/m 2 ( 1.16 mg/ kg) used in CEFA03 resulted in a median total dose of 35 mg and mean total dose of 38mg (range 11-75mg</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>paternal haploidentical HSCT.</s><s>The patient received pre-transplantation therapy with low-dose cytarabine and developed prolonged aplasia and pulmonary aspergillosis.</s><s>The patient went on to receive a megadose of CD34+positively selected PBSC and granulocyte transfusions until engraftment after conditioning with cyclophosphamide.</s><s>fludarabine, and ATG.</s><s>She developed mild cGVHD involving her skin and is alive and well 15</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>years after transplantation. In Tuebingen. one FA patients re-</cell></row><row><cell>ceived a haploidentical transplants from a paternal grandmoth-</cell></row><row><cell>er. Here, the conditioning regimen included cyclophosphamide,</cell></row><row><cell>fludarabine. ATG, irradiation, and TCRaP/CDl 9 depletion of the</cell></row><row><cell>graft. The patient engrafted neutrophils and platelets. The pa-</cell></row><row><cell>tient developed grade I aGVHD but no cGVHD and is alive. Hap-</cell></row><row><cell>loidentical transplantation in FA is emerging as an alternative</cell></row><row><cell>therapy for some FA patients. There appears to be more experi-</cell></row><row><cell>ence using ATG in this setting. Concepts using post stem cell in-</cell></row><row><cell>fusion cyclophosphamide for T cell allodepletion are being de-</cell></row><row><cell>veloped for FA patients receiving mismatched allografts includ-</cell></row><row><cell>ing haploidentical transplants [66(.</cell></row><row><cell>Cord blood transplantation ...</cell></row><row><cell>Although the first successful related cord blood transplantation</cell></row><row><cell>(CBT) occurred in a patient with FA [26), there is a paucity of</cell></row><row><cell>information regarding FA patients and CBT. EBMT retrospective-</cell></row><row><cell>ly analyzed the results of unrelated cord blood transplantation</cell></row><row><cell>(UCBT) in 93 FA patients from 26 centers worldwide transplant-</cell></row><row><cell>ed between 1994 and 2005 [29(. The median age at transplanta-</cell></row><row><cell>.tion was 8.6 years. The majority of patients received an HLA mis-</cell></row><row><cell>matched cord blood allograft (1 HLA difference 35 cases and 2 or</cell></row><row><cell>3 HLA differences 45 cases). The median number of nucleated</cell></row><row><cell>cells and CD34+cells infused was 4.9x10 7 /kg and 1.9xl0 5 /kg,</cell></row><row><cell>respectively. The transplants were completed using varying pre-</cell></row><row><cell>parative regimens; 61 % of patients received fludarabine [29).</cell></row><row><cell>Cumulative incidence of neutrophil recovery was 60±5 % at</cell></row><row><cell>day +60. The incidence of grade II-IV aGVHD and cGVHD was</cell></row><row><cell>32±5% and 16±4%, respectively. Overall survival was 40±5%. In</cell></row><row><cell>multivariate analysis, factors associated with favorable outcome</cell></row><row><cell>were use of fludarabine in the conditioning regimen, ~4.9x10 7 /kg</cell></row><row><cell>nucleated cells infused, and negative recipient CMV serology</cell></row><row><cell>[29). More recent reports describe small institutional experi-</cell></row><row><cell>ences and demonstrate confli cting results. Ayas et al. reported</cell></row><row><cell>on 7 FA patients who received pa rtially matched unrelated cord</cell></row><row><cell>blood grafts. The patients were conditioned with cyclophospha-</cell></row><row><cell>mide (5 mg/kg/day for 4 days). fludarabine (3 0mg/m 2 /dose for 5</cell></row><row><cell>days). and rabbit ATC (5 mg/kg/day for 4 days) [ 1 j. The therapy</cell></row><row><cell>was generally well tolerated with mucositis and CMV viremia</cell></row><row><cell>representing major therapy-related complications I 1J.4 patients</cell></row><row><cell>failed to engraft and another patient had secondary graft failure</cell></row><row><cell>7 months post-transplantation. One patient developed grade II</cell></row><row><cell>aGVHD of t he skin that evolved to cGVHD. At last follow-up</cell></row><row><cell>ranging from 29 to 34 months, 3 patients are alive but only 2 are</cell></row><row><cell>transfusion independent [I). jaing et al. administered fludara-</cell></row><row><cell>bine (30mg/m/day for 6 days). cyclophosphamide (60mg/kg/</cell></row><row><cell>day for 2 days), and rabbit ATG (2.5 mg/kg/day for 3 days) in 3 FA</cell></row><row><cell>patients who received unmanipulated umbilical cord blood</cell></row><row><cell>altografts (36). None of the patients developed significant regi-</cell></row><row><cell>men related toxicity and all engrafted within 10-19 days [36(.</cell></row><row><cell>All patients are well with stable or full donor chim erism after a</cell></row><row><cell>median follow-up of 64 months [36). In summary, CBT in FA is</cell></row><row><cell>evolving.</cell></row></table><note><p><s>He eventually d ied of AML 8 years after the first transplantation.</s><s>At Hannover Medical School Children's Hospital, one FA patient with AML underwent Chao MM et al.</s><s>Consensus of German Transplant ... Klin Padiatr 2015; 227: 157-165 a</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>References 1 Ayas M. Al-Seraihi A. El-Solh H et al.</s><s>The Saudi experience in fludarabine-based conditioning regimens in patients with Fanconi anemia undergoing stem cell transplantation: excellent outcome in recipients of matched related stem cells but not in recipients of unrelated cord blood stem cells.</s><s>Biology of blood and marrow transplantation: journal of the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation 2012: 18: 627-632 2 Ayas M. Saber w.</s><s>Davies SM er al. Allogeneic hematopoietic cell transplantation for fanconi anemia in patients with pretransplantation cytogenetic abnormalities, myelodysplastic syndrome.</s><s>or acute leukemia.</s><s>j Clin Oncol 2013; 31: 1669-1676 3 Ayas M , Siddiqui K. Al-Jefri A et al.</s><s>Factors Affecting the Outcome of Related Allogeneic Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation in Patients with Fanconi Anemia.</s><s>Biology of blood and marrow transplantation: journal of the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation 2014.</s><s>doi: 10.1016/j.bbmt.2014.06.016 4 Baker JM.</s><s>Lewis VA, Fernandez CV et al.</s><s>Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation of patients with FA and high risk features using fludarabine without radiation Pediatr Blood Cancer 2009; 52: 683-685 5 Bastien JP, Roy J. Roy DC.</s><s>Selective T-cell depletion for haplotype-mismatched allogeneic stem cell transplantation.</s><s>Seminars in oncology 2012; 39: 674-682 6 Beaccy PG.</s><s>Clift RA.</s><s>Mickelson EM et al.</s><s>Marrow transplantation from related donors other than HLA-identical siblings.</s><s>The New England journal of medicine 1985; 313: 765-771 7 Berrz H.</s></p></div></figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements y</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HH are s upported by the Deutsche Kinderkrebsstiftung. The GEFA Registry is s upported by the Deutsche Fanconi Anamie Hilfe e</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="middle">Ck</forename><surname>Mmc</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">HH and CPK are supported by the Aktionskreis Fanconi-Anamie e. V. and the Fanconi-Anamie-Stiftung</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Conflict of interest: The authors have no conflict of interest to disclose</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Germ any Paed iatric Hematology and Oncology</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Germany Hematology/Onkology. Hannover Medical School</title>
		<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Affiliations Pediatric Hematolo gy/Oncology. Hannover Medical School. Hannover, Germany Pediatric Hematology/Oncology and Stem Cell Transplantatio n, Charite University Medicine Berlin, Berlin, Germany Zentrum fUr Kinder• und jugendmedizin, Klinikum der Johann-Wolfgang• Goethe-Universitat. Klinik Ill, Frankfurt, Germany Pediatric Hematology/Oncology, University of Muenster, Muenster, Germany Pediatric hematology/Oncology. University Children&apos;s Hospital Tuebingen, Tuebingen. Germany Department of Pediatrics, Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, IN, USA Department of Otorhinolaryngology and Head/Neck Surgery. Heinrich Heine University. Diisseldorf, Germany Institute of Cellular Therapeutics ; University of Essen, Essen. Germany Department of Pediatric Hematology Oncology, University of Diisseldorf Medical School, Diisseldorf. Germany Pediatric He matologie/Oncology, University Medical Center Hamburg•Eppendorf. Hamburg, Germany Childrens Hospitals, University ofWiirzburg, Germany Univ.•Klinik !Ur Kinder• und Jugendmedizin. Ulm. Germany Pediatric Hematolog y and Oncology. University Freiburg</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Medical Center</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Consensus of German Transplant ... Klin Padiatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">227</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="165" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation for Fanconi Anemia: Analysis of 126 Pts Surviving More Than 2 Years After Transplant</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ASH Annual Meeting Abstracts</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3079</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">HLA-matched related donor hematopoietic cell transplantation in 43 patients with Fanconi anemia conditioned with 60mg/kg of cyclophosphamide. Biology of blood and marrow transplantation: journal of the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bonjim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>De Medeiros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bicencourr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1455" to="1460" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemotherapy-Only Preparative Regimen for T-Cell Depleted Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation of Patients with Fanconi Anemia From Alternative Donors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Boulad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ASH Annual Meeting Abstracts</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3471</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of in vivo alemtuzumab dose before reduced intensity conditioning and HLA-identical sibling stem cell transplantation: pharmacokinetics. GVHD. and immune reconstitution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chakravercy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Orti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Roughton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3080" to="3088" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">HSCT for Fanconi anemia in children: factors that influence early and late results</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Daile</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bone marrow transplantation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="S51" to="S53" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scltoch Get al. Malignancies after marrow transplantation for a plastic anemia and fanconi anemia: a joint Seattle and Paris analysis of results in 700 patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Deeg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Socie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="386" to="392" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Radiation response in vitro of fibroblasts from a fanconi anemia patient with marked clinical radiosensitivity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Djuzenova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Plowman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Strahlenther Onkol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">180</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="789" to="797" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evolving strategies to address adverse transplant outcomes associated with T cell depletion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Drobyski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">journal of hematotherapy &amp; stem cell research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="327" to="337" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Feasibility and outcome of haploidentical SCT in pediatric high-risk hematologic malignancies and Fanconi anemia in Uruguay</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Dufort</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pisano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bone marrow transplantation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2012</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="663" to="668" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Related donor hematopoietic stem cell transplantation for Fanconi anemia without radiation: a si ngle center experience in Turkey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ertem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Jleri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Azik</forename><surname>Fetal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatr Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Consensus of German Transplant ... Klin Padiatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">227</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="165" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stem Cell Tranplantation in Fanconi Anemia -Recent Advances with Alternative Donors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eyrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Winkler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Schlegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Fanconi Anemia</title>
				<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Schindler</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hoelw</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="182" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Onset of thymic recovery and plateau of thymic output are differentially regulated after stem cell transplantation in children. Biology of blood and marrow transplantation: journal of the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eyriclr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wollny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tzaribaschev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="194" to="205" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bone marrow transplantation between a histocompatible parent and child for acute leukemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Falk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Herzog</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transplantation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="90" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Familial constitutional panmyelocytopathy, Fanconi&apos;s anemia (F.A.). I. Clinical aspects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Fanconi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Seminars in hematology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1967</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="240" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immune reconstitution following hematopoietic stem-cell transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Geddes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Starek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Best Pract Res Clin Haematol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="329" to="348" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Radiosensitivity in Fanconi anemia: application to the conditioning for bone marrow transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gluckman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Radiotherapy and oncology: journal of the European Society for Therapeutic Radiology and Oncology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="93" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hematopoietic n~con stitution in a patient with Fanconi&apos;s anemia by means of umbilicalcord blood from an HLA-identical sibling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gluckman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Broxmeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Auerbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The New England journal of medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">321</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1174" to="1178" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Radiosensitivity in Fanconi anaemia: application to the conditioning regimen for bone marrow transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gluckman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Devergie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">)</forename><surname>Dutreix</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br j Haematol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="431" to="440" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bone marrow transplantation in Fanconi anaemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gluckman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Devergie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Schaison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">British journal of haematology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="557" to="564" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Results of unrelated cord blood transplant in fanconi anemia patients: risk factor analysis for engraftment and survival. Biology of blood and marrow transplantation: journal of the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gluckman</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rocha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ionescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1073" to="1082" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">ESID Guidelines for Haematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation for Primary Immunodeficiencies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Eew</forename><surname>Group</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ebmt/</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.embt.org" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Outcome of 69 allogeneic stem cell transplantations for Fanconi anemia using HLA-matched unrelated donors: a study on behalf of the European Group for Blood and Marrow Transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Guardiola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pasquini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Dokal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="422" to="429" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acute graft-versus-host disease in patients with Fanconi anemia or acquired aplastic anemia undergoing bone marrow transplantation from HLA-identical sibling donors: risk factors and influence on outcome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Guardiola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Socie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Reduced-intensity conditioning and HLA-matched haemopoietic stem-cell transplantation in patients with chronic granulomatous disease: a prospective multicentre study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gungor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Teira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Slatter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">Lancet2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">383</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="436" to="448" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long-term results of non-fludarabine versus fludarabine-based stem ceU transplant.1tion without total body irradiation in Fanconi anemia patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hamidieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Alimoghaddam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jal1ani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hematol Oncol Stem Cell Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="109" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Negative depletion of CD3( +) and TcRalphabeta( +) T cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Handgretinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current opinion in hematology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="434" to="439" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Successful Hematopoietic Reconstitution by Unrelated Donor Cord Blood Transplantation in Children With Fanconi Anemia: Report of 3 Cases. journal of pediatric hematology/ oncology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Jaing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Clten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>l0.1097/mph.0000000000000215</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lack of sensitivity of primary Fanconi&apos;s anemia fibroblasts to UV and ionizing radiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kalb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Duerr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Radiat Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">161</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="318" to="325" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alemtuzumab for the prevention and treatment of graft-versus-host disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kanda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lopez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rizzieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International journal of hematology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="586" to="593" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A fludarabine-based protocol for bone marrow transplantation in Fanconi&apos;s anemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kapeluslwikj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Or</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Slavin</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bone marrow transplantation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1109" to="1110" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multivariate analyses of immune reconstitution in children after allo-SCT: risk-estimation based on age-matched leukocyte sub-populations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Koenig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Huenecke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Salzmann-Manrique</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bone marrow transplantation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="613" to="621" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A 20-year perspective on the International Fanconi Anemia Registry (IFAR)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">/</forename><surname>Kut</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Di</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sacagopanj</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1249" to="1256" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transplantation Of Tc Ra~/ CD19 Depleted Stem Cells From Haploidentical Donors In Children: Current Results</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lang</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Feuchtinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Teltschik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H-M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="692" to="692" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Full Donor Myeloid Engraftment with Minimal Toxicity in Dyskeratosis Congenita Patients Undergoing Allogeneic Bone Marrow Transplantation without Radiation or Alkylating Agents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Lehmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>London</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">56th ASH Annual Meeting and Exposition</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Negative depletion of alpha/ beta+T cells and of CD19+B lymphocytes: a novel frontier to optimize the effect of innate immunity in HLA-mismatched hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Locatelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bauquet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Palumbo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Immunology letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Haematopoietic cell transplantation in patients with Fanconi anaemia using alternate donors: results of a total body irradiation dose escalation trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Macmillan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Auerbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Haematol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternative Donor Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation for Patients with Fanconi Anemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Macmillan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Blazar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Defor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ASH Annual Meeting Abstracts</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3081</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternate Donor HCT for Fanconi Anemia (FA): Results of a Total Body Irradiation (TBI) Dose De-Escalation Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Macmillan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Blazar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Defor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biology of Blood and Marrow Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="4" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Haematopoeitic cell transplantation for Fanconi anaemia -when and how?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Macmillan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">)</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Haematol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">149</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Normal cellular radiosensitivity in an adult Fanconi anaemia patient with marked clinical radiosensitivity. Radiotherapy and oncology: journal of the European Society for Therapeutic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Marcou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>D'andrea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Radiology and Oncology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="79" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Retrospective study of alemtuzumab vs ATC -based conditioning without irradiation for unrelated and matched sibling donor transplants in acquired severe aplastic anemia : a study from the British Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Marsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pearce</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Koh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bone marrow transplantation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="42" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Antibody Conditioning Regimen for Allogeneic Donor Stem Cell Transplantation of Patients with Fanconi Anemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Medicine</forename><surname>Bco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New strategies for haploidentical transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Oevermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Handgretinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatric research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2012</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="418" to="426" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immune reconstitution and strategies for rebuilding the immu ne system after haploidentical stem cell transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Oevermarm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Feuchtinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="170" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">HLA-matched sibling hematopoietic stem cell transplantation for fanconi anemia: comparison of irradiation and nonirradiation containing conditioning regimens. Biology of blood and marrow transplantation: journal of the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pasquini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">)</forename><surname>Carreras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Pasquini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1141" to="1147" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in Fanconi anemia: the European Group for Blood and Marrow Transplantation experience</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Pejfault De Latour R</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Porcher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Daile</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">122</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4279" to="4286" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bonfim C et al Immune reconstitution in patients with Fanconi anemia after allogeneic bone marrow transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Perlingeiro</forename><surname>Beltrame</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Malvezzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cytotherapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="976" to="989" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alemtuzumab in allogeneic hematopoetic stem cell transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Poire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Van Besien</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Expert Opin Biol Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="1099" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mismatched family donors for bone-marrow transplantation as treatment for acute leukaemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Powles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Morgenstern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="612" to="615" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Risk of head and neck squamous cell cancer and death in patients with Fanconi anemia who did and did not receive t ransplants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rosenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Socie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Alter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Treatment of the bone marrow failure in Fanconi anemia patients with danazol</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Scheckenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Morgan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Filger-Brillinger J</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood Cells Mol Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="128" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The effects of Campath 1 H upon graft-versus-host disease, infection, relapse, and immune reconstitution in recipients of pediatric unrelated transplants. Biology of blood and marrow transplantation: journal of the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A)</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kapoor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Crooks</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="584" to="593" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Excellent outcome of allogeneic bone marrow transplantation for Fanconi anemia using fludarabine-based reduced-intensity conditioning regimen</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Shimada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Takahashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Muramatsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International journal of hematology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="675" to="679" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bone marrow transplantation for Fanconi anemia using low-dose cyclophosphamide/ thoracoabdominal irradiation as conditioning regimen: chimerism study by the polymerase chain reaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Socie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gluckman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">/</forename><surname>Rayna</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2249" to="2256" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of immune modulation with anti-T-cell antibodies on the outcome of reduced-intensity allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation for hematologic malignancies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Soijfer</forename><surname>Rj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">)</forename><surname>Lerademacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6963" to="6970" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bone marrow transplantation for Fanconi anemia using fludarabine-based conditioning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Scepensky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Shapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Balashov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biology of blood and marrow transplantation: journal of the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1282" to="1288" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cyclophosphamide-based in vivo T-cell depletion for HLA-haploidentical transplantation in fanconi anemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Thakar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bonfim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Sandmaier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatr Hematol Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="568" to="578" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Treatment of Fanconi anemia patients using fludarabine and low-dose TBI. followed by unrelated donor hematopoietic cell transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>T11akar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kurre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Storb</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bone marrow transplantation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="544" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unrelated donor bone marrow transplantation for the treatment of Fanconi anemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eapen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Macmillan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2256" to="2262" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ratajczak Pet al. Increased apoptosis is linked to severe acute GVHD in patients with Fanconi anemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Romero</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bone marrow transplantation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="849" to="853" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Matched sibling donor stem cell transplantation for Fanconi anemia patients with T-cell somatic mosaicism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Shimizu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Morimoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatr Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="340" to="345" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Better posttransplant outcome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Yesilipek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Karasu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kupesiza</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
