<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Targeting epithelial-mesenchymal transition</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-06-14">14 June 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Friedrich</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Luft</surname></persName>
							<email>luft@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Experimental and Clinical Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Charité Medical Faculty</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Max Delbrück Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Lindenbergerweg 80</addrLine>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Targeting epithelial-mesenchymal transition</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-06-14">14 June 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">ACEF4533970F17725F5C5A13E3134642</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00109-015-1302-2</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:35+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>The epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) is a process in which epithelial cells dedifferentiate to become mesenchymal cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s>The process requires them to lose their cell polarity, to relinquish their cell-cell adhesion, and to gain migratory and invasive properties.</s><s>The mesenchymal cells are multipotent stromal cells (mesenchymal stem cells) that can differentiate into various cell types.</s><s>EMT is essential for the developing embryo to enable mesoderm and neural tube formation.</s><s>EMT is also necessary for wound healing and other physiological processes.</s><s>On the other hand, EMT can also be an initiator for metastasis, cancer progression, organ fibrosis, and other pathological conditions.</s><s>These are disorderly processes.</s></p><p><s>The induction of EMT is complex (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>A fundamental event appears to be the loss of E-cadherin.</s><s>Transcription factors that can repress E-cadherin directly or indirectly are important to this process.</s><s>SNAI1/Snail 1, SNAI2/Snail 2 (also known as Slug), ZEB1, ZEB2, E47, and Krüppel-like factor-8 (KLF8) can repress E-cadherin transcription by binding to its promoter.</s><s>Indirect repressors, such as Twist, Goosecoid, TCF4 (sometimes referred to as immunoglobulin transcription factor 2), homeobox protein SIX1, and FOXC2 (fork-head box protein C2) are able to repress E-cadherin indirectly <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s>Other junction proteins, such as claudins and desmosomes, are also suppressed, facilitating EMT.</s><s>Various transcription factors such as grainyhead-like protein 2 homologue (GRHL2) and ETS-related transcription factors ELF3 and ELF5 are downregulated during EMT <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7]</ref>.</s><s>The induction of EMT is dependent on numerous signaling pathways including TGF-beta, FGF, EGF, HGF, Wnt/beta-catenin, Notch, and hypoxia-induced mechanisms.</s><s>Ras-MAPK signaling activates Snail and Slug during EMT induction.</s><s>Slug is involved in disrupting desmosomes, inducing cell spreading, and separating the cell-cell borders <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s><s>However, EMT involves a second phase that cannot be triggered by Slug.</s><s>This phase includes the induction of cell motility, repression of the cytokeratin expression, and activation of vimentin expression <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</s><s>Phosphatidylinositol 3′ kinase (PI3K)/AKT-axis activation is emerging as pivotal to EMT.</s><s>Similarly, hedgehog, nuclear factor-kappaB (NF-κB), and activating transcription factor-2 have been implicated <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s>Of course, the EMT processes are specific, so that while Wnt signaling pathways regulate EMT in embryonic development, cardiac valve formation, and cancer, other pathways are important to wound healing and fibrosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>EMT is central to two recent J Mol Med contributions.</s><s>Kimura et al. report on the attenuation of EMT in retinal pigment epithelial cells and subretinal fibrosis by a retinoic-acid receptor-gamma (RAR-γ) agonist <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s><s>The retinal pigment epithelium belongs the neural retina and is indispensable for vision.</s><s>In humans, proliferation and transformation (EMT switching) of retinal pigment epithelial cells after injury causes retinal disorders and loss of vision <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s><s>On the other hand, EMT could develop into a therapeutic target <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</s><s>Subretinal fibrosis contributes to the loss of vision associated with age-related macular degeneration (AMD), a devastating and common disease in older people.</s></p><p><s>The authors began with retinal epithelial cells in culture.</s><s>When subjected to TGF-β2, the cells expressed mesenchymal markers including α-smooth muscle actin and fibronectin.</s><s>The cells also released interleukin-6.</s><s>Paxillin was phosphorylated; MAPK constituents such as ERK, p38, and JNK were activated, as were Smad2 and AKT.</s><s>A RAR-γ agonist, R667, attenuated the EMT responses.</s><s>Furthermore, the cells treated with R667 no longer released matrix metalloproteinases.</s><s>The authors were successful in translating these cell-based findings to a mouse model of subretinal fibrosis.</s><s>The expression of glial fibrillary acidic protein was reduced in response to R667 injected into the subretinal space, as was the fibrosis area.</s><s>Interestingly, R667 is palovarotene, a highly selective RAR-γ agonist that is also under investigation as a potential treatment for emphysema, another chronic disease involving EMT <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Renal fibrosis is another condition in which EMT is implicated.</s><s>Similar to the EMT occurring in AMD, the EMT in fibrosis as well as in cancer is an anarchic cellular process actually developing at the expense of the whole organism <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</s><s>Kang et al. also first studied renal proximal tubular epithelial cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>.</s><s>The cells were subjected to high glucose concentrations (30 mmol/L).</s><s>E-cadherin expression was reduced, while vimentin, α-smooth muscle actin, fibroblast specific protein-1, matrix metalloproteinases, and collagen production were increased.</s><s>This state-of-affairs were improved considerably when the cells were exposed to 5,7dihydroxyflavone, better known as chrysin.</s><s>This Bhealth food^supplement has been used by body builders, rumored to raise testosterone levels, is claimed to be anti-inflammatory, and is claimed to be anxiolytic.</s><s>The authors next treated db/db mice.</s><s>The db/db mouse is a model of obesity, diabetes, and dyslipidemia.</s><s>Over time, the mice develop diabetic nephropathy.</s><s>The leptin receptor activity is deficient in db/db mice because the mice are homozygous for a point mutation in the gene for the leptin receptor.</s><s>Chrysin administration to the mice decreased collagen production in the kidneys.</s><s>Furthermore, chrysin treatment reduced tubular-cell migration concurrent with decreased matrix metalloproteinase-2 activity.</s><s>These effects indicated less epithelial cell derangement and tubular basement membrane disruption.</s><s>The compound appeared to restore tight junction proteins and to inhibit EMTmediated tubulointerstitial fibrosis.</s></p><p><s>Sounds quite good but how much does EMT really contribute to this model?</s><s>The contribution of EMT to the formation of renal fibrosis has been debated in several lineagetracing studies, with conflicting findings.</s><s>Different disease models, the mouse strains, and type of genetic alteration used could confound results.</s><s>To determine the contribution of these factors to EMT, Inoue et al. generated four kidney disease models in several mouse strains genetically modified to express enhanced green fluorescence protein (EGFP) in cortical tubular epithelial cells under the control of the γ-glutamyl transpeptidase promoter <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>.</s><s>The approach allowed them to visualize EMT and quantify EMT-related effects based on a count of EGFP-positive interstitial cells in the fibrotic kidney sections of the four renal disease models that they could then</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Epithelial cells Mesenchymal cells</head><p><s>Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> The effector molecules regulate the different stages epithelialmesenchymal transition (EMT) and the reverse process, mesenchymalepithelial transition (MET).</s><s>The regulation of the tight junctions and the adherent junctions are crucial.</s><s>Epithelial (E)-cadherin, extracellular matrix (ECM), fibroblast-growth-factor receptor-2 (FGF-2), fibroblastspecific protein-1 (FSP-1), microfilaments (MF), and numerous other molecules are pivotal.</s><s>Physiological transitions are orderly; nonphysiological transitions are not.</s><s>Adapted from <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> classify to be either EMT-prone or -resistant.</s><s>The EMT-prone models were unilateral ureteral obstruction and ischemic nephropathy in SJL mice.</s><s>The EMT-resistant models consisted of ureteral obstruction in C57B/6 and F1(C57B/6×SJL) mice, adriamycin nephrosis in 129 mice, and nephrotoxic serum nephritis in SJL mice.</s><s>Analyses of these renal disease models suggested that EMT-derived fibroblasts arose in a diseasespecific and strain-dependent manner.</s><s>Thus, when considering molecular mechanisms and involvement of the EMT in renal fibrosis, the authors suggest that taking experimental conditions, particularly the mouse strain and type of disease model, is important.</s><s>Before we can accept the idea that RXR-g agonists or chrysin specifically act by inhibiting EMT, the role of EMT in these models should be more precisely defined.</s></p><p><s>Respectfully, Friedrich C. Luft</s></p></div>			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">J Mol Med (2015) 93:703-705</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epithelialmesenchymal transitions in development and disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Thiery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Acloque</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nieto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="871" to="890" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epithelial-mesenchymal transitions in development and disease: old views and new perspectives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nieto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Dev Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1541" to="1547" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epithelial-mesenchymal transitions: the importance of changing cell state in development and disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Acloque</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Fishwick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bronner-Fraser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nieto</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JCI</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1438" to="1449" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Complex networks orchestrate epithelial-mesenchymal transitions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Thiery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Sleeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Zeb and bhlh factors in tumour progression: an alliance against the epithelial phenotype?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Peinado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Olmeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Snail</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="415" to="428" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulatory networks defining emt during cancer initiation and progression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>De Craene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Berx</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Elf5 inhibits the epithelial-mesenchymal transition in mammary gland development and breast cancer metastasis by transcriptionally repressing snail2</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chakrabarti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andres</forename><surname>Blanco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lukacisin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Romano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Smalley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Ibrahim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1212" to="1222" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The zinc-finger protein slug causes desmosome dissociation, an initial and necessary step for growth factor-induced epithelial-mesenchymal transition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Savagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Yamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Thiery</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1403" to="1419" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rearrangements of desmosomal and cytoskeletal proteins during the transition from epithelial to fibroblastoid organization in cultured rat bladder carcinoma cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Boyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Tucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Valles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Franke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Thiery</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1495" to="1509" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epithelial-mesenchymal transition: Nf-kappab takes center stage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Huber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Beug</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wirth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Cycle</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1477" to="1480" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epithelial mesenchymal transition: a double-edged sword</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Barriere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Fici</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gallerani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fabbri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rigaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Transl Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attenuation of EMT in RPE cells and subretinal fibrosis by an RAR-γ agonist</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Orita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tokuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kurakazu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Noda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yanai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Morishige</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Takeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00109-015-1289-8</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Mol Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The retinal pigment epithelium: an important player of retinal disorders and regeneration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chiba</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp Eye Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Blockade of jagged/notch pathway abrogates transforming growth factor beta2-induced epithelial-mesenchymal transition in human retinal pigment epithelium cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Mol Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="523" to="534" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recent advances in understanding inflammation and remodeling in the airways in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sohal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Danial</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wood-Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Walters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Expert Rev Respir Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="275" to="288" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emt-met in renal disease: should we curb our enthusiasm?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Galichon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Finianos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hertig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">341</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chrysin inhibits diabetic renal tubulointerstitial fibrosis through blocking epithelial to mesenchymal transition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M-K</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S-H</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y-J</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Shin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y-H</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00109-015-1301-3</idno>
		<idno>doi:10.1007/ s00109-015-1301-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Mol Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The contribution of epithelial-mesenchymal transition to renal fibrosis differs among kidney disease models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Inoue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Umezawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Takenaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Okada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Kidney Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
