<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Sensitivity Comparison of 68 Ga-OPS202 and 68 Ga-DOTATOC PET/CT in Patients with Gastroenteropancreatic Neuroendocrine Tumors: A Prospective Phase II Imaging Study</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Guillaume</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nicolas</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Nuclear Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Basel</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Neuroendocrine and Endocrine Tumors</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Basel</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nils</forename><surname>Schreiter</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Nuclear Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Medwave Medical Imaging</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Rotterdam</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Felix</forename><surname>Kaul</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Nuclear Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Basel</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Neuroendocrine and Endocrine Tumors</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Basel</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Uiters</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Medwave Medical Imaging</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Rotterdam</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Syneed Medidata</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Konstanz</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hakim</forename><surname>Bouterfa</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">OctreoPharm Sciences GmbH</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Ipsen Group</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jens</forename><surname>Kaufmann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">OctreoPharm Sciences GmbH</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Ipsen Group</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tobias</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Erlanger</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Clinical Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Clinical Trial Unit</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Basel</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Cathomas</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Oncology/Hematology Kantonsspital Graubünden</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Chur</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Emanuel</forename><surname>Christ</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Neuroendocrine and Endocrine Tumors</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Basel</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="institution">Inselspital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bern</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Melpomeni</forename><surname>Fani</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Nuclear Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Basel</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Radiopharmaceutical Chemistry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Basel</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Damian</forename><surname>Wild</surname></persName>
							<email>damian.wild@usb.ch</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Nuclear Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Basel</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Neuroendocrine and Endocrine Tumors</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Basel</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff10">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Nuclear Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Basel</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Petersgraben 4</addrLine>
									<postCode>CH-4031</postCode>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Sensitivity Comparison of 68 Ga-OPS202 and 68 Ga-DOTATOC PET/CT in Patients with Gastroenteropancreatic Neuroendocrine Tumors: A Prospective Phase II Imaging Study</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">18B32D67D9F92CE67CCA7DE5BE28061B</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.2967/jnumed.117.199760</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received Jul. 25, 2017; revision accepted Nov. 3, 2017.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:35+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>See an invited perspective on this article on page 907.</s></p><p><s>Radiolabeled somatostatin (sst) receptor agonists are integral to the diagnosis of gastroenteropancreatic neuroendocrine tumors (NETs), but detection rates, especially of liver metastases, remain limited even with PET/CT. 68</s><s>Ga-OPS202 ( 68 Ga-NODAGA-JR11; NODAGA 5 1,4,7-triazacyclononane,1-glutaric acid-4,7-acetic acid and JR11 5 Cpa-c(DCys-Aph(Hor)-DAph(Cbm)-Lys-Thr-Cys)-DTyr-NH 2 )), a novel radiolabeled sst receptor antagonist with a high affinity for the sst 2 receptor, has the potential to perform better than sst receptor agonists.</s><s>Here, we present the results of the phase II component of a phase I/II study that evaluated the sensitivity of 68 Ga-OPS202, compared with the reference compound, 68 Ga-DOTATOC (an sst receptor agonist), in PET imaging.</s><s>Methods: Patients received a single 150-MBq intravenous injection of 68 Ga-DOTATOC (15 μg of peptide) and 2 single 150-MBq intravenous injections of 68 Ga-OPS202 (15 μg of peptide at visit 1 and 50 μg at visit 2).</s><s>Wholebody PET/CT acquisitions were performed 1 h after injection on the same calibrated PET/CT scanner.</s><s>Diagnostic efficacy measures were compared against contrast medium-enhanced CT or MRI as the gold standard.</s><s>Two independent masked experts read the scans, and both outcomes were combined for analysis.</s><s>Results: Twelve consecutive patients with low-or intermediate-grade gastroenteropancreatic NETs took part in this prospective study.</s><s>Image contrast for matched malignant liver lesions was significantly higher for the 68 Ga-OPS202 scans than for the 68 Ga-DOTATOC scan: the median of the mean tumor-to-background SUV max ratios were significantly higher for 15 and 50 μg of 68 Ga-OPS202 (5.3 and 4.3, with interquartile ranges of 2.9-5.7 and 3.4-6.3</s><s>and P values of 0.004 and 0.008) than for 68 Ga-DOTATOC (1.9, with an interquartile range of 1.4-2.9).</s><s>The higher tumor-to-background ratio of 68 Ga-OPS202 resulted not only in a higher detection rate of liver metastases but also in a significantly higher lesion-based overall sensitivity with the antagonist than with 68 Ga-DOTATOC: 94% and 88% for 50 and 15 μg of 68 Ga-OPS202, respectively, and 59% for 15 μg of 68 Ga-DOTATOC (P , 0.001).</s><s>Positive predictive values for 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT and 68 Ga-DOTATOC PET/CT were similar (∼98%).</s><s>There were no significant differences in image contrast, sensitivity, or positive predictive values between the 2 68 Ga-OPS202 peptide doses, indicating a high reproducibility.</s><s>Conclusion: Preliminary diagnostic efficacy data from this phase II study indicate that 68 Ga-OPS202 has high sensitivity for the detection of gastroenteropancreatic NETs.</s><s>Further studies in larger patient populations are warranted.</s></p><p><s>Key Words: neuroendocrine tumors; somatostatin receptor antagonist; 68 Ga-OPS202; 68 Ga-NODAGA-JR11; 68 Ga-DOTATOC J Nucl Med 2018; 59:915-921 DOI: 10.2967/jnumed.117.199760</s></p><p><s>Gast roenteropancreatic neuroendocrine tumors (NETs) are the most frequent neuroendocrine neoplasms, accounting for approximately two thirds of all neuroendocrine neoplasms.</s></p><p><s>Molecular imaging of NETs facilitates not only earlier diagnosis but often also detection of the primary tumor site, which is unknown in approximately 20%-30% of cases <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</s><s>Molecular imaging of NETs also aids in selection of the most appropriate therapy, thus improving outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>.</s><s>For many years, imaging with somatostatin (sst) receptor scintigraphy and SPECT has been central to the diagnostic work-up of patients with NETs (3).</s><s>More recently, it has been shown that PET/CT scanning with 68 Ga-labeled sst receptor agonists is superior to scanning with 111 In-or 99m Tc-labeled sst analogs (4).</s><s>This difference reflects the greater sensitivity and spatial resolution of PET/CT, as well as the higher affinity of 68 Ga radiopharmaceuticals for the sst subtype 2 (sst 2 ) receptor <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6)</ref>. 68</s><s>Ga production is also costeffective, because portable 68 Ge/ 68 Ga generators are available, allowing access to radioisotopes without the need for an onsite cyclotron.</s><s>Another advantage of PET/CT over SPECT/CT is that it better quantifies absolute tumor uptake.</s><s>Although 68 Ga-DOTATOC PET/CT has very high sensitivity versus conventional 111 In-pentetreotide (Octreo-Scan; Mallinckrodt, Inc.), the detection rate of liver metastases and the overall sensitivity were lower for 68 Ga-DOTATOC PET/CT than for hepatic-phase MRI in a lesion-based analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8)</ref>.</s><s>This lack of sensitivity is an issue when it comes to planning surgery and liverdirected therapies.</s><s>Thus, there remains a clinical need for further improvement of sst receptor imaging in patients with NETs.</s></p><p><s>The introduction of 68 Ga-labeled sst receptor antagonists has the potential to improve NET imaging, as more receptor binding sites are bound by sst receptor antagonists than by sst receptor agonists <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>.</s><s>The feasibility of using a radiolabeled antagonist ( 111 In-DOTA-BASS) was demonstrated in patients with NETs (n 5 4) or metastatic thyroid cancer (n 5 1) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref>.</s><s>Indeed, compared with traditional 111 In-pentetreotide scintigraphy, 111 In-DOTA-BASS imaging was more sensitive.</s><s>However, 111 In-DOTA-BASS has a low affinity for the sst 2 receptor, which is the most common sst receptor subtype expressed by NETs <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>.</s><s>Therefore, a series of radiolabeled sst receptor antagonists with higher affinity for the sst 2 receptor was developed <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>.</s><s>Among them, we selected 68 Ga-OPS202 ( 68 Ga-NODAGA-JR11; NODAGA 5 1,4,7-triazacyclononane,1-glutaric acid-4,7-acetic acid and JR11 5 Cpa-c(DCys-Aph (Hor)-DAph(Cbm)-Lys-Thr-Cys)-DTyr-NH 2 )) as the radioligand of choice on the basis of its potential for imaging NETs <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>.</s><s>The corresponding therapeutic radiotracer, 177 Lu-OPS201 ( 177 Lu-DOTA-JR11), for a theranostic approach was associated with tumor doses that were 1.7-to 10.6-fold higher than those observed with the sst receptor agonist 177 Lu-DOTATATE in 4 patients with metastasized NETs <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Our study of 68 Ga-OPS202 in humans was designed to evaluate its safety, biodistribution, and dosimetry (phase I) and its preliminary diagnostic efficacy (phase II) in patients with gastroenteropancreatic NETs.</s><s>The results of phase I of the study, which are summarized in an accompanying paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>, show that there were no safety concerns with 68 Ga-OPS202 and that the mean effective dose (6SD) was 3.6 6 0.3 mSv/150 MBq.</s><s>For the phase II component of the study, our hypothesis was that 68 Ga-OPS202 would be a more sensitive agent than 68 Ga-DOTATOC for diagnosis of gastroenteropancreatic NETs on PET/CT, with a high positive predictive value (PPV).</s><s>The results presented in this article follow the Standards for Reporting Diagnostic Accuracy 2015 statement, which is shown in the supplemental material (supplemental materials are available at http://jnm.snmjournals.org).</s><s>Hormonal status was defined by either presence of clinical features typical of secretory syndrome (e.g., carcinoid syndrome) or by presence of hormones or their catabolites in serum or urine.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MATERIALS AND METHODS</head><p><s>The methodology of the study (ClinicalTrials.gov</s><s>identifier NCT02162446; EudraCT no.</s><s>2014-001881-88) is described in detail in the accompanying paper about phase I of the study <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>.</s><s>The institutional review board approved this study, and all subjects signed a written informed consent form in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Design and Patient Population</head><p><s>This was a prospective, open-label, microdosing phase I/II study.</s><s>Consecutive patients with a histologically confirmed well-differentiated low-or intermediate-grade gastroenteropancreatic NET were included if they had positive results on a 68 Ga-DOTATOC scan in the previous 6 mo.</s><s>Patients were excluded if they had received NET-specific treatments between the 68 Ga-DOTATOC scan and the start of the study, except for sst analogs, provided there was a sufficient washout period (28 d for long-acting somatostatin analogs and 2 d for short-acting somatostatin analogs).</s><s>Potentially eligible patients were identified by the date of their last or planned 68 Ga-DOTATOC scan in our clinic (between January and November 2014) and consultation of their medical records.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Synthesis and Radiolabeling</head><p><s>After elution from the 68 Ge/ 68 Ga generator, 68 Ga was extracted using cation exchange.</s><s>OPS202 and DOTATOC were labeled at 75°C and 95°C, respectively, within 400 s, followed by C18 solidphase extraction to achieve purity of at least 95%.</s><s>Greater detail can be found in the Materials and Methods section of the accompanying paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Imaging</head><p><s>The first administration of 68 Ga-OPS202 (visit 1) was 15 mg/150 MBq 6 25% intravenously over no longer than 1 min (the actual mean administered amount of peptide was 14 6 4 mg [range, 11-19 mg], and the actual mean administered activity was 161 6 21 MBq [range, 125-189 MBq]).</s><s>At 3-4 wk later, the patients received a second administration of 68 Ga-OPS202 (visit 2).</s><s>This second administration was 50 mg/150 MBq 6 25% (the actual mean administered amount of peptide was 50 6 15 mg [range, 37-63 mg], and the actual mean administered activity was 172 6 14 MBq [range, 141-192 MBq]). 68</s><s>Ga-DOTATOC was administered up to 6 mo before 68 Ga-OPS202 (15 6 5 mg/161 6 11 MBq).</s><s>Except for diuretics, use of other medication on scan days was permitted.</s></p><p><s>Three-dimensional whole-body (head to subinguinal region) PET scans were obtained 1 h after injection of 68 Ga-OPS202 and 68 Ga-DOTATOC using the same PET/CT scanner for imaging with both tracers (Discovery STE; GE Healthcare).</s><s>Calibration and quality assurance were performed according to the EARL (European Association of Nuclear Medicine Research Ltd.) procedure.</s><s>Greater detail can be found in the Materials and Methods section of the accompanying paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>.</s><s>At 3-9 mo after the end of the core trial, referring centers performed follow-up imaging using either contrast-enhanced triple-phase multidetector CT or 1.5-or 3-T MRI with a dedicated body array coil for signal reception.</s><s>The pulse sequence requirements for MRI comprised, minimally, axial and coronal T2-weighted sequences and axial multiphasic T1-weighted gradient-echo sequences before and after administration of a gadolinium-based contrast agent.</s><s>Additional, optional, pulse sequences included diffusion-weighted imaging and delayed T1-weighted imaging if a hepatobiliary contrast agent was used.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Image Analysis</head><p><s>Both 68 Ga-OPS202 scans (15 and 50 mg) and the 68 Ga-DOTATOC scan were reviewed by 2 independent, qualified readers, one of whom was on-site (a board-certified nuclear medicine physician  from University Hospital Basel) and the other central (a boardcertified radiologist and nuclear medicine physician).</s><s>Both were masked to the patient, radiopharmaceutical, and peptide dose.</s><s>A sequential locked-read methodology was used for image interpretation; that is, once scans had been reviewed and completed, readers were not permitted to reread them and modify their opinion.</s><s>As an image-reading tool, Mint Lesion (Mint Medical GmbH), was used by both readers.</s><s>The diagnostic efficacy measure was the absolute number of malignant lesions detected.</s><s>Two additional measures were part of an exploratory extension and not part of the original design: SUV max for tumors and reference tissues, and mean tumor-to-background uptake ratio (SUV max of tumor to SUV max of reference tissue).</s><s>The reference tissues were muscle, liver, and lymph nodes, as well as normal tissue near a suspected focus of uptake.</s><s>For each of these measures, the results for the 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT scans (15 and 50 mg) were compared with, as a reference, the results for the 68 Ga-DOTATOC PET/CT scan, which is an accepted state-of-the-art imaging modality for gastroenteropancreatic NETs worldwide.</s><s>SUV max and tumor-to-background ratio were analyzed for matched lesions only (i.e., only lesions that were present not only on the 68 Ga-DOTATOC scan but also on both 68 Ga-OPS202 scans).</s><s>In addition, the 68 Ga-OPS202 scan at visit 1 was compared with the 68 Ga-OPS202 scan at visit 2 to evaluate the reproducibility of tumor uptake, image contrast (tumor-to-background ratios), and sensitivity measurements.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sensitivity and PPV</head><p><s>For sensitivity and PPV analyses, the scans for both 68 Ga-OPS202 doses and for 68 Ga-DOTATOC were compared with up to 9 mo of clinical and imaging follow-up after the end of the core trial by the central reader.</s><s>As a standard of reference, multiple-phase abdominal CT, contrast-enhanced MRI of the liver, or, in one case, biopsy was used for comparison.</s><s>Sensitivity and PPV analyses were part of an exploratory extension and not part of the original study design.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Analysis</head><p><s>It was planned to recruit 12 patients for this phase I/II study.</s><s>This number was considered appropriate for an exploratory study and sufficient to address the study aim.</s><s>Data are median SUV max for normal-organ uptake and median of mean SUV max for tumor uptake and tumor-to-liver ratio, all followed by interquartile range in parentheses.</s><s>Data in this table were acquired as part of extension study and are not part of original study design.</s></p><p><s>P values are for comparisons with 68 Ga-DOTATOC.</s><s>*For comparisons between 15-and 50-μg 68 Ga-OPS202, significant difference was found for physiologic uptake in intestine (P 5 0.032); trend close to statistical significance was found for liver and pancreas (P 5 0.062 and 0.053, respectively); and no significant difference was found for liver lesions, extrahepatic lesions, all lesions, or tumor-to-liver ratio (P 5 0.359, 0.156, 0.186, and 0.547, respectively).</s><s><ref type="figure">E, and F</ref>. PET/CT studies were performed on same scanner within 2 mo of each other and were read using same gray scale (maximal-intensity projections, A and C) and color scale (transaxial fusion images, B and D).</s><s>Findings were correlated with liver MRI performed 4 mo after 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT, with delayed postcontrast acquisitions (E) and diffusion-weighted images (F) confirming additional metastases missed or questionable (arrow with question mark) on 68 Ga-DOTATOC PET/CT.</s><s>Importantly, background activity was lower in liver, intestine, and thyroid with 68 Ga-OPS202 than with 68 Ga-DOTATOC (e.g., for liver, mean SUV max was 2.6 vs. 10.2).</s><s>Repeated thyroidectomy for benign goiter failed to demonstrate malignancy of left thyroid nodule.</s></p><p><s>The nonparametric Wilcoxon signed-rank test was used to compare number of identified lesions, SUV max for lesions and reference tissues, and tumor-to-background ratio between the reference 68 Ga-DOTATOC scan and the visit 1 and 2 68 Ga-OPS202 scans.</s><s>Matched data from the on-site reader were used for the quantitative analysis of SUVs (median of the mean).</s></p><p><s>For the lesion-based sensitivity and PPV analyses, the outcomes from the on-site and central readers were considered to fit a mixedeffects logistic regression model.</s><s>For exposure variables, it was assumed that the scan method was a fixed effect and the patient and reader were random effects.</s><s>Three tests of superiority were performed, 68 Ga-DOTATOC versus 15-mg 68 Ga-OPS202, 68 Ga-DOTATOC versus 50-mg 68 Ga-OPS202, and 15-mg 68 Ga-OPS202 versus 50-mg 68 Ga-OPS202.</s><s>To assess whether the results were robust, the outcomes of only the on-site reader were compared with the outcomes of both readers.</s><s>Statistical testing was exploratory.</s><s>The level of significance was set at 5%, and tests were 2-sided.</s><s>Indeterminate and missing values were not replaced.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patients</head><p><s>The study profile is given in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</s><s>Of the 12 patients screened, all 12 were enrolled; completed the phase I dosimetry, pharmacokinetic, and safety evaluation; and were included in this phase II diagnostic efficacy evaluation.</s><s>Baseline demography and disease characteristics are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s><s>The median time between the 68 Ga-DOTATOC scan and the first 68 Ga-OPS202 scan (visit 1, 15 mg) was 34 d (interquartile range, 27.5-135 d).</s><s>One patient underwent the 68 Ga-DOTATOC scan 16 d after visit 1.</s><s>Both the 68 Ga-OPS202 and the 68 Ga-DOTATOC scans revealed disease in 11 of 12 patients.</s><s>Follow-up imaging confirmed that patient 11 was in complete remission.</s><s>Patients did not receive any treatments between the 68 Ga-DOTATOC and the 68 Ga-OPS202 scans.</s><s>Eleven adverse effects were reported in 6 patients after injection of 68 Ga-OPS202, but none were severe, serious, or fatal.</s><s>More information can be found in the accompanying paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>. 68</s><s>Ga-OPS202 Versus 68 Ga-DOTATOC</s></p><p><s>The total number of malignant lesions and liver lesions was significantly greater with 68 Ga-OPS202 than with 68 Ga-DOTATOC (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>).</s><s>The scans did not significantly differ in the number of malignant lymph nodes found.</s><s>Because only a few patients had lesions in other organs or tissues, statistical comparisons were not feasible.</s></p><p><s>Image contrast (tumor-to-background ratio) for matched malignant liver lesions was significantly higher with 68 Ga-OPS202 than with 68 Ga-DOTATOC (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>; Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>), mainly because of the significantly lower SUV max of liver background (Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3 and 4</ref>) in the 68 Ga-OPS202 scans (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>).</s><s>For matched malignant lymph nodes, there were no significant differences in the median of the mean tumor-to-background ratio between the 68 Ga-OPS202 scans and the 68 Ga-DOTATOC scan, regardless of the reference tissue.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sensitivity and PPV</head><p><s>Outcome analyses for both readers revealed a significantly higher lesion-based sensitivity for both 15 and 50 mg of 68 Ga-OPS202 than for 68 Ga-DOTATOC (P , 0.001 for both) (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref>; Figs. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3 and 4</ref>).</s><s>There was also a significant difference in sensitivity between 15 mg and 50 mg of 68 Ga-OPS202 (P , 0.05), but this significance was not confirmed in the assessment of robustness  68 Ga-DOTATOC scan.</s><s>Mean liver SUV max was 4.6 and 4.7 for 15 and 50 μg of 68 Ga-OPS202, respectively, and 5.6 for 68 Ga-DOTATOC.</s><s>Although 68 Ga-DOTATOC and both 68 Ga-OPS202 scans showed ileal primary, mesenteric malignant mass, and multiple liver metastases (black arrows), 68 Ga-OPS202 scans detected significantly more liver metastases (white arrows).</s><s>Head-to-head comparison with MRI performed 7 mo after 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT confirmed that suggestive findings were true-positive only on 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT (white arrows).</s><s>(P 5 0.76)-that is, if the analysis were done using on-site readings only.</s><s>The PPVs for all 3 tested PET tracers were around 98%.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>To our knowledge, this was the first study to evaluate the diagnostic efficacy of a radiolabeled sst receptor antagonist, 68 Ga-OPS202, for PET/CT imaging of gastroenteropancreatic NETs.</s><s>Of key importance are the results compared with the reference sst receptor agonist PET/CT scan, which was conducted using 68 Ga-DOTATOC.</s><s>Multiple-phase CT of the abdomen and contrastenhanced MRI of the liver were performed during follow-up.</s><s>These are the most accurate methods for establishing the presence or absence of neuroendocrine liver metastases (3) and were chosen as the standards of reference.</s><s>They show that 68 Ga-OPS202 is more sensitive than 68 Ga-DOTATOC (88%-94% vs. 59%), mainly because of a higher detection rate of metastases in the liver, the predominant site of metastasis in patients with gastroenteropancreatic NETs ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>).</s><s>This higher detection of liver metastases reflects the significantly lower uptake of 68 Ga-OPS202 than of 68 Ga-DOTATOC into normal liver tissue and therefore the higher image contrast.</s><s>Sensitive detection of liver metastases is likely to have an impact on patient management, as the presence and extent of liver metastases are the most important prognostic factor <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>.</s><s>Unlike liver metastases, malignant lymph node lesions were not detected at a higher rate by 68 Ga-OPS202 imaging, possibly because of the much smaller sample size for those lesions than of liver lesions.</s></p><p><s>Uptake into the normal pancreas and gastrointestinal tract was lower with 68 Ga-OPS202 than with 68 Ga-DOTATOC, leading to increased tumor-to-background ratios for the former and therefore suggesting that it may be more useful for detecting primary gastroenteropancreatic NETs.</s><s>This ability, in turn, could have a positive impact on clinical management, because currently, the site of the primary tumor is unknown in approximately 20% of cases <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</s><s>Further studies are required to evaluate this aspect of diagnostic efficacy for 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT; it was not possible in the current study because of the small patient population and therefore the low overall numbers of primary lesions.</s></p><p><s>68 Ga-OPS202 is an antagonist with high affinity for the sst 2 receptor <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> and shows more sst receptor binding sites than the agonists 68 Ga-DOTATATE and 68 Ga-DOTATOC (data not shown).</s><s>Preclinical imaging studies comparing radiolabeled JR11 conjugates and 68 Ga-DOTATATE <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> have shown that tumor uptake can be expected to be higher for 68 Ga-OPS202 than for 68 Ga-DOTATOC.</s><s>In our clinical study, this was not the case.</s><s>This unexpected finding might be explained by the short half-life of 68 Ga (68 min), which does not allow scans to be acquired at later time points.</s><s>Posttreatment scans with the therapeutic sister compound of 68 Ga-OPS202-177 Lu-OPS201 ( 177 Lu-DOTA-JR11)-showed the highest tumor uptake between 3 and 24 h after injection of the radiotracer (Supplemental Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>.</s><s>The sst receptor agonist 177 Lu-DOTATATE showed a different behavior, with the highest tumor uptake at around 1 h after injection of the radiotracer (Supplemental Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Besides 68 Ga-DOTATOC, there are other 68 Ga-labeled sst receptor agonists for PET/CT imaging: 68 Ga-DOTATATE and 68 Ga-DOTANOC.</s><s>Like 68 Ga-OPS202, 68 Ga-DOTATATE is an sst 2 receptor-specific tracer, whereas 68 Ga-DOTANOC targets the sst 2 , sst 3 , and sst 5 receptor subtypes <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>.</s><s>The most commonly expressed sst receptor subtypes on gastroenteropancreatic NETs are sst 2 and, to a lesser extent, sst 1 and sst 5 <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>.</s><s>The clinical use of 68 Ga-DOTATATE and 68 Ga-DOTANOC was compared in a crossover study on 18 patients with gastroenteropancreatic NETs <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>.</s><s>Uptake values (median SUV max ) for 68 Ga-DOTATATE and 68 Ga-DOTANOC in liver tumors were similar to those obtained for 68 Ga-OPS202 in the current study, whereas uptake values for 68 Ga-OPS202 in normal liver were lower, resulting in much better tumor-to-background ratios; the medians of the mean tumor-tobackground ratios were 2.0 for about 30 mg of 68 Ga-DOTATATE and 2.7 for about 30 mg of 68 Ga-DOTANOC in that study <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>, compared with 5.3 for 15 mg of 68 Ga-OPS202, 4.3 for 50 mg of 68 Ga-OPS202, and 1.9 for about 15 mg of 68 Ga-DOTATOC in the present study.</s><s>Although indirect comparisons with studies using other 68 Ga-labeled sst analogs should be interpreted with caution, higher hepatic background levels have been consistently reported in the literature for 68 Ga-labeled sst receptor agonists, compared with 68 Ga-OPS202.</s><s>In a study by Wild et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>, median SUV max in the normal liver with approximately 30 mg of 68 Ga-DOTATATE and approximately 30 mg of 68 Ga-DOTANOC was 7.5 (interquartile range, 5.6-9.8) and 5.1 (interquartile range, 4.1-5.8),</s><s>whereas in the current study, corresponding values with 15 mg of 68 Ga-DOTA-TOC, 15 mg of 68 Ga-OPS202, and 50 mg of 68 Ga-OPS202 were 6.5, 3.4, and 2.7, with respective interquartile ranges of 4.8-8.9,</s><s>2.7-3.6, and 2.5-3.1.</s><s>This is consistent with a study by Poeppel et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>, which compared 68 Ga-DOTATATE and 68 Ga-DOTA-TOC with a mean peptide amount of 6 mg (range, 2-13 mg) and failed to show any major difference between them.</s><s>These findings add weight to our conclusion that, compared with sst receptor agonists, 68 Ga-OPS202 has improved imaging contrast for liver metastases.</s></p><p><s>The results obtained for the 2 doses of the peptide component of 68 Ga-OPS202 were generally consistent.</s><s>There were no significant differences in the numbers of malignant liver or lymph node lesions detected per patient, the tumor or reference-tissue uptake values, or the tumor contrast values, indicating a high reproducibility for 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT, which might be relevant for treatment-response evaluation and follow-up imaging.</s><s>There were no safety issues identified with either dose <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>, although the 3 adverse events (all grade 1) assessed as possibly related to the study drug were reported in 2 patients examined with the higher dose (50 mg).</s><s>Because of the radioactive decay of 68 Ge/ 68 Ga generators, it is not practical to keep the ratio of radioactivity to mass dose constant (specific activity), but the results of the current study indicate that OPS202 doses of between 15 and 50 mg are efficient and well tolerated and provide high reproducibility.</s></p><p><s>One of the limitations of the study was the small patient population.</s><s>A small number of patients is typical of early phase II studies.</s><s>Although this affects the power of statistical comparisons, it does allow evaluation of general trends and provides important information for future studies.</s><s>A notable point is that 3 of the 12 patients included in the study had more than 30 lesions.</s><s>To avoid any possible bias, the number of lesions per patient was considered in the statistical analysis.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSION</head><p><s>The preliminary diagnostic efficacy data from this phase II evaluation indicate that 68 Ga-OPS202 has high sensitivity and reproducibility in the detection of gastroenteropancreatic NETs.</s><s>These results, together with the safety profile from the phase I evaluation, suggest that 68 Ga-OPS202 might be a valuable new radiopharmaceutical for staging, localization, treatment-response</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIGURE 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 1. Study profile.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,57.71,41.84,227.85,268.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FIGURE 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 2. Box-and-whiskers plot representing tumor-to-background ratios of matched liver lesions (median of mean SUV max ratios, first and third quartiles) for both 68 Ga-OPS202 scans vs. the 68 Ga-DOTATOC scan (on-site reader).</s><s>Data in this figure were acquired as part of extension study and are not part of original study.</s><s>*In comparison with 68 Ga-DOTA-TOC, both 68 Ga-OPS202 scans showed significant increase in tumor-toliver ratio (P 5 0.004 and 0.008), whereas no statistical difference was shown between the 2 OPS202 peptide amounts (P 5 0.547).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,308.75,431.15,227.85,182.67" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>FIGURE 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 3. Images of patient 9, with ileal NET, showing bilobar liver metastases: 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT (50 μg) (A and B), 68 Ga-DOTATOC PET/CT (C and D), and MRI (E and F).</s><s>Dashed lines in A and C show level of transaxial slices in B,D, E, and F. PET/CT studies were performed on same scanner within 2 mo of each other and were read using same gray scale (maximal-intensity projections, A and C) and color scale (transaxial fusion images, B and D).</s><s>Findings were correlated with liver MRI performed 4 mo after 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT, with delayed postcontrast acquisitions (E) and diffusion-weighted images (F) confirming additional metastases missed or questionable (arrow with question mark) on 68 Ga-DOTATOC PET/CT.</s><s>Importantly, background activity was lower in liver, intestine, and thyroid with 68 Ga-OPS202 than with 68 Ga-DOTATOC (e.g., for liver, mean SUV max was 2.6 vs. 10.2).</s><s>Repeated thyroidectomy for benign goiter failed to demonstrate malignancy of left thyroid nodule.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,308.75,417.88,227.85,139.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>FIGURE 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 4. Images of patient 10, with ileal NET: 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT (50 μg) (A and B), 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT (15 μg) (C and D), 68 Ga-DOTATOC PET/CT (15 μg) (E and F), and MRI (G and H).</s><s>Dashed lines in A, C, and E show level of transaxial slices in B, D, F, G, and H. 68 Ga-OPS202 scans were obtained 25 and 4 d after68 Ga-DOTATOC scan.</s><s>Mean liver SUV max was 4.6 and 4.7 for 15 and 50 μg of 68 Ga-OPS202, respectively, and 5.6 for 68 Ga-DOTATOC.</s><s>Although 68 Ga-DOTATOC and both 68 Ga-OPS202 scans showed ileal primary, mesenteric malignant mass, and multiple liver metastases (black arrows),68 Ga-OPS202 scans detected significantly more liver metastases (white arrows).</s><s>Head-to-head comparison with MRI performed 7 mo after 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT confirmed that suggestive findings were true-positive only on 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT (white arrows).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,57.66,41.84,311.33,128.35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Baseline Demography and Disease Characteristics</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Patient</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Primary tumor</cell><cell>Tumor grade</cell><cell></cell><cell>Indication</cell><cell>Primary tumor</cell></row><row><cell>no.</cell><cell>Age (y)</cell><cell>Sex</cell><cell>location</cell><cell>(Ki-67 value)</cell><cell>Hormonal status</cell><cell>for imaging</cell><cell>resected</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>74</cell><cell>F</cell><cell>Ileum</cell><cell>G1 (,2%)</cell><cell>Functional</cell><cell>Restaging</cell><cell>Yes</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>56</cell><cell>F</cell><cell>Ileum</cell><cell>G1 (,2%)</cell><cell>Functional</cell><cell>Staging</cell><cell>Yes</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>45</cell><cell>F</cell><cell>Pancreas</cell><cell>G2 (5%)</cell><cell>Nonfunctional</cell><cell>Restaging</cell><cell>Yes</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>41</cell><cell>F</cell><cell>Ileum</cell><cell>G1 (1%)</cell><cell>Nonfunctional</cell><cell>Restaging</cell><cell>Yes</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>56</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>Pancreas</cell><cell>G1 (,2%)</cell><cell>Nonfunctional</cell><cell>Restaging</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>39</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>Pancreas</cell><cell>G2 (5%)</cell><cell>Nonfunctional</cell><cell>Restaging</cell><cell>Yes</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>72</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>Ileum</cell><cell>G2 (3%-5%)</cell><cell>Nonfunctional</cell><cell>Restaging</cell><cell>Yes</cell></row><row><cell>8</cell><cell>67</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>Unconfirmed (midgut)</cell><cell>G1 (,2%)</cell><cell>Functional</cell><cell>Restaging</cell><cell>Yes</cell></row><row><cell>9</cell><cell>71</cell><cell>F</cell><cell>Ileum</cell><cell>G2 (NA)</cell><cell>Functional</cell><cell>Restaging</cell><cell>Yes</cell></row><row><cell>10</cell><cell>32</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>Ileum</cell><cell>G2 (2%-5%)</cell><cell>Functional</cell><cell>Restaging</cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell>11</cell><cell>63</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>Ileum</cell><cell>G1 (1%)</cell><cell>Nonfunctional</cell><cell>Restaging</cell><cell>Yes</cell></row><row><cell>12</cell><cell>42</cell><cell>M</cell><cell>Pancreas</cell><cell>G1 (,2%)</cell><cell>Nonfunctional</cell><cell>Restaging</cell><cell>Yes</cell></row></table><note><p><s>G1 5 low grade; G2 5 intermediate grade; NA 5 not available.</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>TABLE 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Lesion-Based Comparison of 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT Scans and 68 Ga-DOTATOC PET/CT Scan</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">50 μg of 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT</cell><cell cols="2">15 μg of 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT</cell><cell cols="2">68 Ga-DOTATOC PET/CT</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Site</cell><cell>On-site reader</cell><cell>Central reader</cell><cell>On-site reader</cell><cell>Central Reader</cell><cell>On-site reader</cell><cell>Central reader</cell><cell>P*</cell></row><row><cell>Liver</cell><cell>149</cell><cell>195</cell><cell>151</cell><cell>157</cell><cell>97</cell><cell>77</cell><cell>,0.05</cell></row><row><cell>Lymph node</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>28</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>NS</cell></row><row><cell>Other sites</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>NS</cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>196</cell><cell>221</cell><cell>203</cell><cell>187</cell><cell>146</cell><cell>102</cell><cell>,0.05</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">*Comparison of 68 Ga-OPS202 and 68 Ga-DOTATOC PET/CT was done separately for on-site and central readers.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">NS 5 not significant.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>TABLE 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Organ, Tumor, and Tumor-to-Background Uptake Ratios: 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT Versus 68 Ga-DOTATOC PET/CT in Matched Lesion Analysis by On-Site Reader</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>68 Ga-OPS202</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>TABLE 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Lesion-Based Comparison of Sensitivity and PPV for 68 Ga-OPS202 PET/CT and 68 Ga-DOTATOC PET/CT in On-Site and Central Readings Both for 15-μg 68 Ga-OPS202 vs.68Ga-DOTATOC and for 50-μg 68 Ga-OPS202 vs. 68 Ga-DOTATOC.</s><s>NS 5 not significant.</s><s>Data in parentheses are 95% confidence intervals.</s><s>Data in this table were acquired as part of extension study and are not part of original study design.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Index</cell><cell>50 μg of 68 Ga-OPS202</cell><cell>15 μg of 68 Ga-OPS202</cell><cell>68 Ga-DOTATOC</cell><cell>Superiority test</cell></row><row><cell>Sensitivity</cell><cell>93.7% (85.3-97.6)</cell><cell>88.1% (74.4-95.2)</cell><cell>59.2% (36.3-79.1)</cell><cell>P , 0.001*</cell></row><row><cell>PPV</cell><cell>98.5% (82.8-99.9)</cell><cell>98.0% (77.9-99.9)</cell><cell>97.8% (76.3-99.9)</cell><cell>NS</cell></row></table><note><p><s>*</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="68">GA-OPS202 PET/CT IMAGING PHASE II STUDY • Nicolas et al.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="68">GA-OPS202 PET/CT IMAGING PHASE II STUDY • Nicolas et al.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="68">GA-OPS202 PET/CT IMAGING PHASE II STUDY • Nicolas et al.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>We thank all the patients who participated in the trial, the OctreoPharm/Ipsen team, and the personnel of the Division of Radiopharmaceutical Chemistry and Nuclear Medicine at University Hospital Basel.</s><s>We also thank Nicky French (Watermeadow Medical) for medical writing support.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>evaluation, and follow-up imaging of NETs.</s><s>Further studies on larger patient populations are warranted.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCLOSURE</head><p><s>Hakim Bouterfa is a founder of OctreoPharm Sciences GmbH and a former employee of Ipsen; he now acts as a consultant for Ipsen.</s><s>Jens Kaufmann is an employee of Ipsen.</s><s>Medical writing support was funded by Ipsen.</s><s>This study was sponsored in part by Ipsen.</s><s>No other potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gastroenteropancreatic neuroendocrine tumours</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Modlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Oberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changing paradigms with molecular imaging of neuroendocrine tumors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hofman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hicks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Discov Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="81" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gastroenteropancreatic neuroendocrine tumours (GEP-NET): imaging and staging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Baumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rottenburger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Nicolas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wild</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Best Pract Res Clin Endocrinol Metab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">68 Ga-DOTA-Tyr 3 -octreotide PET in neuroendocrine tumors: comparison with somatostatin receptor scintigraphy and CT</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gabriel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Decristoforo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kendler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Nucl Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="508" to="518" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Affinity profiles for human somatostatin receptor subtypes SST1-SST5 of somatostatin radiotracers selected for scintigraphic and radiotherapeutic use</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Reubi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Schar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Waser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Nucl Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Are radiogallium-labelled DOTA-conjugated somatostatin analogues superior to those labelled with other radiometals?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Antunes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ginj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="982" to="993" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Simultaneous 68 Ga-DOTA-TOC PET/MRI with gadoxetate disodium in patients with neuroendocrine tumor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hope</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Pampaloni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Nakakura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Abdom Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1432" to="1440" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Morphological and functional imaging for detecting and assessing the resectability of neuroendocrine liver metastases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ronot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Clift</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Baum</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroendocrinology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-07-21">July 21, 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Epub ahead of print</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Radiolabeled somatostatin receptor antagonists are preferable to agonists for in vivo peptide receptor targeting of tumors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ginj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Waser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16436" to="16441" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">First clinical evidence that imaging with somatostatin receptor antagonists is feasible</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wild</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Behe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Nucl Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1412" to="1417" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Concomitant expression of several peptide receptors in neuroendocrine tumours: molecular basis for in vivo multireceptor tumour targeting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Reubi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Waser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="781" to="793" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unexpected sensitivity of sst2 antagonists to N-terminal radiometal modifications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Waser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Nucl Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1481" to="1489" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Somatostatin receptor antagonists for imaging and therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nicolas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wild</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Nucl Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61S" to="66S" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of somatostatin receptor agonist and antagonist for peptide receptor radionuclide therapy: a pilot study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wild</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Nucl Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1248" to="1252" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Safety, biodistribution, and radiation dosimetry of 68 Ga-OPS202 in patients with gastroenteropancreatic neuroendocrine tumors: a prospective phase I imaging study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Nicolas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Beykan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bouterfa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Nucl Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="909" to="914" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An update on gastroenteropancreatic neuroendocrine tumors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cives</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Strosberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="749" to="756" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Therapeutic strategies for neuroendocrine liver metastases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Frilling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Clift</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1172" to="1186" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of 68 Ga-DOTANOC and 68 Ga-DOTATATE PET/CT within patients with gastroenteropancreatic neuroendocrine tumors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wild</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bomanji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Benkert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Nucl Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="364" to="372" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">68 Ga-DOTATOC versus 68 Ga-DOTATATE PET/CT in functional imaging of neuroendocrine tumors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Poeppel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Binse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Petersenn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Nucl Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1864" to="1870" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
