<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Birth Outcomes in Children Fathered by Men Treated with Immunosuppressant Drugs before Conception-A Danish Population-Based Cohort Study</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexander</forename><surname>Egeberg</surname></persName>
							<email>alexander.egeberg@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Dermatology and Allergy</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Herlev and Gentofte Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hellerup</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Gunnar</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gislason</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology, Herlev and Gentofte Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hellerup</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">The Danish Heart Foundation</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Copenhagen</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">The National Institute of Public Health</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Southern Denmark</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Copenhagen</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexander</forename><surname>Nast</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Evidence based Medicine (dEBM)</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Dermatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Venerology und Allergy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Charite ´-Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Birth Outcomes in Children Fathered by Men Treated with Immunosuppressant Drugs before Conception-A Danish Population-Based Cohort Study</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">739CD40A555FB7BBE45467B45EF74963</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jid.2017.03.030</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:22+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>TO THE EDITOR Certain immunosuppressant agents have teratogenic properties when women are exposed during pregnancy <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Buckley et al., 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Chapa et al., 2003)</ref>.</s><s>Moreover, although pregnancy outcomes depend on both maternal and paternal factors, animal studies have indicated that the paternal use of certain drugs may induce congenital abnormalities in the offspring, yet human data remain scarce <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Schirm et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Viktil et al., 2009)</ref>.</s><s>Given the beneficial effects of immunosuppressant drugs in management chronic inflammatory diseases, it is important to ascertain their safety during pregnancy, in particular because nearly half of all pregnancies are unintended <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Finer and Zolna, 2016)</ref>.</s><s>We evaluated the risk of adverse birth outcomes in a nationwide cohort of the Danish population.</s></p><p><s>The Medical Birth Registry keeps information on all hospitals and home births since 1973 to monitor perinatal statistics, comprising data on maternal characteristics, results, or complications of pregnancy and birth process <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Knudsen and Olsen, 1998)</ref>.</s><s>A detailed methodological description is available in Supplementary Materials and Methods online.</s></p><p><s>The study comprised Danish children born between 1 January 2004 and 31 December 2010 with available information on the biological father.</s><s>The study outcomes were any type of congenital abnormality, low birth weight (&lt;2,500 g), and premature birth (birth before 37 weeks of pregnancy).</s><s>Because the presence of certain diseases may not be evident immediately after birth, we performed additional analyses where the outcome was a diagnosis of congenital malformations, deformations, and chromosomal abnormalities in the years after birth.</s><s>Baseline characteristics were described with means and standard deviations for continuous variables and frequencies and percentages for categorical variables.</s><s>We estimated the prevalence odds ratio (OR) for congenital abnormalities, low birth weight, and premature birth.</s><s>We performed logistic regression analyses to estimate the relative risk (prevalence OR) of congenital abnormalities amongst fathers using immunosuppressant therapy before conception.</s><s>Analyses were adjusted for maternal age, parity, maternal smoking, and gender of the child.</s><s>To ensure persistent treatment in the "current users" group, fathers were only considered exposed if they had claimed a prescription within the last 3 months before conception and claimed an additional prescription in the first 3 months after conception.</s><s>Pvalues of less than 0.05 were considered statistically significant and results were reported with 95% confidence intervals where applicable.</s><s>The Hosmer-Lemeshow test was used for model control.</s></p><p><s>The study comprised 417,634 children, of whom 31,238 (7.5%) were born with congenital abnormalities, 22,089 (5.3%) had low birth weight (&lt;2,500 g), and 18,972 (4.5%) were born preterm (&lt;37 weeks).</s><s>The characteristics of the study population are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s><s>A total of 2,123 of fathers had claimed prescriptions for immunosuppressant drugs (azathioprine, n ¼ 1,246; cyclosporine, n ¼ 247; methotrexate, n ¼ 864; mycophenolate mofetil, n ¼ 37) before conception.</s><s>In total, there were 163, 117, and 107 cases of congenital abnormalities, low birth weight, and preterm birth, respectively, among children fathered by men treated with immunosuppressant drugs before conception.</s></p><p><s>Among the 1,246 children born by azathioprine-treated fathers, there were 94, 73, and 66 cases of congenital abnormalities, low birth weight, and preterm birth, respectively.</s><s>After adjustment for confounding factors, the adjusted OR (95% confidence interval) was 0.99 (0.80e1.23) for congenital abnormalities, 1.08 (0.84e1.39) for low birth weight, and 1.10 (0.84e1.43) for preterm birth, respectively (Supplementary Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">S1</ref> online).</s><s>In total, 247 children had fathers treated with cyclosporine before conception.</s><s>Of these, there were 16, 19, and 15 cases of congenital abnormalities, low birth weight, and preterm birth, respectively.</s><s>There was no association between any paternal exposure to cyclosporine and congenital abnormality risk <ref type="bibr">(adjusted OR 0.82 [0.49e1.39]</ref>).</s><s>Of 864 methotrexatetreated fathers, there were 72 cases of congenital abnormalities (adjusted OR 1.12 [0.87e1.43])</s><s>and 40 children had low birth weight (adjusted OR 0.86 [0.62e1.19]).</s><s>Similarly, 39 children were born preterm (adjusted OR 1.02 [0.74e1.42]).</s><s>Only 37 fathers were treated with mycophenolate mofetil before conception, resulting in less than three children with congenital abnormalities (adjusted OR 0.70 [0.17e2.91]),</s><s>and risk of low birth weight (n ¼ 3; adjusted OR 1.55 [0.47e5.09])</s><s>and preterm birth (n ¼ 3; adjusted OR 1.84 [0.56e6.01])</s><s>were also not increased.</s><s>In analyses of "current users," there were no significant changes in any of the reported results (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>).</s><s>There was no association between the number of claimed prescriptions for any of the examined drugs, and adverse birth outcomes (Supplementary Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">S2</ref> online).</s><s>In secondary analyses of congenital malformations, deformations, and chromosomal abnormalities diagnosed after birth, there were no significant associations with any of the examined drugs in the "any previous exposure" group as well as the "current users" group (data not shown).</s></p><p><s>Preconceptual paternal treatment with azathioprine, cyclosporine, methotrexate, and mycophenolate mofetil was not associated with risk of adverse birth outcomes, and our data suggest that the increasing use of these drugs in fertile men should not be a cause for major concern.</s><s>Paternal drug exposure could theoretically impact a birth outcome via its influence on spermatogenesis, direct mutagenic action, or transfer of the drug via the semen to the female.</s><s>For azathioprine, a large number of fathers with previous exposure and even with exposure during the time of conception were identified, allowing for a strong conclusion.</s><s>For cyclosporine and methotrexate, the number of exposed fathers identified in the registries was limited and the use of mycophenolate mofetil was very infrequent, making conclusion regarding this drug difficult; however, even with low numbers, confidence intervals remained narrow, supporting the robustness of the data.</s></p><p><s>Our data included pharmacotherapy prescribed by general practitioners, specialists, as well as during hospitalizations, ensuring complete information of treatment patterns.</s><s>Nevertheless, certain limitations apply to interpretation of the present results.</s><s>We examined only pregnancy outcomes, and the effects of paternal immunosuppressant therapy on chances of successfully conceiving a child were not addressed.</s><s>Also, the number of fathers treated in particular with mycophenolate mofetil was low, and results should therefore be interpreted accordingly.</s></p><p><s>Conclusively, the present study does not provide any evidence for an increased risk of congenital abnormalities, low birth weight, or preterm birth in the offspring.</s><s>This may help physicians in clinical decision making and counseling of men with chronic inflammatory disorders who plan to start a family.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</head><p><s>AE has received research funding from Pfizer and Eli Lilly, and honoraria as consultant and/or speaker from Pfizer, Eli Lilly, Novartis, Galderma, and Janssen Pharmaceuticals.</s><s>GHG is supported by an unrestricted research scholarship from the Novo Nordisk Foundation.</s><s>AN has received honoraria for education activity from Novartis and Bayer.</s><s>The Division of Evidence based Medicine (dEBM) has received research grants/research supports from Pfizer, GSK, and MEDA.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</head><p><s>AE and GHG had full access to all of the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</s><s>All authors contributed to the study concept and design.</s><s>All authors acquired, analyzed, and interpreted the data.</s><s>AE and AN prepared the draft of the manuscript.</s><s>All authors were involved in critical revision of the manuscript for important intellectual content.</s><s>AE and GHG contributed to 9.9 (1.4) 9.9 (0.7) 9.9 (0.6) 9.9 (0.6) 9.9 (0.7) 9.9 (0.4) Single/multiple pregnancy, n (%) Abbreviations: CI, confidence interval; OR, odds ratio.</s></p><p><s>1 Adjusted for mother's age (below 25 y, 25e29 y, and 30 y or more), parity (1 or more than 1), maternal smoking (yes/no), and sex of the child in a logistic regression model.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Abbreviation: OR, odds ratio Accepted manuscript published online 19 April 2017; corrected proof published online 24 June 2017 ª 2017 The Authors.</s><s>Published by Elsevier, Inc. on behalf of the Society for Investigative Dermatology.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Characteristics of pregnancies fathered by men treated with immunosuppressants before conception and of control pregnancies</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Exposed (Paternal Immunosuppressants)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Unexposed</cell><cell>Any</cell><cell>Azathioprine</cell><cell>Cyclosporine</cell><cell>Methotrexate</cell><cell>Mycophenolate Mofetil</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(n [ 415,511)</cell><cell>(n [ 2,123)</cell><cell>(n [ 1,246)</cell><cell>(n [ 247)</cell><cell>(n [ 864)</cell><cell>(n [ 37)</cell></row><row><cell>Sex, n (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Girls</cell><cell>202,528 (48.7)</cell><cell>1,022 (48.1)</cell><cell>577 (46.3)</cell><cell>114 (46.2)</cell><cell>441 (51.0)</cell><cell>16 (43.2)</cell></row><row><cell>Boys</cell><cell>212,983 (51.3)</cell><cell>1,101 (51.9)</cell><cell>669 (53.7)</cell><cell>133 (53.8)</cell><cell>423 (49.0)</cell><cell>21 (56.8)</cell></row><row><cell>Age at birth, mean (SD)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mother</cell><cell>30.3 (4.8)</cell><cell>30.7 (4.5)</cell><cell>30.6 (4.5)</cell><cell>31.6 (5.0)</cell><cell>30.8 (4.4)</cell><cell>33.2 (4.4)</cell></row><row><cell>Father</cell><cell>32.8 (5.6)</cell><cell>33.3 (5.5)</cell><cell>33.0 (5.2)</cell><cell>33.7 (6.5)</cell><cell>33.6 (5.6)</cell><cell>33.7 (5.9)</cell></row><row><cell>Mother's parity &gt;1, n (%)</cell><cell>226,744 (55.0)</cell><cell>1,168 (55.4)</cell><cell>690 (55.7)</cell><cell>135 (55.3)</cell><cell>479 (55.8)</cell><cell>18 (50.0)</cell></row><row><cell>Mother's smoking, n (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Nonsmoker</cell><cell>346,228 (83.3)</cell><cell>1,781 (83.9)</cell><cell>1,062 (85.2)</cell><cell>207 (83.8)</cell><cell>710 (82.2)</cell><cell>33 (89.2)</cell></row><row><cell>1e5 cigarettes/d</cell><cell>15,086 (3.6)</cell><cell>78 (3.7)</cell><cell>38 (3.1)</cell><cell>7 (2.8)</cell><cell>38 (4.4)</cell><cell>0 (0.0)</cell></row><row><cell>6e10 cigarettes/d</cell><cell>18,614 (4.5)</cell><cell>83 (3.9)</cell><cell>43 (3.5)</cell><cell>12 (4.9)</cell><cell>37 (4.3)</cell><cell>3 (not shown)</cell></row><row><cell>11e20 cigarettes/d</cell><cell>13,647 (3.3)</cell><cell>55 (2.6)</cell><cell>36 (2.9)</cell><cell>5 (2.0)</cell><cell>19 (2.2)</cell><cell>0 (0.0)</cell></row><row><cell>20 cigarettes/d</cell><cell>1,963 (0.5)</cell><cell>14 (0.7)</cell><cell>6 (0.5)</cell><cell>4 (1.6)</cell><cell>8 (0.9)</cell><cell>0 (0.0)</cell></row><row><cell>Unknown</cell><cell>19,973 (4.8)</cell><cell>112 (5.3)</cell><cell>61 (4.9)</cell><cell>12 (4.9)</cell><cell>52 (6.0)</cell><cell>3 (not shown)</cell></row><row><cell>Maternal BMI at first visit, mean (SD)</cell><cell>24.2 (4.8)</cell><cell>24.3 (4.8)</cell><cell>24.2 (4.8)</cell><cell>24.5 (4.3)</cell><cell>24.5 (2.9)</cell><cell>24.3 (4.5)</cell></row><row><cell>Previous caesarean section, n (%)</cell><cell>49,002 (11.8)</cell><cell>276 (13.0)</cell><cell>140 (11.2)</cell><cell>34 (13.8)</cell><cell>124 (14.4)</cell><cell>6 (16.2)</cell></row><row><cell>Previous spontaneous abortion, n (%)</cell><cell>57,322 (13.8)</cell><cell>301 (14.2)</cell><cell>157 (12.6)</cell><cell>35 (14.2)</cell><cell>142 (16.4)</cell><cell>8 (21.6)</cell></row><row><cell>APGAR score, mean (SD)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Odds ratios with 95% confidence intervals for congenital abnormalities, low birth weight, and premature birth in children fathered by men treated with azathioprine, cyclosporine, methotrexate, or mycophenolate mofetil within the last 90 d before and after conception</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Singleton</cell><cell>397,636 (95.7)</cell><cell>2,035 (0.5)</cell><cell>1,199 (96.2)</cell><cell>227 (91.9)</cell><cell>825 (95.5)</cell><cell>36 (not shown)</cell></row><row><cell>Twins</cell><cell>17,513 (4.2)</cell><cell>88 (4.2)</cell><cell>47 (3.8)</cell><cell>20 (8.1)</cell><cell>39 (4.5)</cell><cell>3 (not shown)</cell></row><row><cell>Triplets</cell><cell>354 (0.1)</cell><cell>0 (0.0)</cell><cell>0 (0.0)</cell><cell>0 (0.0)</cell><cell>0 (0.0)</cell><cell>0 (0.0)</cell></row><row><cell>Quadruplets or more</cell><cell>8 (0.0)</cell><cell>0 (0.0)</cell><cell>0 (0.0)</cell><cell>0 (0.0)</cell><cell>0 (0.0)</cell><cell>0 (0.0)</cell></row><row><cell>Length (cm) at birth, mean (SD)</cell><cell>51.4 (5.2)</cell><cell>51.3 (5.3)</cell><cell>51.3 (5.4)</cell><cell>50.8 (6.1)</cell><cell>51.5 (4.7)</cell><cell>51.2 (3.7)</cell></row><row><cell>Weight (g) at birth, mean (SD)</cell><cell cols="5">3,476.8 (609.0) 3,463.5 (625.9) 3,470.2 (639.7) 3,411.2 (689.3) 3,463.9 (589.2)</cell><cell>3,361.9 (728.7)</cell></row><row><cell>Gestational age (d) at birth, mean (SD)</cell><cell>277.2 (14.3)</cell><cell>276.5 (15.0)</cell><cell>276.4 (15.4)</cell><cell>275.4 (17.2)</cell><cell>276.7 (13.8)</cell><cell>274.1 (18.1)</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Abbreviations: BMI, body mass index; SD, standard deviation.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>A Egeberg et al.Journal of Investigative Dermatology (2017) 137, 1792e1795; doi:10.1016/j.jid.2017.04.007</s><s>TO THE EDITOR Obesity is a known risk factor for cancer development (Arnold et al., 2016; Basen-Engquist and Chang, 2011; Renehan et al., 2015) and death</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Journal of Investigative Dermatology (2017), Volume 137</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multiple congenital anomalies associated with weekly low-dose methotrexate treatment of the mother</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Buckley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bullaboy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Leichtman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Marquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arthritis Rheum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="971" to="e973" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prenatal diagnosis of methotrexate embryopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Chapa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Hibbard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Abramowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Verp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1104" to="e1107" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Declines in unintended pregnancy in the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Finer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Zolna</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">374</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="843" to="e52" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2008e2011. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Danish Medical Birth Registry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Knudsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Olsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dan Med Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="320" to="e323" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drug use among fathers around time of conception: two register based surveys from Denmark and The Netherlands</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Schirm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pedersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Tobi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Sorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>De Jong-Van Den</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Berg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="609" to="e613" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use of antirheumatic drugs in mothers and fathers before and during pregnancy-a population-based cohort study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Viktil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Engeland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Furu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="737" to="e742" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
