<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Retrospective study of oxaliplatin, leucovarin and 5 fluoruracil regimen in patients with advanced gastric cancer with poor performance status: A study at a tertiary center of South India</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Guruprasad</forename><surname>Bhat</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical Oncology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yenepoya Medical College</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Mangalore</settlement>
									<region>Karnataka</region>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical Oncology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Yenepoya Medical College</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Mangalore</settlement>
									<region>Karnataka</region>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Retrospective study of oxaliplatin, leucovarin and 5 fluoruracil regimen in patients with advanced gastric cancer with poor performance status: A study at a tertiary center of South India</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">0F6D3DFD3A8F49E09903C2A629ACDDA0</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.4103/sajc.sajc_1_18</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:11+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Gastric cancer</term>
					<term>India</term>
					<term>OLF regimen</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>The aim of this study was to assess the clinical activity and toxicity of oxaliplatin with infusional 5-FU and leucovorin administered every 3 weeks in patients with locally advanced and inoperable gastric cancer.</s><s>We also evaluated the progression-free survival and toxicity profile of this regimen.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patients and Methods</head><p><s>This retrospective study was done at the department of oncology, Yenepoya Medical College Mangalore.</s><s>Data of cases of advanced gastric adenocarcinoma on OLF regimen during a period of 2 years from February 2015 to February 2017 were collected from the medical case records.</s><s>Histologically confirmed cases of advanced gastric adenocarcinoma on OLF regimen, over the age of 18 years of either gender, were included in the study.</s><s>The WHO performance status was used, and patients with performance status of 2 or more were considered for the study.</s><s>A semi-structured pro forma was used to collect information from the medical case records.</s><s>Records were checked for any evidence of toxicity and response to the treatment regimen.</s><s>Chemotherapy regimen: oxaliplatin (130 mg/m 2 on day 1) as a 2 h infusion in 1 unit 5% dextrose followed IV infusion of LV 50 mg/m 2 in 100 mL normal saline over 2 h from day 1 to 3 and 5-FU IV (5FU 1000 mg/m 2 daily by continuous infusion on day 1-3).</s><s>Cycles were repeated at 3-week intervals till tumor progression.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical analysis</head><p><s>Data were entered in Microsoft Office Excel worksheet and analyzed using statistical software SPSS version 17.0 (SPSS Inc., USA).</s><s>For qualitative data, Chi-square test was used and P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patient characteristics</head><p><s>Twenty-five cases were eligible for this study after satisfying the inclusion and exclusion criteria.</s><s>Twenty-five patients</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Gastric carcinoma is the second most common cause of cancer-related mortality. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref></s><s>Gastric cancer is the leading cause of cancer in South India, probably due to high consumption of rice, chili, and high-temperature food. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref></s><s>Gastric cancer is frequently diagnosed in or locally advanced or metastatic stage where the 5-year survival is only about 6% in the Indian scenario. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref></s><s>Advanced gastric cancer (AGC) remains incurable with a median survival of 6-9 months. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref></s><s>As majority of patients present at later stages with poor performance status, effective chemotherapy regimen with minimal side effects is the need of the hour.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rationale of study</head><p><s>There is no worldwide accepted standard chemotherapy regimen in AGC.</s><s>In AGC, the therapeutic decision is usually between a strict supportive care and exposing patients to side effects of potential ineffective therapy.</s><s>Chemotherapy has demonstrated to result in both a significant survival advantage and an improved quality of life when compared to best supportive care. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref></s><s>We selected OLF regimen which has lesser toxicity, can be given in poor performance status, and can be administered in patients with gastric obstruction.</s><s>Both 5-fluorouracil (5FU) and oxaliplatin do not cause hair loss, can be used in inlet/outlet obstruction, and both do not cause significant febrile neutropenia.</s><s>The dose of oxaliplatin used was 130 mg/m 2 as per the REAL-2 study. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref></s><s>The 3 weekly dose of 5-FU was derived from the ML17032 trial, the original trial used only 5FU 800 mg/m 2 on days 1-5 every 21 days.</s><s>5FU can be bio-modulated with leucovorin (LV); however, the most effective dosage of LV has not been determined.</s><s>We biomodulated 5FU by adding LV 50 mg/m 2 and reducing the duration of 5FU to 3 days.</s><s>The final regimen being oxaliplatin 130 mg/m 2 on day 1 over 2 h, LV 50 mg/m 2 daily by 2 h infusion on day 1-3, and 5FU 1000 mg/m 2 daily by continuous infusion on day 1-3 every 21 days.</s><s>received 180 cycles of 3 weekly regimen with a median of six cycles (range: 3-12 cycles) per patient.</s><s>The patient characteristics are shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s><s>Median age was 64 years (range: 30-79 years).</s><s>Majority of the study population were males (18 out of 25).</s><s>The predominant site of metastasis was the liver.</s><s>Fifteen (60%) patients did not have ascites at presentation.</s><s>One patient has human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 overexpression.</s><s>The characteristics are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Survival</head><p><s>The median progression-free survival for patients was 6 months (7 months in locally advanced), while the projected 1-year progression-free survival rate was 9% ±4.7% [Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>].</s><s>Progression-free survival was 3 months in patients with peritoneal involvement.</s><s>No difference was found between body mass index (BMI) and outcome.</s><s>Three patients with locally advanced cancer, who progressed on OLF regimen were given weekly paclitaxel.</s><s>Celiac plexus block was done in five patients without ascites for pain relief.</s><s>Four patients underwent gastrojejunostomy with gastric outlet obstruction.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Toxicities</head><p><s>The median number of cycles for patients was 6 (range: 3-12 cycles).</s><s>The most common toxicities were nonhematologic.</s><s>Six patients developed neurotoxicity (Grade: 1-2 in 5 patients and Grade 3-4 in one patient).</s><s>Two patients discontinued treatment, one due to severe diarrhea and other due to neurotoxicity.</s><s>No treatment-related death was reported.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>This study assessed the clinical efficacy and toxicity of OLF regimen in patients with AGC and poor performance status.</s><s>Although gastric cancer is considered a relatively chemosensitive tumor with an overall response rate ranging between 30% and 60%, survival of AGC patients remains unsatisfactory, with a median survival time of only 6-9 months. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref></s><s>Therefore, effective treatment approaches with minimal toxicity profiles are needed, especially in patients with poor general condition.</s></p><p><s>Listed below are some of the common regimens in gastric cancer and their problems we face in routine clinical practice: 1. Capecitabine plus oxaliplatin (CAPOX) is an established regimen in stomach cancer (CLASSIC trial). <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref></s><s>But problems with CAPOX are: a. Patients with advanced gastric carcinoma may not able to swallow capecitabine tablets as they have vomiting, due to inlet/outlet obstruction b.</s><s>Capecitabine produces severe hand-foot syndrome in up to 50% of patients, hence quality of life is affected c.</s><s>Not many tolerate the full dose of capecitabine 1250 mg/m 2 ( 2500 mg/m 2 daily) and dose reductions or interruptions are needed in 33% of patients. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref></s><s>These problems are not seen with OLF regimen.</s><s>2. Discounted Cash Flow (DCF) is also an established regimen in gastric cancer (V-325 study). <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref></s><s>But the problems with DCF are: a. Myelotoxicity with Grade 3 and Grade 4 neutropenia in 82% of patients.</s><s>This is detrimental in poor performance status patients b.</s><s>Nausea, vomiting, and renal toxicity due to cisplatin is a frequent problem c.</s><s>Hair loss.</s><s>These problems are not seen with OLF regimen, needing lesser admission, and better tolerability 3. FOLFOX is also an established regimen in gastric cancer. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12]</ref></s><s>But the problems with FOLFOX are: a.</s><s>It's a 2 weekly regimen, difficult to administer as frequent visits, and hospitalizations are needed b.</s><s>Less frequent admission in OLF regimen is advantageous in elderly, in poor socioeconomic strata, and in patients who come from the remote area.</s><s>Less frequent admission also reduces the burden on health service providers 4. Extracellular fluid (ECF) is also an established regimen in gastric cancer based on a Phase III study. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref></s><s>But the problems with ECF are: a.</s><s>It is a continuous infusion regimen of 5 FU, 200 mg/m 2 daily for 21 days.</s><s>The main disadvantage of this regimen is that an indwelling venous catheter is required to deliver the infusional 5FU and this is associated with infection and thromboembolism risk b.</s><s>Myelotoxicity with Grade 3 and Grade 4 neutropenia seen in 42% of patients c.</s><s>Cardiotoxicity seen in 2.1% of patients d.</s><s>Hair loss e. Epirubicin can cause serious extravasation f.</s><s>Nausea, vomiting (Grade 2-4 in 50%), and renal toxicity (all Grades 7%) due to cisplatin. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref></s><s>These problems are not seen with OLF regimen, needing lesser admission, and better tolerability.</s><s>5. Paclitaxel with carboplatin is also an effective regimen in gastric cancer. <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref></s><s>But the problems with this regimen are:  a. Grade III and IV neutropenia seen in 33% of patients b.</s><s>Grade III peripheral neuropathy is seen in 7% of patients c.</s><s>Hair loss is also a common problem with this regimen.</s><s>6. Cisplatin with 5FU is also an effective regimen in gastric cancer.</s><s>But the problems with this regimen are: a.</s><s>Nearly double the incidence of Grade 3 and 4 neutropenia, alopecia, thromboembolism, and renal dysfunction compared to oxaliplatin 5FU doublet. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">16]</ref></s><s>. Irinotecan with 5FU is also an effective regimen in gastric cancer.</s><s>But the problems with this regimen are: a. Diarrhea with irinotecan is seen in up to 22% of patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref> b.</s><s>Hair loss c.</s><s>Grade III and IV neutropenia is seen in 25% of patients on weekly irinotecan regimen.</s></p><p><s>A combination of 5-FU and platinum compounds is commonly used as first-line treatment in AGC and has a response rate of 30%-50%.</s><s>Similar response rate is seen when any of the above-mentioned drug combination is used. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref></s><s>The response rate in our regimen was 36%, with all patients having stable disease.</s><s>No patient had a complete response.</s><s>Median survival of patients was 6 months (7 months in locally advanced).</s><s>Survival was 3 months in patients with peritoneal carcinomatosis.</s><s>This is lower than other studies done worldwide where the survival ranged from 8 to 11.2 months. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref></s><s>The lower survival in our study was probably due to the poor performance status in most of our patients.</s><s>Poor survival was seen in patients with peritoneal carcinomatosis and Stage IV disease at presentation.</s><s>No difference was found between BMI and outcome.</s></p><p><s>In most of the trials with oxaliplatin-based therapies, neurotoxicity was the most frequent side effect that led to treatment discontinuation.</s><s>The incidence of this chronic event is around 30%, occurring commonly in female, diabetic patients with the prolonged use of oxaliplatin. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref></s><s>Only one patient in our study discontinued the treatment due to this adverse effect.</s></p><p><s>HER2 overexpression is seen in 4%-8% of Indian patients with gastric cancer. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref></s><s>One patient (4%) had HER2 overexpression, but he could not afford trastuzumab.</s></p><p><s>None of the current regimens can be considered as an optimal therapy for AGC and new therapeutic strategies are needed to achieve a better clinical efficacy with an acceptable toxicity profile.</s><s>Our regimen (OLF) has significant effects as a chemotherapeutic regimen for AGC patients because of encouraging response and mild toxicities.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p><s>The results of our study suggest that OLF regimen has activity and acceptable toxicity in patients with AGC with poor performance status and merits further studies.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1: Progression-free survival in advanced gastric cancer with poor performance</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,114.31,657.86,105.24,90.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 : Patient characteristics Variable Number of patients (n=25), n (%)</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Sex</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell>18 (72)</cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>7 (28)</cell></row><row><cell>Age (years)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Median</cell><cell>64</cell></row><row><cell>Range</cell><cell>30-79</cell></row><row><cell>Locally advanced inoperable</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>Site of metastasis (some had multiple sites)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Liver</cell><cell>13</cell></row><row><cell>Ascites (including peritoneal carcinomatosis)</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>Ovary (Krukenberg tumor)</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Response rate</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CR</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Stable disease</cell><cell>9 (36)</cell></row><row><cell>HER2 over-expression</cell><cell>1 (4)</cell></row><row><cell>CR=Complete response</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Published online: 2020-12-21 Bhat: OLF regimen in advanced gastric cancer with poor performance status</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Financial support and sponsorship</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Nil.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflicts of interest</head><p><s>There are no conflicts of interest.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical epidemiology of gastric cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Singapore Medical Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="621" to="628" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gastric cancer in India</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Radhakrishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Indian J Med Paediatr Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="16" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epidemiological review of gastric cancer in India</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dikshit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Mathur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mhatre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Yeole</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Indian J Med Paediatr Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gastric cancer: Epidemiology, pathology and treatment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Alberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cervantes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cjh</forename><surname>Van De Velde</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="36" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Randomized comparison between chemotherapy plus best supportive care with best supportive care in advanced gastric cancer gastric cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Glimelius</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ekstrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Graf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Sjoden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Haglund</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="168" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Randomised comparison of fluorouracil, epidoxorubicin and methotrexate (FEMTX) plus supportive care with supportive care alone in patients with non resectable gastric cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pyrhonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kuitunen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Nyandoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kouri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="587" to="591" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capecitabine and oxaliplatin for advanced esophagogastric cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cunningham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Starling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Iveson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nicolson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Coxon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">358</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adjuvant capecitabine and oxaliplatin for gastric cancer after D2 gastrectomy (CLASSIC): A phase 3 open-label, randomised controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">379</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="315" to="321" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Oshaughnessy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Blum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Moiseyenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Miles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">open-label, phase II trial of oral capecitabine (Xeloda) vs. a reference arm of intravenous CMF (cyclophosphamide, methotrexate and 5-fluorouracil) as first-line therapy for advanced/metastatic breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Randomized</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1247" to="1254" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phase III study of docetaxel and cisplatin plus fluorouracil compared with cisplatin and fluorouracil as first-line therapy for advanced gastric cancer: A report of the V325 Study Group</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Van Cutsem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Moiseyenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tjulandin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Majlis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Constenla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Boni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4991" to="4997" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phase II study of oxaliplatin, fluorouracil, and folinic acid in locally advanced or metastatic gastric cancer patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Louvet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>André</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tigaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gamelin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Douillard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Brunet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4543" to="4548" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A phase II study of biweekly oxaliplatin plus infusional 5-fluorouracil and folinic acid (FOLFOX-4) as first-line treatment of advanced gastric cancer patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Vita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Orditura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Matano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bianco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Carlomagno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Infusino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1644" to="1649" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prospective randomized trial comparing mitomycin, cisplatin, and protracted venous-infusion fluorouracil (PVI 5-FU) With epirubicin, cisplatin, and PVI 5-FU in advanced esophagogastric cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nicolson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cunningham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Valle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Seymour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Harper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1996" to="2004" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cisplatin, epirubicin, leucovorin and 5-fluorouracil (PELF) is more active than 5-fluorouracil, doxorubicin and methotrexate (FAMTX) in advanced gastric carcinoma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cocconi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Carlini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gamboni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gasperoni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rodino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zironi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1258" to="1263" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phase II study of paclitaxel and carboplatin in patients with advanced gastric cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gadgeel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Shields</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Heilbrun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Labadidi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zalupski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chaplen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Clin Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="41" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phase III trial in metastatic gastroesophageal adenocarcinoma with fluorouracil, leucovorin plus either oxaliplatin or cisplatin: A study of the Arbeitsgemeinschaft Internistische Onkologie</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S E</forename><surname>Al -Batran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J T</forename><surname>Hartmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Probst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schmalenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hollerbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hofheinz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1435" to="1442" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Randomized phase III study comparing irinotecan combined with 5-fluorouracil and folinic acid to cisplatin combined with 5-fluorouracil in chemotherapy naive patients with advanced adenocarcinoma of the stomach or esophagogastric junction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zaluski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Barone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Valvere</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yalcin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Peschel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1450" to="1457" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Standard First-Line Chemotherapy for Metastatic Gastric Cancer in Japan Has Met the Global Standard: Evidence From Recent Phase III Trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Takashima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Nakajima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hamaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shimada</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gastrointestinal Cancer Research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="239" to="244" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oxaliplatin-related neuropathy in Indian patients-no difference between generic and original molecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Sirohi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ostwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dawood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lopes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Talole</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nashikkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Indian J Med Paediatr Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Over-expression of HER2 in Indian patients with gastric cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Patil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mehta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mohandas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Indian J Gastroenterol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">350</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
