<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Impact of standardized MONitoring for Detection of Atrial Fibrillation in Ischemic Stroke (MonDAFIS) -Rationale and design of a prospective randomized multicenter study</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Karl</forename><forename type="middle">Georg</forename><surname>Haeusler</surname></persName>
							<email>georg.haeusler@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Stroke Research Berlin &amp; Department of Neurology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">German Stroke Society</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">German Atrial Fibrillation Network association</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Paulus</forename><surname>Kirchhof</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">German Atrial Fibrillation Network association</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for Cardiovascular Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Birmingham</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Heuschmann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Clinical Epidemiology and Biometry</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Failure Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Clinical Trial Centre Würzburg</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University Würzburg &amp; Comprehensive Heart</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Würzburg</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">University Hospital Würzburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Ulrich</forename><surname>Laufs</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Klinik für Innere Medizin III</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Homburg, Saar</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Otto</forename><surname>Busse</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">German Stroke Society</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>BA</roleName><forename type="first">Claudia</forename><surname>Kunze</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Stroke Research Berlin &amp; Department of Neurology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Götz</forename><surname>Thomalla</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Darius</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Nabavi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">German Stroke Society</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vivantes Klinikum Neukölln</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Joachim</forename><surname>Röther</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">German Stroke Society</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Asklepios Klinik Altona</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hamburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Roland</forename><surname>Veltkamp</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">German Stroke Society</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff10">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Stroke Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Imperial College London</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>11 Excellence Cluster NeuroCure</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff11">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Matthias</forename><surname>Endres</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Stroke Research Berlin &amp; Department of Neurology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">German Stroke Society</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff12">
								<orgName type="department">German Center for Neurodegenerative Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Partner Site Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff13">
								<orgName type="department">German Center for Cardiovascular Diseases</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Partner Site Berlin</addrLine>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of cardiovascular medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hospital of the University of Münster</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff14">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Benjamin Franklin Hindenburgdamm 30</addrLine>
									<postCode>12200</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Impact of standardized MONitoring for Detection of Atrial Fibrillation in Ischemic Stroke (MonDAFIS) -Rationale and design of a prospective randomized multicenter study</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">7AF8EFB19B63CB2A297F088BBCD1000C</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ahj.2015.10.010</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted to: American Heart Journal -</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:11+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>atrial fibrillation -stroke -cerebral ischemia -stroke unit -ECG monitoringanticoagulation</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Abstract</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p><s>Atrial fibrillation (AF) is estimated to account for approximately every fifth ischemic stroke.</s><s>In routine clinical practice, detection of undiagnosed, clinically silent AF represents a major diagnostic challenge, and in up to 30% of patients with ischemic stroke AF remains undetected.</s><s>The MonDAFIS study has been designed to quantify the diagnostic yield and clinical relevance of systematic ECG monitoring for patients with acute ischemic stroke during the subsequent in hospital stay.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Design</head><p><s>Prospective randomized multicenter study in 3,470 patients with acute ischemic stroke or TIA and without known AF on hospital admission.</s><s>Over a period of approximately 2 years patients will be enrolled in about 30 German certified stroke units and randomized 1:1 to receive either usual stroke unit diagnostic procedures for detection of AF (control group) or usual stroke unit diagnostic procedures plus standardized and centrally analyzed Holter ECG recording for up to 7 days in hospital (intervention group).</s><s>Results of the ECG core lab analysis will be provided to the patients and treating physicians.</s><s>All patients will be followed for treatment and cardiovascular outcomes at 6, 12, and 24 months after enrolment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outcomes</head><p><s>The primary outcome of the randomized MonDAFIS study is the proportion of patients who receive anticoagulation therapy 12 months after the index stroke.</s><s>Secondary outcomes include the number of stroke patients with newly detected AF in hospital and the rate of recurrent stroke, major bleedings, myocardial infarction or death 6, 12, and 24 months after the index event.</s><s>MonDAFIS will also explore patient-reported adherence to anticoagulants, the clinical relevance of short atrial tachycardia or excessive supraventricular ectopic activity as well as cost-effectiveness of prolonged, centrally analyzed ECG recordings.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>MonDAFIS will be the largest study to date to evaluate whether a prolonged and systematic ECG monitoring during the initial in hospital stay has an impact on secondary stroke prevention.</s><s>In addition, prognosis as well as adherence to medication up to two years after the index stroke will be analyzed.</s><s>The primary results of the MonDAFIS study may have the potential to change the current guidelines recommendations regarding ECG work-up after ischemic stroke.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Trial registration</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinicaltrials.gov NCT02204267</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p><s>Atrial fibrillation (AF) is the most frequent cardiac arrhythmia and, as its incidence is associated with age, the absolute number of patients with AF will increase in the next years due to the ageing of the societies.</s><s>AF is associated with a four-to fivefold increase of stroke risk and may account for every fifth ischemic stroke.</s><s>Moreover, AF patients suffering a stroke have a poorer prognosis and a higher stroke recurrence rate than do stroke patients without AF. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">1</ref> National and international guidelines recommend long-term oral anticoagulation for ischemic stroke patients with paroxysmal, persistent or permanent AF with the highest level of evidence, while the use of antiplatelet agents does not result in a relevant stroke risk reduction in AF patients.</s><s>The clinical availability of non-vitamin K antagonist oral anticoagulants (so called novel oral anticoagulants or NOACs) has overcome many of the practical difficulties of oral anticoagulation therapy, rendering anticoagulation a valid treatment option for the vast majority of stroke survivors with AF. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref> Detection of clinically "silent" paroxysmal AF represents a major diagnostic challenge in patients with acute ischemic stroke, and AF remains undetected in a relevant proportion of stroke patients. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">5</ref></s><s>Prolonged ECG monitoring <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref> and systematic analysis of ECG recordings 11 enhances detection of non-permanent AF after ischemic stroke, but data from randomized prospective trials is limited to the subset of patients with cryptogenic stroke 9,10 while observational data suggest that a substantial portion of noncryptogenic stroke patients also suffers from silent AF. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12</ref> However, the ECG method of choice is still a matter of debate.</s><s>While implantable cardiac-event recorders 9 seem to solve the question of optimal duration of ECG monitoring, its invasive implantation procedure and current costs do not support routine use in unselected stroke patients.</s><s>On the other hand, Holter monitoring is readily available and non-invasive, but recording time is to a certain extent limited. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">10</ref></s><s>rprisingly, current stroke guidelines do not strictly recommend ECG monitoring for longer than 24 hours <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">13</ref> ; nor do they specify the requirements for ECG analysis in stroke survivors.</s><s>Subsequently, there is no common practice or "gold standard" for ECG monitoring in most healthcare systems including the German stroke unit system <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">11</ref> , which most likely results in a substantial under-diagnosis of AF in stroke survivors and potentially the occurrence of otherwise preventable ischemic strokes.</s></p><p><s>MonDAFIS is the first large, prospective multicenter study to include a systematic assessment and a randomized comparison of the diagnostic yield and therapeutic impact of prolonged inpatient ECG monitoring for clinically silent paroxysmal AF in an unselected cohort of stroke survivors.</s><s>Furthermore, this investigator initiated study will assess the clinical relevance of short atrial tachycardia as well as excessive supraventricular ectopic activity, both of which are frequently found in stroke patients. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">14</ref></s><s>In addition, the prospective MonDAFIS study will assess how persistence and adherence to prescribed medication impacts on outcome after ischemic stroke.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T ACCEPTED MANUSCRIPT</head><p><s>Rationale and design of the MonDAFIS study 4</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethical conducts</head><p><s>The Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin is the sponsor of the investigator initiated MonDAFIS study (Clinicaltrials.gov</s><s>NCT02204267).</s><s>The study received primary approval from the Ethics Committee of the Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Germany (EA2/033/14) and all participating centers will procure approval from their respective ethics committees.</s><s>All study procedures are carried out in accordance with the principles of Good Clinical Practice and the Declaration of Helsinki.</s><s>All study patients have to give informed consent.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sources of funding</head><p><s>The MonDAFIS study is supported by an unrestricted research grant to the Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin from Bayer Vital GmbH, Bayer HealthCare Pharmaceuticals, Germany.</s><s>No sources of funding were used to support the creation of this paper.</s><s>The authors are solely responsible for the design and conduct of this study, all study analyses, the drafting and editing of the paper and its final contents.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study design</head><p><s>This study is based on the observations of the non-randomized "Find-AF" study 6 , which demonstrated a significantly increased detection rate of paroxysmal AF in patients with acute ischemic stroke by using a 7 day Holter ECG.</s><s>Stroke patients without known AF who fulfilled the study entry criteria (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>) will be consecutively enrolled and randomized on a 1:1 basis either to undergo additional continuous Holter ECG recording for up to 7 days during the in hospital stay ("intervention group") or to undergo no additional ECG recording ("control group") (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).</s><s>Randomization is stratified by the participating centers.</s><s>Patients and treating physicians will be aware of diagnostic procedure allocation.</s></p><p><s>The rationale of including not only cryptogenic strokes but all ischemic strokes in MonDAFIS is the class I recommendation to anticoagulate AF patients with ischemic stroke, irrespective of stroke etiology. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">1</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study centers</head><p><s>The stroke units chosen for participation will represent a comprehensive coverage of all levels of care.</s></p><p><s>About 30 German stroke units will take part in the study.</s><s>All study centers have to be certified according to the regulations of the German Stroke Society.</s><s>Presently, there are more than 260 certified stroke units in Germany.</s><s>At present, about 80% of all stroke patients are receiving stroke unit</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T ACCEPTED MANUSCRIPT</head><p><s>Rationale and design of the MonDAFIS study 5 care in Germany (OB; personal communication).</s><s>We aim to enroll patients at "regional" stroke units, non university-based stroke centers and university-based stroke centers in a 40%: 30%: 30% ratio.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ECG monitoring</head><p><s>All study patients (control group as well as intervention group) will receive at least 24 hours of (monitor-based) ECG monitoring on the stroke unit (defined as usual care according to the current German Diagnosis Related Groups (DRG) system).</s><s>Additional ECG recording will be performed in parallel using the portable LIFECARD CF recorder (SPACELABS, Germany).</s><s>Additional Holter ECG recording in the intervention group will start as soon as possible (but at the latest 24 hours after admission at the stroke unit), and will be continued (as long as possible) until hospital discharge or for a maximum of 7 days.</s><s>We estimate an average duration of 96 hours in study patients randomized to the intervention group.</s><s>Study ECG data from Holter recordings will be transmitted to a cardiac core lab for analysis.</s><s>Results of the core lab analysis will be communicated to the respective study patient and the patient´s physician if indicated as soon as possible but no later than three weeks after hospital discharge in a telephone follow-up performed by the enrolling study center.</s><s>Moreover, the report will be sent by mail to the patient and the treating physician.</s><s>Additional ECG monitoring after hospital discharge is neither intended, strictly recommended nor restricted, and will be done at the discretion of the treating physicians.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cardiac core lab analysis</head><p><s>ECG data will be transmitted to the Holter ECG core lab in Birmingham, UK (coordinated by PK), analyzed by specifically trained personnel, and reviewed by a trained physician.</s><s>The report will classify each Holter ECG as recording with and without AF.</s><s>Each core lab report will contain the following items:</s></p><p><s>1) Presence or absence of AF, defined in accordance with the current ESC guideline as an absolute arrhythmia lasting ≥ 30 seconds <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">1</ref> .</s><s>In all patients with AF, the number and duration of AF episodes will be reported.</s><s>2) Atrial flutter will be reported separately, and the study protocol stipulates that anticoagulation for atrial flutter must be initiated in the same way as it is for atrial fibrillation.</s><s>3) Underlying heart rhythm.</s><s>4) Minimal, maximal, and mean heart rate.</s><s>5) Longest pause and number of pauses.</s><s>6) Presence or absence of AV block including degree of AV block.</s><s>7) Time and duration of recording.</s><s>Incidental findings of medical relevance (e.g.</s><s>ventricular tachycardia including torsade de pointes) will also be reported.</s><s>Dedicated alerts will be reported when medically relevant findings are identified.</s><s>We will also analyze all ECGs for atrial ectopy, short-lasting atrial arrhythmias not qualifying as AF, and other Holter ECG parameters for pre-specified exploratory analyses.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T ACCEPTED MANUSCRIPT</head><p><s>Rationale and design of the MonDAFIS study 6</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Baseline visit</head><p><s>Baseline assessment of all study patients will include: a detailed analysis of patient demographics, clinical characteristics (including the National Institute of Health Scale Score, the modified Rankin Scale score, the CHADS 2 and CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score), vital signs, medical history, and concomitant diseases, duration, method(s) and success of inpatient ECG recording, laboratory results, imaging results (head CT/MRI, carotid ultrasound of brain-supplying arteries, echocardiography), suspected cause of stroke at hospital discharge according to TOAST criteria <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">15</ref> , and previous symptoms probably related to undetected paroxysmal AF (such as intermittent breathlessness, palpitations, dizziness or fainting) to differentiate symptomatic from asymptomatic AF.</s><s>Despite of a non-standardized monitoring and assessment of supraventricular ectopy and short atrial runs in the control group, we will collect this information by analyzing the final patient report at discharge from the respective study center.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Follow-up</head><p><s>Follow-up will be carried out six months, one and two year(s) after the index stroke by a central, standardized telephone interview conducted by trained study nurses at the Center for Stroke Research Berlin, Germany.</s><s>The following data will be assessed: medication, recurrent ischemic stroke and other major vascular events, major bleeds, (all-cause) death, indications for the prescription of oral anticoagulation (including prescriptions unrelated to AF), the modified Rankin Scale score, the EQ-5D, the European Heart Rhythm Association (EHRA) score of atrial fibrillation as well as the Morisky Medication Adherence scale (MMAS-8; 1 year after the index stroke only) (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).</s><s>Central follow-up will be done in a blinded fashion with regard to the randomization after enrolment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study outcomes</head><p><s>The primary outcome is the difference in the proportion of study patients on oral anticoagulation (NOAC or vitamin K antagonist (VKA)) at 12 months after the index stroke, randomized either to usual in-hospital diagnostic procedures plus standardized prolonged ECG monitoring or to usual in-hospital diagnostic procedures.</s><s>The primary hypothesis is that the self-reported proportion of stroke patients on oral anticoagulants 12 months after the index stroke is higher in the intervention group than in the control group.</s><s>We plan to validate the accuracy of the provided information in a subgroup of patients by double-checking the prescribed medication by the treating physicians.</s><s>There are no study-specific recommendations regarding the individual medical treatment for stroke prevention, which is completely at the discretion of the treating physicians.</s><s>All secondary outcomes are listed in Table <ref type="table">3</ref>.</s></p><p><s>A critical event committee consisting of at least one cardiologist and one neurologist will adjudicate all serious adverse events of special interest (like recurrent stroke, myocardial infarction, major bleeding or death) as well as the primary endpoint of this study (blinded to the result of randomization).</s><s>The</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T ACCEPTED MANUSCRIPT</head><p><s>Rationale and design of the MonDAFIS study 7 data safety monitoring board (DSMB) will monitor potential consequences of delayed communication of core lab results in the intervention group (i.e.</s><s>hospitalization due to cardiac arrhythmia, stroke or death) as well as adverse events in the context of additional ECG monitoring in hospital (i.e.</s><s>falls or skin lesions).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical analysis</head><p><s>The sample size calculation is based on the endpoint "proportion of patients with self-reported oral anticoagulation 12 months after the index stroke".</s><s>We will test the null hypothesis that the proportion of self-reported oral anticoagulation 12 months after index stroke in patients undergoing usual ECG monitoring in hospital (control group) is equal to the proportion in patients with additional continuous ECG monitoring during the in hospital stay (intervention group).</s><s>This will be tested with a two-sided Fisher's exact test at significance level 0.05.</s><s>We assume a 1:1 group proportion.</s><s>According to Rizos et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12</ref> we assume a proportion of 2.8% of paroxysmal AF undergoing usual stroke unit monitoring for 24 hours (control group) and 7.7% with additional continuous ECG monitoring for 3-4 days during the inhospital stay (intervention group).</s><s>We assume that 90% of patients with newly detected paroxysmal AF receive oral anticoagulation or are given a recommendation for oral anticoagulation after hospital discharge.</s><s>At 12 months we assume a proportion of 65% of all patients with persistent use of oral anticoagulation according to previous studies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">16</ref></s><s>This yields a proportion of 1.64% patients on anticoagulation at 12 months in the control group and 4.50% in the intervention group.</s><s>Moreover, we have to keep in mind an additional proportion of patients who receive anticoagulation in both groups for 1 year after hospital discharge due to AF detection after recurrent stroke.</s></p><p><s>By assuming an annual rate for recurrent stroke or systemic embolism of 9.16% in patients with undetected paroxysmal AF 17 in up to 5.0% of patients in the intervention group and in up to 9.9% in the control group (considering a maximal proportion of 12.7% patients with paroxysmal AF 6 ), we assume that an additional proportion of up to 0.91% of patients in the control group and of 0.46% in the intervention group will receive anticoagulation at 1 year due to AF detection after hospital discharge.</s><s>This leads to the assumption of an overall proportion of 2.55% of patients with self-reported oral anticoagulation in the control group and of 4.96% in the intervention group.</s><s>Accordingly, a sample size of 2 x 1,388 = 2,776 will ensure detecting a significant deviation from the null hypothesis with a power of 90%.</s><s>Assuming a dropout rate of 20%, a total sample size of 3,470 patients is needed.</s><s>To ensure a high external validity, we are aiming to recruit from consecutive patients enrolled in settings that are close to clinical reality.</s><s>Therefore, we do not apply any major inclusion or exclusion criteria.</s><s>In observational studies in health services research, a drop-out rate of 20% at one-year follow up is common <ref type="bibr">18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19</ref> and can generally be attributed to loss to follow-up (e.g.</s><s>change of residence without notice of change of address) and to all-cause death within the first year after stroke.</s><s>We would not</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T ACCEPTED MANUSCRIPT</head><p><s>Rationale and design of the MonDAFIS study 8 assume differential dropout rates between the control and the intervention group.</s><s>All secondary outcomes will be evaluated using appropriate descriptive, univariate and multivariate statistical methods based on the underlying distribution of the data.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study schedule</head><p><s>The first patient was enrolled in December 2014 at the Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin.</s><s>After starting enrolment in ten sites in April 2015, we aim for a recruitment period of approximately 2 years, ending in spring 2017.</s><s>With regard to the planned duration of follow-up, first patient in to last-patient out will be approximately 4.5 years.</s><s>The planned duration of the entire study is five years.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Current status of recruitment</head><p><s>As at September 28th,, 2015, 580 (16.7 %) of 3,470 patients were enrolled to the MonDAFIS study in 23 active study centers in Germany.</s><s>Moreover, 3 study centers are initiated but are not yet recruiting.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>By using non-invasive, commonly available Holter monitoring, this investigator-initiated prospective randomized multicenter study will uncover the true burden of undiagnosed AF in a representativealmost unselected -sample of patients with acute ischemic stroke or TIA while they are being treated in hospital.</s><s>These findings have the potential to impact on patient management, as oral anticoagulation is the secondary prevention of choice in stroke or TIA survivors when AF has been documented. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">3</ref></s><s>Early optimization of secondary stroke prevention might help to minimize recurrent stroke in this cohort and further strengthen the importance of stroke unit as well as in hospital care.</s></p><p><s>Unique features of the MonDAFIS study are the very large sample size including not only cryptogenic strokes but all ischemic strokes as well as the control group, allowing us to focus on the potential impact of prolonged in-hospital ECG recording on medical secondary stroke prevention during midterm follow-up.</s><s>MonDAFIS will provide valuable new insights into the detection rate of "silent" AF in almost unselected stroke patients, thereby supplementing the available detailed information on patients with cryptogenic stroke. 9,10</s><s>Moreover, the study ECG data will be analyzed by a cardiologist, while stroke unit monitoring in Germany rarely involves a cardiologist. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">11</ref></s><s>Subsequently, our data will allow us to estimate the impact of advanced diagnostic measures on the rate of cardiovascular events and patient outcome after acute ischemic stroke, as similarly reported for stroke unit treatment. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">20</ref></s><s>nDAFIS therefore has the potential to impact on the so far limited guideline recommendations for ECG monitoring after stroke in hospital. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">11</ref></s><s>By including of approximately 30 study sites, the MonDAFIS</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T ACCEPTED MANUSCRIPT</head><p><s>Rationale and design of the MonDAFIS study 9 study will also provide important data regarding the current level of diagnostic care for AF detection on different levels of stroke units in Germany.</s></p><p><s>Besides patient persistence in taking an oral anticoagulation during clinical course, the important question of adherence to medication will be addressed.</s><s>Moreover, we will explore the clinical relevance of short lasting atrial runs, which are a common finding in stroke patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">6,</ref><ref type="bibr">8</ref> but appear to be independently associated with a twofold higher risk of subsequent stroke according to US claims data. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21</ref></s><s>Furthermore, we will assess the prognostic impact of excessive supraventricular ectopic activity, also frequently found in stroke patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">14</ref> and associated with an almost threefold risk of admission for atrial fibrillation or stroke in the Copenhagen Holter Study. <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">22</ref></s><s>Nevertheless, there is no recommendation to use oral anticoagulants for secondary stroke prevention in patients with excessive supraventricular ectopic activity or short lasting atrial runs.</s><s>Regarding the prognostic impact of excessive supraventricular ectopic activity and the rate of undetected AF in stroke patients, the awaited results of the Find-AF RANDOMIZED study will add substantial information. <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">23</ref></s><s>This randomized study has enrolled 400 patients with acute ischemic stroke in four German Stroke Units.</s><s>By using repetitive ECG recording in the intervention group also during follow-up, the primary endpoint of Find-AF RANDOMIZED is the detection of AF/atrial flutter within six months after the index stroke or before recurrence of stroke or systemic embolism.</s></p><p><s>By assessing stroke unit care in Germany, MonDAFIS might underestimate the effect of prolonged ECG monitoring in other health care systems with less intensive routine ECG work-up.</s><s>Moreover, the duration and quality of additional ECG recording may be influenced by patient empowerment and the participation of nursing staff and physicians.</s><s>In addition, there might be a selection bias by not including stroke patients who are not able to provide informed consent.</s><s>Despite the fact that nurses and treating physicians are blinded for the results of the additional ECG recordings in the intervention group (because the ECG curve is not displayed while being recorded), the open-label design of the study might cause a bias.</s><s>Study centers were, however, encouraged to avoid differences in usual diagnostic care in both study arms.</s><s>While there might be a discrepancy in the quality of ECG analysis between the study arms.</s><s>The control group nevertheless represents clinical routine in Germany.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>In summary, MonDAFIS will be the largest study to date to evaluate systematic ECG monitoring in  MonDAFIS: Inclusion and exclusion criteria.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Inclusion criteria</head><p><s> Written informed consent.</s></p><p><s> Age ≥ 18 years.</s></p><p><s> Acute ischemic stroke or TIA (persisting neurological deficit on admission and / or matching brain lesion on MR imaging).</s></p><p><s> Stroke unit admission within 72 hours after onset of stroke-related symptoms.</s></p><p><s> Enrolment within 24 hours after stroke unit admission.</s></p><p><s> Start of ECG recording within 24 hours after stroke unit admission (according to randomization)</s></p><p><s> Sufficient knowledge of German.</s></p><p><s> Willingness to participate in follow-up.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exclusion criteria</head><p><s> Known AF before hospital admission.</s></p><p><s> AF according to 12-lead ECG on hospital admission.</s></p><p><s> AF according to inpatient ECG recording / stroke unit monitoring before enrolment.</s></p><p><s> Pre-stroke life expectancy less than 1 year.</s></p><p><s> Post-stroke life expectancy less than 1 month.</s></p><p><s> Participation in an interventional study.</s></p><p><s> Pregnancy and / or breast-feeding.</s></p><p><s> Implanted devices with the ability to record AF</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>stroke survivors.</s><s>The MonDAFIS study is in line with the intention of best-medical and individualized therapy.</s><s>If successful, this randomized multicenter study could motivate important modifications of current diagnostic standards after acute ischemic stroke or TIA, and thus improve secondary stroke prevention in daily clinical practice.</s><s>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T ACCEPTED MANUSCRIPT A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">fibrillation after ischemic stroke: a randomized, controlled trial. Stroke 2013;44: 2525-31.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>We thank Dr. Joanna Dietzel (CSB) for their outstanding support of the study conduct.</s><s>Furthermore, we thank Catherine Aubel (CSB) for critically reviewing the manuscript.</s><s>In particular, we thank Uschi von der Osten (Bayer Vital GmbH) for her continued support of the project.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Abbreviations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><note type="other">ACCEPTED MANUSCRIPT Table 3</note><p><s>Primary outcome and secondary outcomes of the MonDAFIS study.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Primary outcome of the MonDAFIS study</head><p><s> The proportional number of study patients on oral anticoagulation (NOAC or VKA) at 12 months after the index stroke, randomized either to usual in-hospital diagnostic procedures plus standardized prolonged ECG monitoring or to usual in-hospital diagnostic procedures.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Secondary outcomes of the MonDAFIS study</head><p><s> Number of stroke patients with AF newly detected in hospital using a standardized prolonged ECG monitoring compared to usual stroke unit diagnostic procedures alone.</s></p><p><s> Proportion of recurrent stroke, major bleeds, myocardial infarction and all-cause death (composite endpoint) within 6, 12 and 24 months after the index stroke in the intervention group or control group, respectively.</s></p><p><s> Overall costs of standardized prolonged ECG monitoring for paroxysmal AF in stroke patients.</s></p><p><s> Self-reported persistence in taking oral anticoagulation (NOAC or VKA) at 24 months after the index stroke in patients with AF.</s></p><p><s> Impact of stroke unit level (i.e.</s><s>primary or comprehensive stroke center) on the rate of AF detection in in-hospital stroke in patients randomized to the intervention group.</s></p><p><s> Proportion of recurrent stroke, major bleeds, myocardial infarction and all-cause death within 6, 12 and 24 months after the index stroke in patients randomized to the intervention group with:</s></p><p><s>(I) sinus rhythm, (II) non-permanent AF detected by usual stroke unit diagnostic procedures or by standardized prolonged continuous ECG monitoring in hospital, (III) paroxysmal short atrial tachycardia in hospital, (IV) excessive supraventricular ectopic activity in hospital.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">OB and CB report no conflicts of interest. GT has received speaker´s honoraria and consulting fees from Acandis, Bayer Healthcare, Boehringer Ingelheim, Covidien, Bristol-Myers-Squibb and Pfizer. DGN has received speaker´s honoraria and consulting fees from Bayer, Boehringer Ingelheim, Bristol-Myers-Squibb, Daiichi Sankyo, Novartis and Pfizer. JR has received speaker´s honoraria and consulting fees from Bayer, Boehringer Ingelheim, Bristol-Myers-Squibb, Pfizer and Astra Zeneca. RV has received speaker´s honoraria, consulting fees and research support from Bayer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Akdä</forename><surname>Abda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Amgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Astrazeneca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Berlin-Chemie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Boehringer-Ingelheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Dach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Daiichi-Sankyo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Dfg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Eu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lilly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Medtronik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Msd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Pfizer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Roche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Sanofi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Servier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Stifterverbad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Synlab</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Uks</forename><surname>Uds</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">honoraria/reimbursements for lectures, participation in studies, scientific cooperations</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Boehringer Ingelheim, Bristol-Myers-Squibb, Daiichi Sankyo; Boehringer Ingelheim, Bristol-Myers-Squibb, Ever</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>with Saarland University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Apoplex medical technologies, Novartis and Pfizer. ME reports lecture fees and study grants by Bayer. Glaxo Smith Kline, MSD, Novartis and Pfizer</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2012 focused update of the ESC Guidelines for the management of atrial fibrillation: an update of the 2010 ESC Guidelines for the management of atrial fibrillation--developed with the special contribution of the European Heart Rhythm Association</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Camm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gyh</forename><surname>Lip</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Caterina R De</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Europace</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1385" to="1413" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">AHA/ACC/HRS guideline for the management of patients with atrial fibrillation: a report of the American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines and the Heart Rhythm Society</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>January</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Alpert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Am. Coll. Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="e1" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno>1.0. 31.01.2015</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.awmf.org/leitlinien/detail/ll/030-133.html" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sekundärprophylaxe ischämischer Schlaganfall und transitorische ischämische Attacke -Part</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<publisher>German Stroke Society</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atrial fibrillation guidelines across the Atlantic: a comparison of the current recommendations of the European Society of Cardiology/European Heart Rhythm Association/European Association of Cardiothoracic Surgeons, the American College of Cardiology Foundation/American Heart Association/Heart Rhythm Society, and the Canadian Cardiovascular Society</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kirchhof</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Curtis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Skanes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1471" to="1474" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cryptogenic stroke: Is silent atrial fibrillation the culprit?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Glotzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ziegler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Heart Rhythm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="234" to="241" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhanced detection of paroxysmal atrial fibrillation by early and prolonged continuous holter monitoring in patients with cerebral ischemia presenting in sinus rhythm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Stahrenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Weber-Krüger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Seegers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2884" to="2888" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Improved detection of silent atrial fibrillation using 72-hour</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hamann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Holter ECG in patients with ischemic stroke: a prospective multicenter cohort study</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3357" to="3364" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cryptogenic stroke and underlying atrial fibrillation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sanna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Diener</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Passman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N. Engl. J. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">370</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2478" to="2486" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atrial fibrillation in patients with cryptogenic stroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gladstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Spring</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dorian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N. Engl. J. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">370</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2467" to="2477" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diagnostic Work-Up for Detection of Paroxysmal Atrial Fibrillation After Acute Ischemic Stroke: Cross-Sectional Survey on German Stroke Units</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Rizos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Quilitzsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Busse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>pii: STROKEAHA.115.009374</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-04-30">2015. Apr 30</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Continuous stroke unit electrocardiographic monitoring versus 24-hour Holter electrocardiography for detection of paroxysmal atrial fibrillation after stroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Rizos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Güntner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Jenetzky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2689" to="2694" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Guidelines for the prevention of stroke in patients with stroke and transient ischemic attack: a guideline for healthcare professionals from the American Heart Association/American Stroke Association</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Kernan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ovbiagele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Black</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2160" to="2236" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Excessive supraventricular ectopic activity is indicative of paroxysmal atrial fibrillation in patients with cerebral ischemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Weber-Krüger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gröschel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mende</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e67602</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Classification of subtype of acute ischemic stroke. Definitions for use in a multicenter clinical trial. TOAST. Trial of Org 10172 in Acute Stroke Treatment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bendixen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kappelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="41" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Persistent use of secondary preventive drugs declines rapidly during the first 2 years after stroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Glader</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sjölander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Eriksson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="397" to="401" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Apixaban versus aspirin in patients with atrial fibrillation and previous stroke or transient ischaemic attack: a predefined subgroup analysis from AVERROES, a randomised trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Diener</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Eikelboom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Connolly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="231" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Association between socioeconomic status and functional impairment 3 months after ischemic stroke: the Berlin Stroke Register</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Grube</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Koennecke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Walter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3325" to="3330" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cluster randomized controlled trial of a patient and general practitioner intervention to improve the management of multiple risk factors after stroke: stop stroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cda</forename><surname>Wolfe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Redfern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Rudd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2470" to="2476" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Organised inpatient (stroke unit) care for stroke</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">D000197</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Paroxysmal supraventricular tachycardia and the risk of ischemic stroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kamel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Msv</forename><surname>Elkind</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bhave</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1550" to="1554" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Excessive supraventricular ectopic activity and increased risk of atrial fibrillation and stroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Binici</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Intzilakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1904" to="1911" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Finding atrial fibrillation in stroke patients: Randomized evaluation of enhanced and prolonged Holter monitoring -Find-AF(RANDOMISED) -rationale and design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Weber-Krüger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gelbrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Stahrenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">168</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="438" to="445" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
