<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Stem Cell-Derived Immature Human Dorsal Root Ganglia Neurons to Identify Peripheral Neurotoxicants</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-03-01">March 1, 2016.</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Lisa</forename><surname>Hoelting</surname></persName>
							<email>lisa.hoelting@uni-konstanz.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">M.Sc</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Box M657</postBox>
									<postCode>D-78457</postCode>
									<settlement>Konstanz</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">M.Sc</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Box M657</postBox>
									<postCode>D-78457</postCode>
									<settlement>Konstanz</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stefanie</forename><surname>Klima</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">M.Sc</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Box M657</postBox>
									<postCode>D-78457</postCode>
									<settlement>Konstanz</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Christiaan</forename><surname>Karreman</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">M.Sc</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Box M657</postBox>
									<postCode>D-78457</postCode>
									<settlement>Konstanz</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Marianna</forename><surname>Grinberg</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">M.Sc</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Box M657</postBox>
									<postCode>D-78457</postCode>
									<settlement>Konstanz</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Johannes</forename><surname>Meisig</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">M.Sc</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Box M657</postBox>
									<postCode>D-78457</postCode>
									<settlement>Konstanz</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Margit</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">M.Sc</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Box M657</postBox>
									<postCode>D-78457</postCode>
									<settlement>Konstanz</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tamara</forename><surname>Rotshteyn</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">M.Sc</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Box M657</postBox>
									<postCode>D-78457</postCode>
									<settlement>Konstanz</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Örg</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">M.Sc</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Box M657</postBox>
									<postCode>D-78457</postCode>
									<settlement>Konstanz</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Rahnenf</forename><surname>Ührer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">M.Sc</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Box M657</postBox>
									<postCode>D-78457</postCode>
									<settlement>Konstanz</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nils</forename><forename type="middle">Bl</forename><surname>Üthgen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">M.Sc</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Box M657</postBox>
									<postCode>D-78457</postCode>
									<settlement>Konstanz</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Agapios</forename><surname>Sachinidis</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">M.Sc</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Box M657</postBox>
									<postCode>D-78457</postCode>
									<settlement>Konstanz</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tanja</forename><surname>Waldmann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">M.Sc</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Box M657</postBox>
									<postCode>D-78457</postCode>
									<settlement>Konstanz</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Marcel</forename><surname>Leist</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">M.Sc</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Konstanz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>Box M657</postBox>
									<postCode>D-78457</postCode>
									<settlement>Konstanz</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Stem Cell-Derived Immature Human Dorsal Root Ganglia Neurons to Identify Peripheral Neurotoxicants</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-03-01">March 1, 2016.</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">4D44DEBCE0F7818EF6DA785E11CDC1C9</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.5966/sctm.2015-0108</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received May 19, 2015; accepted for publication November 19, 2015;</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:12+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Human pluripotent stem cells x Neural differentiation x Peripheral neuropathies x In vitro drug and toxicity testing</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p><s>Peripheral neurotoxicity is a major issue in drug development and environmental medicine.</s><s>For instance, chemical-induced axonopathies play an important role in the toxicity of drugs and environmental chemicals <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>, and testing systems for this pathological endpoint are in high demand.</s><s>Moreover, the growth of neurites during development has been considered a key biological process that can be targeted by chemicals <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s>Therefore, the testing of neurotoxicity on the basis of human cells is an emerging research field in safety sciences.</s><s>The generation of the relevant target cell populations from human pluripotent stem cells has aroused great hopes in biomedical research and the safety sciences <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref> that model systems will be established to identify neurotoxicity hazards and to devise countermeasures.</s></p><p><s>The currently used methods to test for neurotoxicity are all based on experimental animals in accordance with Organization Economic Co-operation and Development test guideline 424.</s><s>These tests cover all relevant target cell types but are expensive, labor-intensive, and associated with uncertainties in the extrapolation of the results to humans <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">8]</ref>.</s><s>Therefore, the U.S. National Research Council and major regulatory agencies have recommended new strategies for toxicity testing (Tox21) based on in vitro high throughput testing and cell-based systems, ideally of human origin <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">10]</ref>.</s><s>Thus, in vitro neurotoxicity and developmental neurotoxicity assays are required that can ultimately be assembled into a test battery covering all relevant cell types and endpoints <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The first newer approaches to establish test systems for neurite integrity and growth used rodent primary neural cultures and immortalized human and nonhuman clonal cell lines to measure neurite length or to quantify the number of neurites and dendrites in low-density cultures <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[13]</ref>.</s><s>The effect of chemicals on neurite network formation and function has also been assessed by manual counting of neurite interconnections <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[14]</ref> or by recording spontaneous network activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[15]</ref>.</s><s>More recently, more physiological high-density cultures have been used for quantification of neurite growth and viability by automated high-content image analysis, which enables a better separation between specific neurite toxicity and general cytotoxicity <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">17]</ref>.</s><s>Human neurons have also been generated from pluripotent stem cells (PSCs) for neurite toxicity testing.</s><s>This approach showed the potential of the use of stem cells to generate target cell types not otherwise accessible <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[18]</ref>.</s><s>However, most work has focused on mechanistic case studies, and broad applications for unbiased comparisons across many compound classes have been extremely sparse.</s><s>Moreover, it has proved surprisingly difficult to generate a system that distinguishes neurotoxicity from general cytotoxicity, that allows sufficient throughput for realistic application (most published studies have reported on only # 3 specific neurotoxicants), and that is technically robust enough, concerning cell differentiation and its toxicological readout.</s></p><p><s>The protein expression patterns in neurites of different neuronal types (e.g., peripheral/central or human/mouse) can differ, and this will also affect the abundance of modulators of axonal degeneration <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[19]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[21]</ref>.</s><s>Therefore, it appears advisable to choose a toxicological model system that matches its pathological reference system (e.g., human peripheral axons) as closely as possible, as far as the type of neurons and the species of their origin are concerned.</s></p><p><s>As primary human peripheral cells are hardly available, we used human stem cells to generate immature dorsal root ganglia neuron (iDRG) cells for use in neurite toxicity testing.</s><s>Previous experience in the field has shown that it is challenging to measure neurite toxicity independent from that of general cytotoxicity <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">22,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">23]</ref>.</s><s>Such specificity can be obtained if a model system depends on a functional feature that is only found in neurites (e.g., outgrowth).</s><s>Growing neurites have been reported to be more susceptible to some neuritedamaging toxicants than established neurites.</s><s>Therefore, cell culture systems with strong neurite growth will allow the detection of toxicant effects at concentrations that did not compromise cell survival <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">16]</ref>.</s><s>To establish a new method to assess peripheral neurotoxicity, we therefore used iDRG cells and followed their neurite growth.</s><s>To test for cell-type specific effects, we compared a broad range of compounds in this new peripheral neurotoxicity (PeriTox) test with the Lund human mesencephalic cells (LUHMES) neurite test (using central neurons), and clearly different hit patterns were revealed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MATERIALS AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cell Culture and Neural Differentiation</head><p><s>Human pluripotent stem cell lines were cultured according to standard protocols <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[24]</ref> and differentiated into immature dorsal root ganglia neurons, as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[25]</ref>, with modifications as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</s><s>In detail, the H9 human embryonic stem cell (hESC) line (WA09 line) was obtained from WiCell Research Institute (Madison, WI, http://www.wicell.org)</s><s>and minicircle induced pluripotent stem cell (mc-iPSC) from System Biosciences (model no.</s><s>SC301A-1; System Biosciences, Mountain View, CA, http://www.systembio.com).</s><s>The import of cells and experiments were authorized under license no.</s><s>170-79-1-4-27 (Robert Koch Institute, Berlin, Germany, http://www.rki.de).</s><s>Differentiation of the pluripotent stem cell lines hESC-H9 and mc-iPSC to iDRG cells was prepared on the day of differentiation minus 3 (DoD239) by replating human pluripotent stem cells (hPSCs) in a single cell suspension onto Matrigel-coated plates (BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ, http://www.bdbiosciences.com;</s><s>30,000 cells per cm 2 ) in "conditioned" keratinocyte culture medium (KCM).</s><s>This KCM was conditioned for 24 hours on mitomycin C-inactivated mouse embryonic fibroblasts.</s><s>It was freshly supplemented with 10 ng/ml fibroblast growth factor 2 (R&amp;D Systems, Minneapolis, MN, http://www.rndsystems.com)</s><s>and ROCK inhibitor Y-27632 (10 mM; Tocris Bioscience, Bristol, U.K., http:// www.tocris.com).</s><s>On DoD09, neural differentiation was started by adding neural differentiation medium KSR-S (knockout Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium [DMEM] with 15% serum replacement, 1 3 Glutamax, 1 3 nonessential amino acids, and 50 mM b-mercaptoethanol; all ingredients from Invitrogen, Darmstadt, Germany, http://www.thermofisher.com) and the combination of six small molecule pathway inhibitors.</s><s>In detail, noggin (35 ng/ml; R&amp;D Systems), dorsomorphin (600 nM; Tocris Bioscience), and SB-431642 (10 mM; Tocris Bioscience) were added on DoD09-59 and CHIR99021 (1.5 mM; Axon Medchem, Vienna, VA, http://www/axonmedchem.com), SU5402 (1.5 mM; Tocris Bioscience), and DAPT (g-Secretase Inhibitor IX; 5 mM; Merck, Darmstadt, Germany, http://www.merck.de)</s><s>were added on DoD29-89.</s><s>From DoD49 onward, the medium was gradually replaced by N2-S medium (DMEM/F12, with 2 mM Glutamax, 0.1 mg/ml apotransferrin, 1.55 mg/ml glucose, 25 mg/ml insulin, 100 mM putrescine, 30 nM selenium, and 20 nM progesterone).</s><s>On DoD89, the cells were cryopreserved.</s><s>After thawing, the obtained neuronal precursors were cultured in 25% KSR-S and 75% N2-S medium supplemented with CHIR99021 (1.5 mM), SU5402 (1.5 mM), and DAPT (5 mM) and seeded at a density of 0.1 3 10 6 cells per milliliter onto Matrigel-coated wells (BD Biosciences).</s><s>For further differentiation, one half of the medium was changed on DoD1 and again on DoD2.</s><s>From DoD3 onward, the cells were grown in the presence of brain-derived neurotrophic factor, glia-derived neurotrophic factor, and nerve growth factor (25 ng/ml; R&amp;D Systems) to facilitate further differentiation and maturation into peripheral neurons.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Transcriptome Analysis</head><p><s>prepared for microarray hybridization on Affymetrix Human Genome U133 plus 2.0 (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA, http:// www.affymetrix.com),</s><s>as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">27]</ref>.</s><s>Data analysis was performed as described in supplemental online data.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Immunocytochemistry</head><p><s>At the indicated DoD, the cells were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde/ 2% sucrose before permeabilization in 0.5% Triton X-100.</s><s>After blocking in 5% bovine serum albumin/phosphate-buffered saline for 1 hour, the cells were incubated with primary antibodies for 1 hour at room temperature and stained with the appropriate secondary antibody for 30 minutes.</s><s>DNA was stained with H-33342 (1 mg/ml), and coverslips were mounted in FluorSave reagent (Merck Millipore, Billerica, MA, http:// www.merckmillipore.com).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Peripheral Neurotoxicity Test</head><p><s>For the PeriTox test, DoD89 cells were thawed and seeded at a density of 0.1 3 10 6 cells per cm 2 in 50 ml of differentiation medium on Matrigel-coated 96-well dishes (BD Biosciences).</s><s>Test chemicals were serially diluted in differentiation medium, and 50 ml was added to the cells, 1 hour after seeding.</s><s>All analyses were performed 24 hours after treatment.</s><s>The neurite area and viability were assessed as described in the supplemental online data.</s><s>In brief, the cells were loaded with 1 mM calcein-AM and 1 mg/ml H-33342 for 1 hour at 37°C.</s><s>For image acquisition, an ArrayScan VTI HCS (highcontent imaging) microscope (Cellomics, Waltham, MA, http://thermofisher.com) was used.</s><s>In an automated procedure, all H-33342 + /calcein-positive cells were analyzed as viable cells.</s><s>The sum of fields evaluated for one data point contained 1,489 6 485 healthy cells with a neurite area of 16,100 6 4,000 pixels.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Quantitative Reverse-Transcription Real Time Polymerase Chain Reaction</head><p><s>RNA was extracted at the indicated DoD, and 1 mg of RNA was reversed transcribed (iScript, Bio-Rad Laboratories, Munich, Germany, http://www.bio-rad.com).</s><s>For quantitative reversetranscription real time polymerase chain reaction (qPCR), SsoFast EvaGreen Supermix was used on a Bio-Rad Light Cycler (Bio-Rad Laboratories).</s><s>Real time quantification for each gene was normalized to the amount of RPL13A mRNA and expressed relative to the transcript level in hESCs using the 2 (2ΔΔC(t)) method <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[28]</ref>, as described in detail previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[29]</ref>.</s><s>The list of primers is given in the supplemental online data.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Analysis</head><p><s>All experiments were repeated at least three times.</s><s>Reference to replicates always means data from different cell preparations (thawings; i.e., biological replicates).</s><s>Data are presented, using GraphPad Prism, version 5.0 (GraphPad Software, La Jolla, CA, http://www.graphpad.com),</s><s>and statistical differences were tested by analysis of variance with post hoc tests as described in the supplemental online data.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Two-Step Differentiation of iDRG Cells From Pluripotent Stem Cells</head><p><s>To provide a sustainable supply of human peripheral neurons, we made use of a recently established protocol that allows conversion of hPSCs to differentiated sensory neurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[25]</ref>.</s><s>A cryopreservation step was introduced on DoD89 to allow the production of large cell lots, available after thawing as a population of rapidly differentiating neurons (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, top).</s><s>Immunostaining showed that the cells had different differentiation states on the day of freezing: a large (desired) subpopulation was Sox10 + (neural crest marker, precursors of peripheral nervous system), few (undesired) cells were PAX6 + (neuroepithelial marker for central nervous system precursors; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>, left), and a few cells expressed TUJ1 + , an early neuronal marker (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>, right).</s><s>A more homogeneous population was obtained after thawing.</s><s>Already at 8 hours after thawing, the developing cells were TUJ1 + and had lost the precursor markers SOX10 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>) and PAX6 (data not shown).</s><s>At 24 hours after thawing (DoD1), the neuronal marker TUJ1 indicated pronounced formation of early neurites (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref>).</s><s>An upregulation of NeuN in TUJ1 + cells indicated the generation of fully postmitotic neurons at DoD4 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1D</ref>).</s><s>Quantification of EdU incorporation showed that, already at DoD1, only a few proliferating cells (15%) were present; on DoD4, proliferation had virtually stopped (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1E</ref>).</s><s>At DoD1, TUJ1 + cells expressed BRN3A (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1F</ref>) and were positive for peripherin and ISL1 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1G</ref>).</s><s>At DoD4, these had formed a dense network.</s><s>Strong and homogeneous expression of the transcription factor BRN3A (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1H</ref>) and positivity for peripherin and ISL1 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1I</ref>) indicated that virtually all cells developed toward peripheral neurons.</s></p><p><s>A differentiation similar to the one of hESCs was also observed for a line of iPSCs (supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A-1D</ref>).</s><s>Our findings are in line with a recent characterization of a one-step protocol to generate sensory neurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[25,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">30]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Functional Characterization of iDRG Cells</head><p><s>We investigated some functional properties of our iDRG cells at relatively early stages after thawing.</s><s>First, the cellular response to depolarization was studied.</s><s>Intracellular free calcium ([Ca 2+ ] i ) was measured after the addition of K + (50 mM) to the extracellular medium or after the opening of voltage-dependent Na + -channels by veratridine.</s><s>On DoD7, virtually all neuronal cells derived from hESCs or iPSCs showed a depolarization-induced increase of [Ca 2+ ] i (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>; supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1E</ref>).</s><s>The intracellular Ca 2+ response was blocked by verapamil and nifedipine, inhibitors of voltage-dependent Ca 2+ channels (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>).</s><s>Thus, the cells obtained by our 2-step protocol expressed functional veratridine-sensitive voltage-dependent Na channels and voltage-dependent Ca channels, as is typical for neurons and a few other excitable cells.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Differentiation Track of iDRG Cells</head><p><s>In order to provide a full characterization of cell identity at different stages (hESCs, DoD89, DoD1, DoD4, and DoD7) of the 2-step differentiation procedure, we used transcriptome profiling.</s><s>A principal component analysis (PCA) showed that replicates from four differentiations clustered closely together and that each differentiation state had clearly distinct characteristics (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A</ref>).</s><s>The large number of 5,000-8,800 probe sets were significantly altered when the differentiating cells were compared with hESCs (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3B</ref>).</s><s>The regulated genes were assigned to different clusters according to the time course of their change: cluster I comprised genes continuously upregulated over time; cluster II contained genes that were upregulated during the first 8 days of differentiation and then stayed constant in their expression level; cluster III included the genes that were downregulated on differentiation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C</ref>).</s><s>To put these changes into a defined general context, we generated a PCA "cell feature map" by plotting our data together with a large set of legacy data.</s><s>As robust calibration points, we used CellNet (available at: http://cellnet.hms.</s><s>harvard.edu/)</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[31]</ref> data from human liver (n = 252) and brain (n = 335).</s><s>Moreover, we added data on primary human DRG, hESCs, various hPSC-derived cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b29">27,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">30]</ref>, and fetal human neural precursors (LUHMES Lu0), sequentially differentiating (Lu3) to postmitotic central neurons in vitro (Lu6) <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">32]</ref>.</s><s>This novel approach of PCA mapping within a biological context showed that all in vitro neuro-differentiations caused a transcriptome shift from hESCs toward brain samples.</s><s>Our twostep protocol and the older one-step protocol followed the same track (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>, red arrows) to get closer to human DRGs.</s><s>The DoD4 of our two-step protocol (i.e., 13 days of differentiation from hESCs) was closer to DRGs than DoD16* of the onestep protocol.</s><s>This suggests that the additional freezing and thawing step actually accelerated iDRG differentiation.</s><s>The LUHMES differentiation pointed in the same direction but showed a clear separation from the iDRG differentiation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A</ref>).</s><s>Having found this distinct and clear overall differentiation track of the iDRG cells, we examined functionally linked groups of genes.</s><s>The gene ontology terms (GOs) that were most overrepresented among the genes upregulated on DoD1 were, for example, "neuron migration," "nervous system development," and "dendrite morphogenesis," and the most significant GOs were largely similar for iDRG cells and later stage neurons (DoD7).</s><s>The top GOs overrepresented among the downregulated transcripts at DoD1 included "somatic stem cell maintenance" and "endodermal cell fate specification."</s><s>The GO overrepresentation analysis therefore confirmed neurodifferentiation as a major biological process on the level of gene regulation, and this was paralleled by inhibition of nonneuronal lineage maintenance/differentiation (supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>).</s></p><p><s>The top 20 individual transcripts upregulated at DoD1 included the neurogenic differentiation factors NeuroD1, SIX1, Hoelting, Klima, Karreman et al. and EBF1, and the peripheral neuron subtype specifiers POU4 (BRN3A) and ISL1 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>; supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>).</s><s>Also when the transcriptome difference was measured between DoD89 and DoD7, a significant overrepresentation of neuronal GO terms was still present among the upregulated genes (7 of the top 10), and 9 of the top 10 overrepresented GOs among the downregulated genes dealt with DNA replication and other DNA-related processes (supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B, 2C</ref>).</s><s>This is well in line with the results from a KEGG pathway overrepresentation analysis (supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>) and with the phenotypically observed neuronal differentiation and the mitotic exit of the cells during that time period.</s><s>The expression of a broad range of differentiation markers was confirmed by qPCR.</s><s>Markers of sensory neurons (i.e., peripherin, ISL1, runt-related transcription factor 1 [RUNX1], vesicular glutamate transporter 2 [VGLUT 2], and the receptor tyrosine kinase RET) were upregulated.</s><s>Also, the purinergic receptor P2RX3 and nociceptive markers such as TRPM8 or the sodium channels SCN9A and SCN10A were upregulated during differentiation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3E</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Toxicant Sensitivity of Early Neurite Growth</head><p><s>In accordance with the neuronal gene expression pattern, the cells had already developed distinct neurites at DoD1 after thawing.</s><s>The growth cones showed the characteristic distribution of microtubules (more toward the somata) and F-actin (at the tip) (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4A</ref>).</s><s>In order to quantify neurite growth, the total neurite area was quantified at several time points after plating of the cells.</s><s>The work flow we used was based on fully automated live cell microscopy, differential staining of nuclei and of the entire cytosol, followed by computational identification and quantification of the cellular parts (neurites) not belonging to the cell soma area (supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A</ref>).</s><s>The neurite area increased continuously from a few hours after plating until DoD4 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B</ref>).</s></p><p><s>In addition to the neurite area per imaging field, the imaging algorithm we used also yielded the number of viable cells by quantifying the ratio of cell bodies that were positive or negative for the viability dye calcein.</s><s>This allowed us to investigate whether drug effects on neurite growth would occur independently of general cytotoxicity.</s></p><p><s>For a technical assessment of the test performance, we used rotenone (10 mM) as a positive control, because this compound has been shown in many other systems to affect neurites <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[33]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[34]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[35]</ref>.</s><s>Inhibition of neurite growth was quantified in 10 different cell preparations.</s><s>The data suggested a sufficient signal-tonoise ratio of the test, as expressed by an average z9 factor of 0.7 (supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3B</ref>).</s><s>To study concentrationdependent changes in detail, we used cytoskeletal toxicants as mechanism-focused positive controls.</s><s>The microtubule toxicants vincristine and colchicine and the actin polymerization inhibitor cytochalasin D reduced neurite growth with high potency, without affecting general cell viability (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4C</ref>; supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1G-1I</ref>; supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3B,  3C</ref>).</s><s>In summary, these data suggest that specific toxicant effects on neurites can be assessed in iDRG cells and be separated from general cytotoxicity.</s></p><p><s>In order to test at which state of neuronal developments the best test results were obtained, we performed toxicity testing of five compounds under standard conditions (i.e., in the 24-hour period following plating; no neurites present at the start of testing), and 3 days later, when an elaborate neurite network was already established.</s><s>A comparison of the selectivity ratios (i.e., neurite toxicity versus general cytotoxicity) showed that the use of immature neurons (DoD1) provided clearly superior test performance (supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>).</s><s>This condition was therefore chosen as the standard setup for a human neurite-based PeriTox test.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Basic Characterization of the PeriTox Test</head><p><s>Two types of negative controls were tested.</s><s>The first subgroup comprised compounds not (,20% of control) assumed to affect any test endpoint.</s><s>Acetylsalicylic acid (data not shown) and mannitol (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5A</ref>) showed such behavior at concentrations up to the mM range.</s><s>The second subgroup comprised compounds that affected viability and neurites in the same concentration range (unspecific controls).</s><s>The detergents sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) and Triton X-100 showed this behavior, as expected (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5B</ref>).</s><s>As a signaling pathway-specific control for PeriTox test performance, we used the guanylyl cyclase inhibitor ODQ, which is known to disrupt human neurite growth <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[36]</ref>.</s><s>This drug was confirmed to affect neurites without other cellular toxicity (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5C</ref>; supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1I</ref>).</s><s>It was therefore used as an acceptability control for further test runs (neurite reduction .40%).</s><s>To test more stringently whether the neurite effects detected in the PeriTox test could be fully uncoupled from cytotoxicity, we performed drug washout/recovery experiments.</s><s>The standard test was run with 200 mM ODQ (for 24 hours).</s><s>Then, the drug was washed out, and we observed complete recovery (i.e., regrowth of the neurites up to the level of untreated controls; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5D</ref>).</s><s>The ROCK inhibitor Y-27632 was used as a second pathwayspecific control (for accelerated growth pathways) to explore the dynamic range of the assay.</s><s>The PeriTox test data suggested that growth-accelerating compounds can also be detected (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5E</ref>).</s></p><p><s>After these basic assay controls, we explored the sensitivity for clinically used drugs known to cause peripheral neuropathies in humans <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[37]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[38]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[39]</ref>.</s><s>Cisplatin and bortezomib significantly affected the neurites at concentrations showing no effect on viability (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5F</ref>).</s><s>Thus, the PeriTox test fulfilled all the basic requirements of a cellular toxicological assay.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Toxicant Screening and Set Up of a PeriTox Test Prediction Model</head><p><s>To design a prediction model for the PeriTox test, we took the following steps: (a) use of the "ratio" of EC 50 (viability)/EC 50 (neurites) as the primary endpoint; (b) measurement of this value for "unspecific toxicants" (the uncoupler CCCP, SDS, Triton-X100, and the topoisomerase inhibitor etoposide; the average ratio was 1.37 6 0.39); (c) definition of a "noise band" (4 SD from the average of the ratios of these compounds); and (d) definition of compounds with a ratio outside the noise band (EC 50 ratio of .3)</s><s>as "neurite specific."</s></p><p><s>This test definition was used to screen three dozen chemicals, preselected for their potential interest for neurite toxicity.</s><s>Altogether, 21 positive hits were identified.</s><s>All microtubule drugs and proteasome inhibitors were classified as positive hits.</s><s>This also included the new drug class of epothilones <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[40,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">41]</ref>, which we found to damage neurites without affecting cell viability (supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3E, 3F</ref>).</s><s>All these data were in good agreement with recent clinical findings.</s><s>Several histone deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitors (HDACi; MS275, SAHA, and TSA) showed neurite toxicity.</s><s>Among the ROCK pathway modulators, the r activator narciclasine was toxic to neurites (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6A, 6B</ref>) and inhibitors, such as blebbistatin, accelerated neurite growth (not shown).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Application of PeriTox Test to Environmental Toxicants</head><p><s>Neurotoxicity testing of environmental chemicals is particularly challenging, as their effects on neurites in vivo often requires prolonged exposure.</s><s>The final toxicity outcome might result from continuous damage accumulation, a process difficult to reproduce in vitro.</s><s>Therefore, we explored the hypothesis that the particular requirements of neurites that are still growing will "sensitize" the cells to neurotoxicants <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[16]</ref> and that this would allow detection of toxicity in the PeriTox test, although it is a short-term assay.</s><s>We found that 24 hours of exposure to acrylamide significantly reduced the neurite area at concentrations of $875 mM but that viability was reduced only at higher ($4.7 mM; EC 50 ratio of 3.2) concentrations (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7A</ref>).</s><s>A comparison of the toxicant sensitivity of growing neurites (DoD1) with that of established neurites (DoD4) showed that selective neurite damage was more readily observed in the neuronal cultures with growing neurites (supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>).</s><s>The structurally related negative control acrylic acid showed hardly any effect on neurites or viability (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7B</ref>).</s><s>Immunostaining for the microtubule marker TUJ1 showed that acrylamide-treated cells still had elaborate cytoskeletal structures but shortened neurites (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7C</ref>).</s><s>Moreover, the partial reversibility of the acrylamide-induced effect on neurites suggests that the cells remained viable in the presence of the drug: after a washout, the neurons significantly accelerated their neurite growth compared with cells that continued to be treated with the chemical (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7D</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Arsenic is another environmental toxicant known to induce neuropathies.</s><s>Exposure to sodium arsenate resulted in an EC 50 ratio (viability/neurites) of .7.</s><s>This large offset led to its classification as a neurotoxicant in the PeriTox test (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7E</ref>).</s><s>For the related compound, arsenic trioxide, some concentrations (0.6-2.5 mM) significantly affected the neurites without cytotoxicity.</s><s>As the EC 50 ratio was only 2.3, this chemical would not be classified as a neurite toxicant (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7F</ref>).</s><s>Finally, the pesticide rotenone was clearly predicted as a neurite toxicant by our prediction model (EC 50 ratio .50;</s><s>Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7G</ref>).</s><s>A recovery experiment showed that cells started growing neurites again after rotenone (0.4-2 mM) washout and had nearly completely caught up with untreated controls by 24 hours after washout (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7H</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PeriTox Test Performance Versus Established LUHMES Neurite Assay</head><p><s>To obtain data on test specificity, we first compared the results of the PeriTox test with published data from the LUHMES neurite test <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[16]</ref>.</s><s>Several compounds with diverse modes of actions behaved similarly in the two assays.</s><s>However, acrylamide, bortezomib, cisplatin, and Taxol, all known for causing human peripheral neuropathies, were only detected by the PeriTox test (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6B</ref>).</s><s>Thus, our new method made full use of the potential of human stem cell technology to identify a large number of humanrelevant peripheral neurotoxicants not identified by the LUHMES assay (supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>).</s><s>Therefore, we consider it an important addition to the battery of existing in vitro tests able to alert for potential neurotoxic hazard of drugs and environmental chemicals.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>Despite the large incidence of peripheral neuropathies (PNs), a dearth of studies is available on relevant human cells.</s><s>Diabetic PNs has reached a two-digit incidence in the U.S. population Hoelting, Klima, Karreman et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[42]</ref>.</s><s>Also, .60% of chemotherapy patients develop PNs <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[43]</ref>, and several other drug classes <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">[44]</ref> have been associated with PNs.</s><s>Moreover, several environmental chemicals either trigger PN or can affect neurites during development <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[17]</ref>.</s><s>For example, acrylamide causes axonal degeneration of exposed workers by affecting the microtubules of the neurites without causing cell death <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s>Moreover, most chemotherapeutic agents are known to induce specific axonal neuropathies <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">38]</ref>.</s><s>As a method to evaluate such toxicity on human peripheral neurons has not been available, the PeriTox test represents pivotal progress toward filling this gap.</s></p><p><s>The first important step was the optimization of a protocol that allowed the generation of iDRG cells at the amounts and with the quality and reproducibility required for a quantitative toxicological assay.</s><s>The second pivotal step was the identification and use of a functional endpoint that allowed sufficient throughput, unbiased quantification, and development of a prediction model to distinguish specific neurite toxicity from general cytotoxicity.</s><s>The PeriTox test reacted correctly (sensitivity of 87%) to many known human PN toxicants, and it discriminated (specificity of 100%) between peripheral neurotoxicants and chemicals not expected to cause PN.</s></p><p><s>The successful establishment and evaluation of the PeriTox test builds on a test development research line that has become increasingly more important in the field: transition from rodent primary cells or from transformed human cells to nontransformed human stem cell-derived specialized cells with characteristics of the relevant target tissue.</s><s>In the past, rodent sensory neurons/DRG have allowed important studies of the mechanisms of peripheral neurotoxicity/degeneration <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">46]</ref>.</s><s>However, the overwhelming majority of reports in this area focused on the underlying mechanisms and never compared more than three toxicants.</s><s>Although stem cell technology has paved the way toward the use of human nontransformed cells, past assays have been built on central neurons and never worked for more than three specific toxicants <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b50">47]</ref>.</s><s>The LUHMES system (using conditionally immortalized central neuronal precursor cells) was the first assay in the field identifying .20 toxicants and systematically examining the relation of neurite growth, neurite toxicity, and cytotoxicity <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[16]</ref>.</s><s>However, LUHMES are central neurons and derived from conditionally immortalized cells.</s><s>It was assumed that the most relevant target cell type (i.e., peripheral neurons to test for peripheral neurotoxicity) would produce the most reliable results, because many examples of cell type-dependent toxicity are available.</s><s>For instance, the chemotherapeutic drug cisplatin accumulates faster in primary sensory neurons than in PC12 cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[39]</ref>, the toxicant effects on neural crest cell migration differs from effects of the same chemical on neural precursor cells or tumor cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[27]</ref>, and even the subtypes of dopaminergic neurons showed different sensitivity in their vulnerability to the toxicant MPTP <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[48]</ref>.</s><s>The PeriTox test has taken a large step past the LUHMES assay by using nonengineered iDRG cells that detected several known PN toxicants missed by the LUHMES assay.</s></p><p><s>That we observed reversibility of some toxicant action (e.g., rotenone) might be important for future applications in risk assessment.</s><s>Moreover, this feature will allow screens for recovery-enhancing compounds, and the use of a panel of iPSCs for the PeriTox test would even consider individual genetic determinants of toxicity/recovery <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[47]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The test results from a mixed group of toxicants used in the present study showed that not only were well-known hazardous drugs and environmental compounds identified, but also potentially neuroprotective drugs (ROCK inhibitors) and so-called alerts (HDACi) were marked for further follow-up.</s><s>We gave the thorough characterization of the developmental stage of the neurons particular attention.</s><s>On the one hand, the PeriTox test was designed as a neurotoxicity assay that makes use of the fact that growing neurites of cultured cells are particularly STEM CELLS TRANSLATIONAL MEDICINE sensitive to neurotoxicants.</s><s>This approach allowed us to overcome the largest problem of in vitro assays in this field <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[16]</ref> (i.e., the separation of specific neurite effects from unspecific cell death).</s><s>On the other hand, an added benefit could also be that some developmental toxicants could be identified <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b53">49]</ref>.</s><s>This might be why the PeriTox test produced an alert on the emerging class of HDACi-based chemotherapeutic agents (and known developmental toxicants) as potential peripheral neurotoxicants.</s><s>Additional patient observations are required to decide whether such predictions hold true in clinical situations (supplemental online Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSION</head><p><s>The generation of immature dorsal root ganglia neurons from human pluripotent stem cells provided the basis for a drug and chemical safety evaluation assay on cells not otherwise available.</s><s>Testing of more than 30 chemicals showed that human neurotoxicants and neurite growth enhancers were correctly identified.</s><s>The adaptations of the protocols we have described (e.g., the introduction of a freezethaw step and the strong focus on the initial neurite growth phase) resulted in an assay that is specific for neurotoxicants (in contrast to cytotoxicants) and is very robust across different operators and assay runs.</s><s>Various classes of chemotherapeutic agents causing human peripheral neuropathies were identified, although they were missed when tested on human central neurons.</s><s>The PeriTox test we established shows the potential of human stem cells for clinically relevant safety testing of drugs in use and new emerging candidates.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Generation of human immature dorsal root ganglia neuron (iDRG) cells for toxicity testing.</s><s>Pluripotent stem cells were differentiated in a two-step procedure, as indicated.</s><s>(A-D): Immunocytochemical characterization of hESC-derived cells.</s><s>Labels are color keyed to images.</s><s>(E): Proliferating cells (EdU + ) were quantified (mean 6 SEM; n = 3).</s><s>(F-I): Immunocytochemical characterization of iDRG cells after thawing.</s><s>Labels are color keyed to images.</s><s>Scale bars = 100 mm (A) and 50 mm (B-D, F-I).</s><s>Abbreviations: BDNF, brain-derived neurotrophic factor; DoD, day of differentiation; GDNF, glia-derived neurotrophic factor; hESC, human embryonic stem cell; NGF, nerve growth factor.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,84.13,78.92,416.84,341.29" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Quantification of calcium signaling of immature dorsal root ganglia neuron cells.</s><s>(A): Intracellular calcium levels measured on DoD7 after depolarization.</s><s>Each cell is depicted by a circle.</s><s>***, p , .001.</s><s>(B): Before depolarization by KCl, cells were pretreated with Verap (100 mM) or Nifed (100 mM; n = 3; ***, p , .001).</s><s>Abbreviations: DMSO, dimethyl sulfoxide; HBSS, Hanks' buffered salt solution; Nifed, nifedipine; rel., relative; Verap, verapamil; Verat, veratridine.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,132.04,78.92,321.07,129.66" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. Differentiation tracking by transcriptome analysis of iDRG cells.</s><s>(A): Samples were obtained at different developmental stages for whole transcriptome analysis; data are displayed as a principal component analysis (PCA) map, together with legacy data from cell cultures or from human dorsal root ganglion, brain, and liver tissue.</s><s>The red arrow indicates the cell differentiation track of the two-step iDRG cell differentiation protocol.</s><s>Note: DoD7 of the two-step protocol is 16 days older than hESCs (i.e., roughly corresponding to DoD16* of the one-step protocol in differentiation time).</s><s>(B): Number of regulated genes over time.</s><s>(C): Top 20 significantly upregulated (red) and downregulated (blue) genes.</s><s>(D): Hierarchical clustering analysis of the top 100 genes with the highest variance during peripheral neuronal differentiation.</s><s>(E): Relative gene expression during differentiation (n = 4-6).</s><s>Abbreviations: DoD, day of differentiation; FC, fold change; hESC, human embryonic stem cell; iDRG, immature dorsal root ganglia neuron; PC1, principal component 1; PC2, principal component 2; rel., relative.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,84.13,78.92,416.84,524.35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. Characterization and quantification of neurite growth of early iDRG cells.</s><s>(A): Immunocytochemical characterization of early neurites; labels are color keyed to images.</s><s>(B): Quantification of neurite area over time (mean 6 SEM; n = 5).</s><s>(C): Effects of vincristine, colchicine, and cytochalasin D on neurite area and viability under PeriTox test conditions (mean 6 SEM; n = 3-4) and exemplary sample images (**, p , .01;</s><s>***, p , .001).</s><s>Scale bars = 20 mm (A, left) and 50 mm (B, right; C).</s><s>Abbreviations: DoD, day of differentiation; untr., untreated.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,84.13,78.92,416.84,302.51" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. Profiling and quantification of negative and positive control toxicant effects on immature dorsal root ganglia neuron neurites.</s><s>Tool compounds were used as in (4C).</s><s>(A): Negative control.</s><s>(B): Unspecific toxicants.</s><s>(C): Guanylyl cyclase inhibitor as pathway-specific control.</s><s>*, p , .05;</s><s>**, p , .01;</s><s>***, p , .001</s><s>versus untr.</s><s>cells.</s><s>(D): Test of reversibility.</s><s>After 24 hours of exposure, ODQ was washed out, and neurites were measured again 24 hours later (n = 3-4).</s><s>(E): ROCK inhibitor as pathway-specific control for accelerated growth.</s><s>(F): Positive controls (drugs causing peripheral neuropathy).</s><s>Scale bars = 50 mm.</s><s>Abbreviations: SDS, sodium dodecyl sulfate; untr., untreated.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,84.13,78.92,416.84,349.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6.</s><s>Classification of toxicant effect on immature dorsal root ganglia neuron neurites.</s><s>(A): Overview of specificity of all compounds tested.</s><s>EC 50 values for effects on neurite area were plotted against EC 50 for effects on viability.</s><s>The solid line indicates an EC 50 ratio of 1.</s><s>The dashed line indicates an EC 50 ratio of 3 (n $3).</s><s>(B): Comparison of positive hits in the PeriTox test and published data on the LUHMES test (based on central neurons).</s><s>For both tests, the EC 50 ratio (EC 50 viability to EC 50 neurite area) of various compounds is shown.</s><s>Abbreviation: HDAC, histone deacetylase.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,132.04,78.92,321.07,211.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 7. Effect of environmental toxicants on immature dorsal root ganglia neuron neurites.</s><s>Neurite area and viability were measured under PeriTox test conditions.</s><s>Effect of acrylamide (A) or acrylic acid (B) (mean 6 SEM; n = 3-5).</s><s>(C): Immunostaining of cells treated with acrylamide as in (A).</s><s>(D): Test of reversibility.</s><s>After 24 hours of exposure, acrylamide was washed out, and neurites were measured again 24 hours later (n = 3-4).</s><s>(E-G): Toxicant testing as in (A).</s><s>(H): Reversibility of rotenone effects was tested as in D. Scale bars = 50 mm (A, C).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,84.13,78.92,416.84,480.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">RNA was extracted at the indicated DoD (hESCs, DoD89, DoD1, DoD4, DoD7) from four independent differentiations and Hoelting, Klima, Karreman et al.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">www.StemCellsTM.com   ©AlphaMed Press 2016</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Peripheral Neurons for Drug Safety Testing ©AlphaMed Press 2016 STEM CELLS TRANSLATIONAL MEDICINE</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>This work was supported by national Doerenkamp-Zbinden Foundation, Konstanz Graduate School Chemical Biology KORS-CB, Research Training Group 1331 (RTG), and BMBF (German Ministry of Education and Research) grants.</s><s>We thank Alex Gutteridge (Pfizer) for providing primary dorsal root ganglia neuron transcriptome data.</s><s>Technical assistance from M. Kapitza and advice from B. Zimmer are gratefully acknowledged.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</head><p><s>L.H.: conception and design, collection and assembly of data, data analysis and interpretation, manuscript writing, final approval of manuscript; S.K., M.G., J.M., J.R., and N.B.: collection and assembly of data, data analysis and interpretation; C.K.: data analysis and interpretation; M.H., T.R., and A.S.: collection and assembly of data; T.W.: conception and design, data analysis and interpretation; M.L.: conception and design, data analysis and interpretation, manuscript writing, final approval of manuscript.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCLOSURE OF POTENTIAL CONFLICTS OF INTEREST</head><p><s>M.L. is a compensated consultant for the European Food Safety Authority and the Doerenkamp-Zbinden Foundation, has received compensated honoraria and uncompensated research funding from the Doerenkamp-Zbinden Foundation and the Center for Alternatives to Animal Testing-Europe, and has provided uncompensated expert testimony for the Swiss Centre for Applied Human Toxicology.</s><s>The other authors indicated no potential conflicts of interest.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toxic neuropathies: Mechanistic insights based on a chemical perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lopachin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gavin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurosci Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">596</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Experimental and Clinical Neurotoxicology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Spencer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Schaumburg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Markers of murine embryonic and neural stem cells, neurons and astrocytes: Reference points for developmental neurotoxicity testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kuegler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zimmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Waldmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ALTEX</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Knudsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Keller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vitro data and in silico models for predictive toxicology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Futuretox</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Toxicol Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">143</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="256" to="267" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ECVAM and new technologies for toxicity testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bouvier D'yvoire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bremer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Casati</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Adv Exp Med Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">745</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="180" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stem cells and stem cell-derived tissues and their use in safety assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kolaja</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">289</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4555" to="4561" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Food for thought ... on the evolution of toxicology and the phasing out of animal testing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hartung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leist</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ALTEX</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="91" to="102" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bal-Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Crofton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leist</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ternational STakeholder NETwork (ISTNET): Creating a developmental neurotoxicity (DNT) testing road map for regulatory purposes</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="269" to="287" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving the human hazard characterization of chemicals: A Tox21 update</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Tice</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Austin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kavlock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ Health Perspect</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="756" to="765" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toxicology: Transforming environmental health protection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Collins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Gray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bucher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">319</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="906" to="907" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of PC12 and cerebellar granule cell cultures for evaluating neurite outgrowth using high content analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Radio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Freudenrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Robinette</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurotoxicol Teratol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Chlorpyrifos exerts opposing effects on axonal and dendritic growth in primary neuronal cultures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Howard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bucelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Toxicol Appl Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">207</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="112" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statins decrease dendritic arborization in rat sympathetic neurons by blocking RhoA activation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gonsiorek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Barnhart</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">108</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1057" to="1071" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The network formation assay: A spatially standardized neurite outgrowth analytical display for neurotoxicity screening</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Frimat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sisnaiske</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Subbiah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lab Chip</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="701" to="709" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Valdivia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Lefew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multi-well microelectrode array recordings detect neuroactivity of ToxCast compounds</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurotoxicology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="204" to="217" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of a human neurite growth assay as specific screen for developmental neurotoxicants</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Krug</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Balmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Matt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch Toxicol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2215" to="2231" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assessment of chemical-induced impairment of human neurite outgrowth by multiparametric live cell imaging in high-density cultures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Stiegler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Krug</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Matt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Toxicol Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="87" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative assessment of neurite outgrowth in human embryonic stem cellderived hN2 cells using automated high-content image analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Harrill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Freudenrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Machacek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurotoxicology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential protection of neuromuscular sensory and motor axons and their endings in Wld(S) mutant mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Oyebode</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hartley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Singhota</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">200</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="158" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Absence of SARM1 rescues development and survival of NMNAT2-deficient axons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gilley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Orsomando</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Nascimento-Ferreira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1974" to="1981" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NAD metabolism and functions: A common therapeutic target for neoplastic, metabolic and neurodegenerative diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Di</forename><surname>Stefano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Manerba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vettraino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Top Med Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2918" to="2929" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Compound selection for in vitro modeling of developmental neurotoxicity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kadereit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zimmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Van Thriel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front Biosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2442" to="2460" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developmental neurotoxicity testing: A path forward</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Crofton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mundy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Shafer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Congenit Anom (Kyoto)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="140" to="146" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Embryonic stem cell lines derived from human blastocysts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Thomson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Itskovitz-Eldor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Shapiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">282</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1145" to="1147" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Combined small-molecule inhibition accelerates developmental timing and converts human pluripotent stem cells into nociceptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chambers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Qi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Mica</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="715" to="720" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human embryonic stem cell-derived test systems for developmental neurotoxicity: A transcriptomics approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Krug</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kolde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gaspar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch Toxicol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="143" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of developmental toxicants and signaling pathways in a functional test based on the migration of human neural crest cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zimmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Balmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Environ Health Perspect</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1116" to="1122" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Livak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Schmittgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="402" to="408" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epigenetic changes and disturbed neural development in a human embryonic stem cell-based model relating to the fetal valproate syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Balmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Weng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Zimmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum Mol Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4104" to="4114" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterizing human stem cell-derived sensory neurons at the single-cell level reveals their ion channel expression and utility in pain research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gutteridge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Fox</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1530" to="1543" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Network biology applied to stem cell engineering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cahan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">158</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="903" to="915" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rapid, complete and large-scale generation of postmitotic neurons from the human LUHMES cell line</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Scholz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Pöltl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Genewsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="957" to="971" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chronic, low-dose rotenone reproduces Lewy neurites found in early stages of Parkinson&apos;s disease, reduces mitochondrial movement and slowly kills differentiated SH-SY5Y neural cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Borland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Trimmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Rubinstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Neurodegener</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sodium channels contribute to degeneration of dorsal root ganglion neurites induced by mitochondrial dysfunction in an in vitro model of axonal injury</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Persson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19250" to="19261" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rotenone-induced toxicity is mediated by Rho-GTPases in hippocampal neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sanchez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gastaldi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Remedi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Toxicol Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="352" to="361" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">1H-[1,2,4] oxadiazolo[4,3-a]quinoxalin-1-one inhibits neurite outgrowth and causes neurite retraction in PC12 cells independently of soluble guanylyl cyclase</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="269" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bortezomib-induced peripheral neuropathy in multiple myeloma: A comprehensive review of the literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Argyriou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Iconomou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kalofonos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1593" to="1599" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chemotherapyinduced neuropathy: A comprehensive survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Boogerd</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Miltenburgnc</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Treat Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="872" to="882" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cisplatin preferentially binds to DNA in dorsal root ganglion neurons in vitro and in vivo: A potential mechanism for neurotoxicity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mcdonald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Randon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Knight</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurobiol Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="313" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epothilone-induced peripheral neuropathy: A review of current knowledge</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Argyriou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Marmiroli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cavaletti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pain Symptom Manage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="931" to="940" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Current perspectives of epothilones in breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Cardoso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>De Azambuja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lago</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="341" to="352" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The prevalence, severity, and impact of painful diabetic peripheral neuropathy in type 2 diabetes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Brophy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabetes Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1518" to="1522" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incidence, prevalence, and predictors of chemotherapy-induced peripheral neuropathy: A systematic review and meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Seretny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Currie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sena</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pain</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2461" to="2470" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rodent models of chemotherapy-induced peripheral neuropathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Höke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ray</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ILAR J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="281" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bortezomib alters microtubule polymerization and axonal transport in rat dorsal root ganglion neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Staff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Podratz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Grassner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurotoxicology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="124" to="131" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gerdts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Summers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sasaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sarm1-mediated axon degeneration requires both SAM and TIR interactions</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13569" to="13580" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Wheeler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Delaney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling chemotherapeutic neurotoxicity with human induced pluripotent stem cellderived neuronal cells</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e0118020</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cell type-specific gene expression of midbrain dopaminergic neurons reveals molecules involved in their vulnerability and protection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Seo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sonntag</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum Mol Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1709" to="1725" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Putative adverse outcome pathways relevant to neurotoxicity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bal-Price</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Crofton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sachana</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Crit Rev Toxicol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="91" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">StemCellsTM.com for supporting information available online</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Klima</forename><surname>Hoelting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Karreman</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
