<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Breakthrough attacks in patients with hereditary angioedema receiving long-term prophylaxis are responsive to icatibant: findings from the Icatibant Outcome Survey</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Werner</forename><surname>Aberer</surname></persName>
							<email>werner.aberer@medunigraz.at</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Dermatology and Venerology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Medical University of Graz</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Auenbruggerplatz 8</addrLine>
									<postCode>A-8036</postCode>
									<settlement>Graz</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Marcus</forename><surname>Maurer</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laurence</forename><surname>Bouillet</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><surname>Zanichelli</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Teresa</forename><surname>Caballero</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hilary</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Longhurst</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Amandine</forename><surname>Perrin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">IOS Study Group</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Irmgard</forename><surname>Andresen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Breakthrough attacks in patients with hereditary angioedema receiving long-term prophylaxis are responsive to icatibant: findings from the Icatibant Outcome Survey</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">909DE8430FE37D7D130D0862DF310AC3</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s13223-017-0203-z</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 19 January 2017 Accepted: 20 June 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:22+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Hereditary angioedema</term>
					<term>Icatibant</term>
					<term>Breakthrough attacks</term>
					<term>Prophylaxis</term>
					<term>Bradykinin</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Background: Patients with hereditary angioedema (HAE) due to C1-inhibitor deficiency (C1-INH-HAE) experience recurrent attacks of cutaneous or submucosal edema that may be frequent and severe; prophylactic treatments can be prescribed to prevent attacks.</s><s>However, despite the use of long-term prophylaxis (LTP), breakthrough attacks are known to occur.</s><s>We used data from the Icatibant Outcome Survey (IOS) to evaluate the characteristics of breakthrough attacks and the effectiveness of icatibant as a treatment option.</s></p><p><s>Methods: Data on LTP use, attacks, and treatments were recorded.</s><s>Attack characteristics, treatment characteristics, and outcomes (time to treatment, time to resolution, and duration of attack) were compared for attacks that occurred with versus without LTP.</s></p><p><s>Results: Data on 3228 icatibant-treated attacks from 448 patients with C1-INH-HAE were analyzed; 30.1% of attacks occurred while patients were using LTP.</s><s>Attack rate, attack severity, and the distribution of attack sites were similar across all types of LTP used, and were comparable to the results found in patients who did not receive LTP. Attacks were successfully treated with icatibant; 82.5% of all breakthrough attacks were treated with a single icatibant injection without C1-INH rescue medication.</s><s>Treatment outcomes were comparable for breakthrough attacks across all LTP types, and for attacks without LTP.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions:</head><p><s>Patients who use LTP should be aware that breakthrough attacks can occur, and such attacks can be severe.</s><s>Thus, patients with C1-INH-HAE using LTP should have emergency treatment readily available.</s><s>Data from IOS show that icatibant is effective for the treatment of breakthrough attacks.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p><s>Hereditary angioedema (HAE) is a rare genetic disorder characterized by recurrent attacks of cutaneous or submucosal edema associated with C1-inhibitor (C1-INH) deficiency (C1-INH-HAE type 1) or dysfunction (C1-INH-HAE type 2), leading to the overproduction of bradykinin, activation of bradykinin B2 receptors, capillary leakage, and local edema <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>It is recommended that all patients with C1-INH-HAE have access to therapy that can be used to treat acute angioedema attacks ("on-demand treatment") <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</s><s>In addition, patients with C1-INH-HAE may receive longterm prophylaxis (LTP) to reduce the frequency and severity of attacks <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s>However, despite the use of LTP, angioedema attacks, some of them severe, have been reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</s><s>Therefore, patients receiving LTP also should carry an effective on-demand treatment for acute attacks.</s><s>The characteristics of attacks occurring during LTP, referred to here as breakthrough attacks, have not been formally examined in depth.</s><s>Furthermore, there are currently no reports evaluating treatments for breakthrough attacks in detail.</s></p><p><s>Icatibant (Firazyr ® , Shire, Zug, Switzerland) is a subcutaneously administered bradykinin B2 receptor antagonist for the treatment of acute angioedema attacks in adults with type 1 or 2 C1-INH-HAE.</s><s>The Icatibant Outcome Survey (IOS; NCT01034969) is an ongoing, prospective, international, observational study monitoring the safety and effectiveness of icatibant during longterm treatment in the real-world setting.</s><s>We conducted an analysis of data from IOS to evaluate the characteristics of breakthrough attacks, and compared them with attacks that did not occur during LTP.</s><s>Outcomes following treatment of these attacks with icatibant also were examined.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study design and patients</head><p><s>Details for the design and conduct of IOS are described elsewhere <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s><s>IOS captures real-world data on treatment with icatibant.</s><s>Enrollment in IOS is open to all patients who have taken at least one dose of icatibant, regardless of attack frequency and level of icatibant usage.</s><s>Patients with diagnosed C1-INH-HAE were included in this analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>Data on icatibant-treated attacks and LTP use were collected between July 2009 and February 2016 via physician-completed electronic forms at routine visits (recommended at 6-month intervals), and with the aid of patient diaries.</s><s>Characteristics of attacks and details regarding treatment with icatibant and any concomitant medications were recorded.</s><s>Data on attacks and treatments during the 12 months before enrollment are referred to as historical.</s><s>Attack severity was classified as very mild (very mild interference with daily activities), mild (mild interference with daily activities), moderate (moderate interference with daily activities and no other countermeasures required), severe (severe interference with daily activities with or without other countermeasures), or very severe (very severe interference with daily activities and other countermeasures required).</s></p><p><s>The type of LTP administered, as well as dose, start and end dates, and frequency of dosing were recorded.</s><s>Adherence to prophylaxis treatment was not monitored.</s><s>Attacks that occurred outside a start-end interval were considered to have occurred without LTP; attacks that occurred on the day that LTP started or ended were considered to have occurred with LTP.</s><s>The total duration of treatment was calculated as the sum of the maximum duration of each type of LTP administered for each patient, irrespective of the occurrence of icatibant-treated attacks.</s><s>The attack frequency for each type of LTP was calculated by dividing the number of attacks by the total duration of treatment.</s><s>It was noted that some LTP regimens, such as androgens, had been started years before the availability of icatibant as a treatment option.</s><s>To avoid underestimating the attack frequency, the date of LTP initiation was replaced with the date of the first treated attack if LTP began before the first treated attack.</s><s>LTP regimens that started and stopped before the first treated attack were excluded.</s></p><p><s>Patients received subcutaneous injections of icatibant 30 mg for acute attacks.</s><s>Icatibant was self-administered (after training by a health care professional), or administered by a health care professional.</s><s>Many patients selfadministered icatibant before the formal approval of this mode of administration in 2011.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical analyses</head><p><s>Data comparisons were made for attacks occurring with LTP versus without LTP.</s><s>Attacks with complete data for all three outcomes, (1) time to treatment (defined as time from attack onset to first icatibant injection), (2) time to resolution (defined as time from first icatibant injection to complete symptom resolution of all angioedema), and (3) duration of attack (defined as time from attack onset to complete resolution of symptoms), were compared using a mixed-model analysis of repeated measures (PROC MIXED; SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC).</s><s>A generalized linear mixed-model for repeated measures (PROC GLIMMIX) was used to compare the severity of attacks (e.g., very mild/mild/moderate versus severe/very severe).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patient characteristics</head><p><s>Data from 3228 icatibant-treated attacks were analyzed from 448 patients with C1-INH-HAE.</s><s>Most (94.4%) patients had a diagnosis of C1-INH-HAE type 1 and 58.7% of patients were female.</s><s>Demographic characteristics of the patients are summarized in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HAE attacks that occurred with and without LTP shared similar characteristics</head><p><s>Of the 3228 total icatibant-treated attacks recorded, 973 (30.1%) attacks occurred in 171 patients during LTP (38.2% of the total 448 patients in this analysis), and 2255 (69.9%) attacks occurred in 323 patients (72.1%) who either never received LTP (n = 277) or who were not using LTP at the time of the attack (n = 46; Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>).</s><s>The analysis included attacks that occurred over a mean (SD) duration of 3.5 (1.8) years per patient on LTP, and 3.6 (1.8) years for patients who were not prescribed LTP (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Androgens (danazol, oxandrolone, or stanozolol) were the most commonly used form of LTP.</s><s>Androgens were used by 108/171 (63.2%) patients, while 43 (25.1%)</s><s>patients used tranexamic acid and 15 (8.8%) patients used C1-INH.</s><s>In addition, 17 (9.9%)</s><s>patients used various combinations of these three medications.</s><s>The mean (SD) duration of use was 3.5 (1.9), 3.4 (1.8), and 3.4 (1.4) years for androgens, tranexamic acid, and C1-INH, respectively.</s><s>The rate of icatibant-treated breakthrough attacks was similar irrespective of the type of prophylaxis; there were 1.5, 1.6, and 2.3 attacks/year reported in patients using androgens, tranexamic acid, and C1-INH for LTP, respectively.</s><s>In comparison, there were 2.0 attacks/year in patients who never received LTP.</s></p><p><s>There were no statistically significant differences in attack severity in patients who used androgens, C1-INH, or tranexamic acid for LTP compared with attacks that occurred without LTP (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>).</s><s>In patients who used androgens for LTP, 68.9% of attacks were severe/very severe and 31.1% of attacks were very mild/mild/moderate compared with 53.2 and 46.8%, respectively, in attacks without LTP (P = 0.056).</s><s>The proportions of severe/very severe and very mild/mild/moderate attacks were comparable between patients receiving C1-INH or tranexamic acid and were similar to those without LTP (P = 0.321 and P = 0.989 for C1-INH and tranexamic acid, respectively, versus patients without LTP).</s></p><p><s>The most frequent site of attack was the abdomen (47.6% with and 52.1% without LTP), followed by the skin (35.1 and 30.1%, respectively), and larynx (3.0 and 5.0%, respectively; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1b</ref>).</s><s>Multiple sites were affected in 12.0% of attacks with LTP and 10.5% of attacks without LTP.</s><s>The distribution of attack sites was comparable across the different types of LTP.</s><s>Of the attacks involving the larynx or abdomen, 63.6 and 73.9%, respectively, were severe/very severe.</s><s>Patients also reported using other medications in addition to icatibant, the most frequent being androgens, analgesics, and antifibrinolytics.</s><s>These were used in addition to icatibant in 3.5, 2.4, and 2.8% of breakthrough attacks, respectively, and in 1.0, 1.6, and 1.2% of attacks without LTP, respectively.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outcomes of icatibant-treated HAE attacks were similar for attacks with and without LTP</head><p><s>The median times to treatment with icatibant, time to resolution, and duration of attack were not significantly different for attacks that occurred with versus without LTP (Table <ref type="table">4</ref>).</s><s>Among the different types of LTP, only the combined treatments ("other") had a shorter time to treatment (P = 0.029).</s><s>There was no significant difference (P &gt; 0.100) among the different types of LTP with respect to time to resolution.</s><s>Duration of attack was significantly longer for breakthrough attacks that occurred while using tranexamic acid (P = 0.016), and shorter for attacks with C1-INH (P = 0.041).</s><s>Of note, patients who used tranexamic acid for LTP also had longer time to treatment and longer time to resolution compared with patients who used other types of LTP.</s><s>Two patients were previously identified as outliers based on their reinjection characteristics <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s><s>These patients used LTP (danazol and C1-INH, respectively) during enrollment in the study.</s><s>The results for icatibant reinjection and treatment outcomes between attacks that occurred with or without LTP were not significantly impacted when data from these outliers were excluded.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Prophylactic treatment for C1-INH-HAE has been shown to reduce the frequency and severity of attacks <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>.</s><s>The present analyses of real-world data from IOS support that patients receiving LTP (who usually have high disease activity) experience attacks of similar duration and frequency as patients who do not use LTP.</s><s>Our findings show that icatibant, when used as on-demand medication, is similarly effective in controlling attacks in patients who are taking LTP and in those who are not.</s></p><p><s>In our dataset, patients across all LTP groups experienced breakthrough attacks, including those that involved the larynx and those that significantly impaired physical function.</s><s>Breakthrough attacks may have occurred because local C1-INH levels fell below or did not reach the normal range despite administration of LTP, resulting in inadequate regulation of the contact system <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>It is possible that doses of LTP administered were insufficient, or the dosing was not frequent enough  to completely prevent attacks.</s><s>In addition, data regarding patient adherence to LTP were not available, and breakthrough attacks may have resulted from delays in dosing, or errors in the administration of prophylactic medications.</s></p><p><s>Patients who are candidates for LTP typically have more severe disease (i.e., frequent and severe attacks) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>.</s><s>Approximately half of the attacks reported in patients taking LTP were severe/very severe, which is comparable to attacks that occurred without LTP.</s><s>This  further emphasizes the fact that breakthrough attacks can occur often and can be severe.</s><s>Interestingly, there was a higher proportion of severe/very severe attacks in patients who were using androgens for LTP (68.9%) compared with patients who were using tranexamic acid, C1-INH, or a combination of the three treatments (45.5-55.6%).</s><s>However, we cannot make conclusions regarding efficacy from this observation as the severity of disease prior to starting LTP among the patients who used the various types of LTP is not known.</s><s>Furthermore, androgens are associated with numerous side effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, which may compromise patient compliance and subsequently treatment effectiveness.</s><s>Irrespective of LTP use, patients responded well to icatibant, and &gt;80% of C1-INH-HAE attacks were successfully treated with only a single injection of icatibant.</s><s>This is consistent with previous results reported from IOS <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>.</s><s>The rate of on-demand medication use was comparable for attacks that occurred with or without LTP, and there was no difference in treatment outcomes between attacks that occurred with or without LTP.</s><s>Duration of attack was longer for attacks that occurred while taking tranexamic acid, and shorter with C1-INH treatment, in accordance with previous reports <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref>.</s><s>Statistically significant effects of individual types of LTP on time to treatment and duration of attack should be interpreted with caution in this analysis, however, as both the number of patients and frequency of attacks within these groups were small.</s></p><p><s>Overall, the findings from IOS indicate that attack characteristics and outcomes with icatibant treatment were similar for patients with high disease activity (i.e., those who require LTP treatment), and for those with less severe disease.</s><s>These results are consistent with our clinical experience with icatibant treatment in patients with C1-INH-HAE.</s><s>Furthermore, the results support the theory that attacks in patients with high-and low-disease severity share a common pathogenic mechanism <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</s><s>Specifically, this involves elevation of bradykinin levels subsequent to contact system activation in the absence of sufficient, protective C1-INH levels; icatibant counteracts this activity by inhibiting the bradykinin receptor.</s></p><p><s>The results also revealed some surprising information concerning the use of icatibant plus add-on medications to treat attacks.</s><s>Although attenuated androgens and antifibrinolytics are not recommended for the treatment of acute attacks <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, approximately 3% of total attacks were treated with these medications following dosing with icatibant.</s><s>Of the 56 attacks that were treated with icatibant plus on-demand androgens, 34 (60.7%)</s><s>attacks occurred while androgens were also used for LTP, suggesting that if icatibant were determined to be insufficient for resolving an attack, patients simply resorted to readily available treatments for rescue.</s><s>The remaining 22 attacks that were treated with on-demand androgens occurred without LTP; these attacks were reported by 11 patients, and may reflect a lack of knowledge on the part of the patients or physicians regarding selection of appropriate treatments for acute attacks.</s><s>Androgens might also be used as a form of short-term prophylaxis to reduce the chance of occurrence of a later attack (for example prior to traveling or a dental procedure).</s></p><p><s>Some limitations of this study should be noted.</s><s>Although the data suggest that the attack rate while using C1-INH, androgens, or tranexamic acid for LTP was similar and that LTP was effective in reducing the attack rate of patients with severe disease to the same rate as patients with less severe disease, this was not a randomized trial in which patients were randomly assigned to receive LTP, and adherence to LTP treatment was not monitored.</s><s>The goal of this analysis was to evaluate the effectiveness of icatibant in treating breakthrough attacks, rather than to compare different LTP options.</s><s>Data confirming disease severity prior to initiation of prophylactic treatment were also not available as a baseline comparison.</s><s>In addition, the C1-INH treatment group was relatively small.</s><s>Thus, these data cannot be used to evaluate the effectiveness of LTP or to compare the various LTP treatments.</s><s>The small number of C1-INH users in the database population does reflect our clinical experience in that very few patients use C1-INH at the recommended dose of 1000 U every 3-4 days; instead, doses and regimens are often adjusted according to individual patients' responses.</s><s>Thus it is difficult to fully assess the impact of C1-INH in comparison to other LTP treatments.</s><s>In addition, C1-INH is indicated for both LTP and the treatment of acute attacks, and patients who use C1-INH for LTP often use it to treat breakthrough attacks as well <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>.</s><s>As this analysis only includes attacks treated with icatibant, it is possible that some attacks were treated with C1-INH or other medications instead of icatibant, thus the true number of attacks with and without LTP could potentially be higher than reported here.</s><s>Information on attacks that were treated with medications other than icatibant is not included in IOS.</s><s>Of the 121 breakthrough attacks that occurred while on prophylaxis with C1-INH, 20 attacks were treated with rescue medication, and C1-INH was used exclusively for all 20 attacks.</s><s>This further emphasizes the high frequency of C1-INH use for both prophylaxis and acute treatment indications.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p><s>Icatibant was successfully used to treat both breakthrough attacks in patients with C1-INH-HAE receiving prophylaxis as well as attacks that occurred without LTP.</s><s>Patients who are prescribed LTP should be aware of the</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 a</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1 a Severity and b site of attacks by type of long-term prophylaxis (LTP).</s><s>P values compared severity of attacks with LTP versus attacks without LTP.</s><s>Attacks with a unknown severity and b unknown attack site were excluded.</s><s>*Androgens include danazol, stanozolol, and oxandrolone.</s><s>† Other includes all LTP treatments that combined &gt;1 type of LTP</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 Table 4</head><label>24</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 2 Proportion of attacks treated with 1, 2, or ≥3 injections of icatibant and C1-inhibitor (C1-INH) rescue medication(s) in patients who received or did not receive long-term prophylaxis (LTP)</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Demographic characteristicsHAE hereditary angioedema, max maximum, min minimum</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Characteristic</cell><cell>Total</cell></row><row><cell>Patients, N</cell><cell>448</cell></row><row><cell>HAE diagnosis, n (%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Type 1</cell><cell>423 (94.4)</cell></row><row><cell>Type 2</cell><cell>25 (5.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Sex, n (%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>263 (58.7)</cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell>185 (41.3)</cell></row><row><cell>Age at enrollment, y</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean (SD)</cell><cell>40.8 (14.7)</cell></row><row><cell>Median (min, max)</cell><cell>39.1 (16.5, 81.8)</cell></row><row><cell>Country, n (%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>France</cell><cell>119 (26.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Spain</cell><cell>69 (15.4)</cell></row><row><cell>Germany</cell><cell>57 (12.7)</cell></row><row><cell>United Kingdom</cell><cell>53 (11.8)</cell></row><row><cell>Italy</cell><cell>46 (10.3)</cell></row><row><cell>Israel</cell><cell>45 (10.0)</cell></row><row><cell>Denmark</cell><cell>19 (4.2)</cell></row><row><cell>Brazil</cell><cell>16 (3.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Greece</cell><cell>14 (3.1)</cell></row><row><cell>Austria</cell><cell>8 (1.8)</cell></row><row><cell>Sweden</cell><cell>2 (0.4)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 Characteristics of icatibant-treated attacks in patients with and without LTP Analysis</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>included attack data for patients who were or were not receiving LTP at the time of the attack(s) and who were treated with icatibant for acute attacks HCP health care provider, LTP long-term prophylaxis a Some patients reported attacks with LTP as well as without LTP</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>b P = 0.147 for comparison of very mild/mild/moderate versus severe/very severe attacks</cell></row><row><cell>c Excludes attacks with missing or unknown data</cell></row><row><cell>d Other organs affected by ≥2 attacks include tongue, bladder, esophagus, lungs, respiratory tract, breast, genitals, testicles, bowel, stomach, uvula, joints,</cell></row><row><cell>and brain</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 Duration of treatment and attack frequency for each type of LTP C1</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>-INH C1-inhibitor, IQR interquartile range, LTP long-term prophylaxis a The start date of LTP was imputed to the date of the first treated attack if the patient started LTP before the date of the first attack b The sum of maximum treatment duration.</s><s>Treatments received by patients were included even if they were not related to treated attacks c Icatibant-treated attacks that occurred with or without LTP d Androgens include danazol, stanozolol, and oxandrolone e The duration (follow-up time) of icatibant treatment for patients who never received LTP.</s><s>Duration was computed from first attack date to extract date, death date, or discontinuation date, as applicable.</s><s>Patients who reported attacks with and without LTP were excluded</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Type of LTP</cell><cell>No. of attacks (%)</cell><cell>No. of patients (%)</cell><cell cols="2">Duration of LTP, y a</cell><cell></cell><cell>Attack frequency</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Mean (SD)</cell><cell>Median (IQR)</cell><cell>Total duration b</cell><cell>(attacks/year) c</cell></row><row><cell>C1-INH</cell><cell>121 (12.4)</cell><cell>15 (8.8)</cell><cell>3.4 (1.4)</cell><cell>3.1 (2.6-3.7)</cell><cell>51.5</cell><cell>2.3</cell></row><row><cell>C1-INH/androgens d</cell><cell>9 (0.9)</cell><cell>4 (2.3)</cell><cell>4.6 (1.4)</cell><cell>4.6 (3.4-5.8)</cell><cell>18.6</cell><cell>0.5</cell></row><row><cell>C1-INH/androgens/</cell><cell>4 (0.4)</cell><cell>2 (1.2)</cell><cell>3.3 (1.9)</cell><cell>3.3 (1.9-4.6)</cell><cell>6.5</cell><cell>0.6</cell></row><row><cell>tranexamic acid</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>C1-INH/tranexamic acid</cell><cell>24 (2.5)</cell><cell>2 (1.2)</cell><cell>3.8 (1.1)</cell><cell>3.8 (3.1-4.6)</cell><cell>7.7</cell><cell>3.1</cell></row><row><cell>Androgens</cell><cell>542 (55.7)</cell><cell>108 (63.2)</cell><cell>3.5 (1.9)</cell><cell>3.4 (2.2-5.0)</cell><cell>372.7</cell><cell>1.5</cell></row><row><cell>Androgens/tranexamic acid</cell><cell>41 (4.2)</cell><cell>9 (5.3)</cell><cell>5.0 (1.3)</cell><cell>4.5 (4.1-6.0)</cell><cell>44.8</cell><cell>0.9</cell></row><row><cell>Tranexamic acid</cell><cell>232 (23.8)</cell><cell>43 (25.1)</cell><cell>3.4 (1.8)</cell><cell>3.8 (1.6-4.6)</cell><cell>147.1</cell><cell>1.6</cell></row><row><cell>Overall</cell><cell>973</cell><cell>171</cell><cell>3.5 (1.8)</cell><cell>3.6 (2.2-4.8)</cell><cell>620.5</cell><cell>1.6</cell></row><row><cell>No LTP e</cell><cell>1941</cell><cell>277</cell><cell>3.6 (1.8)</cell><cell>3.4 (2.1-5.0)</cell><cell>985.4</cell><cell>2.0</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> Aberer et al. Allergy Asthma Clin Immunol (2017)   13:31    <p><s>potential for breakthrough attacks, including those of high severity and involving the larynx, and should be prepared by having easily accessible emergency treatment.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Abbreviations</head><p><s>C1-INH: C1-inhibitor; C1-INH-HAE: hereditary angioedema due to C1-inhibitor deficiency; HAE: hereditary angioedema; HCP: health care provider; IOS: Icatibant Outcome Survey; IQR: interquartile range; LTP: long-term prophylaxis.</s></p><p><s>Authors' contributions WA, MM, LB, AZ, TC, HJL and IA contributed to study conception and design, data acquisition, analysis and interpretation, drafting the manuscript and critical content revisions; AP contributed to analysis and interpretation of data, drafting the manuscript and critical content revisions.</s><s>Although employees of the Sponsor were involved in the design, collection, analysis, interpretation, and fact checking of information, the content of this manuscript, the interpretation of the data, and the decision to submit the manuscript for publication in Allergy, Asthma &amp; Clinical Immunology was made by the authors independently.</s><s>All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</s></p><p><s>Author details 1 Department of Dermatology and Venerology, Medical University of Graz, Auenbruggerplatz 8, A-8036 Graz, Austria. 2 Department of Dermatology and Allergy, Allergie-Centrum-Charité, Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Charitéplatz 1, 10117 Berlin, Germany. 3 National Reference Centre for Angioedema, Internal Medicine Department, Grenoble University Hospital, Boulevard de la Chantourne-CS10217, 38043 Grenoble, France. 4</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>Under the direction of the authors, Shirley Teng, Ph.D., CMPP, of Excel Scientific Solutions provided writing assistance for this publication.</s><s>Editorial assistance in formatting, proofreading, copy editing, and fact checking was also provided by Excel Scientific Solutions.</s><s>Funding for writing and editorial assistance was provided by Shire Human Genetic Therapies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IOS Investigators</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Competing interests</head><p><s>W. Aberer has acted as a medical advisor and speaker for BioCryst, CSL Behring, Pharming, and Shire, and has participated in clinical trials and received funding to attend conferences and educational events, in addition to donations to his departmental fund from Shire.</s><s>M. Maurer has received research grant support and/or speaker/consultancy fees from BioCryst, CSL Behring, Dyax, and Shire.</s><s>L. Bouillet has received honoraria from BioCryst, CSL Behring, Novartis, Pharming, and Shire, and her institute has received research funding from CSL Behring, GlaxoSmithKline, Novartis, Roche, and Shire. A. Zanichelli has received speaker/consultancy fees from CSL Behring, Shire, and SOBI.</s><s>T. Caballero has received speaker fees from CSL Behring, GlaxoSmith-Kline, MSD, Novartis, and Shire; consultancy fees from BioCryst, CSL Behring, Novartis, Shire, and SOBI; funding for travel and meeting attendance from CSL Behring, Novartis, and Shire; and has participated in clinical trials/registries for CSL Behring, Dyax, Novartis, Pharming, and Shire.</s><s>She is a researcher from the IdiPaz program promoting research activities.</s><s>H.J. Longhurst has received research grant support and/or speaker/consultancy fees from BioCryst, CSL Behring, Dyax, Shire, and SOBI.</s><s>Amandine Perrin and Irmgard Andresen are full-time employees of Shire, Zug, Switzerland.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Availability of data and materials</head><p><s>The datasets generated during the current study are not publicly available because the data from IOS reside in a proprietary database maintained by Shire but data are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request and with permission of Shire.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethics approval and consent to participate</head><p><s>IOS is conducted in multiple sites across 11 countries in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and the International Conference on Harmonisation Good Clinical Practice guidelines.</s><s>All sites obtained approval from local ethics committees and/or health authorities (where applicable), and all patients provided written informed consent before the initiation of data collection.</s><s>Consent from parents or a legal representative was obtained for patients who were younger than 18 years of age at the time of enrollment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Funding</head><p><s>IOS is sponsored by Shire International GmbH.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Publisher's Note</head><p><s>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hereditary angio-oedema</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Longhurst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cicardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">379</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="474" to="481" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A focused parameter update: hereditary angioedema, acquired C1 inhibitor deficiency, and angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor-associated angioedema</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zuraw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bernstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Craig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dreyfus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hsieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1491" to="1493" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evidencebased recommendations for the therapeutic management of angioedema owing to hereditary C1 inhibitor deficiency: consensus report of an International Working Group</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cicardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bork</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Caballero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Craig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Longhurst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Allergy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WAO guideline for the management of hereditary angioedema</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Craig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Aygören-Pürsün</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bork</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bowen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Boysen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Farkas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Allergy Organ J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="182" to="199" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Classification, diagnosis, and approach to treatment for angioedema: consensus report from the Hereditary Angioedema International Working Group</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cicardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Aberer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Banerji</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bernstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bork</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Allergy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="602" to="616" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">C1 inhibitor deficiency: 2014 United Kingdom consensus document</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Longhurst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Tarzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ashworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bethune</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dempster</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Exp Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">180</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="475" to="483" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Safety and efficacy of prophylactic nanofiltered C1-inhibitor in hereditary angioedema</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zuraw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Kalfus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="938" to="e939" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recombinant human C1 inhibitor for the prophylaxis of hereditary angioedema attacks: a pilot study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Reshef</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Moldovan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Obtulowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Leibovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mihaly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Visscher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Allergy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="118" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long-term prophylaxis with C1-inhibitor concentrate in patients with hereditary angioedema</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pedrosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lobera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Panizo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jurado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Caballero</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Investig Allergol Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="271" to="273" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Treatment of hereditary angioedema with danazol: reversal of clinical and biochemical abnormalities</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gelfand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sherins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Alling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Frank</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">295</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1444" to="1448" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical and biochemical effects of stanozolol therapy for hereditary angioedema</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Sheffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Fearon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Austen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="187" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hereditary angioedema attacks resolve faster and are shorter after early icatibant treatment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maurer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Aberer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bouillet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Caballero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Fabien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kanny</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e53773</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of characteristics associated with reinjection of icatibant: results from the Icatibant Outcome Survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Longhurst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Aberer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bouillet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Caballero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Fabien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zanichelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Allergy Asthma Proc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="399" to="406" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nanofiltered C1 inhibitor concentrate for treatment of hereditary angioedema</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Zuraw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Busse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jacobs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Lumry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Baker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">363</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="513" to="522" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Benefits and risks of danazol in hereditary angioedema: a long-term survey of 118 patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bork</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bygum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Allergy Asthma Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="161" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The safety of treatments for angioedema with hereditary C1 inhibitor deficiency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zanichelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Andreoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mansi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cicardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Expert Opin Drug Saf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1725" to="1736" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Icatibant Outcome Survey: treatment of laryngeal angioedema attacks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Longhurst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Aberer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bouillet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Caballero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maurer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Fabien</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Emerg Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="224" to="227" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficacy of on-demand treatment in reducing morbidity in patients with hereditary angioedema due to C1 inhibitor deficiency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zanichelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mansi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Azin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Periti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Casazza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Allergy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1553" to="1558" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathophysiology of hereditary angioedema</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Caccia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Suffritti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cicardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatr Allergy Immunol Pulmonol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="163" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">C1 inhibitor for routine prophylaxis in patients with hereditary angioedema: interim results from a European registry study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Aygören-Pürsün</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Magerl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Martinez-Saguer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">B251</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
