<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">nature neuroscience | reporting checklist</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-03">March 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">nature neuroscience | reporting checklist</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-03">March 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">945B8785073F952D94E9A53332BAB788</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nn.4364</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:44+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Reporting Checklist for Nature Neuroscience</s></p><p><s>This checklist is used to ensure good reporting standards and to improve the reproducibility of published results.</s><s>For more information, please read Reporting Life Sciences Research.</s></p><p><s>Please note that in the event of publication, it is mandatory that authors include all relevant methodological and statistical information in the manuscript.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Statistics reporting, by figure</head><p><s>Please specify the following information for each panel reporting quantitative data, and where each item is reported (section, e.g.</s><s>Results, &amp; paragraph number).</s></p><p><s>Each figure legend should ideally contain an exact sample size (n) for each experimental group/condition, where n is an exact number and not a range, a clear definition of how n is defined (for example x cells from x slices from x animals from x litters, collected over x days), a description of the statistical test used, the results of the tests, any descriptive statistics and clearly defined error bars if applicable.</s></p><p><s>For any experiments using custom statistics, please indicate the test used and stats obtained for each experiment.</s></p><p><s>Each figure legend should include a statement of how many times the experiment shown was replicated in the lab; the details of sample collection should be sufficiently clear so that the replicability of the experiment is obvious to the reader.</s></p><p><s>For experiments reported in the text but not in the figures, please use the paragraph number instead of the figure number.</s></p><p><s>Note: Mean and standard deviation are not appropriate on small samples, and plotting independent data points is usually more informative.</s><s>When technical replicates are reported, error and significance measures reflect the experimental variability and not the variability of the biological process; it is misleading not to state this clearly.</s><s>2. For each representative image, is there a clear statement of how many times this experiment was successfully repeated and a discussion of any limitations in repeatability?</s></p><p><s>If so, where is this reported (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Yes, there is a statement included in every figure legend.</s></p><p><s> Statistics and general methods 1.</s><s>Is there a justification of the sample size?</s></p><p><s>If so, how was it justified?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Even if no sample size calculation was performed, authors should report why the sample size is adequate to measure their effect size.</s></p><p><s>Typical sample sizes where chosen in accordance with previous publications and are similar to those generally enmployed in the field.</s><s>We included a statement in the methods part.</s></p><p><s>2. Are statistical tests justified as appropriate for every figure?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>The Where is this described (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Yes, the data meet the assumptions for the specific statistical test we chose.</s></p><p><s>c.</s><s>Is there any estimate of variance within each group of data?</s></p><p><s>Is the variance similar between groups that are being statistically compared?</s></p><p><s>Where is this described (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Yes, we checked for variation among different groups within each dataset.</s><s>The used tests were adjusted when variances differed.</s><s>We did not mention this in the manuscript but we are prepared to do so if requested.</s></p><p><s>d. Are tests specified as one-or two-sided?</s><s>Tests were specified for one-way ANOVA and two tailed t-tests (see statistics methods section).</s></p><p><s>e. Are there adjustments for multiple comparisons?</s><s>For multiple comparison tests, one-way ANOVA has been used for all of the experiments.</s></p><p><s>3. To promote transparency, Nature Neuroscience has stopped allowing bar graphs to report statistics in the papers it publishes.</s><s>If you have bar graphs in your paper, please make sure to switch them to dotplots (with central and dispersion statistics displayed) or to box-andwhisker plots to show data distributions.</s></p><p><s>All bar plots have been edited accordingly.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Are criteria for excluding data points reported?</head><p><s>Was this criterion established prior to data collection?</s></p><p><s>Where is this described (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Yes.</s><s>Cells were excluded if the Hill equation (Fig. <ref type="figure">7b</ref>, Fig. <ref type="figure">S4a-c</ref>) could not be properly fit to the data (affected only 2 cells in Unc13ANull).</s><s>This criterion was not established prior to data collection as we did not know that this would happen.</s><s>This is stated in the methods section for electrophysiology.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>nature neuroscience | reporting checklist</head><p><s>March 2016</s></p><p><s>5. Define the method of randomization used to assign subjects (or samples) to the experimental groups and to collect and process data.</s></p><p><s>If no randomization was used, state so.</s></p><p><s>Where does this appear (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>HPF images were randomized by changing the genotype name to random numbers.</s><s>Subsequently the analysis of the HPF images (Fig. <ref type="figure">6</ref>) was performed by a third person.</s><s>Otherwise, no randomization was used.</s><s>However, for immunostainings, all genotypes were prepped in one session, stained in one cup and strictly analyzed in an unbiased manner.</s><s>For electrophysiological recordings, genotypes were measured in an alternating fashion on the same day and strictly analyzed in an unbiased manner.</s></p><p><s>6.</s><s>Is a statement of the extent to which investigator knew the group allocation during the experiment and in assessing outcome included?</s></p><p><s>If no blinding was done, state so.</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>No randomization was applied.</s><s>However, all genotypes were prepped in one session, stained in one cup and strictly analyzed in an unbiased manner.</s><s>For electrophysiological recordings, genotypes were measured in an alternating fashion on the same day and strictly analyzed in an unbiased manner.</s></p><p><s>7. For experiments in live vertebrates, is a statement of compliance with ethical guidelines/regulations included?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Not applicable 8.</s><s>Is the species of the animals used reported?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>For all experiments, Drosophila melanogaster (fruit flies) were used.</s><s>This has been clearly mentioned throughout the manuscript starting from the introduction and also in the abstract.</s><s>9. Is the strain of the animals (including background strains of KO/ transgenic animals used) reported?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Yes, the fly strains have been clearly reported under the genetics section in material and methods of the manuscript.</s></p><p><s>10.</s><s>Is the sex of the animals/subjects used reported?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Yes, the sex of the animals used for different experiments has been explicitly mentioned in material and methods part.</s></p><p><s>11.</s><s>Is the age of the animals/subjects reported?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>No specific age is mentioned, but all of the larvae analyzed were in late third-instar stage, as mentioned in the methods part.</s></p><p><s>12. For animals housed in a vivarium, is the light/dark cycle reported?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>We did not mention this in the manuscript but all animals were reared in a 12h light/dark cycle for animals housed in a vivarium.</s><s>We are prepared to mention it in the methods section if requested.</s></p><p><s>13.</s><s>For animals housed in a vivarium, is the housing group (i.e.</s><s>number of animals per cage) reported?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>This is not mentioned because it is hard to exactly define the number of flies in each vial, but care was taken that overcrowding did not happen, and that animal numbers were comparable and not systematically different, especially during experiments.</s><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>No animals/subjects were excluded.</s></p><p><s>a. How were the criteria for exclusion defined?</s></p><p><s>Where is this described (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Not applicable b.</s><s>Specify reasons for any discrepancy between the number of animals at the beginning and end of the study.</s></p><p><s>Where is this described (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Not applicable  Reagents 1. Have antibodies been validated for use in the system under study (assay and species)?</s></p><p><s>Yes, all antibodies that were specifically created in that study were validated, which is also shown in figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</s><s>All the other antibodies used for immunohistochemistry have been previously reported.</s></p><p><s>a. Is antibody catalog number given?</s></p><p><s>Where does this appear (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Catalog numbers are provided in additon to the source companies in the material and method section.</s></p><p><s>b.</s><s>Where were the validation data reported (citation, supplementary information, Antibodypedia)?</s></p><p><s>Where does this appear (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>The validation of the Unc13A and -B antibodies is reported in figure 1.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Cell line identity</head><p><s>a. Are any cell lines used in this paper listed in the database of commonly misidentified cell lines maintained by ICLAC and NCBI Biosample?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Not applicable b.</s><s>If yes, include in the Methods section a scientific justification of their use--indicate here in which section and paragraph the justification can be found.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Not applicable</head><p><s>2. If computer code was used to generate results that are central to the paper's conclusions, include a statement in the Methods section under "Code availability" to indicate whether and how the code can be accessed.</s><s>Include version information as necessary and any restrictions on availability.</s></p><p><s>We included a statement mentioning the availability of our customwritten codes.</s></p><p><s> Human subjects 1.</s><s>Which IRB approved the protocol?</s></p><p><s>Where is this stated (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Not applicable 2. Is demographic information on all subjects provided?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Not applicable 3. Is the number of human subjects, their age and sex clearly defined?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Not applicable 4. Are the inclusion and exclusion criteria (if any) clearly specified?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Not applicable 5. How well were the groups matched?</s></p><p><s>Where is this information described (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Not applicable 6.</s><s>Is a statement included confirming that informed consent was obtained from all subjects?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s><s>Not applicable 7.</s><s>For publication of patient photos, is a statement included confirming that consent to publish was obtained?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Not applicable</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> fMRI studies</head><p><s>For papers reporting functional imaging (fMRI) results please ensure that these minimal reporting guidelines are met and that all this information is clearly provided in the methods:</s></p><p><s>1. Were any subjects scanned but then rejected for the analysis after the data was collected?</s><s>Not applicable a.</s><s>If yes, is the number rejected and reasons for rejection described?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Not applicable</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1c-</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig.1c-i; Fig.2b-g; Fig.3a,b,e,f,i,j; Fig.4a,h,e,l; Fig.5; Fig.6a,b,d,e; Fig.7a,d,f; Fig.S1a,b,g,h; Fig.S3a-c,g-i; Fig.S5g,l;</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>statistical tests are explicitly mentioned in each figure legend and in table S1.</s><s>Statistical tests are chosen appropriate to sample sizes, SEM values or whether two or more groups were compared. .</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>a. If there is a section summarizing the statistical methods in</cell><cell>Statistical tests for each experiment are specified in every figure</cell></row><row><cell>the methods, is the statistical test for each experiment</cell><cell>legend as well as in table S1. A summary is provided in the methods</cell></row><row><cell>clearly defined?</cell><cell>section.</cell></row></table><note><p><s>b. Do the data meet the assumptions of the specific statistical test you chose (e.g.</s><s>normality for a parametric test)?</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">nature neuroscience | reporting checklist</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Nature Neuroscience: doi:10.1038/nn.4364</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">nature neuroscience | reporting checklistMarch 2016</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>nature neuroscience | reporting checklist</head><p><s>March 2016 c.</s><s>For each cell line, include in the Methods section a statement that specifies:</s></p><p><s>-the source of the cell lines -have the cell lines been authenticated?</s><s>If so, by which method?</s></p><p><s>-have the cell lines been tested for mycoplasma contamination?</s></p><p><s>Where (section, paragraph #)?</s></p><p><s>Not applicable</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Data availability</head><p><s>Provide a Data availability statement in the Methods section under "Data availability", which should include, where applicable:</s></p><p><s>• Accession codes for deposited data Protein sequences of all used Y2H fragments and antibody epitopes are provided in the material and methods section.</s></p><p><s>Resources and clones used for isoform specific mutants are provided in the material and methods section.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Computer code/software</head><p><s>Any custom algorithm/software that is central to the methods must be supplied by the authors in a usable and readable form for readers at the time of publication.</s><s>However, referees may ask for this information at any time during the review process.</s></p><p><s>1. Identify all custom software or scripts that were required to conduct the study and where in the procedures each was used.</s></p><p><s>All custom written MATLAB scripts used for mathematical modeling will be made accessible by request upon publication or before if required.</s></p><p><s>nature neuroscience | reporting checklist</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Is the number of blocks, trials or experimental units per session and/ or subjects specified? Where (section</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Not applicable</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Is the length of each trial and interval between trials specified? Not applicable</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Is a blocked, event-related, or mixed design being used? If applicable, please specify the block length or how the event-related or mixed design was optimized</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Not applicable</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Is the task design clearly described? Where (section, paragraph #)? Not applicable</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">How was behavioral performance measured? Not applicable</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Is an ANOVA or factorial design being used? Not applicable</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">For data acquisition, is a whole brain scan used? If not, state area of acquisition</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Not applicable a. How was this region determined? Not applicable</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is the pulse sequence type (gradient/spin echo, EPI/spiral) stated?</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Is the field strength (in Tesla) of the MRI system stated? Not applicable a</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Not applicable</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Are the field-of-view, matrix size, slice thickness, and TE/TR/ flip angle clearly stated</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Not applicable</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Are the software and specific parameters (model/functions, smoothing kernel size if applicable, etc.) used for data processing and pre-processing clearly stated</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Not applicable</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is the coordinate space for the anatomical/functional imaging data clearly defined as subject/native space or standardized stereotaxic space</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">original Talairach, MNI305, ICBM152, etc? Where (section, paragraph #)? Not applicable</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">If there was data normalization/standardization to a specific space template, are the type of transformation (linear vs. nonlinear) used and image types being transformed clearly described? Where (section</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Not applicable</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">How were anatomical locations determined, e.g., via an automated labeling algorithm (AAL), standardized coordinate database (Talairach daemon), probabilistic atlases, etc</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Not applicable</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nn.4364</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
