<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Acyclovir-induced thrombocytopaenia in a patient with SLE</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-05-25">25 May 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Irene</forename><surname>Tsappa</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Medical school</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cyprus</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nicosia</settlement>
									<country key="CY">Cyprus</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Constantinos</forename><surname>Missouris</surname></persName>
							<email>dinos.missouris@fhft.nhs.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Medical school</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cyprus</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nicosia</settlement>
									<country key="CY">Cyprus</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Frimley Health NHs trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Cardiology</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">rheumatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Nicosia General Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nicosia</settlement>
									<country key="CY">Cyprus</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Acyclovir-induced thrombocytopaenia in a patient with SLE</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-05-25">25 May 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">95852B28203D7F0B212F4607929D02C5</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1136/bcr-2018-225118</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:44+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>tsappa I</term>
					<term>Missouris C</term>
					<term>psarellis s. BMJ Case Rep published online First: [please include Day Month Year]</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>acyclovir has been used in the treatment of herpes simplex and varicella zoster viral infections for over 30 years. the side effects of oral treatment at standard doses are rare and include headache, diarrhoea, dizziness and malaise.</s><s>We report a patient with a new diagnosis of systemic lupus erythematosus (sLe) who developed thrombocytopaenia within days on a therapeutic dose with acyclovir.</s><s>prompt discontinuation of acyclovir and treatment with intravenous immunoglobulin resulted in reversal of the above potentially serious complication.</s><s>therefore a high index of suspicion should be exercised in patients with sLe who require treatment with acyclovir for herpes viral infections.</s><s>In these patients regular platelet count measurement should be considered while on treatment with the above antiviral agent.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BaCkground</head><p><s>Acyclovir has been used to treat infections with herpes simplex and varicella zoster viruses for over 30 years.</s><s>It is widely distributed in almost every organ in the body and is excreted in the urine.</s><s>The drug has mild side effects at therapeutic doses as it is only absorbed by the virus infected and not the host cells.</s><s>Common adverse effects include nausea, vomiting, malaise and diarrhoea.</s><s>Less common adverse effects, usually related to high-dose intravenous administration, include neurotoxicity, renal, hepatic and psychiatric disorders, and rarely myelosuppressive complications and skin dyscrasias have been reported. <ref type="bibr">1 2</ref></s><s>e report a patient with a diagnosis of systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) who developed severe isolated thrombocytopaenia within days following treatment at a therapeutic dose with acyclovir.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CaSe preSenTaTion</head><p><s>A 54-year-old Caucasian female patient with no medical or family history of note was referred to the rheumatology department of our hospital with photosensitivity, malaise, high fever and oral ulcers.</s><s>Shortly after admission she developed an acute severe hypertensive crisis with pulmonary oedema, pleural and pericardial effusions, and proteinuria.</s><s>She also had evidence of non-erosive arthritis.</s><s>Renal biopsy suggested the presence of diffuse proliferative nephritis.</s><s>Her haemoglobin was 11.0 g/ dL, white cell count was 2.16×10 9 /L and platelet count was 176×10 9 /L.</s><s>Furthermore she had positive antinuclear antibodies, antidouble-stranded DNA, anti-Ro/SSA antibodies, IgA anticardiolipin, IgG and IgA anti-β2glycoprotein I antibodies.</s><s>The diagnosis of SLE was made. <ref type="bibr">3</ref></s><s>The patient was therefore treated with intravenous methylprednisolone (1 g/day for 3 days) and cyclophosphamide (1 g for 1 day).</s><s>She was discharged home on a maintenance dose of prednisolone and made an uneventful recovery.</s></p><p><s>A month later she re-presented with a painful unilateral vesicular rash on the left side of the face and neck in keeping with herpes zoster infection affecting the branches of the left trigeminal nerve (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>She also reported tingling sensation at the site of the rash but denied any constitutional symptoms like fever or malaise.</s><s>At the time the patient was on treatment with prednisolone (1 mg per kg/day).</s><s>She was apyrexial and the clinical examination was unremarkable.</s><s>Her haemoglobin was 10 g/dL, white cell count was 6.64×10 9 /L and platelet count was 275×10 9 /L.</s><s>The patient was therefore prescribed oral acyclovir 1 g once a day.</s></p><p><s>Five days after treatment with acyclovir, her platelet count dropped to 9×10 9 /L.</s><s>Her white cell count was 9.47×10 9 /L, red blood cell count was 3.52×10 12 /L and haemoglobin was 9.7 g/dL.</s><s>She had no overt symptoms and no evidence of a purpuric rash or cutaneous haematomas.</s><s>Due to the temporal relation between the introduction of the drug and the onset of thrombocytopaenia, the diagnosis acyclovir-induced thrombocytopaenia was made, likely to have been immune in origin.</s><s>The patient had no symptoms related to the SLE and her autoimmune condition was quiescent.</s><s>Acyclovir-specific antibodies are not available at our institution.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TreaTmenT</head><p><s>Acyclovir was discontinued and the patient was promptly treated with intravenous IgG (0.4 g per kg/day for 4 days).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ouTCome and follow-up</head><p><s>Three days later the platelet count recovered to 140×10 9 /L.</s><s>One year later the patient is completely asymptomatic on treatment with hydroxychloroquine (400 mg per day), prednisone (2.5 mg per day) and mycophenolate mofetil (2 g per day).</s><s>Furthermore the platelet count remains stable at 270×10 9 /L.</s><s>unexpected outcome (positive or negative) including adverse drug reactions may lead to thrombocytopaenia, which unless recognised and treated promptly may lead to life-threatening complications.</s><s>To our knowledge, this is the first case report of the above condition occurring after treatment with acyclovir in a patient with SLE.</s></p><p><s>Acyclovir is a purine nucleoside analogue antiviral drug which inhibits viral replication.</s><s>Its mechanism of action involves three stages, the first of which involves metabolism by viral thymidine kinase and the last two stages by a cellular kinase, thereby converting acyclovir to acyclovir monophosphate, diphosphate and triphosphate, respectively.</s><s>The active triphosphate form of the drug binds to viral DNA polymerase, inactivates it and inhibits further viral DNA chain growth. 1 Acyclovir is widely used to treat mucocutaneous herpes, herpes zoster, herpes encephalitis and genital herpes simplex.</s><s>The drug has wide distribution in almost every organ of the body.</s><s>It is only absorbed by the cells that are infected with the virus; hence, acyclovir has minimal side effects at therapeutic doses.</s><s>However, high intravenous infusions may cause multisystem side effects and blood dyscrasias.</s></p><p><s>Drug-induced thrombocytopaenia is caused by either bone marrow suppression or by accelerated platelet destruction, usually immune-mediated.</s></p><p><s>5]<ref type="bibr">[6]</ref> Hong et al 5 reported a patient who developed immune thrombocytopaenia with tongue haematoma 10 days after intravenous acyclovir treatment.</s><s>They postulated that in their patient with extensive purpuric rash and tongue haematoma, the presence of thrombocytopaenia was unlikely to be related to bone marrow suppression (as the haemoglobin and white cell count were unaffected) and more likely to be mediated by drug-dependent immune mechanism.</s></p><p><s>In our patient the likely diagnosis is one of acyclovir-induced immune thrombocytopaenia.</s><s>This is based on the temporal relationship between starting acyclovir and the onset of thrombocytopaenia and the absence of any active clinical conditions, or the use of other pharmacological agents that are known to affect platelet count.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>►figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>figure 1 Unilateral vesicular rash on the left side of the face and neck suggestive of varicella zoster viral infection.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,44.81,48.00,240.96,347.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>unexpected outcome (positive or negative) including adverse drug reactions</head><p><s>Copyright 2018 BMJ publishing Group.</s><s>all rights reserved.</s><s>For permission to reuse any of this content visit http://group.bmj.com/group/rights-licensing/permissions.</s><s>BMJ Case report Fellows may re-use this article for personal use and teaching without any further permission.</s></p><p><s>Become a Fellow of BMJ Case reports today and you can: ► submit as many cases as you like ► enjoy fast sympathetic peer review and rapid publication of accepted articles ► access all the published articles ► re-use any of the published material for personal use and teaching without further permission For information on Institutional Fellowships contact consortiasales@bmjgroup.com Visit casereports.bmj.com for more articles like this and to become a Fellow</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
