<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Publication date: March 2018 Citation: Fair GL, Harris MF, Smith MM. Transition from an asylum seeker-specific health service to mainstream primary care for community-based asylum seekers: a qualitative interview study. Public Health Res Pract</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Genevieve</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fair</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Primary Health Care and Equity</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">UNSW Sydney</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Mark</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
							<email>m.f.harris@unsw.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Centre for Primary Health Care and Equity</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">UNSW Sydney</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Guest Editor</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Public Health Research &amp; Practice</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Issue 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>2018</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mitchell</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Guest Editor</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Public Health Research &amp; Practice</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Issue 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>2018</postCode>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">NSW Refugee Health Service</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Sydney</settlement>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Publication date: March 2018 Citation: Fair GL, Harris MF, Smith MM. Transition from an asylum seeker-specific health service to mainstream primary care for community-based asylum seekers: a qualitative interview study. Public Health Res Pract</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B20359784CD84491DD1A074089940045</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.17061/phrp2811805</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:44+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Background and aim: Transition of asylum seekers from special-purpose health services to mainstream primary care is both necessary and difficult.</s><s>This study explores the issues encountered by asylum seekers undergoing this transition in Sydney, Australia.</s></p><p><s>Methods: Qualitative semistructured interviews were conducted with nine asylum seeker patients and nine staff working in the sector.</s></p><p><s>Results: Asylum seekers faced significant challenges in the transition to mainstream primary care.</s><s>Contributing factors included the complexity of health and immigration systems, the way in which asylum seeker-specific services provide care, lack of understanding and accommodation by mainstream general practioner (GP) services, asylum seekers' own lack of understanding of the health system, mental illness, and social and financial pressures.</s></p><p><s>Conclusions: There is a need for better preparation of asylum seekers for the transition to mainstream primary care.</s><s>Mainstream GPs and other providers need more education and support so that they can better accommodate the needs of asylum seeker patients.</s><s>This is an important role for Australia's refugee health services and Primary Health Networks.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>In 2016, an estimated 29 560 asylum seekers resided in Australia <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> , many of them in the community.</s><s>The United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees considers asylum seekers to be "individuals who have sought international protection and whose claims for refugee status have not yet been determined". <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref></s><s>ansition from an asylum seeker-specific health service to mainstream primary care for community-based asylum seekers: a qualitative interview study</s></p><p><s>• Asylum seekers, like other refugees, face significant problems in transitioning from asylum seeker-specific services to mainstream primary care • Many factors contribute to these problems, including the approach of both asylum seeker-specific health services and mainstream general practitioners (GPs) • Asylum seekers should be prepared for the transition to mainstream primary care in advance.</s><s>GPs require education and support to better accommodate the needs of asylum seeker patients</s></p><p><s>Community-based asylum seekers face diverse and complex health problems, including infectious, nutritional and chronic noncommunicable diseases.</s><s>Many asylum seekers have experienced torture and trauma, and develop psychological illnesses.</s><s>Both physical and psychological conditions are often complicated by migration, asylum status and settlement. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> Despite a great need for health services, it has been recognised that many asylum seekers face significant barriers to accessing primary health care. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Services for asylum seekers in Sydney</head><p><s>This paper defines 'asylum seeker-specific health services' as those that provide free primary health care to asylum seekers while they are ineligible for the Australian Government's universal health insurance program, Medicare.</s><s>In Sydney, New South Wales (NSW), there are two services: the Asylum Seekers Centre (ASC) and the NSW Refugee Health Service (RHS).</s><s>The ASC is a nongovernment organisation that is dependent on donations and pro bono arrangements.</s><s>It delivers free primary care, and social and financial support to asylum seekers, including more than 3000 health consultations and 450 free medications each year.</s><s>The ASC employs one full-time health manager and two part-time registered nurses, and has pro bono arrangements with general practitioners (GPs), offering up to two primary care halfday sessions a week. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">4</ref></s><s>Limited dental, physiotherapy, psychology and counselling services are available.</s><s>The RHS provides health assessments and a GP clinic for Medicare-ineligible asylum seekers. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">5</ref></s><s>The resources of both services are limited, necessitating the transition of patients to mainstream primary health care once they are eligible for Medicare. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">7</ref></s><s>he Status Resolution Support Services (SRSS) program, funded by the Australian Government Department of Home Affairs (DHA), provides services to asylum seekers while their claims are being resolved.</s><s>These may include financial assistance, housing, case management and access to schooling.</s><s>SRSS providers are contracted by the DHA to administer payments and services. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">8</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Transitions in care</head><p><s>The transition from asylum seeker-specific to mainstream primary care has proven to be difficult in a number of Australian and international contexts. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">6</ref></s><s>The transition is often complicated by a lack of coordination between specialised and mainstream services <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">9</ref> , reluctance among patients to transition <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">10</ref> , difficulties in medical record transfer <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">11</ref> , and the vulnerability of patients from a refugee background. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12</ref></s><s>However, the literature is limited and mostly considers refugees alone.</s><s>The relevance of these issues to asylum seekers has not been fully established.</s><s>Significantly, the views of asylum seekers themselves have not been comprehensively explored in the literature.</s></p><p><s>This study aims to inform and improve the transition process by exploring current issues through interviews with asylum seeker patients and healthcare providers, focused on the following research questions: 1.</s><s>What knowledge, attitudes and experiences exist among healthcare providers working with asylum seekers about transition from asylum seeker-specific primary care to ongoing mainstream primary health care services?</s><s>2. What are the views and experiences of asylum seekers making the transition from asylum seekerspecific primary care to mainstream primary health care services?</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p><s>Qualitative semistructured interviews were conducted with nine asylum seeker patients and nine healthcare providers working in the asylum seeker sector between April and August 2016.</s><s>Healthcare provider participants were recruited via the professional networks of the researchers and asylum seeker-specific health service staff.</s><s>Participants were interviewed in person by author GF, who obtained written consent, and recorded and transcribed interviews verbatim.</s><s>Topics included the health needs of asylum seekers, perceptions of the transition process and suggestions for improvement.</s></p><p><s>Asylum seeker participants were former or current clients of the ASC health service.</s><s>Clients were invited to participate if they had been eligible for Medicare at some point and thus had transitioned from the ASC to a mainstream GP.</s><s>Some clients had returned to the ASC because of loss of their Medicare entitlements.</s><s>Purposive sampling was used to ensure diverse backgrounds and experiences.</s><s>Clients were approached by an ASC nurse and informed about the study.</s><s>Interested and eligible participants were interviewed at the ASC by GF.</s><s>Verbal consent was obtained and handwritten notes were taken during the interview, rather than audio recording.</s><s>This was agreed among the researchers to be preferable based on prior experience with asylum seeker clients, who could be suspicious of recordings and feel uncomfortable signing written documents.</s><s>Participants who were known to clinic staff to not be fluent in English were offered an appropriate telephone interpreter; this was used in approximately half the interviews.</s><s>Interviews focused on participants' experiences of primary care and transition between services.</s></p><p><s>Interviews were carried out until thematic saturation was achieved.</s><s>Descriptive qualitative methods were used to analyse the data.</s><s>Transcripts were coded using an inductive approach to produce a list of themes with the aid of NVivo qualitative analysis software (Melbourne: QSR International; Version 11).</s><s>Researchers reviewed transcripts collaboratively to discuss differences in coding and interpretation.</s><s>A smaller list of cross-cutting themes was compiled and discussed, and data were recoded into these categories.</s><s>These were presented to key stakeholders for feedback and discussion.</s><s>The key stakeholders were from the same organisations as those of the healthcare provider participants, but they were not necessarily the same individuals who were interviewed.</s></p><p><s>Ethics approval was granted by the UNSW Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee Executive (HC15735).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Relevant descriptive information was collected about the 18 participants, as shown in Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1 and 2</ref>. Each participant was identified using a code: S1-9 for healthcare providers and P1-9 for patients.</s><s>Asylum seeker participants were from Cameroon, Guinea, Malaysia, Russia, Sri Lanka and Turkey.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Process of transition</head><p><s>The ad hoc process of transition from asylum seekerspecific primary care to mainstream primary care was characterised through interviews and discussions with healthcare providers.</s><s>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> outlines the general pathway described by participants.</s><s>Some patients readily accepted the need to transition, but others were strongly opposed, and some continued attending asylum seeker-specific primary care.</s><s>For those willing to transition, a mainstream GP was identified through personal networks or with assistance from ASC staff.</s><s>When staff helped patients to find GPs, they sought an appropriately located doctor who spoke the patient's language and offered bulk-billing.</s><s>Often, staff  Transition of asylum seekers to mainstream primary care had ongoing contact with former patients to supply free medications; assist with booking appointments; and help with casework, employment guidance and food.</s><s>Many patients reported dissatisfaction with their mainstream GP, and some sought out a different GP or returned to asylum seeker-specific primary care.</s><s>Other catalysts for returning to familiar services included loss of Medicare access or SRSS assistance and difficulty accessing mainstream care.</s></p><p><s>The ASC does not have an established process for transferring medical records to mainstream GPs.</s><s>Staff usually waited until GPs made contact to ask for records.</s><s>Most patients interviewed were unaware that transfer of records might be required, or did not know whether it had occurred.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Health system factors</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Medicare instability</head><p><s>Interviewees regularly recounted examples of disrupted access to Medicare because of expiry or policy changes.</s><s>Medicare instability resulted in severe physical and mental health consequences in numerous cases.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>When my Medicare stopped, for a few months I didn't take any medicines. There was damage to my eyes -I am now a little blind in my left eye here. (P8) Somehow he had lost access to healthcare, and he ended up homeless [and] quite suicidal … It was that bureaucracy of not being able to access services that nearly caused him to lose his life. (S4)</head><p><s>These disruptions to access affected the abilities of asylum seekers to maintain independent interactions with the health system.</s><s>The instability caused patients to return to asylum seeker-specific services, creating administrative and resource issues for already strained services.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Complexity of the health system and integration of services</head><p><s>Patients and healthcare providers communicated frustrations about the complexity of the health system and the difficulties encountered by patients learning to navigate it.</s><s>Healthcare providers emphasised the need for changes in the system to better support patients with complex health and psychosocial issues.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>It's not the client's job to fix themselves enough to be able to connect to the healthcare system -it's our job as healthcare professionals to understand what's going on for that client and do what's needed to get that client the right kind of care. (S2)</head><p><s>Many patients received healthcare and support from multiple organisations, and difficulties arose in communication and integration between services.</s></p><p><s>This resulted in patients receiving fragmented care, and fostered a sense of confusion.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I get a sense that he's got a GP … who I think speaks his language, but he can't tell me who that is. And therefore I can't find out what work's been done … or what treatment or testing is planned. (S8)</head><p><s>This affected the transition process significantly.</s><s>Healthcare providers reported a smoother transition when there was an integrated transition with communication between all relevant services.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Asylum seeker-specific primary care services</head><p><s>The ASC provides a comprehensive and adaptable service model for patients, which helps foster a sense of inclusiveness and security.</s><s>This model is quite different from mainstream general practice, in which set appointment times and procedures are the norm.</s><s>Many healthcare providers acknowledged that these differences played a role in the development of overreliance on asylum seeker-specific services, and compromised the opportunity for patients to develop vital health literacy skills required for independent interaction with mainstream services.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>[At the ASC] there's an open-door policy, some structure, but you can go and have lunch and then maybe see the nurse after lunch, you know. You can't go into a GP practice and say I'm just going for a coffee and then I'll be back in half an hour. (S1)</head><p><s>Some interviewees characterised the relationship between the ASC and its clients as one of parent and child.</s><s>Although this demonstrates the strong sense of belonging and support that patients felt at the ASC, it also contributed to reluctance to transition to mainstream primary care.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I really appreciate the ASC. Everybody's really good, as soon as I get here they ask about health, they take us on excursions even, they give us food. Like a mum and dad take care of their child, they do everything for us. (P2)</head><p><s>Transition to mainstream care presented an opportunity for patients to become more independent.</s><s>This produced mixed feelings among many asylum seekers.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>They were glad about getting protection, but upset about having to move on. And they said it was like graduating from primary school to high school, and they had to go out into this kind of bigger space where they didn't know anyone, and had to do it themselves. (S2)</head><p><s>Many patients continued to attend asylum seekerspecific primary care despite having Medicare eligibility and theoretical access to mainstream primary care.</s></p><p><s>Many who did transition required ongoing support to navigate the health system, organise appointments or access free medications.</s><s>This burden of ongoing management affected the capacity of the service to meet the needs of new Medicare-ineligible patients.</s></p><p><s>Healthcare provider interviewees frequently identified the key role they could play in managing the transition process for and with patients.</s><s>This involved two key components: managing communication with the mainstream health provider, and managing the expectations and skill development of the individual or family making the transition.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I think it's up to [the ASC staff] to give a really sensible transition … to liaise with the caseworkers from other agencies, to explain what's going on, to bring the client in as well, where we can, and find the right fit for a GP. (S1)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mainstream primary care services</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Understanding of asylum seekers' health and entitlements</head><p><s>Interviewees frequently identified that mainstream GPs did not have a good understanding of issues affecting asylum seekers, including physical and mental health issues, social circumstances, and access to entitlements such as Medicare.</s></p><p><s>Factors reported to contribute to this lack of understanding included infrequent contact with asylum seekers, and sometimes dismissal of mental illnesses such as post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) as political rather than mental health issues.</s></p><p><s>The lack of understanding frequently manifested as insensitivity to asylum seekers' concerns.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I don't understand him, he doesn't seem to understand what I want … The way he approaches questions, I don't like it. If I have headache and he ask me how long, I say I have headache 10 years, he says it's probably nightmare and prescribes medications. I don't feel at ease. The way he speaks to you is different to the doctor [at the ASC]. (P3)</head><p><s>Additionally, healthcare entitlements were often a source of confusion.</s><s>SRSS providers had some clients who were eligible for primary care services despite not having Medicare access.</s><s>Payments to healthcare providers were made by the SRSS provider, rather than by Medicare.</s><s>The process of billing the SRSS provider and waiting for payment was unfamiliar and time-consuming for healthcare providers, resulting in resistance to taking on asylum seeker patients.</s></p><p><s>Patients and healthcare providers expressed the need to educate GPs about these issues.</s><s>Some information sessions about refugee health issues had been organised by the local Primary Health Network (PHN) and the RHS, but attendance at these was low.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Continuity of care</head><p><s>Patients commonly highlighted the difficulty of finding a GP they felt they could consult with on an ongoing basis.</s><s>Many attended high-throughput, bulk-billing practices for isolated issues in an episodic fashion, but did not develop sustained doctor-patient relationships.</s><s>Patients frequently expressed the importance of having their own personal GP, but were unsure how to find one.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>It's not our doctor, it's only, you have problem, you visit a doctor. He didn't ask about previous visits, just some general questions. (P6)</head><p><s>This often meant that only acute health issues were addressed, while preventive care was neglected.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Individual factors</head><p><s>Interviewees reported considerable variability in how patients coped with the transition process.</s><s>Those who transitioned to mainstream care more easily often had better English language proficiency, good general literacy skills, and greater independence and ability to self-advocate.</s><s>Patients who experienced more difficulty tended to rely more heavily on asylum seeker-specific services, and often had more severe mental illness affecting their memory, concentration and organisational skills.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Understanding the health system</head><p><s>Almost all interviewees identified difficulty understanding the Australian health system as a major issue.</s><s>Concepts such as the gatekeeper role of the GP, specialist referral processes and obtaining prescriptions were often unfamiliar to asylum seekers, particularly when newly arrived.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I feel ... like a kid, not knowing very simple thing, it takes you time to find maybe in internet, and maybe you get to the wrong conclusion. I've never even thought about all of this. (P6)</head><p><s>Staff of asylum seeker-specific primary care services provided explanations to patients about relevant aspects of the health system as required, but there was no systematic process for conveying this information to all patients.</s><s>Numerous interviewees suggested methods to improve patients' understanding, such as an information booklet or workshops.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mental health</head><p><s>The substantial levels of mental illness experienced by asylum seekers affected their ability to cope with the logistical aspects of the transition.</s><s>High instances of PTSD affected concentration, memory and organisational abilities.</s><s>Transition of asylum seekers to mainstream primary care 6</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>When someone's really unwell, it affects their engagement, their capacity to actually connect with other people. It affects their memory and …</head><p><s>In addition to logistical barriers, mental illness affected patients' ability to establish trust in unfamiliar health professionals.</s><s>As a result, patients often returned to asylum seeker-specific services.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Social and financial stability</head><p><s>For many asylum seekers, issues such as accommodation and finances were more immediate than health issues, and hence took precedence over managing their transition into mainstream primary care.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>[I am] solving problems for today, you know: work, job, accommodation. My son fell ill, that's a problem, so we go to see doctor. (P6)</head><p><s>Social and financial circumstances affected living conditions, and subsequently affected patients' physical and mental health, and their ability to interact with health services.</s></p><p><s>Numerous patients became eligible for Medicare but did not receive work rights.</s><s>Despite transitioning to mainstream care, they continued to rely on the ASC for access to free medications (not incurring the copayments required under Australia's Pharmaceutical Benefits Scheme).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ASC always helps with medications, that's why I'm so grateful. I don't have any money to buy, but ASC buys, I don't have to worry. (P2)</head><p><s>This ongoing financial dependence on the ASC limited the ability of individuals to manage their own healthcare.</s><s>It also placed strain on the finite financial resources and staff capacity at the ASC.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>The reported experiences of asylum seekers and their healthcare providers demonstrate that transition to mainstream care is often difficult and confronting.</s><s>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref> outlines the interdependent factors affecting the success and ease of the transition.</s></p><p><s>Asylum seekers faced significant challenges transitioning into mainstream primary care because of their limited understanding of the health system and concurrent psychosocial issues.</s><s>Staff of asylum seekerspecific health services played a central role in managing the transition and supporting mainstream providers, but this was not clearly defined and occurred on an ad hoc basis.</s><s>Mainstream GPs often had poor understanding of asylum seekers' health and psychosocial issues.</s><s>This occurred in the context of a complex health system, Medicare instability for many patients and a lack of integration between services.</s><s>]<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref> Patients' reluctance to transition has previously been attributed to a lack of clarity and coordination in the process, and a lack of available GPs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">14</ref> This study supports the notion that transition processes may be ill-defined and confusing for both patients and staff.</s><s>It also contributes a deeper exploration of the reasons for reluctance from the individual's perspective.</s><s>Social and financial instability around the time of transition adversely affected asylum seekers' abilities to cope with logistical aspects of the transition, thus increasing the likelihood of ongoing reliance on asylum seeker-specific primary care.</s><s>This supports previous research that suggests that accommodation insecurity <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref> , employment issues <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref> , social isolation <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19</ref> and fear of prosecution <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">20</ref> contribute to poor health by affecting continuity of care and ability to seek care. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">16</ref></s><s>he comprehensive and welcoming nature of asylum seeker-specific services promotes acceptance, but also facilitates dependence in some patients.</s><s>To reduce reliance on asylum seeker-specific services, patients need to be prepared to integrate into the mainstream health system well before the transition. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">7</ref></s><s>This may conflict with providing for a patient's immediate needs, and put a significant burden on asylum seeker-specific health services.</s><s>However, not preparing patients for the transition creates an even greater burden, because patients end up continually reliant on resource-limited services.</s></p><p><s>The repeated gain and loss of Medicare benefits affected patients medically and psychosocially, reducing their ability to navigate the health system and cope with the transition process.</s><s>Ensuring continuity of Medicare access would reduce physical and psychological harm to asylum seekers, and relieve some of the burden on asylum seeker-specific health services.</s></p><p><s>2]<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref> Asylum seeker-specific services and PHNs must work synergistically to educate mainstream GPs about asylum seeker health issues and support GPs who have asylum seeker patients.</s></p><p><s>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref> outlines a potential framework for the transition process, developed in consultation with ASC staff.</s></p><p><s>This study was potentially limited by recruitment through a single centre and the location of the interviews.</s><s>Despite the small sample size, thematic saturation was reached.</s><s>Significantly, this study investigates the views of asylum seekers themselves about the transition process.</s><s>Future research could further explore the prevalence of these views among the asylum seeker population, and the perspectives of mainstream GPs receiving asylum seeker patients into their practices.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>Transition from asylum seeker-specific to mainstream primary care is a complex process.</s><s>Significant problems occur because of the nature of the relationship between patients and asylum seeker-specific services, deficiencies in the process of transition, psychosocial pressures, and lack of accommodation of asylum seekers by some mainstream providers.</s><s>Asylum seeker-specific services need to increase understanding of the health system and health literacy among asylum seekers.</s><s>Mainstream primary care providers need to be supported to increase their understanding of, and sensitivity to, asylum seeker health and psychosocial issues.</s><s>This could be achieved through partnerships between asylum seeker-specific health services and PHNs.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Current transition pathway</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>[what] they can take in, it affects how much they can tolerate.</s><s>(S2) Public Health Research &amp; Practice March 2018; Vol.</s><s>28(1):e2811805 • https://doi.org/10.17061/phrp2811805</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Thematic map</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. Potential pathway for transition</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Characteristics of healthcare provider interview participants</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Number of participants</cell></row><row><cell>Characteristic</cell><cell>(n = 9)</cell></row><row><cell>Organisation Asylum seeker-specific health</cell><cell>6 (S1, S2, S3, S4, S5, S6)</cell></row><row><cell>service</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Other health service</cell><cell>3 (S7, S8, S9)</cell></row><row><cell>Age (years) 25-44</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>45-64</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>Sex</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>Time working in asylum seeker</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>sector (years) &lt;1</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>1-5</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>≥5</cell><cell>2</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Characteristics of asylum seeker interview participants</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Characteristic</cell><cell>Number of participants (n = 9)</cell></row><row><cell>Medicare status Eligible, recently transitioned</cell><cell>5 (P1, P2, P3, P4, P5)</cell></row><row><cell>to mainstream primary care</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Eligible, still attending ASC;</cell><cell>2 (P6, P7)</cell></row><row><cell>child recently transitioned to</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>mainstream primary care</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>No longer eligible, receiving primary care at ASC</cell><cell>2 (P8, P9)</cell></row><row><cell>Age (years) 25-44</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>45-64</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Sex Male</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>Time in Australia (years) &lt;1</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>1-5</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>≥5</cell><cell>2</cell></row></table><note><p><s>ASC = Asylum Seekers Centre</s></p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Competing interests</head><p><s>MH is a volunteer medical officer at the ASC, and a board member of the Central and Eastern Sydney PHN.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author contributions</head><p><s>GF was involved in conducting the literature review, planning and designing the study, collecting and analysing the data, and writing the paper.</s><s>MS was involved in planning and designing the study, interpreting the findings, and reviewing and editing the paper.</s><s>MH was involved in planning and designing the study, supervising the collection and analysis of the data, and reviewing and editing the paper.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees. Global trends: forced displacement in 2016</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>UNHCR</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Geneva</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The health needs of asylum seekers living in the community</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Telfer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med J Aust</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">175</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11-12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="589" to="592" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Asylum seeker health and wellbeing scoping study. Melbourne: St. Vincent&apos;s Health Australia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hadgkiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lethborg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Al-Mousa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Marck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>cited</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Available from: svha.org.au/wps/wcm/ connect/cb7b96fc-6653-42ea-9683-749a184d3aed/ Asylum_Seeker_Health_and_Wellbeing_Scoping_ Study.pdf?</title>
		<imprint>
			<date>Apr 1. MOD=AJPERES&amp;amp%3bCONVERT_ TO=url&amp;amp%3bCACHEID=cb7b96fc-6653-42ea-9683-749a184d3aed</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Asylum Seekers Centre annual report</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Asylum Seekers Centre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="asylumseekerscentre.org.au/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/ASC-Annual-Report-2014-15.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014-2015. 2015. 2018 Jan 10</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Sydney: ASC</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Sydney: SWSLHD</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-06-16">2017 June 16</date>
			<pubPlace>NSW Refugee Health Service</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>South Western Sydney Local Health District</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A narrative synthesis of the impact of primary health care delivery models for refugees in resettlement countries on access, quality and coordination</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Joshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Russell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Pottie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alston</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Equity Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">88</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How primary care services can incorporate refugee health care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Le</forename><surname>Feuvre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Confl Surviv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sydney: SSI. What is the Status Resolution Support Service?</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Settlement Services International</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>cited</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">I don&apos;t think general practice should be the front line: experiences of general practitioners working with refugees in South Australia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ziersch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Burgess</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aust N Z J Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A multidisciplinary primary healthcare clinic for newly arrived humanitarian entrants in regional NSW: model of service delivery and summary of preliminary findings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Gould</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Viney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Greenwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kramer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Corben</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aust N Z J Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="326" to="329" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patient experienced continuity of care in the psychiatric healthcare system -a study including immigrants, refugees and ethnic Danes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Johansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kastrup</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Krasnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Norredam</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Environ Res Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9739" to="9759" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Understanding vulnerability in primary health care: overcoming barriers to consumer transitions through the primary health system. Canberra: Australian Primary Health Care Research Institute</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Marsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hanley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Macmillan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Morgain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Silburn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013. 2018 Jan 10</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Australian National University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>Available from: files.aphcri.anu.edu.au/reports/Lewis.Final. Report.25.pdf</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Demographics and utilisation of health services by paediatric refugees from East Africa: implications for service planning and provision</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cooke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Murray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Carapetis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rice</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mulholland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Skull</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aust Health Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="40" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Integrated primary care improves access to healthcare for newly arrived refugees in Canada</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcmurray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Breward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Breward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Alder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Arya</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Immigr Minor Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="576" to="585" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Locations of care: meeting the mental health and social care needs of refugees in Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Watters</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ingleby</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Law Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="549" to="570" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experiences of refugees and asylum seekers in general practice: a qualitative study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Bhatia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wallace</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Fam Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">48</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Access to primary health care services by community-based asylum seekers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Spike</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med J Aust</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">195</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="188" to="191" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring the &apos;fit&apos; between people and providers: refugee health needs and health care services in Mt Roskill</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lawrence</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kearns</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Soc Care Community</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="451" to="461" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Equitable health-care access: the experiences of refugee and refugee claimant mothers with an ill preschooler</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Wahoush</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Can J Nurs Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="206" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mental health problems of undocumented migrants (UMs) in The Netherlands: a qualitative exploration of help-seeking behaviour and experiences with primary care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Teunissen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sherally</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Van Den Muijsenbergh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dowrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Van Weel-Baumgarten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Van Weel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e005738</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Views of general practitioners towards refugees and asylum seekers: an interview study. Divers Equal Health Care</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Begg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Gill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="305" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GP and registrar involvement in refugee health -a needs assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Duncan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Harding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gilmour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Seal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aust Fam Physician</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="405" to="408" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How do general practitioners experience providing care to refugees with mental health problems? A qualitative study from Denmark</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Jensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Norredam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Priebe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Krasnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Fam Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">17</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
