<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Clinical Study Copeptin: Limited Usefulness in Early Stroke Differentiation?</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Johannes</forename><surname>Von Recum</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Emergency Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Julia</forename><surname>Searle</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Emergency Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anna</forename><surname>Slagman</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Emergency Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jörn</forename><forename type="middle">Ole</forename><surname>Vollert</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">B.R.A.H.M.S GmbH</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Thermo Scientific Clinical Diagnostics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>16761</postCode>
									<settlement>Hennigsdorf</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Matthias</forename><surname>Endres</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Stroke Research Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">German Center for Neurodegenerative Diseases (DZNE)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="laboratory">German Centre for Cardiovascular Research (DZHK)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Möckel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division of Emergency Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Ebinger</surname></persName>
							<email>martin.ebinger@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neurology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Stroke Research Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Clinical Study Copeptin: Limited Usefulness in Early Stroke Differentiation?</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">73EBA91E0EA361828182CFF61E06C08A</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1155/2015/768401</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 18 March 2015; Revised 27 May 2015; Accepted 28 May 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:45+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Background.</s><s>Stroke can be a challenging diagnosis in an emergency-setting.</s><s>We sought to determine whether copeptin may be a useful biomarker to differentiate between ischemic stroke (IS), transient ischemic attack (TIA), and stroke-mimics.</s><s>Methods.</s><s>In patients with suspected stroke arriving within 4.5 hours of symptom-onset, copeptin-levels were measured in initial blood-samples.</s><s>The final diagnosis was adjudicated by vascular neurologists blinded to copeptin-values.</s><s>Results.</s><s>Of all 36 patients with available copeptin-values (median age 71 years, IQR: 54-76; 44% female), 20 patients (56%) were diagnosed with IS, no patient was diagnosed with hemorrhagic stroke, nine patients (25%) were diagnosed with TIA, and seven patients (19%) were stroke-mimics.</s><s>Copeptinlevels (in pmol/L) tended to be higher in patients with )] compared to ].</s><s>In stroke-mimics the range of values was extremely broad [33.3 (7.57-255.7)].</s><s>The diagnostic accuracy of copeptin for IS was 63% with a sensitivity of 80% and a positive predictive value of 64%.</s><s>Conclusion.</s><s>In this cohort of patients copeptin-levels within 4.5 hours of symptom onset were higher in patients with IS compared to TIA but the broad range of values in stroke-mimics limits diagnostic accuracy.</s><s>This trial is registered with UTN: U1111-1119-7602.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p><s>Thrombolysis and mechanical thrombectomy are currently the only proven effective treatments for patients in the early stage of acute ischemic stroke (IS) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>However, effects of both treatments are time-dependent.</s><s>Therefore, fast diagnosis of IS is required.</s><s>The clinical diagnosis of stroke in an emergency-setting can be challenging and prior to treatment imaging of the brain is mandatory.</s><s>In most emergency departments (ED), only computed tomography (CT) is available to exclude hemorrhagic stroke.</s><s>In these cases, the time-critical decision to start treatment is mainly based on the clinical impression of an acute stroke in the absence of intracerebral bleeds.</s><s>Biomarkers may be helpful to differentiate between IS, TIA, and strokemimics.</s></p><p><s>One of the biomarkers that have recently gained attention is copeptin <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>.</s><s>Copeptin is a 39-amino-acid peptide and correlates with the secretion of Vasopressin (AVP).</s><s>Not an organ-specific marker, copeptin increases early after acute hemodynamic stress <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>.</s><s>Copeptin-levels were shown to be elevated in patients with sepsis <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, acute respiratory diseases <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, and acute myocardial infarction <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In this exploratory pilot study, we analyzed acute copeptin-levels in patients who were admitted to the ED with suspected stroke.</s><s>We sought to evaluate for the first time whether copeptin-levels differ between IS, TIA, and strokemimics.</s><s><ref type="formula">12</ref>) 19 ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>) 22 ( <ref type="formula">8</ref>) 11 ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) 80 ( <ref type="formula">16</ref>) 35 ( <ref type="formula">7</ref>) 20 ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) 15 ( <ref type="formula">3</ref>) 20 ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) 86 ( <ref type="formula">6</ref>) 29 ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) 14 ( <ref type="formula">1</ref>) 43 ( <ref type="formula">3</ref>) 0 67 ( <ref type="formula">6</ref>) 33 ( <ref type="formula">3</ref>) 22 ( <ref type="formula">2</ref>) 22 (2) 0 Mortality within 1 year % () (unknown = 3) 11 ( <ref type="formula">4</ref>) 19 (4) 0 0</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Methods</head><p><s>The local ethics committee approved this study.</s><s>Patients 18 years or older arriving within 4.5 hours of symptomonset with suspected stroke as the cause of symptoms were eligible if code-stroke was activated.</s><s>The code-stroke alarms the stroke unit, the CT staff, and the neurologist on duty in order to facilitate emergency treatment in stroke patients without contraindications.</s><s>Routine blood-draw was performed at admission.</s><s>Eligible patients were asked for written informed consent to participate in this study.</s><s>Serumsamples from routine blood draw were then frozen at −80 ∘ C within 12 hours.</s><s>Copeptin was measured in a single batch measurement using the B.R.A.H.M.S ultrasensitive (us) Copeptin KRYPTOR-assay after recruitment had finished.</s><s>The assay time given by the manufacturer is 19 minutes.</s><s>SPSS Statistics Version 20 was used for analysis.</s><s>Patients' discharge-summaries were reviewed by a neurologist blinded to copeptin-levels to adjudicate the diagnoses IS, strokemimics, and TIA.</s><s>The diagnosis of TIA followed the criteria of the World Health Organization defining TIA as rapidly developing clinical signs of focal or global disturbance of cerebral function, resolving within 24 hours in the absence of a nonvascular cause <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s><s>In case of visible lesions on brain imaging with resolving symptoms within 24 hours the term transient symptoms with infarction (TSI) was used <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head><p><s>Between March and August, 2011, we enrolled 45 adult patients with an activated code-stroke in the ED.</s><s>Of 36 patients (median age 71 years, IQR 54-76; 44% female) admission blood-samples were available for the current analysis.</s><s>Of these, 20 patients (56%) were discharged with the final diagnosis of IS, 9 (25%) with TIA and 7 (19%) with stroke-mimics; no patient was diagnosed with hemorrhagic stroke or TSI.</s><s>The final diagnoses in patients with strokemimics were epilepsy ( = 3), vestibular neuropathy ( = 1), migraine ( = 1), withdrawal delirium ( = 1), and loss of consciousness (not suggestive of TIA, MRI without evidence of stroke,  = 1).</s><s>The median NIHSS-score of all patients was 4 (IQR 2-9).</s><s>In patients with IS, the median NIHSSscore (7; IQR 3-11) was higher than in patients with strokemimics (6, IQR 1-9) or TIA (2, IQR 1-3).</s><s>Mortality within one year was 11%.</s><s>All patients who died ( = 4) were diagnosed with IS (copeptin-levels in pmol/L: 7.8/11.2/14.4/52.4,</s><s>median of all survivors [ = 29]: 13.9).</s><s>No patient died during the initial hospital stay.</s><s>For patients' characteristics, see Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s><s>Median copeptin-level of all study patients on admission was 13.8 pmol/L (IQR 9.1-48.5).</s><s>Median levels in patients with IS [19.1 pmol/L (IQR 11.2-48.5)]</s><s>and in patients with stroke-mimics [33.31 pmol/L (IQR 7.57-255.7)]</s><s>were higher than copeptin-levels in patients with TIA [9.4 pmol/L (IQR 5.4-13.8)]</s><s>( = 0.081;  = 0.153, resp., Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>There was no significant correlation between copeptin values and NIHSS or age (NIHSS: Pearson  = 0.709, Spearman rho  = 0.076, age: Pearson  = 0.576, Spearman rho  = 0.907, resp.).</s><s>Patients with stroke-mimics showed the largest range of copeptin-levels.</s><s>Copeptin as a diagnostic marker at a predefined cut-off of 10 pmol/L yielded a sensitivity of 80% and a specificity of 44%.</s><s>Using a cut-off of 14 pmol/L derived from previous cardiovascular studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref> sensitivity dropped to 55% and specificity increased to 69% (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p><s>This is the first analysis of very early copeptin-levels in patients with suspected stroke in an attempt to differentiate patients with IS from TIA and stroke-mimics.</s><s>Previous stroke studies focused primarily on the prognostic value of copeptin <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17]</ref>.</s><s>All studies showed a correlation of copeptin and NIHSS score, lesion size, or ICH volume.</s></p><p><s>Patients with TIA showed the lowest copeptin-levels.</s><s>Patients with stroke-mimics other than TIA had the highest copeptin-levels and displayed a wide range of values.</s><s>Overall, this led to a low specificity for copeptin as a discriminatory marker for stroke at the cut-off level of 14 pmol/L.</s><s>This cut-off level was derived from previous cardiovascular studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref> and coincides with the upper IQR boundary for patients with TIA in our cohort.</s><s>The median copeptin-levels in a recently published stroke cohort ( = 783) within 12 hours from symptom-onset were 14.2 pmol/L (IQR 5.9-46.5).</s><s>Although this copeptin value is close to the median copeptin value in our study, their IQR also shows a wide range.</s><s>Stroke patients in this cohort with favorable outcome had a median copeptin-level below 10 pmol/L (9.6, IQR 4.7-25.8)</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref>.</s><s>A wide range of copeptin values in neurologic disorders has been observed before and is not clear yet.</s><s>It may be influenced by different factors like individual levels of stress or the broad variety of neurologic disorders and needs to be further investigated.</s><s>There is no specific clinical factor in our cohort causing the increase of the copeptin values in the mimic group.</s><s>Sample calculations based on our findings revealed that more than 250 patients are required to detect significant differences between our three groups (power 80%).</s><s>Given this relatively high number, the diagnostic usefulness of such a marker cannot be assessed appropriately with the data of this study and needs to be evaluated in further studies with more specific endpoints regarding lesion size and overall severity.</s><s>The relatively short measurement time of 19 minutes qualifies copeptin as an excellent marker for the acute setting, if logistics at the institution allow for a short turnaround time.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p><s>In this cohort of patients with initially suspected stroke, copeptin-levels within 4.5 hours of symptom-onset were higher in patients with IS compared to TIA but the broad range of values in stroke-mimics limits diagnostic accuracy.</s><s>Copeptin may aid prediction of stroke outcome but its usefulness in the differentiation between cerebral ischemia and stroke-mimics could not be proven positive in this small study.</s><s>Further studies with larger sample sizes should be undertaken to elucidate whether the usefulness of copeptin in this setting adds diagnostic value to ease early decisions in the acute treatment of stroke.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1: Copeptin-levels of patients with ischemic stroke, strokemimics, and TIA.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Patients' characteristics.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Variables</cell><cell>All study patients (𝑁 = 36)</cell><cell>Patients with stroke (𝑁 = 20)</cell><cell>Patients with mimics (𝑁 = 7)</cell><cell>Patients with TIA (𝑁 = 9)</cell></row><row><cell>Female %</cell><cell>44</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>42.9</cell><cell>22</cell></row><row><cell>Age median (IQR)</cell><cell>71 (54/76)</cell><cell>68 (51/76)</cell><cell>59 (53/83)</cell><cell>71 (57/82)</cell></row><row><cell>Medical history:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Previous stroke in % (𝑁) (unknown = 1)</cell><cell>33 (12)</cell><cell>40 (8)</cell><cell>28 (2)</cell><cell>22 (2)</cell></row><row><cell>Previous TIA in % (𝑁)</cell><cell>6 (2)</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>14 (1)</cell><cell>11 (1)</cell></row><row><cell>Copeptin in pmol/L Median (25%/75%)</cell><cell>13.8 (9.1/48.5)</cell><cell>19.1 (11.2/48.5)</cell><cell>33.31 (7.57/255.7)</cell><cell>9.4 (5.4/13.8)</cell></row><row><cell>tPA administered in % (𝑁)</cell><cell>42 (15)</cell><cell>70 (14)</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>11 (1)</cell></row><row><cell>Stroke severity, median NIHSS score (25%/75%)</cell><cell>4 (2/9)</cell><cell>7 (3/11)</cell><cell>6 (1/9)</cell><cell>2 (1/3)</cell></row><row><cell>Length of inpatient stay in days Median (25%/75%)</cell><cell>8 (4/10)</cell><cell>9 (4/12)</cell><cell>6 (5/8)</cell><cell>6 (4/8)</cell></row><row><cell>TOAST score in % (𝑁)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Large artery atherosclerosis</cell><cell>36.1 (13)</cell><cell>55 (11)</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>22.2 (2)</cell></row><row><cell>Cardioembolism</cell><cell>16.7 (6)</cell><cell>15 (3)</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>33.3 (3)</cell></row><row><cell>Small vessel occlusion</cell><cell>16.7 (6)</cell><cell>15 (3)</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>22.2 (2)</cell></row><row><cell>Other determined aetiology</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Undetermined aetiology</cell><cell>2.8 (1)</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Unknown</cell><cell>27.8 (10)</cell><cell>15 (3)</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>22.2 (2)</cell></row><row><cell>Risk factors in % (𝑁)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Hypertension</cell><cell>83 (30)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Diabetes mellitus</cell><cell>33 (</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Hypercholesterolemia</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Neurologic disorders</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Coronary heart disease</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Ischemic stroke diagnostic performance of Copeptin at different cut-offs.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Patients with confirmed ischemic stroke</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Number of patients above cut-off (total)</cell><cell>Sensitivity</cell><cell>Specificity</cell><cell>PPV</cell><cell>NPV</cell><cell>Accuracy</cell></row><row><cell>Copeptin 10 pmol/L</cell><cell>16 (20)</cell><cell>80%</cell><cell>44%</cell><cell>64%</cell><cell>63%</cell><cell>63%</cell></row><row><cell>Copeptin 14 pmol/L</cell><cell>11 (20)</cell><cell>55%</cell><cell>69%</cell><cell>69%</cell><cell>55%</cell><cell>61%</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p><s>The authors would like to thank the study team members and staff of the emergency department and the neurology department for their effort to undertake this study in an acute setting.</s><s>Special thanks go to Fabian Holert carrying out all measurements and being the useful link between the ED and the laboratory.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disclosure</head><p><s>The authors are fully responsible for the writing of this paper.</s><s>Dr. Vollert is a medical director working for Brahms GmbH, Thermo Fisher Scientific in Hennigsdorf, Germany.</s><s>All other authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</s><s>The study was funded by Abbott Diagnostics.</s><s>Furthermore, the research group of Martin Möckel receives grants from Radiometer and Siemens.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of Interests</head><p><s>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</s></p><p><s>Submit your manuscripts at http://www.hindawi.com</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stem Cells International</head><p><s>Hindawi</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of treatment delay, age, and stroke severity on the effects of intravenous thrombolysis with alteplase for acute ischaemic stroke: a metaanalysis of individual patient data from randomised trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Emberson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Lees</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lyden</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">384</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9958</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1929" to="1935" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A randomized trial of intraarterial treatment for acute ischemic stroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Berkhemer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S S</forename><surname>Fransen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Beumer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The New England Journal of Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">372</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Randomized assessment of rapid endovascular treatment of ischemic stroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goyal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Demchuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Menon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The New England Journal of Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">372</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1019" to="1030" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Endovascular therapy for ischemic stroke with perfusion-imaging selection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kleinig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The New England Journal of Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">372</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1009" to="1018" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Copeptin: a novel, independent prognostic marker in patients with ischemic stroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Katan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fluri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Morgenthaler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Neurology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="799" to="808" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Copeptin and risk stratification in patients with ischemic stroke and transient ischemic attack: the CoRisk Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>De Marchis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Katan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Weck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="214" to="218" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antidiuretic hormone: normal and disordered function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Endocrinology and Metabolism Clinics of North America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="671" to="694" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Management of vasodilatory shock: defining the role of arginine vasopressin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Dünser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Wenzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mayr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hasibeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Drugs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="256" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Copeptin, a stable peptide derived from the vasopressin precursor, is elevated in serum of sepsis patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Struck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Morgenthaler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bergmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Peptides</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2500" to="2504" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Circulating levels of copeptin, a novel biomarker, in lower respiratory tract infections</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Morgenthaler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stolz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European Journal of Clinical Investigation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="152" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Copeptin adds to high-sensitivity troponin T in rapid rule out of acute myocardial infarction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mockel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical Chemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">58</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="309" to="311" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The World Health Organization MONICA project (monitoring trends and determinants in cardiovascular disease): a major international collaboration. WHO MONICA Project Principal Investigators</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Clinical Epidemiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transient ischemic attack with infarction: a unique syndrome?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Koroshetz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Benner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Neurology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="679" to="686" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Copeptin improves early diagnosis of acute myocardial infarction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Keller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tzikas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Zeller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American College of Cardiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2096" to="2106" />
			<date type="published" when="2096">2096</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incremental value of copeptin for rapid rule out of acute myocardial infarction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Reichlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hochholzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Stelzig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the American College of Cardiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="60" to="68" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prognostic value of copeptin: one-year outcome in patients with acute stroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Urwyler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schuetz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fluri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1564" to="1567" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Copeptin is associated with mortality and outcome in patients with acute intracerebral hemorrhage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zweifel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Katan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schuetz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Neurology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">34</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Copeptin adds prognostic information after ischemic stroke: results from the CoRisk study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>De Marchis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Katan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Weck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1278" to="1286" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
