<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Impact of social deprivation, demographics and centre on HbA1c outcomes with continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Angela</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Paisley</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Impact of Social Deprivation</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Demographics and Centre on HbA1c</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Salford Royal NHS Foundation Trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Salford</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><surname>Beynon</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital of South Manchester</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Catherine</forename><surname>Fullwood</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Research and Innovation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Manchester University NHS foundation Trust</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Manchester Academic Health Science Centre</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Centre for Biostatistics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Manchester</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><surname>Hindle</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">The School of Medical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Manchester</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tayiba</forename><surname>Alam</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">The School of Medical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Manchester</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><surname>Urwin</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Manchester Diabetes Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Manchester Royal Infirmary</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alyson</forename><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Manchester Diabetes Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Manchester Royal Infirmary</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Juliet</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Manchester Diabetes Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Manchester Royal Infirmary</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hood</forename><surname>Thabit</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Manchester Diabetes Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Manchester Royal Infirmary</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Diabetes, Endocrinology and Gastroenterology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Manchester</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Rutter</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Manchester Diabetes Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Manchester Royal Infirmary</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Diabetes, Endocrinology and Gastroenterology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Manchester</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Lalantha</forename><surname>Leelarathna</surname></persName>
							<email>lalantha.leelarathna@mft.nhs.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Manchester Diabetes Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Manchester Royal Infirmary</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Manchester University NHS Foundation Trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Diabetes, Endocrinology and Gastroenterology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Manchester</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Minimed</forename><surname>Sanofi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Animas</forename><surname>Medtronic</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Novo</forename><surname>Nordisk</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Manchester Research</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="institution">Manchester Academic Health Science Centre</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Impact of social deprivation, demographics and centre on HbA1c outcomes with continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">CDF08BAA6BC91933A7D69E79978DF7FE</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1111/dme.13833</idno>
					<note type="submission">Accepted author manuscript Link to publication record in Manchester Research Explorer received lecture fees from MSD and grant support from Novo Nordisk, MSD and GSK. AP, JB,</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:31+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Diabetic medicine: a journal of the British Diabetic Association LL reports having received speaker honoraria from Minimed Medtronic</term>
					<term>Animas</term>
					<term>Roche</term>
					<term>Sanofi</term>
					<term>Insulet and Novo Nordisk</term>
					<term>serving on advisory panel for Abbott Diabetes Care</term>
					<term>Roche</term>
					<term>type 1 diabetes</term>
					<term>continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion</term>
					<term>insulin pump therapy</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Novelty Statement</head><p><s>• Continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion (CSII) is often considered the 'gold standard' method of insulin replacement therapy for individual with Type 1 diabetes • This is the first UK study to specifically report on the interaction of social deprivation, demographics and centre on pre-and post CSII HbA1c levels.</s><s>• Those with higher social deprivation and women had higher baseline HbA1c levels.</s></p><p><s>However, the benefits of CSII therapy were not found to be associated with social deprivation or demographics, but only with pre-CSII HbA1c and centre.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Insulin pump therapy, also known as continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion (CSII), is considered the 'gold standard' of insulin replacement therapy for people living with Type 1 diabetes (T1DM) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(1)</ref>.</s><s>Use of CSII has been shown to improve overall glycaemic control, as measured by HbA1c, and reduce the burden of hypoglycaemia <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(2)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(3)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(4)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>There is considerable variation in access to CSII in the United Kingdom (5).</s><s>According to the National Insulin Pump audit of 2016/2017, the proportion of those with T1DM treated with CSII varies from less than 5% to more than 50% in participating centres.</s><s>Notably, there is considerable variation in HbA1c levels achieved between individual centres, including the proportion of those with HbA1c below 7.5% (59 mmol/mol) (from 17% to 69%).</s><s>Overall, approximately 15% of people living with type 1 diabetes in England are treated with CSII, but the proportions are lower in areas with higher deprivation (5).</s></p><p><s>Greater Manchester has a population of 2.8 million, with multi-ethnic and socially diverse groups.</s><s>It is the first region in the UK to have a fully devolved health and social care budget, providing new opportunities to better serve the needs of the people living and working in the area <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(6)</ref>.</s><s>As recent national diabetes audits have shown variation of treatment target achieved, it is thus imperative to understand potential factors such as demographics and level of deprivation which may influence diabetes care and outcomes.</s><s>Our objective was to compare and evaluate factors associated with changes in HbA1c levels within a year of starting CSII between the three hospitals in the region, accounting for demographics and deprivation measured with the postcode derived English Index of Multiple Deprivation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research Design and Methods</head><p><s>Setting: We conducted this study at three Greater Manchester hospitals -University Hospital of South Manchester (UHSM), Salford Royal Foundation Hospital (SRFT) and Manchester Diabetes Centre, Manchester Royal Infirmary (MRI).</s></p><p><s>Design: Retrospective observational cohort study.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Inclusion criteria:</head><p><s>We included individuals initiated on CSII therapy between the years 2000 and 2015 who had paired HbA1c data.</s></p><p><s>Exclusion criteria: We excluded individuals whose CSII start date was unknown or those whose relevant pre/post-CSII data were unavailable.</s></p><p><s>Indication for CSII: In line with current national guidance, indications for CSII included poor glycaemic control, problems with hypoglycaemia, or glycaemic variability/erratic control.</s></p><p><s>Data collection: Demographic variables and HbA1c data were obtained from electronic medical records at individual centres.</s><s>HbA1c data were collected from 12 months before and up to 12 months after initiation of CSII.</s><s>The mean annual HbA1c (pre and post CSII) were used for all analysis.</s><s>Typically, one to three HbA1c tests were available per patient before and after pump start.</s><s>We obtained the English Index of Multiple Deprivation 2015 for each participant's postcode from the Ministry of Housing, Communities and Local Government(7).</s><s>The English Index of Multiple Deprivation is the official measure of relative deprivation for small areas in England and ranks these areas from 1 (most deprived area) to 32,844 (least deprived area).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Pre and post HbA1c data were available for 693 individuals (78%).</s><s>Demographics and HBA1c data for the whole cohort and individual centres are shown in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</s><s>Significant differences in gender and deprivation index were noted between the three centres.</s><s>Although the spread of deprivation was wide across all three centres, median deprivation index was lowest (highest deprivation) in MRI.</s><s>Overall, HbA1c improved from median 69 (IQR 61-80) to 64 (55-73) mmol/mol, (8.5% to 8.0%) within 1 year of CSII.</s><s>The percentage of individuals with HbA1c level ≥ 69 mmol/mol (8.5%) reduced from 51.7% pre-CSII to 34.5% post-CSII.</s><s>Patients with poorer glycaemic control at baseline showed larger HbA1c improvements compared to those with lower HbA1c levels (Supplemental Fig <ref type="figure">1)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In a multivariable regression model combining deprivation index, age, duration of diabetes and gender, higher pre-CSII HbA1c levels were associated with higher levels of deprivation (p=0.011) and being female (p=0.001).</s><s>However none of the demographic variables remained significant for post-CSII HbA1c or HbA1c change, when pre-pump HbA1c levels were adjusted for.</s></p><p><s>In the unadjusted analysis, significant differences were found between centres in pre and post HbA1c levels (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</s><s>However the percentages of individuals achieving greater than 5 mmol/mol (0.5%) reduction in HbA1c were similar across centres (UHSM: 67.8% vs. SRFT: 64.3 vs. MRI: 63.7%, p=0.783).</s></p><p><s>Centres UHSM &amp; SRFT were associated with lower pre-CSII HbA1c levels than MRI, even after adjusting for demographics and Index of Multiple Deprivation (p=0.015 and 0.012 respectively).</s><s>Similarly, UHSM &amp; SRFT demonstrated significantly lower post-CSII HbA1c levels (p=0.042 and 0.004 respectively) and greater change in HbA1c levels than MRI (median change -7.0 [-0.6%] vs. -6.0</s><s>[-0.55%] vs. -4.5 [-0.45%] respectively, p=0.005), even after adjusting for demographics, Index of Multiple Deprivation and pre-CSII HbA1c levels.</s></p><p><s>Table <ref type="table">2</ref> quantifies the covariate effects along with the adjusted overall HbA1c changes from baseline.</s><s>Change in HbA1c levels post-CSII was significantly associated with baseline HbA1c and centre.</s><s>The model suggests each one mmol/mol higher baseline HbA1c level is associated with a 0.45 mmol/mol greater lowering in post-CSII HbA1c level.</s><s>This translates to a HbA1c lowering of 29 mmol/mol (4.8%) for a woman from MRI with a pre-CSII HbA1c of 120 mmol/mol (13.1%) when all other covariates are fixed at their sample median.</s></p><p><s>Out of the whole cohort 141 (20%) had undertaken the Dose Adjustment for Normal Eating (DAFNE) course prior to starting on CSII.</s><s>Those with DAFNE training had lower pre-CSII HbA1c; 67 (58, 73) vs 70 (61, 81), p=0.001 [8.3% (7.5, 8.8) vs 8.6% (7.7, 9.6%)] and lower post-CSII HbA1c 60 (54, 68) vs 65 (56, 74), p&lt;0.001 [7.6% (7.1, 8.4) vs 8.1% (7.3, 8.9], compared to those who had not done DAFNE.</s><s>However once adjusted for pre-CSII HbA1c,</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Our study shows that CSII improves HbA1c irrespective of social deprivation status and demographics, however variation in HbA1c outcomes exists between different diabetes centres.</s><s>The majority of individuals at UHSM &amp; SRFT had participated in a validated structured education programme (DAFNE) before starting CSII therapy.</s><s>In the unadjusted analysis those who had done DAFNE had lower pre and post CSII HbA1c levels.</s><s>However after adjusting for deprivation index, pre-CSII HbA1c and centre, participation in DAFNE was not associated with HbA1c differences.</s><s>Overall improvements in HbA1c during our study are broadly in keeping with published literature from UK (2; 8) and elsewhere <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(9)</ref>.</s><s>Notably our data also confirms other studies which showed larger HbA1c improvements in individuals with higher pre-CSII HbA1c values <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(3)</ref>.</s><s>In our study the number of individuals using CSII was considerably larger at MRI than UHSM and SRFT.</s><s>At MRI approximately 44% of adults with T1D are treated with CSII, in contrast to UHSM and SRFT where 18-20% are treated with CSII.</s><s>This may be due to some differences in the interpretation of CSII entry criteria or patient selection even amongst neighbouring Trusts.</s><s>Impact of any differential interpretation of entry criteria or patient selection on HbA1c outcomes remains unclear.</s></p><p><s>In a previous study of children and adolescents, a 500 patient higher centre size was associated with a 1.5 higher odds of CSII use in an analysis that adjusted for age, gender and diabetes duration.</s><s>However, the authors of this paper found no correlation between the proportion of CSII users in each centre and HbA1c (r= -0.26, p=0.084).</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(10)</ref> We also used National Diabetes Audit, Insulin Pump Report 2016-17 (5), to evaluate relationships between the number of CSII users at each centre and: a) mean achieved HbA1c; and b) the percentage of individuals with HbA1c below 7.5% (Report available at: https://digital.nhs.uk/data-and-information/publications/statistical/national-diabetesaudit/insulin-pump-report-2016-17).</s><s>We found no relationship with number of CSII users and HbA1c outcomes.</s></p><p><s>Our study has several strengths, one of which being the first UK study to specifically report on the impact of social deprivation on pre-and post-CSII HbA1c levels.</s><s>Those with higher social deprivation had notably higher baseline HbA1c levels.</s><s>However the benefits of CSII therapy were not found to be associated with social deprivation, only with pre-CSII HbA1c and centre.</s><s>Yearly-averaged pre-and post-CSII HbA1c levels were used to maximise precision in estimating change in glycaemic control.</s><s>We included a large sample size with wide socioeconomic status (Interquartile range of the Index of Multiple Deprivation from 6312 to 25727).</s></p><p><s>Limitations and caveats include the observational nature of the study, lack of information about hypoglycaemia, ethnicity, psychological status, staffing ratios and number of contacts and clinic visits among pump users in the three centres.</s></p><p><s>In conclusion, higher pre-CSII HbA1c levels were associated with higher levels of deprivation and being female.</s><s>We also found significant differences in HbA1c outcomes with</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>CSII training: There were differences in pre-CSII structured education participation in all centres.</s><s>Approximately 84% and 53% of individuals in UHSM and SRFT respectively had completed the Dose Adjustment for Normal Eating (DAFNE) structured education course prior to starting CSII, whilst 20% in MRI had participated in a local structured education course.</s><s>The remaining individuals in MRI received individualised training lasting 1 to 3 hours, which encompassed carbohydrate counting and other aspects of diabetes self-management, before commencing CSII therapy.</s><s>In all three centres, a CSII training session lasting 3 to 4 hours, which included sick day rules and technical trouble shooting, was provided to all individuals.</s><s>Established methods were applied to set initial basal rate settings (i.e.</s><s>70 to 80% of total daily dose on multiple daily injections, divided by 2).</s><s>Statistical analysis: Descriptive statistics were used to examine the demographics and HbA1c levels (raw and change), alongside boxplots.</s><s>Differences between centres were tested via Fisher's exact tests (discrete data) and Kruskal Walis tests, with a post-hoc nemenyi test applied to analyse for differences between the three centres.</s><s>Univariable and multivariable regression models (full models alone) were utilised to assess relationships between individual outcomes: pre-and post-pump HbA1c, change in HbA1c and explanatory variables: age at pump start (years, standard and centred on the median), deprivation index (standard and centred on the median, scaled in units of 10 -3 ), gender (baseline female) and duration of diabetes at pump start (years, standard and centred on the median).</s><s>All p-values are two-tailed and values less than 0.05 were considered statistically significant.</s><s>All analyses were conducted in R version 3.2.4</s><s>[R Core Team (2016).</s><s>R: A language and environment for statistical computing.</s><s>R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria.[URL:</s><s>https://www.R-project.org/]</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">due to social deprivation or commonly measured demographics such as age, sex or duration of diabetes. Although the two centres with better outcomes had more patients who had undertaken structured education, there were no differences in HbA1c outcomes between those who had undertaken structured education vs. those who have not, after adjusting for deprivation index, pre-CSII HbA1c and centre. Further work is warranted to understand whether other unmeasured confounders, such as psychological factors may explain these differences. People with type 1 diabetes from deprived backgrounds should be provided with equal access to CSII; there should be more comparisons of outcomes between units providing CSII services.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>Author contributions: JB (UHSM), AP (SRFT), LL Centre (MRI) takes responsibility for the integrity of the data from each centre.</s><s>LL and CF take responsibility for the accuracy of the data analysis.</s><s>LL, JB, AP, HT and MKR co-designed the study.</s><s>AH, TA, JB, AP, AC, JM, AU collected data.</s><s>CF carried out the data and statistical analyses.</s><s>HT, MKR, LL, JB, AP contributed to the interpretation of the results.</s><s>HT and LL wrote the manuscript.</s><s>All authors critically reviewed the report.</s><s>No writing assistance was provided.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Index</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Centre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">DAFNE was not associated with pre, post or change in HbA1c with CSII. (Data not shown</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Insulin-pump therapy for type 1 diabetes mellitus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Pickup</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">366</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1616" to="1624" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sustained benefit of continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion on glycaemic control and hypoglycaemia in adults with Type 1 diabetes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Beato-Vibora</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Yeoh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hopkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Amiel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Choudhary</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabet Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1453" to="1459" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Severe hypoglycaemia and glycaemic control in Type 1 diabetes: meta-analysis of multiple daily insulin injections compared with continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Pickup</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sutton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabet Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="765" to="774" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of different insulin pump makes under routine care conditions in adults with Type 1 diabetes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Leelarathna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hindle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Markakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Alam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chapman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Urwin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jinadev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Rutter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabet Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Digital: The National Diabetes Audit Insulin Pump Report</title>
				<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2016" to="2017" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Greater Manchester Health and Social Care Partnership: About Devolution. Available at wwwgmhscorguk Last accessed 10/06</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ministry of Housing Communities &amp; Local Government: English indices of deprivation</title>
		<ptr target="https://wwwgovuk/government/statistics/english-indices-of-deprivation-20152015:Lastaccessed10/06/2018" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion (CSII) therapy at Derby Teaching Hospitals: sustained benefits in glucose control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Anyanwagu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Olaoye</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jennings</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ashton-Cleary</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sugunendran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Idris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Wilmot</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabet Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion (CSII) versus multiple insulin injections for type 1 diabetes mellitus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Misso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Egberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Page</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O'</forename><surname>Connor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2010</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">D005103</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Insulin pump therapy in children with type 1 diabetes: analysis of data from the SWEET registry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Szypowska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schwandt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Svensson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shalitin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cardona-Hernandez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Forsander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Sundberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Beaufort</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Maahs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Maffeis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>O'riordan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Krisane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Scharf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Konstantinova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Obermannova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Casteels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Goksen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Galhardo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kanaka-Gantenbein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rami-Merhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Madacsy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatr Diabetes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="45" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
