<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Selective cell targeting and lineage tracing of human induced pluripotent stem cells using recombinant avian retroviruses</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Laura</forename><surname>Hildebrand</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies (BCRT)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Petra</forename><surname>Seemann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies (BCRT)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Kurtz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies (BCRT)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">College of Veterinary Medicine and Research Institute for Veterinary Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Seoul National University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Seoul</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jochen</forename><surname>Hecht</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies (BCRT)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jörg</forename><surname>Contzen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies (BCRT)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biomaterial Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">) Helmholtz-Zentrum Geesthacht (HZG)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Teltow</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Manfred</forename><surname>Gossen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies (BCRT)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biomaterial Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">) Helmholtz-Zentrum Geesthacht (HZG)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Teltow</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Harald</forename><surname>Stachelscheid</surname></persName>
							<email>harald.stachelscheid@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies (BCRT)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Berlin Institute of Health</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Regenerative Therapies (BCRT)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite -Universitätsmedizin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin Berlin-Brandenburg</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="institution">Berlin Institute of Health -Stem Cell Core Facility Augustenburger Platz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Selective cell targeting and lineage tracing of human induced pluripotent stem cells using recombinant avian retroviruses</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B46DDEB66D1CAFE4DC078E77C928E610</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00018-015-1957-4</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:32+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Induced Pluripotent Stem Cells</term>
					<term>TVA</term>
					<term>ALV</term>
					<term>selective cell targeting</term>
					<term>lineage tracing</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Human induced pluripotent stem cells (hiPSC) differentiate into multiple cell types.</s><s>Selective cell targeting is often needed for analyzing gene function by overexpressing proteins in a distinct population of hiPSC-derived cell types and for monitoring cell fate in response to stimuli.</s><s>However, to date this has not been possible, as commonly used viruses enter the hiPSC via ubiquitously expressed receptors.</s><s>Here, we report for the first time the application of a heterologous avian receptor, the tumor virus receptor A (TVA), to selectively transduce TVA + cells in a mixed cell population.</s><s>Expression of the TVA surface receptor via genetic engineering renders cells susceptible for infection by avian leucosis virus (ALV).</s><s>We generated hiPSC lines with this stably integrated, ectopic TVA receptor gene that expressed the receptor while retaining pluripotency.</s><s>The undifferentiated hiPSC TVA+ as well as their differentiated progeny could be infected by recombinant ALV (socalled RCAS virus) with high efficiency.</s><s>Due to incomplete receptor blocking, even sequential infection of differentiated or undifferentiated TVA+ cells was possible.</s></p><p><s>In conclusion, the TVA/RCAS system provides an efficient and gentle gene transfer system for hiPSC and extends our possibilities for selective cell targeting and lineage tracing studies.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Induced pluripotent cells (iPSC) have the capacity for unlimited self-renewal in vitro and for differentiation into nearly every cell type of the mammalian body <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[20]</ref>.</s><s>As such, differentiated cells derived from human iPSC (hiPSC) are ideally suited for mode-of-action-analyses, the establishment of disease models or pharmacological screenings <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref>.</s><s>Most of these applications involve genetic engineering to introduce transgenes like reporter constructs or overexpression cassettes to study e. g. the influence of specific genes on cell differentiation or for establishing reporter cell lines.</s><s>Here, besides transfection, transduction is often considered an alternative technology as it avoids many of the stress triggers usually associated with chemical and physical transfection methods.</s><s>It is currently not easily possible to selectively target specific subpopulations of cells for transfection or transduction.</s><s>The ability to efficiently transduce only specific subpopulations of cells would be of benefit especially for stem cells and their differentiated progeny for example to trigger transgene expression and monitor cell fate of only the targeted cell types in a mixed cell population.</s></p><p><s>For overexpression studies in avian cells the avian replication competent ALV long terminal repeat (LTR) with a splice acceptor (RCAS) virus is a well-established tool (Figure <ref type="figure">1A</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">11]</ref>.</s><s>The virus enters avian cells via interaction with the tumor virus surface receptor (TVA) that is not present in mammalian cells (Figure <ref type="figure">1B</ref>).</s><s>It has been shown that the range of host cell lines for RCAS virus can be expanded to non-avian cell lines by TVA receptor expression <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">14]</ref>.</s><s>Aside from its high transduction efficiency, recombinant RCAS virus technology enables the selective targeting of TVA receptor positive (TVA + ) cells and their tracing in a mixed cell population.</s><s>Additionally, it is possible to transfer multiple genes, located on different viral vectors through coinfection <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref> as well as by sequential infection, due to impaired TVA receptor blocking by the RCAS virus in infected mammalian TVA + cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>There have been several studies reporting the application of this TVA-RCAS system in non-avian organisms, mostly in mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">21]</ref>.</s><s>In 1994, Federspiel et al. were the first to generate a transgenic mouse, in which the TVA receptor was under the control of the promoter of the chicken gene skeletal muscle α-actin <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>.</s><s>Thus, the TVA receptor was only expressed in skeletal muscle cells, rendering them susceptible for selective RCAS virus infection.</s><s>To date, however, the extension of the RCAS overexpression system has not been applied in human iPSC, despite its potential benefit for versatile and targeted gene transfer and cell tracing of hiPSC TVA+ and their progeny.</s></p><p><s>The exceptional properties of the RCAS overexpression system exploits the distant genetic origin of the RCAS virus compared to other viruses usually used when working with hiPSC.</s><s>The RCAS virus is a member of the avian leucosis and sarcoma virus (ALSV) family.</s><s>In this study, the replication competent avian leukoma virus long terminal repeat (LTR) with a splice acceptor with bryan high-titer polymerase (BP) virus (RCASBP(A)), created by Hughes and colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref>, has been used.</s><s>The RCASBP(A) virus is assigned to group A, because it expresses the envelope A protein (envA), enabling it to bind specifically to the TVA receptor.</s><s>To facilitate overexpression studies, the oncogene virus-sarcoma (v-src) gene in this viral vector has been replaced by a multiple cloning site (MCS), allowing insertion of cDNA sequences with a length of up to 2.8 kb.</s><s>The gene of interest is transcribed from the viral LTR.</s><s>There is also another version of this RCASBP(A) virus that has no splice acceptor, which is called replication competent ALV LTR with no splice acceptor with BP virus (RCANBP(A)).</s><s>Here, the transgene expression is not driven by the LTR and to get a reliable expression of the gene of interest, introduction of a heterologous promoter into the viral genome is required.</s></p><p><s>The aim of the study was to apply the TVA-RCAS system to hiPSC, implementing the versatility of this gene transfer technology to human stem cell research.</s><s>For that, we introduced the gene coding the avian TVA receptor into the genome of a hiPSC line using transposon technology (Figure <ref type="figure">1C</ref>) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">13]</ref>.</s><s>Stable hiPSC TVA+ clones remained pluripotent and the RCAS virus was able to infect both, undifferentiated cells as well as their differentiated progeny.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods:</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cell culture</head><p><s>Human iPSCs (IMR90-4, WiCell, Madison, US) and hiPSC TVA+ were cultured in TeSR E8 medium (StemCell Technologies, Cologne, Germany) supplemented with 100 UI/ml of each penicillin/streptomycin (Lonza, Basel, Switzerland) in 6 well dishes (Costar, Washington, DC, US) coated with Geltrex (Gibco, Paisley, UK) and routinely passaged using Gentle Cell Dissociation Reagent (StemCell Technologies) every 5-7 days at a splitting ratio of ~1:6.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TVA receptor expression vector cloning</head><p><s>A myc-tagged TVA950 <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[19]</ref> has been cloned into a modified pPB-CAG.EBNXN plasmid <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[24]</ref>.</s><s>Briefly, the PiggyBac transposon vector used contains a human EF1α promoter driving transgene expression and an additional puromycin resistance cassette.</s><s>Cloning details and vector sequence are available on request.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Transfection and selection of hiPSC TVA+</head><p><s>For transfection, hiPSC were dissociated into a single cell suspension by treatment with accutase (Gibco) followed by washing and resuspension in TeSR E8 medium containing 10 nM ROCK inhibitor Y26732 (Wako Chemicals, Neuss, Germany).</s><s>Transfection was carried out using the Neon Transfection System (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, US).</s><s>Briefly, 1x10 5 cells were transfected with 0,5 µg total DNA consisting of PB TVA950 transposon and PB transposase <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[24]</ref> in a ratio of 10:1 (w/w), using 10µl tips, settings 1.200 V for 30 ms, 1 pulse.</s><s>After transfection, cells were seeded in Geltrex coated culture dishes in TeSR E8 medium.</s><s>10 nM ROCK inhibitor was added for the first 24h of culture.</s><s>After six days, stably transfected cells were selected by addition of 1 µg/ml puromycin (Invivogen, Toulouse, France) to the culture medium.</s></p><p><s>Single cell clones were isolated using the CloneStem Kit (Biolamina, Sundbyberg, Sweden), following the manufacturer's instructions.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Immunofluorescence</head><p><s>hiPSC TVA+ were cultured on 96 well imaging plates (CellCarrier, Perkin Elmer, Waltham, US) in TeSR E8 for three days.</s><s>For detection of the extracellular Myc-tag attached to the TVA receptor, cells were fixed with Cytofix (BD, San Jose, US), blocked with blocking buffer (10 % FCS superior (Biochrom, Berlin, Germany) in PBS (Lonza)) and then incubated with anti-Myc-tag antibody (Cell Signaling, Leiden, Netherlands; dilution 1:2000).</s><s>The cells were washed with PBS and incubated with Alexa Fluor 488 goat anti-mouse IgG secondary antibody (Invitrogen, 1:2000).</s><s>Nuclei were stained with Hoechst 33342 (2,5 µg/ml in PBS; Life Technologies, Grand Island, NY, US).</s></p><p><s>Staining of pluripotency markers was performed by fixation with Cytofix reagent, followed by blocking and permeabilization with 1X PermWash reagent (both BD) supplemented with 5% chicken serum (Life Technologies).</s><s>Thereafter, cells were incubated using anti-Nanog rabbit mAb (Cell Signaling, 1:400), followed by secondary antibody anti-rabbit Alexa Fluor594 (Life Technologies).</s><s>Then, staining with the fluorescence dyeconjugated antibodies octamer transcription factor 3/4 (Oct3/4) (PerCP-Cy7, BD, 1:100), stage specific embryonic antigen 4 (SSEA4) (FITC, R&amp;D, Minneapolis, US; 1:100) and tumor rejection antigen 1-81 (Tra-1-81) (DyLight 650, Novus Biologicals, Littleton, US; 1:100) was performed.</s><s>Nuclei were stained with Hoechst 33342 (2,5 µg/ml in PBS).</s></p><p><s>Microscopic analysis was performed with either a 2 Photon microscope (LEICA SP5 confocal microscope equipped with a Mai Tai HP multiphoton laser), or an Operetta imaging system (Perkin Elmer), as indicated.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RCASBP(A) and RCANBP(A) cloning and production</head><p><s>RCASBP(A)/RCANBP(A) vectors were obtained from Stephen Hughes.</s><s>Insertion of GFP, RFP, monomeric Cherry (mCherry) and the simian virus 40(SV40) promoter (Addgene accession numbers #17619, #20972, #18807, Cambridge, US) was done by performing Gibson Assembly (NEB, Hitchin, UK; described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Primers were purchased from Eurofins (Berlin, Germany, Supplemental Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</s><s>RCASBP(A)/RCANBP(A) viruses were produced in DF1 cells (ATCC, Manassas, US) after transfection of the viral plasmids with PEI (Polysciences Inc., Eppelheim, Germany).</s><s>On three consecutive days viral particles were harvested by collecting the supernatant, followed by ultracentrifugation for high-titer concentrates.</s><s>Titers were determined as plaque forming units (PFU/ml) one day after DF1 cell infection <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Infection of hiPSC TVAs</head><p><s>For RCAS infection, hiPSC TVA+ were cultured in 24 well plates (TPP, Trasadingen, Switzerland) or 96 well plates.</s><s>Viral transduction was performed at a MOI of 50.</s><s>Medium was changed every day.</s><s>2-3 days post infection hiPSC TVA+ were analyzed after live cell staining for nuclei (Hoechst 33342 in medium, 2,5 µg/ml in PBS) using an Operetta imaging system.</s><s>Sequential infection was done 3 days apart.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fluorescence activated cell sorting (FACS) analysis</head><p><s>Cells were dissociated using Gentle Cell Dissociation Reagent and fixed with Cytofix.</s><s>For Myc-tag quantification, cells were stained with anti-Myc-tag antibody (Cell Signaling, 1:2000), washed with PBS, followed by staining with secondary antibody Alexa Fluor 488 goat anti-mouse IgG secondary antibody (Invitrogen, 1:2000).</s><s>Afterwards, cells were diluted in FACS buffer, consisting of 2 % bovine serum albumin (Sigma Aldrich, Seelze, Germany) and 2 mM EDTA (Sigma Aldrich) in PBS.</s><s>To quantify transduction, cells, diluted in FACS buffer, were directly used for FACS analysis, which was performed with an Accuri C6 (BD, San Jose, US).</s><s>Data was analyzed with the FCS express 4 software (De Novo, Los Angeles, US).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Undirected differentiation of hiPSC in 2D and 3D culture</head><p><s>Undirected differentiation of hiPSC TVA+ in 2D culture was induced by culture in DMEM Low Glucose (Biochrom), 10 % FCS superior, 2mM/ml L-Glutamine (Biochrom) and 100 UI/ml Penicillin/Streptomycin (Biochrom) for three days, following immune staining and FACS analysis.</s></p><p><s>To differentiate hiPSC TVA+ in 3D culture, embryoid bodies (EBs) were generated either by cell aggregation in ultra low attachment plates (Costar) or in AggreWell plates (StemCell Technologies).</s><s>Subsequently, after aggregate formation, EBs were cultured either in DMEM Low Glucose supplemented with 10 % FCS superior, 2mM/ml L-Glutamine and 100 UI/ml Penicillin/Streptomycin for 10 days or in KnockOut DMEM/F12 (Invitrogen) supplemented with 20 % KnockOut Serum Replacer (Invitrogen), 50 µM 2-Mercaptoethanol (Invitrogen), 1X MEM Non-Essential Amino Acids (Invitrogen), 2mM/ml L-Glutamine and 100 UI/ml Penicillin/Streptomycin for 7 days.</s><s>Medium was changed every other day.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Splinkerette PCR</head><p><s>A Splinkerette PCR was performed according to Potter and Luo 2014 <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref> to determine copy number and chromosomal integration site of the PB transposon.</s><s>In short: genomic DNA was isolated using the Genomic DNA from tissue kit (Machery-Nagel, Dueren, Germany). 1 µg of this gDNA was digested with BstYI (Fermentas, Burlington, Canada) for 2 h, followed by ligation of the resulting DNA fragments to Splinkerette oligos (sequences according to <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref>, Supplemental Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</s><s>Two rounds of PCR were conducted, amplification products separated using an 1 % agarose gel (Invitrogen) and bands indicating single-copy events were purified with the Omnipure OLS kit (Omni Life Science, East Taunton, US).</s><s>These PCR products then were sequenced using a 3730 DNA Analyzer (Life Technologies; primer sequences are listed in Supplemental Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Resulting sequence information was analyzed using the BLAT tool using the UCSC genome browser (http://genome.ucsc.edu/).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RNA isolation and quantitative PCR analysis of marker genes</head><p><s>Undifferentiated iPSC TVA+ and EBs were harvested and disrupted using a Shredder (Qiagen, Valencia, US), followed by RNA extraction (RNeasy Plus Mini Kit, Qiagen). 1 µg of total RNA were reverse transcribed into cDNA with the TaqMan Reverse Transcription Reagents (Invitrogen).</s><s>After confirming RNA integrity by 2 % agarose gel electrophoresis, cDNA was applied for quantitative analysis of trilineage differentiation potential performing quantitative PCR analysis using commercially available Taqman probes and measured on a QuantStudio 6 machine (Life Technologies, Supplemental Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).</s><s>For normalization the expression of the housekeeping genes β-Actin, Transcriptional repressor CTCF, E1A binding protein p300 and Mothers against decapentaplegic homolog 1 (Smad1) were determined.</s><s>To obtain the ΔCt values of the genes of interest (GOI), the mean of the housekeeping genes (ranging between 23 and 25) was subtracted from their Ct value.</s><s>The ΔΔCt value was calculated by ΔCt (GOI) minus ΔCt of the reference values of undifferentiated hiPSC TVA+ .</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistics</head><p><s>Statistical analysis for standard derivation of RCAS infection of hiPSC TVA+ and its differentiated progeny was calculated using Prism 6 software (GraphPad, La Jolla, USA).</s><s>Groups consisted of three independent experiments each.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results:</head><p><s>Ectopic TVA receptor is located on the cell surface in human iPSC hiPSC were transfected with a PiggyBac transposon carrying the TVA receptor under the control of the housekeeping promoter elongation factor 1 (EF1).</s><s>Transgene-positive cells were isolated by antibiotic selection, cloned and analyzed for single transposon integration.</s><s>TVA receptor expression in the three isolated hiPSC TVA+ clones was analyzed by immunofluorescence staining of the Myc-tag fused to the extracellular c-terminus of the TVA receptor protein.</s></p><p><s>Using 2 photon microscopy, expression of the TVA receptor on the cell surface of hiPSC TVA+ was shown (Figure <ref type="figure">2A+C</ref>).</s><s>FACS analysis was performed and revealed the presence of the TVA receptor in 93.31 % of the cells (Figure <ref type="figure">2B</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>hiPSC TVA+ are susceptible to RCAS virus infection</head><p><s>To analyze the efficiency by which hiPSC TVA+ and their differentiated progeny can be infected by RCAS virus, hiPSC TVA+ were infected with RCASBP(A) carrying the green fluorescent protein (GFP) gene as reporter.</s><s>No viral reporter gene expression could be observed in undifferentiated hiPSC TVA+ three days post infection (Figure <ref type="figure">3D</ref>).</s><s>Interestingly, after spontaneous differentiation of RCASBP(A) GFP-transduced hiPSC TVA+ , viral gene expression was initiated as evidenced by GFP expression (Figure <ref type="figure">3A</ref>).</s><s>When differentiated cells derived from the hiPSC TVA+ were infected with RCASBP(A), GFP expression was observed 72 hours after infection (Figure <ref type="figure">3B</ref>).</s><s>In these experiments, high infection efficiencies were observed by FACS analysis, specifically 73.3 % (± 7.6 %) for undifferentiated cells and 64.0 % (± 7.2 %) for differentiated cells (Figures <ref type="figure">3E, F</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To test the influence of the specific promoter on the transgene expression in undifferentiated hiPSC, an alternative promoter to the viral LTR for initiation of the GFP reporter gene expression was tested.</s><s>When hiPSC TVA+ were infected with a RCANBP(A) carrying GFP under SV40 promoter control GFP expression was detected 72 hours post infection (Figure <ref type="figure">3C</ref>).</s><s>FACS analysis showed an infection efficiency of 56.0 % (± 13.1 %) (Figure <ref type="figure">3G</ref>).</s><s>GFP expression was retained upon cell differentiation (data not shown).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>hiPSC TVA+ are pluripotent and have a single transposon integration site</head><p><s>For most conceivable applications of the hiPSC TVA+ technology, it is mandatory to confirm the continued pluripotency of the cells after the genetic engineering by introduction of the TVA cDNA.</s><s>Pluripotency of the hiPSC TVA+ was confirmed by detection of the expression of pluripotency markers in undifferentiated cells and evaluation of the differentiation capability into cells of all three germ layers.</s><s>First, co-expression of the pluripotency markers SSEA4, TRA-1-81, Oct3/4 and NANOG in undifferentiated hiPSC TVA+ was confirmed by positive immunofluorescence staining (Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref>).</s><s>Second, gene expression was analyzed in undifferentiated hiPSC TVA+ and embryoid bodies (EBs) by quantitative RT-PCR using markers of all three germ layers.</s><s>In the EBs the expression of the ectodermal markers Paired box protein 3 (PAX3), Myosin III B (MYO3B) and Wingless-Type MMTV Integration Site Family, Member 1 (WNT1), the endodermal markers Krueppel-like factor 5 (KLF5), SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 17(SOX17) and Hepatocyte nuclear factor 4-alpha (HNF4A) as well as the mesodermal markers Heart-and neural crest derivatives-expressed protein 1(HAND1), HAND2 and Homeodomain-only protein (HOPX) was detected.</s><s>In parallel, the pluripotency markers POU domain, class 5, transcription factor 1(POU5F1/Oct 4), Nanog and sex determining region Y box 2(Sox 2) were down regulated (Supplemental Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Splinkerette PCR was performed to examine the number and position of integration sites of the PB transposon .</s></p><p><s>For the hiPSC TVA+ clone#1 used mostly throughout the investigation reported here, intra-intronic integration into the zinc finger matrin-type protein 4 (ZMAT4) gene was determined (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Infection of human cells with RCAS vectors is highly specific to TVA expressing cells</head><p><s>Next we tested the application for the selective targeting of hiPSC TVA+ in mixed cell populations.</s></p><p><s>As a proof of concept hiPSC TVA+ were co-cultured with a stable hiPSC GFP+ cell line.</s><s>This mixed population was infected with a RCANBP(A) virus, containing mCherry under the control of the SV40 promoter.</s><s>Microscopic analysis three days after infection revealed that expression of the fluorescent proteins on the cellular level was mutually exclusive.</s><s>In consequence, only GFP-negative hiPSC TVA+ were infected by the mCherry encoding RCAN virus, as evident from cell clusters of the respective hiPSC subpopulations growing into each other (Figure <ref type="figure">5</ref>).</s><s>Moreover, sequential infection with two RCAS viruses at different time points was possible.</s><s>This has been tested in hiPSC TVA+ (Data not shown), as well as their differentiated progeny (Figure <ref type="figure">5B</ref>).</s><s>Here, hiPSC TVA+ were first infected with a RCAS RFP virus, followed by infection with a RCAS GFP virus three days later.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion:</head><p><s>The aim of this study was to establish the avian leukosis virus (ALV)-based retroviral vector TVA-RCAS system for human iPSC, expanding its reach to stem cell research.</s><s>To establish and evaluate the TVA-RCAS system in stem cells, we generated hiPSC clones expressing the TVA receptor gene, evaluated the presence and functionality of the receptor, confirmed their continued pluripotency and lastly characterized the potency of the system by determining the infection efficiency and selectivity in a mixed cell population using RCAS viral vectors.</s></p><p><s>In our study we were able to stably transfect and express the TVA receptor in hiPSC using a PiggyBac transposon, taking advantage of the high chromosomal integration activity of this gene transfer system <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[23]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>There was no obvious effect on pluripotency subsequent to the genetic manipulation of the hiPSC.</s><s>As previously described in the literature, the EF1 promoter proved to be suitable for high ectopic gene expression in hiPSC, as well as in their differentiated progeny <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">16]</ref>.</s><s>Correct localization of the TVA receptor on the cell surface and susceptibility of hiPSC TVA+ for the RCAS virus were verified.</s><s>However, viral gene expression in hiPSC TVA+ turned out to be problematic as RCAS-vector based GFP-transgene expression was not detected in hiPSC TVA+ after infection, when using the viral LTR for gene overexpression (Figure <ref type="figure">3D</ref>).</s><s>One explanation could be that the hiPSC are not permissive for the RCAS virus.</s><s>This possibility was ruled out by showing that LTR-driven GFP transgene expression started after differentiation of hiPSC TVA+ infected with a RCAS vector.</s><s>Another explanation could be the lack of functionality of the viral LTR in hiPSC.</s><s>Our study suggests that this is the case as we were able to overcome this problem by using the heterologous SV40 promoter in a modified RCAS version, the RCAN virus.</s></p><p><s>We also tested the EOS-C 3+ (Early transposon promoter and Oct4 and Sox2 enhancers) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref>, Thymidine Kinase (TK) <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref> and CMV promoters, which were functional in initiating ectopic gene expression in hiPSC, but gene expression was lower compared to SV40 (data not shown).</s></p><p><s>When using the EF1 and Cytomegalovirus (CMV) early enhancer/chicken beta actin (CAG) promoters, there was no functional RCAN virus production even in the DF1 production cell line.</s><s>We hypothesize that this is due to intron sequences being recognized and spliced before integration into the hiPSC genome, which leads to a non-functional shortened promoter version.</s><s>Nevertheless, we observed higher infection efficiencies in differentiated hiPSC TVA+ progeny than in hiPSC TVA+ .</s><s>This might be explained by increased silencing of retroviral DNA in hiPSC after integration into the genome.</s></p><p><s>Whatever the mechanism, the RCAS vector system introduced here, provides not only the opportunity for infection with at least two different viral constructs, but also for multiple re-infection at later time points.</s><s>This enhances the utility of the RCAS viruses for e.g.</s><s>lineage tracing.</s><s>The unusual possibility for subsequent transductions is most likely due to incomplete blocking of the TVA receptors by EnvA protein on the cell surface, since there is no sufficient viral protein production in non-avian cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The final purpose of this study was to confirm selectivity of RCASBP(A) infection towards hiPSC TVA+ in a mixed cell population, which could be shown accurately, when co-culturing hiPSC TVA+ with hiPSC stably expressing GFP followed by infection with a RCANBP(A) SV40 mCherry virus.</s><s>This highlights one uniqueness of this newly designed tool: most of the commonly used retro-and lentiviral vector systems used for stem cell transduction enter cells by interactions of the vesicular stomatitis virus glycoprotein (VSV-G protein) and the corresponding receptor, which is ubiquitously present on mammalian cell membranes and therefore makes selective infection impossible <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[3]</ref>.</s><s>In contrast to that, RCAS virus infection is guarded by the EnvA protein <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref> recognizing the TVA receptor.</s><s>Therefore, cellular selectivity for the RCAS virus is given, after ectopic TVA receptor expression <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">5]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Taken together, a novel tool for the efficient transduction of hiPSC was developed.</s><s>We foresee the selective targeting of defined subpopulations of cells, either in mixed stem cell cultures or in lineage tracing experiments, as well as possible sequential infection as main areas of application for this technology.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion:</head><p><s>In this study we report for the first time the successful application of the TVA-RCAS system for efficient infection of hiPSC.</s><s>It represents a promising new avenue for generating genetically engineered stem cells via viral transduction for differentiation, cell fate and gene function studies.</s><s>The TVA-RCAS system has the added value of selective targeting hiPSC TVA+ in mixed populations as well as sequential infection with different viruses.</s><s>Undirected differentiation of the hiPSCTVA+ as embryoid bodies (EBs) in two different media showed upregulation of markers for the three germ layers, while markers for pluripotency were downregulated.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure legends : Figure 1 :</head><label>:1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure legends: Figure 1: Scheme of the TVA-RCAS system in avian and mammalian cells The genome of the RCAS virus consists of two Long Terminal Repeats (LTR) flanking the three viral genes (1) group specific antigen (gag) (2) polymerase (pol) (3) envelope (env) and the multiple cloning site (MCS).</s><s>[A] In avian cells the RCASBP(A) virus enters through the TVA receptor and is replication competent.</s><s>[B] In mammalian cells the virus cannot enter, as the TVA receptor is not expressed.</s><s>[C] By transfecting a transposon holding the TVA receptor cDNA, infection of mammalian cells becomes possible; however, no functional RCASBP(A) virus is produced.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :Figure 3 :Figure 4 :Figure 5 :Supplemental Figure 1 :</head><label>23451</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2: Immunolocalisation of TVA receptor in hiPSC TVA+ [A] Anti-Myc-tag stained hiPSC TVA+ for detection of TVA receptor expression (left panel).</s><s>Merge of Hoechst33342 and Myc-tag staining and view of the xz and yz plane (right panel).</s><s>[B] Quantification of TVA receptor using FACS analysis.</s><s>[C] Magnification of Hoechst33342 and Myc-Tag staining.</s><s>(Scale bar = 61 µm)</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="19,106.40,232.88,385.96,373.51" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="21,50.37,294.44,498.01,250.39" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="22,50.37,325.57,498.01,187.45" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgement</head><p><s>We thank Mareen Schmidt-von Kegler and Maria Walther as well as the Berlin Institute of Health (BIH) Stem Cell Core Facility for excellent technical assistance and the people from the laboratory of Prof. Petra Seemann and Dr. Andreas Kurtz for helpful discussions regarding the study.</s><s>Additionally, we thank Dr. Stephen Hughes for kindly providing us with the RCAS and RCAN vectors and Dr. Ansgar Petersen for help at the 2 photon microscope.</s><s>We appreciate the financial support and provision of laboratory facilities by Prof. Petra Reinke.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p><s>All authors state that they have no conflict of interest.</s></p><p><s>!Laura Hildebrand is a member of the DFG funded Berlin-Brandenburg School for Regenerative Therapies GSC 203.</s><s>This work was supported by the grant 1315848A for the Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies (BCRT) by the Initiative and Networking Fund of the Helmholtz Association, Germany.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p><s>All authors state that they have no conflict of interest.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">This work was supported by the Helmholtz President&apos;s Initiative and Networking Fund and the Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies (BCRT) (1315848A) References</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Avian sarcoma and leukosis virus-receptor interactions: from classical genetics to novel insights into virus-cell membrane fusion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Barnard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Elleder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Virology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">344</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modelling schizophrenia using human induced pluripotent stem cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Brennand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Simone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">473</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="221" to="225" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Altering the tropism of lentiviral vectors through pseudotyping</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cronin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Reiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Current gene therapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="387" to="398" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Induced pluripotent stem cells and their implication for regenerative medicine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Csobonyeiova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Polak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Koller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Tissue Bank</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A system for tissue-specific gene targeting: transgenic mice susceptible to subgroup A avian leukosis virus-based retroviral vectors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Federspiel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11241" to="11245" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acquisition of Host Cell DNA Sequences by Baculoviruses: Relationship Between Host DNA Insertions and FP Mutants of Autographa californica and Galleria mellonella Nuclear Polyhedrosis Viruses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fraser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Summers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Virol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="287" to="300" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient induction of transgene-free human pluripotent stem cells using a vector based on Sendai virus, an RNA virus that does not integrate into the host genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fusaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ban</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nishiyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Jpn Acad Ser B Phys Biol Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">85</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="348" to="362" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enzymatic assembly of DNA molecules up to several hundred kilobases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Gibson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Chuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="343" to="345" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional analysis of various promoters in lentiviral vectors at different stages of in vitro differentiation of mouse embryonic stem cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Hwang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1630" to="1639" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isolation of human iPS cells using EOS lentiviral vectors to select for pluripotency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hotta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Cheung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Farra</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="370" to="376" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The RCAS vector system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Folia Biol (Praha)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="119" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adaptor plasmids simplify the insertion of foreign DNA into helper-independent retroviral vectors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Hughes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Greenhouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Petropoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Virol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3004" to="3012" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Size matters: versatile use of PiggyBac transposons as a genetic manipulation tool</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Pyykko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Cell Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">354</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="301" to="309" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development of an avian leukosis-sarcoma virus subgroup A pseudotyped lentiviral vector</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Chinnasamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Morgan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Virol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9339" to="9344" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Manipulating gene expression with replicationcompetent retroviruses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Morgan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fekete</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Methods Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="218" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantitative comparison of constitutive promoters in human ES cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Norrman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bonnamy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e12413</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Targeting of herpes simplex virus 1 thymidine kinase gene sequences into the OCT4 locus of human induced pluripotent stem cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Reiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e81131</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Splinkerette PCR for mapping transposable elements in Drosophila</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Potter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e10168</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conversion of a human low-density lipoprotein receptor ligandbinding repeat to a virus receptor: identification of residues important for ligand specificity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Rong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gendron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Bates</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8467" to="8472" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Induction of pluripotent stem cells from adult human fibroblasts by defined factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Takahashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tanabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ohnuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="861" to="872" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel Flk1-TVA transgenic mouse model for gene delivery to angiogenic vasculature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vervoort</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Valencia</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transgenic research</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="403" to="415" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Production of avian retroviruses and tissue-specific somatic retroviral gene transfer in vivo using the RCAS/TVA system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Von</forename><surname>Werder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Seidler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schmid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature protocols</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1167" to="1183" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PiggyBac transposon-mediated gene transfer in human cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Wilson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Coates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>George</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jr</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generation of transgene-free induced pluripotent mouse stem cells by the piggyBac transposon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yusa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Takeda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="363" to="369" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
