<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Siblings of children with cancer-the price they pay to function</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-04-28">28 April 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Guggemos</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatric Oncology/Hematology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Children&apos;s Hospital Cologne</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Amsterdamerstraße 59</addrLine>
									<postCode>50735</postCode>
									<settlement>Cologne</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatric Oncology/Hematology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitaetsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Augustenburger Platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Florian</forename><surname>Juen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institut of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Innsbruck</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Innrain 52</addrLine>
									<postCode>6020</postCode>
									<settlement>Innsbruck</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lina</forename><surname>Engelmann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institut of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Innsbruck</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Innrain 52</addrLine>
									<postCode>6020</postCode>
									<settlement>Innsbruck</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Viola</forename><surname>Diesselhorst</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatric Oncology/Hematology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitaetsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Augustenburger Platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Günter</forename><surname>Henze</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatric Oncology/Hematology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitaetsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Augustenburger Platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Alain</forename><surname>Di Gallo</surname></persName>
							<email>alain.digallo@upkbs.ch</email>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">University Clinic of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Kinder-und Jugendpsychiatrische Klinik</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitäre Psychiatrische Kliniken (UPK) Basel</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Schaffhauserrheinweg 55</addrLine>
									<postCode>4058</postCode>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Alain Di Gallo</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Siblings of children with cancer-the price they pay to function</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-04-28">28 April 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">C855B5B59F0D154DBBB3E2BADEB6179A</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00520-015-2716-7</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 7 November 2014 / Accepted: 23 March 2015 /</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:33+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Siblings</term>
					<term>Children</term>
					<term>Cancer</term>
					<term>Coping</term>
					<term>SDQ</term>
					<term>MSSB</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>When a child is diagnosed with cancer, this might generate an existential crisis and the emotional balance of the entire family is deeply disturbed.</s><s>This is also because parental attention, worries and care strongly focus on the sick child.</s><s>When there are siblings, there is no doubt that they are also in need of their parents' care and attention to adjust to this challenging situation.</s><s>Being exposed to cancer increases the risk of adverse mental reactions in combination with other risk factors such as low social support, pre-existing adjustment problems or parental mental disease.</s><s>Empirical findings regarding quality, quantity and intensity of specific reactions of siblings to a cancer diagnosis are inconsistent.</s><s>Whereas some researchers point to a higher prevalence of psychopathology, such as behavioural and mood disorders or impaired development among these children, others do not report any abnormalities at all <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s>These heterogenous findings are likely to be due to the diversity of accompanying risk factors, as well as to different times and intervals of assessment.</s><s>Further reasons might be the diversity of (a) research methods (questionnaires vs. interviews), (b) dimensions observed (behavioural outcome vs. intrapsychic effort) or (c) the sources of information (self vs. proxy rating).</s><s>Questionnaires provide adequate behavioural screening; however, when used as a single measure, they may not always be sufficiently sensitive in assessing subjective and affective dimensions.</s><s>With questionnaires alone, we might underestimate aspects of the burden siblings suffer from and not be able to detect precursors of maladaptive development.</s><s>For this reason, we advocate the use of complementary assessment methods in order to study siblings' specific intrapsychic reactions and adjustment to this challenging experiences.</s><s>In child and adolescent psychiatry and psychosomatic medicine, we use child's play as a valuable source of information about the child's inner world.</s><s>The Mac Arthur Story Stem Battery (MSSB) is a standardized self-report measure designed to assess the intrapsychic strain and conflicts of children <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>By acting out the beginnings of conflictual stories, the interviewer seeks to generate emotional tension within the child.</s><s>Once the interviewer has told the beginning of the story, the child is asked to continue it and to show and tell what happens next.</s><s>The narration and the way the child plays with the figurines provide insight into its inner world, its fears and wishes <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>.</s><s>The child's stories also yield information about how it deals with present problems.</s><s>As we know from other studies, the MSSB is sensitive to intrapsychic changes even weeks or months before behavioural outcomes are observed using questionnaires <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In the present study, we compared 14 siblings of children diagnosed with cancer (7 girls, 7 boys) with a matched control Andreas Guggemos and Florian Juen contributed equally to this work.</s><s>group of 18 children (9 girls, 9 boys).</s><s>Children's ages ranged 6 to 12 years.</s><s>Siblings of children with cancer were interviewed 2 weeks after the cancer diagnosis (time 1) and 2 weeks after the end of therapy (time 2).</s><s>We also asked parents to fill in the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, a behavioural diagnostic screening tool that measures psychopathological symptoms in children.</s><s>Our control sample was assessed using the same method and with a time interval of 6 months.</s><s>An extensive description of the methods and results of this study can be found elsewhere <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</s><s>In this commentary, we aim to discuss the specific challenges of siblings of children with cancer in terms of intrapsychic efforts to adjust that are not directly observable on a behavioural level.</s><s>An important result of our study was that we found no differences in the questionnaire-based measures (SDQ) between the affected group and the control group and between the two times of assessment in either group, whereas significant differences and changes did emerge in the play assessment method (MSSB).</s><s>In our sample, the affected siblings coped well on the behavioural level within the 6-month time period.</s><s>At both assessments, the SDQ mean scores on the total difficulties scale of all participants were far below the clinical cut-off.</s><s>In the MSSB narratives, at time 1, we found significantly more themes (topics arising in the narratives) in the stories of the affected children compared with those of the controls.</s><s>The siblings of children with cancer more often displayed themes of morality (like guilt or shame), avoided displaying interpersonal conflicts, showed problems in keeping the characters and situations regulated (themes of dysregulation) and even showed significantly more elements of magic disruptions, destruction and threat (themes of dissociation).</s><s>In other studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>, these last three elements have been shown to be highly predictive of later psychopathological outcomes.</s><s>In addition, the affected group showed a tendency to manipulate and control the situation and the interviewer by changing the rules of play, which might reflect their confusion and fear of losing control over the course of the story.</s><s>In summary, we have evidence that shortly after the cancer diagnosis, the siblings showed clear reactions of intrapsychic adjustment that may hold prognostic value for anxiety disorders, depressive symptoms or even aggressive and hostile behaviour, despite the fact that they were coping well on the behavioural level.</s></p><p><s>After the end of cancer treatment (time 2), we found changes in the MSSB narratives of the affected group only.</s><s>The siblings of the children with cancer presented a reestablished feeling of control and reduced avoidance of conflicts but still displayed dysregulative aspects more often than the control group.</s><s>These children, who were coping behaviourally well with the situation and not showing manifestations of psychiatric disorders, clearly remained at risk <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref>.</s><s>Despite our multimethod longitudinal approach with a comparison group, our study comprises several limitations, mainly the small sample size.</s><s>In future research, a detailed analysis of accompanying risk factors, as well as an analysis of long-term effects in order to screen for high-and low-risk children, using diverse methods of assessment, would be of interest.</s><s>In addition, taking into consideration the concept of posttraumatic growth within children seems highly relevant <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</s><s>In summary, our results showed that parents did not observe particular symptoms in their children, although the MSSB stories demonstrated significant differences between the two groups and-in the affected group-over time.</s><s>These findings should raise our awareness for the often so well functioning siblings of children with cancer, who are actually in need of attention and of a sensitive understanding of their emotional challenges.</s><s>Even psychological support at a low frequency may be a very helpful tool in fostering their coping strategies, with the aim of preventing later psychiatric pathology.</s></p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p><s>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</s></p><p><s>Funding This work was supported by the BSchweizerische Arbeitsgemeinschaft für Klinische Krebsforschung^and the BDeutsche José Carreras Leukämie-Stiftung^.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Psychosocial adjustment of siblings of children with cancer: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Alderfer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Long</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychooncology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="789" to="805" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adjustment of siblings to childhood cancer: a literature review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Houtzager</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Grootenhuis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Last</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Support Care Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="302" to="320" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A review of qualitative research on the childhood cancer experience from the perspective of siblings: a need to give them a voice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Wilkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Woodgate</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pediatr Oncol Nurs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="319" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Story stem evaluation in clinical practice with young children</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Von Klitzing</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prax Kinderpsychol Kinderpsychiatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="333" to="346" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Revealing the inner worlds of young children: the MacArthur Story Stem Battery and parent-child narratives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Emde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Oppenheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Oxford; New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Engaging imagination and the future: frontiers for clinical work</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Emde</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Attach Hum Dev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="302" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Can emotions and themes in children&apos;s play predict behavior problems?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Warren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Oppenheim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Emde</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Acad Child Adolesc Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="637" to="644" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The extended version of the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire as a guide to child psychiatric caseness and consequent burden</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Goodman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Child Psychol Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="791" to="799" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How children who&apos;s siblings are diagnosed with cancer experience and regulate the disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Juen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Guggemos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Engelmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Diesselhorst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Di</forename><surname>Gallo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prax Kinderpsychol Kinderpsychiatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="491" to="504" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experiences and support needs of siblings of children with cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sloper</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Health Soc Care Community</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="298" to="306" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The use of a play narrative story stem technique with maltreated children: implications for theory and practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Buchsbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Toth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Clyman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cicchetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Emde</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev Psychopathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="603" to="625" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How siblings of pediatric cancer patients experience the first time after diagnosis: a qualitative study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Prchal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Landolt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Nurs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="140" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Experience of siblings of children treated for cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nolbris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Enskar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hellstrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Oncol Nurs</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="116" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Trauma and transformation: growing in the aftermath of suffering</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tedeschi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Calhoun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<publisher>Sage Publications Ltd</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Newbury Park</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
