<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Placenta-Derived Adherent Stromal Cells Improve Diabetes Mellitus-Associated Left Ventricular Diastolic Performance</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-10-10">October 10, 2017.</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sophie</forename><surname>Van Linthout</surname></persName>
							<idno type="ORCID">0000-0002-7581-7870</idno>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nazha</forename><surname>Hamdani</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kapka</forename><surname>Miteva</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Annika</forename><surname>Koschel</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Irene</forename><surname>Mu ¨ller</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lena</forename><surname>Pinzur</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zami</forename><surname>Aberman</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kathleen</forename><surname>Pappritz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Albrecht</forename><surname>Wolfgang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Linke</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Carsten</forename><surname>Tscho ¨pe</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Placenta-Derived Adherent Stromal Cells Improve Diabetes Mellitus-Associated Left Ventricular Diastolic Performance</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2017-10-10">October 10, 2017.</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">41BCAF734EF0E49AE46B2461390A258B</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1002/sctm.17-0130</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received May 18, 2017; accepted for publication August 25, 2017;</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:17+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Left ventricular (LV) diastolic dysfunction is among others attributed to cardiomyocyte stiffness.</s><s>Mesenchymal stromal cells (MSC) have cardiac-protective properties.</s><s>We explored whether intravenous (i.v.) application of PLacenta-eXpanded (PLX) MSC-like cells (PLX) improves LV diastolic relaxation in streptozotocin (STZ)-induced diabetic mice and investigated underlying mechanisms.</s><s>Diabetes mellitus was induced by STZ application (50 mg/kg body weight) during five subsequent days.</s><s>One week after the first STZ injection, PLX or saline were i.v.</s><s>applied.</s><s>Two weeks later, mice were hemodynamically characterized and sacrificed.</s><s>At this early stage of diabetic cardiomyopathy with low-grade inflammation and no cardiac fibrosis, PLX reduced LV vascular cell adhesion molecule-1, transforming growth factor-b1, and interferon-c mRNA expression, induced the percentage of circulating regulatory T cells, and decreased the splenic pro-fibrotic potential in STZ mice.</s><s>STZ 1 PLX mice exhibited higher LV vascular endothelial growth factor mRNA expression and arteriole density versus STZ mice.</s><s>In vitro, hyperglycemic PLX conditioned medium restored the hyperglycemia-impaired tube formation and adhesion capacity of human umbelical vein endothelial cells (HUVEC) via increasing nitric oxide (NO) bioavailability.</s><s>PLX further induced the diabetesdownregulated activity of the NO downstream protein kinase G, as well as of protein kinase A, in STZ mice, which was associated with a raise in phosphorylation of the titin isoforms N2BA and N2B.</s><s>Concomitantly, the passive force was lower in single isolated cardiomyocytes from STZ 1 PLX versus from STZ mice, which led to an improvement of LV diastolic relaxation.</s><s>We conclude that i.v.</s><s>PLX injection improves diabetes mellitus-associated diastolic performance via decreasing cardiomyocyte stiffness.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p><s>Chronic heart failure in diabetic patients can be caused by a clinical entity referred as "diabetic cardiomyopathy", which takes place in the absence of hypertension and coronary artery disease, and is among other features characterized by interstitial inflammation <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, interstitial and perivascular fibrosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, impaired vascularization <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, endothelial dysfunction <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, and cardiomyocyte stiffness <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>.</s><s>Several lines of evidence demonstrate that impaired left ventricular (LV) diastolic relaxation represents the earliest preclinical manifestation of diabetic cardiomyopathy and indicate that it can progress to symptomatic heart failure <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">7]</ref>.</s><s>Due to the impairment in LV diastolic performance, diabetic patients are more prone to heart failure after myocardial infarction <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[8]</ref> and have a poorer prognosis on heart failure development <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">10]</ref>.</s><s>Impaired LV diastolic performance is attributed to excessive collagen deposition <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">12]</ref> and cardiomyocyte stiffness <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">14]</ref>, of which the latter has recently been shown to be sufficient to induce diastolic dysfunction without any involvement of the extracellular matrix <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[15]</ref>.</s><s>Evidence shows that endothelial dysfunction <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[16]</ref> and vascular rarefaction <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[17]</ref> underlie impaired diastolic relaxation and particularly a systemic, low-grade inflammation contributes to diastolic LV dysfunction <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[18]</ref> through coronary microvascular endothelial activation, which alters paracrine signalling to cardiomyocytes and predisposes them to high diastolic stiffness <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[19]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Mesenchymal stromal cells (MSC) are an attractive cell type for cell therapy given their immunomodulatory <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[20]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[21]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[22]</ref>, antifibrotic <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[21]</ref>, proangiogenic <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[23]</ref>, endothelial-protective features <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[24]</ref> and their ability to be used allogenically <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[25]</ref>.</s><s>With respect to diabetes mellitus, MSC have been shown to exert anti-diabetic effects and to improve experimental diabetic cardiomyopathy <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">27]</ref>.</s><s>However, the effect of MSC on the onset of diabetic cardiomyopathy and ON its preclinical manifestation-diastolic dysfunction-HAS not been unraveled so far.</s><s>Placental-derived MSC-like cells, termed PLX, are stable adhesive stromal cells isolated from full-term human placentas, cultured on carriers, and expanded in a bioreactor <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[28]</ref>.</s><s>They can be expanded in vitro without phenotypic or karyotypic changes <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[28]</ref> and have already been successfully used for the treatment of experimental hind limb ischemia <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[24]</ref> and myocardial infarction <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[23]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The aims of the present study were to investigate whether intravenous (i.v.) application of PLX could improve diabetes mellitus-associated impaired LV diastolic relaxation at the early onset of diabetic cardiomyopathy and to analyze underlying mechanisms.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MATERIALS AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PLX Cell Preparation</head><p><s>The details of the PLX production process have been described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[28]</ref>.</s><s>In brief, full-term human donor placentas were processed at Pluristem Ltd., Haifa (Israel).</s><s>Adherent cells were first selected and grown in two-dimensional culture flasks for approximately 1 month and later expanded in a dedicated bioreactor system on a fibrous carrier material for 1 week.</s><s>Cells were shipped frozen, thawed immediately prior to the experiment, and injected in vivo without further cultivation steps as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[23]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PLX Characterization</head><p><s>PLX cells were thawed, washed, resuspended in FACS buffer (phosphate buffered saline (PBS); Biochrom, Berlin, Germany) with 1% FBS), and aliquoted for immunostaining ($200,000 cells per tube).</s><s>Manufacturer recommended concentrations of fluorescein (FITC)-or phycoerythrin (PE)-conjugated mouse anti-human monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) (Becton Dickinson, Heidelberg, Germany) of interest (mesenchymal markers endothelial and leukocyte markers or their isotypes) were added, and cells were incubated at room temperature for 15 minutes.</s><s>Cells were washed twice before they were subjected to flow cytometry in a Beckman Coulter FC-500 system.</s><s>Representative flow cytometry charts of PLX are illustrated in Supporting Information Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Animals</head><p><s>Diabetes mellitus was induced in 8-to 9-week-old male C57BL6/J mice from the Forschungseinrichtung f€ ur Experimentelle Medizin (FEM; Berlin) by streptozotocin (STZ; Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) application (i.p.; 50 mg/kg body weight) during 5 subsequent days.</s><s>10 6 PLX or saline were randomly i.v.</s><s>injected 1 week after the first STZ injection.</s><s>Nondiabetic controls received PSB instead of STZ.</s><s>Fourteen days after PLX application or saline injection, mice were hemodynamically characterized and subsequently sacrificed.</s><s>After euthanization of mice, LV tissues were excised, immediately snap frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at 2808C for molecular biology and immunohistological analyses.</s><s>For the evaluation of immunomodulatory mechanisms, blood was collected and the spleen isolated.</s><s>To evaluate the engraftment of PLX after i.v.</s><s>injection, the left ventricle, spleen, lung, kidney, liver, and pancreas were collected, snap frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at 2808C for molecular biology.</s><s>The investigation conformed to the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals published in the European legislation (Directive 2010/63/EU) and was approved by the local ethics committee (Landesamt f€ ur Gesundheit und Soziales, Tierschutz, Berlin).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Blood Glucose</head><p><s>Blood glucose levels were measured with a commercial kit (MBL International, Woburn, MA) according to the manufacturer's protocol.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Assessment of PLX Engraftment</head><p><s>The engraftment of PLX in the left ventricle, lung, kidney, liver, spleen, and pancreas after i.v.</s><s>application was determined according to the method of McBride et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[29]</ref>, slightly modified, as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[30]</ref>.</s><s>In brief, genomic DNA was extracted from frozen tissues as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[31]</ref>.</s><s>A standard curve was generated using human genomic DNA obtained from HUVEC serially diluted over a 100,000-fold dilution range, into murine spleen genomic DNA.</s><s>Real-time PCR was performed with 800 ng of target DNA, Alu specific primers and a fluorescent probe <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[29]</ref>.</s><s>Values are expressed as percentage of human DNA per 800 ng (phosphate buffered saline (PBS); Biochrom, Berlin, Germany) of murine tissue.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Immunohistology</head><p><s>Immunohistochemistry was carried out on 5 mm-thick cryosections using following antibodies: anti-collagen I (Chemicon, Limburg/Lahn, Germany), anti-collagen III (Merck Millipore, Darmstadt, Germany), anti-CD68 (Abcam, Cambridge, U.K.), anti-CD3 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Heidelberg, Germany) anti-CD4 (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA), and anti-CD8a (BD Biosciences).</s><s>Analysis of stained sections was made in a blinded fashion by digital image analysis on a Leica DMRB microscope (Leica Microsystems, Wetzlar, Germay) at 3200 magnification.</s><s>Artery and arteriole density was measured using immunohistochemistry with an anti-a-smooth muscle actin (SMA) antibody (1:200, Abcam).</s><s>Microscopy was performed on a Leica DM2000 light microscope.</s><s>Arteries and arterioles were counted in 10 high power fields (hpf) per animal at a magnification of 3100.</s><s>The density is presented as number of arteries or arterioles per hpf.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gene Expression Analysis</head><p><s>RNA was isolated using the RNeasy Mini Kit according to the manufacturer's protocol (Qiagen GmbH, Hilden, Germany), followed by cDNA synthesis.</s><s>To assess the mRNA expression of the target genes vascular cell adhesion molecule (VCAM)-1, transforming growth factor (TGF)-b1, interferon (IFN)-g, vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), and L32, real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) (Eppendorf Mastercycler epgradient realplex, Hamburg, Germany) was performed using gene expression assays for VCAM-1: Mm01320970_m1, TGF-ß: Mm00441724_m1, interferon-g (IFN-g): Mm00801778_m1, and VEGF: Mm01281447_m1 from Applied Biosystems.</s><s>mRNA expression was normalized to the housekeeping gene L32 and relatively expressed with the control group set as 1.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cell Culture</head><p><s>PLX were cultured at a density of 6,000 cells per cm 2 in DMEM medium containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) (Biochrom, Berlin, Germany).</s><s>Human cardiac fibroblasts (Cell Applications, Inc.</s><s>San Diego, CA) were propagated and cultured in Lung/Cardiac Fibroblasts Basal Medium (Cell Applications, Inc.</s><s>San DiegoCA) plus supplements (Cell Applications).</s><s>Cardiac fibroblasts at passage 4 or 5 were plated at a cell density of 10,000 cells per 96-well or 135,000 cells per 6-well in Lung/Cardiac Fibroblasts Basal Medium (Cell Applications) plus supplements (Cell Applications).</s><s>Twenty-four hours later, cells were washed, and cells were cultured in the presence of standard or conditioned PLX medium with or without 10 ng/ml of transforming growth factor-b1 (TGF-b1) (R&amp;D Systems) for 24 hours for crystal violet, Sirius Red staining, or a-SMA flow cytometry.</s></p><p><s>Human umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVEC) were propagated and cultured in endothelial basal medium (EBM)-2 basal medium (Lonza Walkersville, Walkersville, MD) with endothelial cell growth medium (EGM)-2 supplements (Lonza).</s><s>HUVEC at passage 4 or 5 were plated at a cell density of 125,000 cells per 6-well (adhesion assay), 150,000 cells per 6-well (flow cytometry, Western blot) or 10,000 cells per 96-well (caspase 3/7 activity assay) in EBM-2 Medium (Lonza) plus supplements (Lonza).</s><s>Twenty-four hours later, cells were washed and cultured in the presence of standard or conditioned normo-or hyperglycemic PLX medium for 24 hours for DAF-FM (NO) or CMH 2 DCFDA (reactive oxygen species; ROS) flow cytometry, Western blot, or collected for adhesion assay.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Preparation of PLX-Conditioned Medium</head><p><s>PLX were plated at a density of 150,000 cells per 6-well in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM) medium containing 10% FBS.</s><s>After 24 hours, the medium was removed, cells were washed with PBS, and 1 ml of normo-or hyperglycemic EBM-2 medium with supplements (PLX-conditioned medium for endothelial cells) or 1 ml of standard PLX medium with or without 10 ng/ml of TGF-b1 (PLX-conditioned medium for cardiac fibroblasts) was added on the cells.</s><s>In parallel, normo-or hyperglycemic EBM-2 medium or standard PLX medium with or without 10 ng/ml of TGF-b1 was added to wells without cells.</s><s>These media served as respective controls.</s><s>Twenty-four hours later, the medium was collected, centrifuged to discard cellular debris, and stored at 2808C until use.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Coculture of Fibroblasts with Splenocytes</head><p><s>Murine C4 fibroblasts were plated at a cell density of 10,000 cells per 96-well in Basal Iscove medium supplemented with 10% FBS and 1% penicillin/streptomycin. Twenty-four hours after plating, medium was removed and splenocytes isolated from control 1 PBS, control 1 PLX, STZ 1 PBS, and STZ 1 PLX mice, according to Van Linthout et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[20]</ref>, were added to the fibroblasts at a ratio of 10 splenic cells to 1 fibroblast in RPMI medium 10% FBS, 1% penicillin/ streptomycin, as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[21]</ref>.</s><s>After 3 days, splenocytes were removed and Sirius Red staining was performed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sirius Red Staining</head><p><s>Sirius Red staining of fibroblasts was performed as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[32]</ref>.</s><s>In brief, fibroblasts were fixed in methanol overnight at 2208C, washed once with PBS and incubated in 0.1% Direct Red 80 (Sirius Red; Sigma Aldrich) staining solution at room temperature for 1 hour.</s><s>After a second wash with PBS, the Sirius red staining of the fibroblasts was eluted in 0.1N sodium hydroxide at room temperature for 1 hour on a rocking platform.</s><s>The optical density representative for the accumulation of collagen I and III was measured at 540 nm on a SpectraMax 340PC microplate reader (Molecular Device GmbH, Biberach an der Rib, Germany).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Western Blot</head><p><s>Twenty-four hours after culture in standard or conditioned normoor hyperglycemic PLX medium, HUVEC were lysed in lysis buffer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA) supplemented with proteinase inhibitors (Roche).</s><s>An equal amount of protein (40 mg) was loaded into 12% sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS)-polyacrylamide gels.</s><s>Total endothelial nitric oxide synthase ([Enos] BD Biosciences) and b tubulin (Santa Cruz Biotechnology) were detected with each specific antibody, followed by incubation with an IR dye secondary antibody (LI-COR Biosciences, Lincoln, NE).</s><s>The blots were visualized with Odyssey (LI-COR Biosciences).</s><s>Quantitative analysis of the intensity of the bands was performed with Odyssey V3.0 software, as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">34]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Caspase 3/7 Activity Assay</head><p><s>Twenty-four hours after culture in 100 ml of standard or conditioned normo-or hyperglycemic PLX medium, caspase 3/7 activity was determined with a Caspase Glo 3/7 activity kit (Promega, Madison, WI) according to the manufacturer's protocol.</s><s>Luminescence was measured in a microplate-reading luminometer (Mithras LB 940, Berthold Technologies GmbH &amp; Co KG, Germany) as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[33]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adhesion Assay</head><p><s>HUVEC, 24 hours cultured in standard or conditioned normo-or hyperglycemic PLX medium, were plated at a cell density of 40,000 cells/96-well in PBS for 2 hours on 96-well plates precoated with 2.5 mg/ml fibronectin (Sigma Aldrich).</s><s>Medium and cells were removed and wells were next twice washed with warm PBS, followed by fixation with paraformaldehyde and crystal violet staining.</s><s>The absorbance was next measured at 495 nm on a Spec-traMax 340PC microplate reader (Molecular Device GmbH).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tube Formation</head><p><s>HUVEC (20,000 cells per well) were resuspended in normo-or hyperglycemic EBM-2 medium, or conditioned full normo-or hyperglycemic PLX medium (see preparation of conditioned medium) and plated on top of a matrigel (BD Biosciencs).</s><s>Twentyfour hours after seeding, pictures of eight fields per condition were taken at magnification 35 and send to Wimasis for analysis via WimTube software (Wimasis GmbH, M€ unchen, Germany).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Flow Cytometry</head><p><s>Flow cytometry analysis of blood mononuclear cells (MNCs) isolated with Histopaque 1083 (Sigma Aldrich) and cardiac fibroblasts was performed using directly conjugated monoclonal antibodies.</s><s>The a-SMA antibody was purchased from BD Biosciences (Franklin Lakes, NJ).</s><s>The mouse Treg detection kit containg CD4, CD25, FoxP3 antibodies, fixation, and wash solutions was purchased from Miltenyi Biotec (Bergisch Gladbach, Germany).</s><s>Surface staining was performed according to the manufacturer's instructions.</s><s>MNCs were first stained with anti-mouse CD4 and CD25 antibodies, and after fixation, intracellular FOXP3 staining was performed.</s><s>MNC samples were acquired on a MACSQuant Analyzer (Miltenyi Biotec), and cardiac fibroblast samples on fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) BD FACSCanto II with BD FACSDiva software version 6.1.3.</s><s>For the analysis of NO and ROS in HUVEC, cells were stained with 5 lM of DAF-FM Diacetate (4-amino-5-methylamino-2 0 ,7 0 -difluorofluorescein diacetate, Thermo Fisher Scientific) or of CM-H 2 DCFDA (5-(and-6)-chloromethyl-2 0 ,7 0 -dichlorodihydrofluorescein diacetate, acety ester) (Thermo Fisher Scientific) in PBS, respectively, and incubated for 30 minutes at 378C, as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[20]</ref>.</s><s>Next, cells were washed with 200 ml of PBS and after resuspending in fresh PBS, incubated for an additional 30 minutes at 378C.</s><s>Flow cytometry analysis was performed on a MACSQuant Analyzer (Miltenyi Biotec).</s><s>Analysis of flow cytometry data was performed using FlowJo software version 8.8.6.</s><s>(Tree Star Inc.).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Titin Isoform Separation</head><p><s>Titin isoforms were separated as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[13]</ref>.</s><s>Tissue samples were solubilized in 50 mM Tris SDS buffer (pH 6.8) containing 8 lg/ml leupeptin (Peptin Institute, Japan) and phosphatase inhibitor cocktail (PIC [P2880], 10 ll/ml; Sigma Aldrich).</s><s>Samples were heated for 3 minutes at 968C and centrifuged.</s><s>Then, samples (20 lg) were separated on agarose-strengthened 1.8% sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gels.</s><s>The gel was run at 5 mA constant current for 16 hours.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>All-Titin Phosphorylation by Pro-Q Diamond Stain</head><p><s>The phosphorylation state of cardiac titin isoforms, N2BA and N2B, was determined using Pro-Q Diamond phosphoprotein stain (Thermo Fisher Scientific).</s><s>To preserve the endogenous phosphorylation state of the proteins, frozen tissues from LV mouse hearts were solubilized and treated as described above in the Titin Isoform Separation section.</s><s>The gels were stained for 1 hour with Pro-Q Diamond phosphoprotein stain.</s><s>Fixation, washing, and destaining were performed according to the manufacturer's guidelines (Thermo Fisher Scientific).</s><s>To assess total protein content, gels were stained overnight with SYPRO Ruby (Thermo Fisher Scientific).</s><s>Staining was visualized using the LAS-4000 Image Reader (460 nm/605 nm Ex/Em; 2 seconds illumination), and signals were analyzed with Multi Gauge V3.2 and AIDA software.</s><s>Titin-isoform phosphorylation was expressed in relative numbers, assuming that the combined phosphorylation of N2BA 1 N2B titin in control samples is 100%.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Myocardial Protein Kinase G Activity</head><p><s>Myocardial protein kinase G (PKG) activity was assessed in homogenized tissue samples.</s><s>Tissues samples were homogenized in 25 mmol/l Tris (pH 7.4), 1 mmol/l EDTA, 2 mmol/l EGTA, 5 mmol/l dithiothreitol (DTT), 0.05% Triton X-100, and protease inhibitor cocktail (Sigma Aldrich) and centrifuged for 5 minutes.</s><s>Supernatants containing equal amounts of total protein were analyzed for PKG activity.</s><s>The reaction mixture contained (at final concentration): 40 mmol/l Tris-HCl (pHÁ7.4),</s><s>20 mmol/l magnesium acetate, 0.2 mmol/l [32P] ATP (500-1,000 c.p.m.Ápmol 21 ) (GE Healthcare LifeScience, Little Chalfont, U.K.), 113 mg/ml heptapeptide (RKRSRAE), 3 mmol/l cGMP (Promega, Madison, WI) and a highly specific inhibitor of cAMP-dependent protein kinase (5-24, Merck Millipore).</s><s>The reaction mixtures were incubated at 308C for 10 minutes, followed by termination of the reaction by spotting 70Áll of the reaction mix onto Whatman P-81 filters, which were then soaked with 75Ámmol/l H 3 PO 4 for 5 minutes and washed three times with 75Ámmol/l H 3 PO 4 to remove any unbound [32P] ATP.</s><s>Filters were rinsed with 100% ethanol and air dried before quantification.</s><s>For quantification of PKG activity, counts were taken in a Wallac 1409 Liquid Scintillation Counter using universal scintillation cocktail.</s><s>Specific activity of PKG was expressed as pmol of [ 32 P] incorporated into the substrate (pmol/minute/mg protein).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Myocardial Protein Kinase A and C Activity</head><p><s>Protein kinase A (PKA) and protein kinase C (PKC) activity was analyzed using a nonradioactive PKA and PKC kinase activity assay kit (Enzo Life Science).</s><s>Samples were homogenized in cell lysis buffer (20 mmol/l MOPS, 50 mmol/l b-glycerolphosphate, 50 mmol/l sodium fluoride, 1 mmol/l sodium vanadate, 5 mmol/l EGTA, 2 mmol/L EDTA, 1% NP40, 1 mmol/l DTT, 1 mmol/l benzamidine, 1 mmol/l phenylmethanesulphonylfluoride, and 10 lg/ml leupeptin and aprotinin, each).</s><s>Supernatants were collected after centrifugation at 13.000 rpm for 30 minutes.</s><s>Supernatants containing equal amounts of total protein (30 ng/ll protein aliquots were assayed according to manufacturer's instructions) were added into the appropriate wells of the substrate microliter plate.</s><s>The kinase reaction was initiated by addition of ATP, and samples were subsequently incubated at 308C for 90 minutes.</s><s>Phosphorylated peptide substrates were recognized by phosphospecific substrate antibody.</s><s>The phosphospecific antibody was subsequently bound by a peroxidase conjugated secondary antibody anti-rabbit IgG:HRP.</s><s>The assay was developed with tetramethylbenzidine, and the intensity of the color was measured in a microplate reader at 450 nm.</s><s>Results of triplicate determinations were averaged, and specific activity of the kinase was expressed as ng/ll.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ca 21 Calmodulin Dependent Protein Kinase II Activity</head><p><s>Ca 21 calmodulin dependent protein kinase II (CaMKII) activity was determined using a CycLex CaMKII assay kit (CY-1173; MBL Corporation, MA) according to the manufacturer's guidelines.</s><s>Briefly, frozen tissues were homogenized in sample buffer containing 15% glycerol, 62.5 mmol/l Tris; pH 6.8; 1% (wt/vol) SDS, protease inhibitor, and protein phosphatase inhibitor, all prepared in distilled H 2 O. Homogenates were centrifuged at 10.000g for 15 minutes at 48C.</s><s>The supernatant was removed and stored at 2808C.</s><s>Protein samples were loaded onto microtiter wells (concentration, $2.0 lg per well) coated with CaMKII specific substrate, syntide-2, along with kinase reaction buffer with or without Ca 21 /calmodulin.</s><s>To quantify CaMKII activity, a standard curve correlating the amount of active CaMKII and the level of phosphorylation of syntide-2 was constructed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Passive Force</head><p><s>Force measurements were performed on single skinned cardiomyocytes as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[35,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">36]</ref>.</s><s>Briefly, samples were defrozen in relaxing solution (in mmol/l: free Mg, 1; KCl, 100; EGTA, 2; Mg-ATP, 4; imidazole, 10; pH 7.0), mechanically disrupted and incubated for 5 minutes in relaxing solution supplemented with 0.5% Triton X-100.</s><s>The cell suspension was washed 5 times in relaxing solution.</s><s>Single cardiomyocytes were selected under an inverted microscope (Zeiss Axiovert 135, 340 objective, Oberkochen, Germany) and attached with silicone adhesive between a force transducer and a piezoelectric motor as part of a "Permeabilized Myocyte Test System" (1600A; with force transducer 403A; Aurora Scientific, Aurora, Ontario, Canada).</s><s>Cardiomyocyte F passive was measured in relaxing buffer at room temperature within a sarcomere-length range between 1.9 and 2.4 lm.</s><s>Force values were normalized to myocyte cross-sectional area calculated from the diameter of the cells, assuming a circular shape.</s><s>As a test of cell viability, each cardiomyocyte was also transferred from relaxing to maximally activating solution (pCa4.5), at which isometric force developed.</s><s>Once a steady state force was reached, the cell was shortened within 1 ms to 80% of its original length to determine baseline force.</s><s>Only cells developing active forces &gt;20 kN/ m 2 were included in the analysis.</s><s>The passive tension values shown were measured at the end of each stretch step and thus consisted of both the viscous and the elastic force component.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hemodynamic Measurements</head><p><s>Fourteen days after i.v.</s><s>PLX injection, mice were anesthetized (0.8-1.2 g/kg urethane and 0.05 mg/kg buprenorphine i.p.), intubated, and artificially ventilated with a rodent ventilator type 7025 (Ugo Basile, Comerio VA, Italy).</s><s>A 1.2F micro-tip catheter (Scisense Inc., Ontario, Canada) was positioned in the LV through the apex in an open chest model.</s><s>Heart rate and LV contractility, measured by the peak rate of LV pressure rise dP/dt max were measured.</s><s>Diastolic performance was measured by the peak rate of LV pressure decrease dP/dt min and the time constant of LV relaxation Tau (s).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Analysis</head><p><s>Statistical analysis was performed using Prism 7 for Mac OS X (GraphPad Software, Inc., La Jolla, CA).</s><s>Ordinary one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used for statistical analysis of the data with correction for multiple comparisons via the Tukey test or as stated elsewhere.</s><s>Data are presented as mean 6 SEM.</s><s>Differences were considered to be significant when the two-sided p value was lower than .05.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Engraftment of PLX After Intravenous Injection</head><p><s>We evaluated the presence of PLX in the left ventricle, lung, kidney, liver, spleen, and pancreas at the day of sacrifice, 14 days after i.v PLX application in control and STZ-induced diabetic mice via the detection of human Alu sequences (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>PLX were retrieved in all analyzed tissues.</s><s>Interestingly, STZ-induced diabetes mellitus raised the engraftment of PLX to the left ventricle, lung, kidney, pancreas, and tendentiously to the spleen as obviated by 4.5-fold (p &lt; .005),</s><s>19-fold (p &lt; .005),</s><s>4.7-fold (p &lt; .05),</s><s>47-fold (p &lt; .05),</s><s>and 2.4-fold (p 5 .1694)</s><s>higher PLX presence in respective tissues of diabetic compared with control mice.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PLX Exert Anti-Inflammatory/Immunomodulatory Effects in Streptozotocin-Induced Diabetic Mice</head><p><s>Given the immunomodulatory properties of MSC <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">[37]</ref> and the importance of cardiac inflammation in diabetic cardiomyopathy <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[38]</ref>, we next evaluated whether i.v.</s><s>PLX application decreased cardiac inflammation in STZ-induced diabetic mice.</s><s>In this STZ diabetic model of low-grade inflammation with no increased cardiac presence of CD68 macrophages, CD31, CD41, and CD81 T lymphocytes (Supporting Information Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>), PLX application downregulated the 1.8-fold (p &lt; .0001)</s><s>STZ-induced increase in LV VCAM-1 expression to levels not significantly different from controls (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>) and led to a 1.8-fold (p &lt; .05)</s><s>and 3.1-fold (p &lt; .05)</s><s>decrease in STZ-induced transforming growth factor-b1 (TGF-b1) and IFN-g mRNA expression (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>, 2C), respectively.</s><s>Systemically, PLX induced the percentage of circulating regulatory T cells (CD4 1 CD25 1 FoxP31 cells) by 1.6-fold in STZ mice (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>).</s><s>PLX application did not reduce blood glucose levels (control: 7.5 6 0.85; STZ: 24 6 3.0; control PLX: 4.6 6 0.72; STZ PLX: 24 6 2.9; p &lt; .0001</s><s>STZ vs. control).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PLX Exert Antifibrotic Effects</head><p><s>Given the relevance of cardiac fibrosis in diabetic cardiomyopathy <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> and the antifibrotic potential of MSC <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[21]</ref>, we further evaluated whether PLX also exert antifibrotic effects.</s><s>Therefore, we first examined in vitro whether PLX decrease collagen deposition and the expression of the myofibroblast marker a-SMA in cardiac fibroblasts in a paracrine manner.</s><s>Addition of the pro-fibrotic factor TGF-b1 to cardiac fibroblasts induced collagen deposition and a-SMA expression by 1.2-fold (p &lt; .001)</s><s>and 1.5-fold (p &lt; .001),</s><s>respectively.</s><s>In contrast, collagen deposition and a-SMA expression was 1.7-fold (p &lt; .0001)</s><s>and 2.3-fold (p &lt; .0001)</s><s>lower in cardiac fibroblasts supplemented with PLX 1 TGF-b1 conditioned medium compared with TGF-b1 medium (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A, 3B</ref>), respectively.</s><s>Given the link between inflammation and fibrosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">[39]</ref> and the relevance of the cardiosplenic axis, that is, the homing of immune cells from the spleen toward the heart and their subsequent involvement in cardiac remodeling <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[40]</ref>, we next evaluated whether the PLX-mediated immunomodulatory effect could influence fibroblast collagen production.</s><s>Therefore, splenocytes of all in vivo experimental groups were cocultured with murine fibroblasts and their impact on collagen deposition of murine fibroblasts was determined (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C</ref>).</s><s>Supplementation of splenocytes from control mice did not induce collagen production compared with monocultured fibroblasts.</s><s>In contrast, addition of STZ splenocytes to fibroblasts raised collagen production by 16% (p &lt; .001)</s><s>versus monocultured fibroblasts.</s><s>STZ 1 PLX splenocytes did not induce collagen production compared with monocultured fibroblasts or fibroblasts cocultured with control splenocytes (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>).</s><s>Finally, we evaluated the impact of i.v.</s><s>PLX application on cardiac fibrosis in STZ mice via immunohistochemistry. Concomitant with the low cardiac inflammation, cardiac fibrosis was not prominent at this stage of diabetic cardiomyopathy, as indicated by no STZ-induced accumulation of collagen I and III (Supporting Information Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PLX Improve Vascularization in Streptozotocin-Induced Diabetic Mice</head><p><s>Endothelial inflammation and impaired vascularization underlie diastolic dysfunction <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">41]</ref>.</s><s>On the other hand, PLX have endothelial-protective and proangiogenic properties <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">24]</ref>.</s><s>Therefore, we next explored the endothelial-protective and proangiogenic potential of PLX in STZ-induced diabetic mice and under hyperglycemic conditions.</s><s>In STZ mice, LV mRNA expression of VEGF was 2.1-fold (p &lt; .05)</s><s>lower versus nondiabetic control mice, whereas STZ 1 PLX mice exhibited 2.2-fold (p &lt; .05)</s><s>higher LV VEGF mRNA expression compared with STZ mice (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4A</ref>).</s><s>In parallel, LV arteriole density was 1.4-fold (p &lt; .0001)</s><s>lower in STZ versus control mice and 1.2-fold (p &lt; .05)</s><s>higher in the STZ mice receiving PLX compared with untreated STZ mice (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B, 4C</ref>).</s><s>Artery density was comparable in STZ versus control mice (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B-4D</ref>).</s><s>In vitro, hyperglycemia resulted in a 1.6-fold (p &lt; .01)</s><s>increase in eNOS expression, which was not altered in HUVEC cultured with conditioned hyperglycemic PLX medium (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4E</ref>).</s><s>The hyperglycemia-induced eNOS expression did not affect NO production in HUVEC (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4F</ref>), but led to a 1.6-fold (p &lt; .0001)</s><s>rise in ROS (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4G</ref>).</s><s>This increase in oxidative stress was not associated with prominent endothelial apoptosis (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4H</ref>), but reflected in a 1.1fold (p &lt; .05)</s><s>reduced adhesion capacity of HUVEC (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4I</ref>) and impaired tube formation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4J-4M</ref>) as indicated by 3.0-fold (p &lt; .0001),</s><s>1.7-fold (p &lt; .0001),</s><s>and 1.5-fold (p &lt; .001)</s><s>decreased total branching points, total tubes, and tube length, respectively.</s><s>PLX abrogated the hyperglycemia-triggered ROS in a paracrine manner by 1.2-fold (p &lt; .0001),</s><s>which was paralleled by a 1.2-fold (p 5 0.13) lower caspase 3/7 activity (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4H</ref>), a 1.2-fold (p &lt; .001)</s><s>higher adhesion capacity (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4I</ref>) and improved tube formation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4J-4M</ref>) as shown by 1.9-fold (p &lt; .05),</s><s>1.4-fold (p &lt; .01),</s><s>and 1.3-fold (p &lt; .05)</s><s>higher total branching points, total tubes, and tube length in HUVEC cultured in hyperglycemic PLX condition medium compared with hyperglycemic medium alone, respectively.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PLX Decrease Cardiomyocyte Stiffness and Improve Diastolic Relaxation in Streptozotocin-Induced Diabetic Mice</head><p><s>Given the importance of cardiac titin dysregulation and cardiomyocyte stiffness in diastolic dysfunction <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[13]</ref>, the impact of PLX on cardiac titin phosphorylation and cardiomyocyte passive tension was investigated.</s><s>PLX elevated the STZ-impaired phosphorylation state of titin isoforms N2BA and N2B by 3.3-fold (p &lt; .0005)</s><s>and 6.1-fold (p &lt; .0001),</s><s>respectively, to values not different from controls (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5A-5C</ref>).</s><s>Concomitantly, PLX restored the diabetesdownregulated PKA and PKG activity by 1.2-fold (p &lt; .05)</s><s>and 1.8-fold (p &lt; .05) to control values (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5D, 5E</ref>), respectively, and tendencially increased the diabetes-downregulated CaMKII activity (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5F</ref>).</s><s>Protein kinase C activity was not different among the groups (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5G</ref>).</s><s>In parallel, passive force in single isolated cardiomyocytes from STZ 1 PLX mice was comparable to control mice and was lower than diabetes-induced passive force of cardiomyocytes from STZ mice (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5H</ref>).</s><s>In vivo, STZ 1 PLX mice showed an improved diastolic function compared with STZ diabetic mice as indicated by the heart-rate independent 1.2-fold (p &lt; .005)</s><s>lower time constant of LV relaxation parameter Tau and the 1.2-fold (p &lt; .05)</s><s>increase of the relaxation parameter dP/dt min (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5I,  5J</ref>).</s><s>As known for the early time point in the STZ animal model <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[42]</ref>, LV contractility was slightly reduced in both STZ-groups versus controls (STZ: 15% and STZ1 PLX: 13% versus controls; p 5 NS), but did not differ significantly between the four groups.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>The salient finding of the present study is that i.v.</s><s>PLX application reduces cardiomyocyte stiffness and improves LV diastolic relaxation in an early phase of STZ-induced diabetic mice.</s><s>Endothelial dysfunction <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[16]</ref>, impaired vascularization <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, microvascular inflammation [43], cardiac fibrosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">12]</ref>, and cardiomyocyte stiffness <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[15]</ref> all underlie impaired LV diastolic relaxation, one of the first clinical signs of diabetic cardiomyopathy.</s><s>In this model of low-grade STZ-induced diabetes mellitus, i.v.</s><s>PLX application improved LV diastolic relaxation and cardiomyocyte stiffness without affecting glucose levels.</s><s>PLX reduced the diabetes-associated low-grade inflammation as indicated by the decrease in diabetesinduced LV TGF-b1 and IFN-g expression, and the increase of blood regulatory T cells, which have on their own vascularprotective <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">[44,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">45]</ref> and antifibrotic features <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">[46]</ref>.</s><s>Cardiac fibrosis was not yet pronounced in this STZ-induced diabetes mellitus model.</s><s>Nevertheless, splenocytes of STZ mice displayed already a higher pro-fibrotic potential compared with splenocytes of control mice, which follows from their higher capacity to induce collagen deposition in murine fibroblasts upon coculture relative to control splenocytes, an effect, which could previously also be observed with splenocytes from ob/ob versus control mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">[47]</ref>.</s><s>The profibrotic splenocyte activity of STZ mice was abolished in STZ mice receiving PLX, indicating the immunomodulatory and antifibrotic potential of PLX under diabetic conditions.</s><s>These findings are supported by observations in myocarditis mice, where splenocytes from Coxsackievirus B3-infected mice injected with MSC induced less collagen production compared with splenocytes from Coxsackievirus B3 mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[21]</ref>, be it now in a diabetic setting.</s><s>Given the importance of the cardiosplenic axis <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">[40]</ref>, these findings foresee that i.v.</s><s>PLX application may counteract the cardiac fibrogenesis process during the pathogenesis of diabetic cardiomyopathy in this systemic manner, that is, independently from their, as also shown in vitro, direct paracrine antifibrotic potential.</s></p><p><s>In agreement with previously demonstrated endothelialprotective and proangiogenic features of PLX in experimental models of hind limb ischemia <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[24]</ref> and myocardial infarction <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">[23]</ref>, PLX further decreased the LV VCAM-1 expression and reinstated the diabetes-downregulated LV VEGF expression and arteriole density in STZ mice.</s><s>In vitro experiments with hyperglycemic PLX conditioned medium support that PLX restore the hyperglycemiaimpaired vascularization in a paracrine manner as indicated by the increased tube formation (total branching points, tubes and tube length) of HUVEC cultured in hyperglycemic PLX conditioned medium versus hyperglycemic medium.</s><s>In parallel, hyperglycemic PLX conditioned medium raised the adhesion potential of endothelial cells.</s><s>These effects were found in the presence of a decrease in hyperglycemia-induced ROS levels and unaltered NO levels compared with hyperglycemic conditions, indicative for an improved NO bioavailability <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[33,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b49">48]</ref>.</s><s>In agreement with the potential of PLX to increase NO bioavailability, PLX administration in STZ mice raised the low activity of the NO-downstream target PKG in STZ mice to levels of control mice.</s><s>Low PKG activity increases resting tension due to hypophosphorylation of titin <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">13,</ref><ref type="bibr">49</ref>].</s><s>In addition, low PKA <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">[50]</ref> and low CaMKII <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[36]</ref> activities are both associated with hypophosphorylation of titin and increased cardiomyocyte stiffness.</s><s>In contrast, increased PKC activity and subsequent PKC phosphorylation of titin's PEVK element leads to myocardial stiffness <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">[51]</ref>.</s><s>STZ mice displayed reduced cardiac PKA and CaMKII activity compared with control mice, whereas PLX recovered the diabetes-downregulated PKA activity and tendencially raised CaMKII activity in STZ mice.</s><s>PKC activity was not different among the groups.</s><s>In parallel to the restored PKG and PKA activity, the hypophosphorylation of the titin isoforms N2B and N2BA found in STZ mice was repaired in STZ PLX mice and normalized to controls.</s><s>Consequently, STZ PLX mice exhibited lower cardiomyocyte stiffness compared with STZ mice, which was further translated into ameliorated diastolic relaxation as shown by an improvement in Tau and the relaxation parameter dP/dt min .</s><s>Our findings are consistent with the postulated paradigm that comorbidities including diabetes mellitus induce a systemic pro-inflammatory state, which triggers endothelial inflammation, which in turn reduces NO bioavailability and PKG activity in adjacent cardiomyocytes leading to cardiomyocyte stiffness <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[41]</ref> and/or provoke cardiac fibrosis.</s><s>In obese, diabetic ZSF1 rats, diastolic dysfunction is present due to cardiomyocyte stiffness in the absence of cardiac fibrosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[13]</ref>.</s><s>Similarly, at this early Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of AlphaMed Press stage of STZ-induced diabetic cardiomyopathy without signs of cardiac fibrosis, cardiomyocyte stiffness underlied the diastolic stiffness, which could be improved via i.v.</s><s>PLX application.</s><s>Conform to the capacity of MSC to home to damaged tissue upon i.v.</s><s>application <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[21]</ref>, cardiac engraftment of PLX was higher in STZ compared with control mice.</s><s>In contrast to previous reports with MSC <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">[52]</ref>, no anti-diabetic effect of PLX could be observed in the STZ mice.</s><s>We suggest that the cardioprotective outcome of PLX in STZ mice are a consequence of their paracrine endothelialprotective and proangiogenic effects upon cardiac engraftment,  and their systemic extracardiac immunomodulatory effects <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">[53]</ref>, which may be of extra relevance in this model of systemic lowgrade inflammation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSION</head><p><s>In conclusion, i.v.</s><s>PLX application improves LV diastolic relaxation and cardiomyocyte stiffness at an early stage of diabetic cardiomyopathy through increased titin phosphorylation.</s><s>These findings offer new insights into the cardioprotective effects of PLX, advancing their potential use for cardiac therapies.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Engraftment of PLacenta-eXpanded (PLX) 14 days after intravenous injection.</s><s>Bar graphs represent human DNA infused as cells (%) in the left ventricle, lung, kidney, liver, spleen, and pancreas of control mice (open bars) and streptozotocin (STZ)-treated mice (closed bars) i.v.</s><s>injected with PLX.</s><s>For comparison of PLX presence per respective tissue of control versus STZ mice, an unpaired Student's t test was used with *, p &lt; .05;</s><s>**, p &lt; .005;</s><s>n 5 4/group.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,322.07,75.86,216.70,128.81" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. PLX reduce cardiac inflammation and increase blood regulatory T cells in streptozotocin-induced diabetic mice.</s><s>Bar graphs represent the mean 6 SEM of LV. (A): VCAM-1, (B): TGF-b, (C): IFN-g, with n 5 7-8/PBS groups and n 5 5-6/PLX groups, and (D): blood Treg cells, depicted as CD4CD25FoxP3 (% of CD4 cells) with n 5 4/group in control (open bars) and STZ (closed bars) mice injected with PBS or PLX, as indicated.</s><s>For all data: *, p &lt; .05;</s><s>**, p &lt; .01;</s><s>***, p &lt; .001;</s><s>****, p &lt; .0001.</s><s>Abbreviations: IFN-g, interferon-g; PLX, placenta-expanded cell; STZ, streptozotocin; TGF-b1, transforming growth factor-b1; Treg, regulatory T cells; VCAM, vascular cell adhesion molecule.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,96.15,75.86,420.80,175.47" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. PLX exert antifibrotic effects in vitro.</s><s>PLX conditioned medium reduces TGF-b1-induced collagen deposition and a-SMA expression in cardiac fibroblasts.</s><s>Bar graphs represent the mean 6 SEM of (A) the absorbance at 540 nm detected after Sirus Red staining, depicting collagen deposition, and (B) a-SMA expression of cardiac fibroblasts cultured in PLX medium, PLX medium 1 TGF-b1, PLX conditioned (cond.)</s><s>medium, or PLX cond.</s><s>medium 1 TGF-b1 as indicated, with open bars representing without TGF-b1 and black bars with TGF-b1 conditions, and n 5 6/group.</s><s>Splenocytes derived from STZ PLX mice induce lower collagen deposition in murine fibroblasts upon coculture compared with splenocytes from STZ mice.</s><s>(C): Schematic representation of the experimental set-up.</s><s>(D): Bar graph represents the mean 6 SEM of the absorbance at 540 nm detected after Sirus Red staining of fibroblasts cultured in monoculture or cocultured with splenocytes from control, STZ, control PLX, or STZ PLX mice as indicated, with n 5 5-6/group.</s><s>For all data: *, p &lt; .05;</s><s>**, p &lt; .01;</s><s>***, p &lt; .001;</s><s>****, p &lt; .0001.</s><s>Abbrevaitions: PLX, PLacenta-eXpanded cell; STZ, streptozotocin; TGF-ß1, transforming growth factor-b1.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,69.96,75.86,225.72,402.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. PLX improve hyperglycemia-impaired vascularization and endothelial function.</s><s>(A): Bar graphs represent the mean 6 SEM of LV VEGF mRNA expression in control (open bars) and STZ (closed bars) mice injected with PBS or PLX, as indicated with n 5 7/control and n 5 6/ STZ and PLX groups.</s><s>(B): Representative pictures at magnification 3100 of arteries and arterioles in the LV of control, STZ, control 1 PLX, and STZ 1 PLX mice as indicated.</s><s>Bar graphs represent the mean 6 SEM of LV (C) arteriole and (D) artery density per high power field (hpf) in control (open bars) and STZ (closed bars) mice injected with PBS or PLX, as indicated with n 5 8/control, n 5 10/STZ, n 5 5/control 1 PLX, and n 5 11/STZ 1 PLX groups.</s><s>In vitro, PLX-conditioned hyperglycemic medium modulate (E) eNOS expression, (F) NO, (G) ROS levels, and (H) caspase 3/7 activity in HUVEC, which is translated in improved (I). adhesion capacity and (J-M) tube formation versus HUVEC cultured under hyperglycemic conditions.</s><s>Bar graphs represent the mean 6 SEM of (E) eNOS expression normalized to b-tubulin and the control groups set as 100%, (F) % of DAF-positive, (G) % of DCF-positive gated cells, with all n 5 4/condition, (H) caspase 3/7 activity depicted with the normoglycemia group set as 100% with n 5 8-10/condition, and (I) adhered crystal violet-stained HUVEC depicted as the absorbance at 495 nm with n 5 5-6/condition.</s><s>(J): Representative pictures of HUVEC cultured in normo-(5 mM glucose), hyperglycemic (30 mM glucose) medium, or normo-(5 mM glucose), hyperglycemic (30 mM glucose) conditioned PLX medium, as indicated.</s><s>Bar graphs represent the mean 6 SEM of (K) total branching points, (L) total tubes, and (M) tube length analyzed from n 5 7 to 8 fields/condition.</s><s>For all data: *, p &lt; .05;</s><s>**, p &lt; .01;</s><s>***, p &lt; .001;</s><s>****, p &lt; .0001.</s><s>Abbrevaitions: eNos, endothelial nitric oxide synthase; NO, nitric oxide; ROS, reactive oxygen species, PLX, placenta-expanded cell; ROS, reactive oxygen species; STZ, streptozotocin.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,69.51,75.86,474.12,460.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. PLX restore cardiomyocyte stiffness and improve diastolic relaxation in streptozotocin-induced diabetic mice.</s><s>(A): Representative images of titin N2BA and N2B phosphoproteins and total proteins in control, STZ, control PLX, and STZ PLX mice, as indicated.</s><s>Bar graphs represent the mean 6 SEM of (B) N2BA phosphorylation and (C) N2B phosphorylation depicted as % with the control set as 100% of control (open bars) and STZ (closed bars) mice injected with PBS or PLX, as indicated with n 5 7/control, n 5 10/STZ, n 5 5-7/control 1 PLX and n 5 7-8/STZ 1 PLX groups and *, p &lt; .05;</s><s>**, p &lt; .01;</s><s>***, p &lt; .0005;</s><s>****, p &lt; .0001 of (D) PKA (ng/ml) in control (open bars) and STZ (closed bars) mice injected with PBS or PLX, as indicated with n 5 3/group and *, p &lt; .05;</s><s>(E) PKG (pmol/min/mg protein) in control (open bars) and STZ (closed bars) mice injected with PBS or PLX, as indicated with n 5 4/PBS group, n 5 3/PLX group and *, p &lt; .05,</s><s>(F) CaMKII activity (CaMKII; mU/ml) in control (open bars) and STZ (closed bars) mice injected with PBS or PLX, as indicated with n 5 5/control group, n 5 9/STZ group, and n 5 4/PLX groups, and *, p &lt; .05,</s><s>(G) PKC (ng/ml) in control (open bars) and STZ (closed bars) mice injected with PBS or PLX, as indicated with n 5 3/group and *, p &lt; .05,</s><s>(H) Passive tension F passive (kN/m2) versus sarcomere length (mm) in control (-•-), STZ (-᭺-), control 1 PLX (--), and STZ 1 PLX (-ٗ-), as indicated, with n 5 15-19 cardiomyocytes/group and *, p &lt; .05</s><s>versus control and STZ 1 PLX and §, p &lt; .05</s><s>versus control 1 PLX.</s><s>Bar graphs represent the mean 6 SEM of (I) dP/dt min and (J) Tau with n 5 8 and n 5 11 for the control and STZ groups, respectively, and *, p &lt; .05;</s><s>**, p &lt; .01;</s><s>***, p &lt;.0005 analyzed by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) without correction for multiple comparison.</s><s>Abbreviations: PKA, protein kinase A; PKC, protein kinase C; PKG, protein kinase G; PLX, placentaexpanded cell; STZ, streptozotocin.</s><s>www.StemCellsTM.com</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,87.59,77.22,438.12,523.52" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">www.StemCellsTM.com O c 2017 The Authors STEM CELLS TRANSLATIONAL MEDICINE published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. on behalf of AlphaMed Press</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>We thank Alejandro Cabezas-Cruz, Josefine Dunst, Ulrike Fritz, Kerstin Puhl, and Norbert G. Zingler for excellent technical assistance.</s><s>We acknowledge the assistance of the BCRT Flow Cytometry Lab.</s><s>This study was supported by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) funding through the Berlin-Brandenburg School for Regenerative Therapies, and by the Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies -BCRT (Bundesministerium f€ ur Bildung und Forschung -0313911) and MEDIA (The MEtabolic Road to DIAstolic Heart Failure) consortium from the Framework Programme 7 of the European Commission to C.T. and Z.A. N.H. and W.A.L. were supported by the German Research Foundation grant HA 7512/2-1.</s><s>S.V.L. was supported by the Dr. Marija Orlovic Stiftung.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</head><p><s>S.V.L.: conception and design, administrative support, collection and/or assembly of data, data analysis and interpretation, manuscript writing; N.H.: conception and design, collection and/or assembly of data; data analysis and interpretation; K.M., A.K., I.M., and L.P.: collection and/or assembly of data, data analysis and interpretation; Z.A.: financial support, final approval of manuscript; K.P.: collection and/or assembly of data; W.A.L.: data analysis and interpretation, final approval of manuscript; C.T.: conception and design, data analysis and interpretation, financial support, final approval of manuscript.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCLOSURE OF POTENTIAL CONFLICTS OF INTEREST</head><p><s>L.P. is an employee of Pluristem Therapeutics Inc. and holds stock and stock options.</s><s>Z.A. is an employee and shareholder of Pluristem Therapeutics Inc. and has intellectual property rights.</s><s>The other authors indicated no potential conflicts of interest.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human apolipoprotein A-I gene transfer reduces the development of experimental diabetic cardiomyopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Linthout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Spillmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Riad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1563" to="1573" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prevention of cardiac fibrosis and left ventricular dysfunction in diabetic cardiomyopathy in rats by transgenic expression of the human tissue kallikrein gene</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tschope</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Walther</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FASEB J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="828" to="835" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Overexpression of angiopoietin-2 impairs myocardial angiogenesis and exacerbates cardiac fibrosis in the diabetic db/db mouse model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Reese</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">302</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="H1003" to="H1012" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Farhangkhoee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kaur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Vascular endothelial dysfunction in diabetic cardiomyopathy: Pathogenesis and potential treatment targets</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacol Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="384" to="399" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kruger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Babicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Frieling</forename><surname>Von</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Insulin signaling regulates cardiac titin properties in heart development and diabetic cardiomyopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Salewsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Mol Cell Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="910" to="916" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Which left ventricular function is impaired earlier in the evolution of diabetic cardiomyopathy? An echocardiographic study of young type I diabetic patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Raev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabetes Care</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="633" to="639" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Left ventricular diastolic dysfunction: An early sign of diabetic cardiomyopathy?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cosson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Kevorkian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diabetes Metab</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="455" to="466" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of diabetes mellitus on prognosis and serial left ventricular function after acute myocardial infarction: Contribution of both coronary disease and diastolic left ventricular dysfunction to the adverse prognosis. The MILIS Study Group</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Muller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hartwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="57" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of diabetes on outcomes in patients with low and preserved ejection fraction heart failure: An analysis of the Candesartan in Heart failure: Assessment of Reduction in Mortality and morbidity (CHARM) programme</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Macdonald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Petrie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Varyani</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1377" to="1385" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diabetes mellitus worsens diastolic left ventricular dysfunction in aortic stenosis through altered myocardial structure and cardiomyocyte stiffness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Falcao-Pires</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hamdani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Borb Ely A</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1151" to="1159" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cardiac inflammation contributes to changes in the extracellular matrix in patients with heart failure and normal ejection fraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Westermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lindner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kasner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circ Heart Fail</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="52" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New insights in (inter)cellular mechanisms by heart failure with preserved ejection fraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tschope</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Linthout</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Heart Fail Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="436" to="444" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Myocardial titin hypophosphorylation importantly contributes to heart failure with preserved ejection fraction in a rat metabolic risk model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hamdani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Franssen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lourenc</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circ Heart Fail</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1239" to="1249" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Myocardial titin and collagen in cardiac diastolic dysfunction: Partners in crime</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hamdani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Paulus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="8" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shortening of the elastic tandem immunoglobulin segment of titin leads to diastolic dysfunction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hutchinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Methawasin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="28" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High prevalence of cardiac parvovirus B19 infection in patients with isolated left ventricular diastolic dysfunction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tschope</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kasner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="879" to="886" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Coronary microvascular rarefaction and myocardial fibrosis in heart failure with preserved ejection fraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Mohammed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hussain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mirzoyev</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="550" to="559" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inflammation-Cause or consequence of heart failure or both?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Linthout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tschope</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Heart Fail Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="265" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Myocardial microvascular inflammatory endothelial activation in heart failure with preserved ejection fraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Franssen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Unger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JACC Heart Fail</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="312" to="324" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mesenchymal stem cells improve murine acute coxsackievirus B3-induced myocarditis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Linthout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Savvatis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Miteva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2168" to="2178" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mesenchymal stromal cells but not cardiac fibroblasts exert beneficial systemic immunomodulatory effects in experimental myocarditis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Savvatis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Linthout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Miteva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e41047</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mesenchymal stromal cells modulate monocytes trafficking in Coxsackievirus B3-induced myocarditis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Miteva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Pappritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>El-Shafeey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">STEM CELLS TRANSLATIONAL MEDICINE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1249" to="1261" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cardioprotection by placenta-derived stromal cells in a murine myocardial infarction model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brodarac</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kukucka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Surg Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">185</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of placental-derived adherent stromal cell (PLX-PAD) in the treatment of critical limb ischemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Prather</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Toren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Meiron</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cytotherapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="427" to="434" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, dose-escalation study of intravenous adult human mesenchymal stem cells (prochymal) after acute myocardial infarction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hare</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Traverse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Henry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2277" to="2286" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bone marrow mesenchymal stem cells induce angiogenesis and attenuate the remodeling of diabetic cardiomyopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Exp Clin Endocrinol Diabetes</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="104" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intramyocardial delivery of mesenchymal stem cells ameliorates left ventricular and cardiomyocyte contractile dysfunction following myocardial infarction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Turdi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Toxicol Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">195</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="126" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Safety and biodistribution profile of placentalderived mesenchymal stromal cells (PLX-PAD) following intramuscular delivery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ramot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Meiron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Toren</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Toxicol Pathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="606" to="616" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantifying levels of transpolanted murine and human mesenchymal stem cells in vivo via real-time PCR</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mcbride</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gaupp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Phinney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cytotherapy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human cardiac-derived adherent proliferating cells reduce murine acute Coxsackievirus B3-induced myocarditis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Miteva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Haag</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Peng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e28513</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Persistent hepatic expression of human apo A-I after transfer with a helper-virus independent adenoviral vector</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Linthout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lusky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Collen</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gene Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1520" to="1528" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Spillmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Miteva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Pieske</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-density lipoproteins reduce endothelialto-mesenchymal transition</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1774" to="1777" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LXR agonism improves TNF-alphainduced endothelial dysfunction in the absence of its cholesterol-modulating effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Spillmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Linthout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Miteva</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Atherosclerosis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">232</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human endomyocardial biopsy specimen-derived stromal cells modulate angiotensin II-induced cardiac remodeling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Miteva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Linthout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Pappritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">STEM CELLS TRANSLATIONAL MEDICINE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1707" to="1718" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deranged myofilament phosphorylation and function in experimental heart failure with preserved ejection fraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hamdani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Bishu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Von Frieling-Salewsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cardiovasc Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="464" to="471" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crucial role for Ca2(1)/calmodulindependent protein kinase-II in regulating diastolic stress of normal and failing hearts via titin phosphorylation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Hamdani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Krysiak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kreusser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circ Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="664" to="674" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mesenchymal stem cell-mediated immunosuppression occurs via concerted action of chemokines and nitric oxide</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Stem Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="150" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transgenic activation of the kallikrein-kinin system inhibits intramyocardial inflammation, endothelial dysfunction and oxidative stress in experimental diabetic cardiomyopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tschope</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Walther</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Escher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FASEB J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2057" to="2059" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crosstalk between fibroblasts and inflammatory cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Linthout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Miteva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tschope</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cardiovasc Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="258" to="269" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Remodeling of the mononuclear phagocyte network underlies chronic inflammation and disease progression in heart failure: Critical importance of the cardiosplenic axis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ismahil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hamid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Bansal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circ Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="266" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel paradigm for heart failure with preserved ejection fraction: Comorbidities drive myocardial dysfunction and remodeling through coronary microvascular endothelial inflammation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Paulus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tschope</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="271" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distinct endothelial cell responses in the heart and kidney microvasculature characterize the progression of heart failure with preserved ejection fraction in the obese ZSF1 rat with cardiorenal metabolic syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Riad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>108. 43</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clinic Experiment Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e002760</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Circ Heart Fail</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">T regulatory lymphocytes prevent aldosteroneinduced vascular injury</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kasal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Barhoumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hypertension</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="324" to="330" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deficiency of T-regulatory cells exaggerates angiotensin II-induced microvascular injury by enhancing immune responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Mian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Barhoumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Briet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Hypertens</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="108" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adoptive transfer of regulatory T cells protects against Coxsackievirus B3-induced cardiac fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Xiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e74955</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Apolipoprotein A-I gene transfer exerts immunomodulatory effects and reduces vascular inflammation and fibrosis in ob/ob mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Spillmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Geest</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Muthuramu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Inflamm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">49 van Heerebeek L, Hamdani N, Falcão-Pires I et al. Low myocardial protein kinase G activity in heart failure with preserved ejection fraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Linthout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Spillmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lorenz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hypertension</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="830" to="839" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009. 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Circulation</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Protein kinase A phosphorylates titin&apos;s cardiacspecific N2B domain and reduces passive tension in rat cardiac myocytes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Yamasaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mcnabb</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circ Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1181" to="1188" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PKC phosphorylation of titin&apos;s PEVK element: A novel and conserved pathway for modulating myocardial stiffness</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Hidalgo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bogomolovas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circ Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">638</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effects of mesenchymal stromal cells on diabetic cardiomyopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Linthout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Spillmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Schultheiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Pharm Des</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3341" to="3347" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intravenous hmscs improve myocardial infarction in mice because cells embolized in lung are activated to secrete the anti-inflammatory protein tsg-6</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pulin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Seo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Stem Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
