<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">BASIC AND TRANSLATIONAL-ALIMENTARY TRACT Helicobacter pylori Depletes Cholesterol in Gastric Glands to Prevent Interferon Gamma Signaling and Escape the Inflammatory Response</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Pau</forename><surname>Morey</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lennart</forename><surname>Pfannkuch</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ervinna</forename><surname>Pang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Francesco</forename><surname>Boccellato</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Sigal</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Hepatology and Gastroenterology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité University Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Aki</forename><surname>Imai-Matsushima</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Victoria</forename><surname>Dyer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Manuel</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hans-Joachim</forename><surname>Mollenkopf</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Philipp</forename><surname>Schlaermann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
							<email>meyer@mpiib-berlin.mpg.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Molecular Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">BASIC AND TRANSLATIONAL-ALIMENTARY TRACT Helicobacter pylori Depletes Cholesterol in Gastric Glands to Prevent Interferon Gamma Signaling and Escape the Inflammatory Response</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">501F30F6D44043996AEE7580EDBC1C68</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1053/j.gastro.2017.12.008</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received May 26, 2017. Accepted December 14, 2017.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:17+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>aCAG, cholesteryl-6&apos;-O-aycl-a-glucoside</term>
					<term>aCPG, cholesteryl-6&apos;-O-phosphatidyl-a-glucoside</term>
					<term>ALI, air-liquid interface</term>
					<term>CagA, cytotoxin-associated gene A</term>
					<term>hBD3, human b-defensin 3</term>
					<term>IFN, interferon</term>
					<term>IFNG, interferon gamma</term>
					<term>IL, interleukin</term>
					<term>IRF, interferon regulatory factors</term>
					<term>JAK, Janus Kinase</term>
					<term>mbCD, methyl-b-cyclodextrin</term>
					<term>MAPK, mitogen-activated protein kinase</term>
					<term>MOI, multiplicity of infection</term>
					<term>NF-kB, nuclear factor kB</term>
					<term>PEG, polyethylene glycol</term>
					<term>RT-qPCR, reverse transcription quantitative polymerase chain reaction</term>
					<term>STAT, signaling transducer and activator of transcription</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>See Covering the Cover synopsis on page 1216.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>BACKGROUND &amp; AIMS: Despite inducing an inflammatory response, Helicobacter pylori can persist in the gastric mucosa for decades.</s><s>H pylori expression of cholesterol-aglucosyltransferase (encoded by cgt) is required for gastric colonization and T-cell activation.</s><s>We investigated how cgt affects gastric epithelial cells and the host immune response.</s><s>METHODS: MKN45 gastric epithelial cells, AGS cells, and human primary gastric epithelial cells (obtained from patients undergoing gastrectomy or sleeve resection or gastric antral organoids) were incubated with interferon gamma (IFNG) or interferon beta (IFNB) and exposed to H pylori, including cagPAI and cgt mutant strains.</s><s>Some cells were incubated with methyl-b-cyclodextrin (to deplete cholesterol from membranes) or myriocin and zaragozic acid to prevent biosynthesis of sphingolipids and cholesterol and analyzed by immunoblot, immunofluorescence, and reverse transcription quantitative polymerase chain reaction analyses.</s><s>We compared gene expression patterns among primary human gastric cells, uninfected or infected with H pylori P12 wt or P12Dcgt, using microarray analysis.</s><s>Mice with disruption of the IFNG receptor 1 (Ifngr1-/-mice) and C57BL6 (control) mice were infected with PMSS1 (wild-type) or PMSS1Dcgt H pylori; gastric tissues were collected and analyzed by reverse transcription quantitative polymerase chain reaction or confocal microscopy.</s><s>RESULTS: In primary gastric cells and cell lines, infection with H pylori, but not cgt mutants, blocked IFNG-induced signaling via JAK and STAT.</s><s>Cells infected with H pylori were depleted of cholesterol, which reduced IFNG signaling by disrupting lipid rafts, leading to reduced phosphorylation (activation) of JAK and STAT1.</s><s>H pylori infection of cells also blocked signaling by IFNB, interleukin 6 (IL6), and IL22 and reduced activation of genes regulated by these signaling pathways, including cytokines that regulate T-cell function (MIG and IP10) and anti-microbial peptides such as human b-defensin 3 (hBD3).</s><s>We found that this mechanism allows H pylori to persist in proximity to infected cells while inducing inflammation only in the neighboring, non-infected epithelium.</s><s>Stomach tissues from mice infected with PMSS1 had increased levels of IFNG, but did not express higher levels of interferon-response genes.</s><s>Expression of the IFNGresponse gene IRF1 was substantially higher in PMSS1Dcgtinfected mice than PMSS1-infected mice.</s><s>Ifngr1-/mice were colonized by PMSS1 to a greater extent than control mice.</s></p><p><s>Gastroenterology 2018;154:1391-1404 CONCLUSIONS: H pylori expression of cgt reduces cholesterol levels in infected gastric epithelial cells and thereby blocks IFNG signaling, allowing the bacteria to escape the host inflammatory response.</s><s>These findings provide insight into the mechanisms by which H pylori might promote gastric carcinogenesis (persisting despite constant inflammation) and ineffectiveness of T-cell-based vaccines against H pylori. Keywords: JAK/STAT; IL-22; hBD3.</s></p><p><s>A bout half the world's population is chronically infected with the gram-negative bacterium Helicobacter pylori, which is implicated in severe gastric disease, including peptic ulcer and adenocarcinoma. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref></s><s>Colonization takes place in the gastric mucus and eventually involves bacterial adherence to the glandular epithelium. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> The infection is characterized by a rapid and strong nuclear factor kB (NF-kB)-driven response, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> which leads to the recruitment and activation of immune cells: CD4þ T cells, dominated by the Th1 lineage <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> play a decisive role in controlling the Helicobacter load via secretion of interferon gamma (IFNG). <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s>his Th1 response is also fueled by type I IFNs (a/b) released from gastric epithelial cells themselves. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>Th17 and Th22 T cells, characterized by interleukin (IL)17 and IL22 production, also promote the inflammatory milieu, helping to control infection. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref></s><s>Yet, H pylori is able to escape full elimination by host immunity through an unknown mechanism, resulting in a severe chronic inflammatory condition that represents a crucial aspect of its pathogenesis.</s></p><p><s>Gastric epithelial cells display receptors for type I (a/b) and type II (g) interferons, the subunits of which (IFNAR1/ IFNAR2 and IFNGR1/IFNGR2, respectively) are assembled in specialized cholesterol-rich membrane microdomains, known as lipid rafts. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref></s><s>Microdomain-dependent receptor activation <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> triggers JAK (Janus Kinase) and STAT (signaling transducer and activator of transcription) signaling via STAT1/2 phosphorylation and nuclear translocation to promote downstream expression of genes involved in inflammation and defense, including interferon regulatory factors (IRF), which further amplify the IFN response through positive feedback via STATs. <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref></s><s>Gastric epithelial cells also express receptors for IL22 <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> , which can stimulate the production of antimicrobial factors that defend against mucosal pathogens. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref></s><s>he effector mechanisms controlling colonization by H pylori remain sparsely understood.</s><s>7]<ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> Strikingly, despite continued inflammation, hBD3 is not detected in infected human gastric biopsies. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref></s><s>e have previously shown that H pylori prevents hBD3 expression through a CagA (cytotoxin-associated gene A)dependent mechanism. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref></s><s>However, how hBD3 remains blocked despite IFNG and IL22 stimulation is unclear.</s></p><p><s>1]<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">[22]</ref> Cgt is the first in a series of H pylori enzymes that cause additional modifications to generate cholesteryl-6'-O-aycl-a-glucoside (aCAG) or cholesteryl-6'-O-phosphatidyl-a-glucoside (aCPG). <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref></s><s>3]<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">[24]</ref> We previously reported that a cholesterol-rich diet leads to a reduction of the H pylori load concomitant with an increased Th1 response. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref></s><s>ere, we provide insight into the underlying mechanism by showing that the IFN response is subverted by H pylori in gastric epithelial cells.</s><s>This is caused by Cgt-dependent cholesterol depletion, resulting in the destruction of lipid rafts, failure of IFN receptor subunit assembly and, ultimately, lack of downstream signaling.</s><s>Similarly, Cgt blocks IL6 and IL22 signaling.</s><s>Our data provide evidence for the highly effective destruction of the responsiveness of H pylori-infected epithelium, even in the presence of strong</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EDITOR'S NOTES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BACKGROUND AND CONTEXT</head><p><s>For reasons not well-understood, Helicobacter pylori can persist life-long in the stomach despite causing a strong inflammatory response, increasing the risk for serious sequelae such as ulcers and cancer.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>NEW FINDINGS</head><p><s>By extracting cholesterol from host cells, H pylori blocks the assembly of IFN and other cytokine receptors, rendering the infected mucosa unable to respond properly to inflammatory signals from stroma and immune cells.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>LIMITATIONS</head><p><s>Bacterial mutants for the cgt gene, which is required for cholesterol extraction, are unable to establish an in vivo infection, preventing a detailed analysis of its effects in the animal model.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IMPACT</head><p><s>This study provides important insight into the pitfalls of past vaccination approaches for H pylori.</s><s>It also explains how cholesterol rich diet could negatively influence the inflammatory condition of the infected stomach mucosa.</s></p><p><s>cytokine signals from the adjacent micro-environment, thus impairing mucosal defense.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials and Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethical Permissions</head><p><s>Human gastric tissue specimens were obtained from individuals undergoing gastrectomy or sleeve resection, under the ethics approval by the Charité Ethics Committee (EA1/058/ 11 and EA1/129/12).</s><s>Animal experiments were performed in mice maintained under pathogen-free conditions based on approval by the Ethics Committee for Animal Experimentation of the State of Berlin (G0205/12).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cell Culture Infection and Treatment</head><p><s>Bacteria were collected from plates and resuspended in RPMI 1640 (serum-free).</s><s>All cells were grown to 60% confluency, washed twice with phosphate-buffered saline, and serum starved with RPMI 1640 for 16 hours prior to experiments.</s><s>Infection was carried out under serum-starved conditions at 37 C, 5% CO 2 for the indicated times at multiplicity of infection (MOI) 20 or 50.</s><s>Treatment with methyl-bcyclodextrin (mbCD; Sigma, St. Louis, MO) was carried out for 5 hours at indicated concentrations.</s><s>Biosynthesis of sphingolipids and cholesterol was inhibited by treating cells with myriocin (50 mmol/L; Sigma) for 72 hours and zaragozic acid (50 mmol/ L, Cayman Chemical: Ann Arbor, MI) for the last 18 hours.</s><s>In selected experiments, bacteria were treated with water-soluble cholesterol (Sigma) at 1 mg/mL for 1 hour prior to infection.</s><s>Alternatively, polyethylene glycol (PEG)-cholesterol (10 mg/ mL; Sigma) was added to cultures during the last hour of infection, while mock-infected cells were treated with an equal volume containing cholesterol.</s><s>After infection, recombinant human IFNG (R&amp;D Systems: Minneapolis, MN; 10 ng/mL), IFNB (PBL Assay Science, Piscataway, NJ; 2300 U/mL), IL6 (Peprotech, Rocky Hill, NJ; 25 ng/mL) or IL22 (Peprotech; 50 ng/mL) were added to selected wells and maintained for indicated times until the end of the experiment.</s></p><p><s>Primary Gastric Epithelial Air-Liquid Interface Cultures.</s><s>Cells from organoids or freshly isolated glands were seeded in trans-well inserts (Millipore (Merck): Darmstadt, GE; PIHP01250) in 24-well plates and wells filled with 400 mL primary cell culture medium.</s><s>Once cells had formed a confluent monolayer, medium on top of the cells was removed to start air-liquid interface (ALI) culture.</s><s>Cultures were kept at 37 C, 5% CO 2 in a humidified incubator.</s><s>Ten days later cells were infected by placing 50 mL of bacteria in phosphatebuffered saline (MOI 100) on top of the filters for 3 days.</s></p><p><s>For further information see Supplementary Materials and Methods.</s><s>All RT-qPCR primers listed in Supplementary Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Deposition. Microarray data have been deposited</head><p><s>in the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO; www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</s><s>geo/) of the National Center for Biotechnology Information under GEO accession number GSE76589.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H pylori Blocks JAK/STAT Signaling upon IFNG Treatment</head><p><s>To assess the influence of H pylori on the response to IFNG, we infected MKN45 gastric epithelial cells with strains P12 and P1 for 6 or 24 hours, followed by treatment with IFNG for 30 minutes.</s><s>Immunoblotting revealed STAT1 phosphorylation in response to IFNG treatment in noninfected cells, cells infected with heat-killed bacteria, and cells infected for 6 hours (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>).</s><s>Surprisingly, after prolonged infection (24 hours) IFNG stimulation failed to activate STAT1, irrespective of the H pylori strain (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>).</s><s>To analyze the dynamics of this phenotype, we performed a time course experiment, showing that STAT1 phosphorylation was diminished after 16 hours and completely blocked from 24 until 96 hours of infection with P12 (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>).</s><s>To investigate the underlying mechanisms, we thus chose the 24 hour time point of infection as a reference.</s><s>In AGS cells, too, 24 hours of infection inhibited the response to IFNG (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>).</s><s>MOI 10 was sufficient to partially block IFNG signaling in MKN45 cells within 24 hours and a complete block was observed with MOI 50 (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref>), which was therefore chosen for further experiments.</s></p><p><s>Upon IFNG stimulation, an activated IFNGR complex phosphorylates JAK1 and JAK2 kinases, which in turn phosphorylate STAT1.</s><s>After 24 hours of infection with P12 or P1, neither JAK1 nor JAK2 was phosphorylated any more in MKN45 cells (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref> and 1C, middle panel; Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1D</ref>).</s><s>Notably, JAK1 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>) and JAK2 (data not shown) were activated in non-infected MKN45 cells even without IFNG stimulation; however, this was also diminished after infection.</s><s>Infection conditions did not compromise cell viability (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1E</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cgt is Required for Inactivation of IFNG-JAK/STAT1 Pathway</head><p><s>To identify the bacterial factor involved in the block of IFNG signaling, we infected MKN45 cells with H pylori wild type and mutant strains.</s><s>As a recent report linked CagA translocation to STAT1 dephosphorylation via SHP-2 activation, <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref> we tested deletion mutants for cagPAI, which encodes the entire type IV secretion system, cagA and cgt.</s><s>While the cagA and cagPAI mutant strains still inhibited JAK/STAT1 signaling upon IFNG stimulation, the cgt mutant did not (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1D</ref> and Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>).</s><s>Immunofluorescence analysis showed that P12Dcgt (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref> and Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1D</ref>) did not block JAK2 activation upon IFNG treatment, despite adhering to epithelial cells at levels comparable to wild type.</s><s>Similarly, STAT1 signaling upon IFNG treatment was still inhibited in a Cgt-dependent manner at 48 h.p.i.</s><s>(Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1F</ref>).</s><s>Although genetic complementation of the cgt-mutant strain only partially reconstituted Cgt expression (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1G</ref>), it was enough to restore the ability to impair JAK/STAT1 activation (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1E</ref>) in MKN45 cells.</s><s>Finally, we evaluated the consequences of disrupted JAK/STAT1 signaling by analyzing expression of downstream genes after IFN treatment, by infecting MKN45 cells for 24 hours with P12 wild type or P12Dcgt prior to treatment with IFNG for 2.5 or 5 hours, followed by reverse transcriptionquantitative polymerase chain reaction (RT-qPCR).</s><s>Expression of IRF1, as well as the T-cell attractant chemokines MIG and IFNG-inducible protein 10 (IP)-10 (encoded by CXCL9 and CXCL10 genes, respectively), was strongly up-regulated in non-infected cells upon IFNG treatment (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1H</ref>).</s><s>Cells infected with P12Dcgt also responded to IFNG, but after infection with wt P12 the response was significantly reduced.</s><s>Accordingly, Cgt activity blocks the JAK/STAT1 pathway, as well as transcription of downstream genes involved in amplification of the IFNG response.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Inhibition of IFNG Response is Linked to Host Cholesterol Depletion, Lipid Raft Disruption, and IFNGR Assembly</head><p><s>Cholesterol acquisition by H pylori has been linked to the destruction of lipid rafts in epithelial cells. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref></s><s>Lipid rafts serve as platforms for cell signaling cascades, including IFN signaling. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26</ref></s><s>As previously described, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref> we observed cholesterol depletion in cells infected with wild-type H pylori (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>).</s><s>To connect this to the block of the IFNG response, we treated cells with mbCD, which depletes cholesterol from eukaryotic membranes.</s><s>Treatment did not affect cellular viability (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>) but impaired both JAK1 and STAT1 phosphorylation (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>).</s><s>We also inhibited the biosynthesis of sphingolipids and cholesterol by combined treatment with myriocin and zaragozic acid to disrupt lipid raft function. <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref></s><s>yriocin and zaragozic acid treatment indeed significantly blocked the induction of IRF1 expression in response to IFNG (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2C</ref>).</s><s>In addition, when we coated H pylori with water-soluble cholesterol before infection to abolish cholesterol transfer from host cells, they did not block the cellular response to IFNG treatment (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>).</s><s>Cholesterol coating also restored the capacity of wt H pylori-infected cells to up-regulate IRF1 in response to IFNG, at levels comparable to non-infected cells (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>).</s><s>Cholesterol coating did not affect bacterial viability (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2E</ref>).</s><s>To control for any effects on the initial host-pathogen interplay (eg, by masking bacterial adhesins), we repeated the experiment by adding PEG-cholesterol to the medium during the last hour of infection.</s><s>This partially rescued the capacity of infected cells to respond to IFNG treatment, further highlighting the importance of cholesterol as a mediator of inflammation in response to H pylori (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2C</ref>).</s></p><p><s>The IFNGR subunits 1 and 2 need to merge at cholesterol-rich micro-domains <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref> to respond to IFNG (A) Immunoblot analysis of JAK1/STAT1 phosphorylation after 5 hours mbCD treatment at indicated concentrations or in nontreated cells (-), with or without IFNG treatment (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes).</s><s>(B) Immunoblot analysis of JAK1 and STAT1 phosphorylation upon IFNG treatment (þ).</s><s>MKN45 cells were infected for 24 hours with the indicated strains or non-infected, then treated with IFNG (þ) (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes).</s><s>Cholesterol-coating of bacteria was started 1 hour before infection and applied to non-infected cells accordingly.</s><s>(C) Immunoblot analysis of STAT1 phosphorylation upon IFNG and/or PEG-cholesterol treatment.</s><s>MKN45 cells were infected for 24 hours with H pylori wt or non-infected.</s><s>In selected wells (þ), PEG-cholesterol (5 mg/mL) was added during the final hour of infection.</s><s>Then, cells were treated with IFNG (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes) (þ) or mock-treated (-).</s><s>Quantification: band intensity ratio STAT1pY:actin.</s><s>(D) Confocal microscopy analysis (x-y sections with lateral views along dotted lines: x-z, bottom; y-z right) of the lipid raft marker GM1 (green) in membranes of cells non-infected or infected for 24 hours with indicated strains.</s><s>Nuclei stained with DAPI (blue).</s><s>Scale bar: 5 mm.</s><s>(E) Immunoblot analysis of detergent-resistant membranes for IFNGR1, IFNGR2, caveolin, or dot blot analysis with CTxB-HRP.</s><s>Cells were non-infected or infected for 24 hours with indicated strains, followed by treatment (þ) or mock-treatment (-) with IFNG (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes).</s><s>(F and G) Immunoprecipitation (IP) and immunoblot analysis of IFNGR subunits 1 and 2. IFNGR2 was pulled down using IFNGR2 antibody.</s><s>MKN45 cells were infected with H pylori P12 wt or coated with water-soluble cholesterol before infection.</s><s>Results representative of 2 independent experiments.</s><s>stimulation and initiate downstream signaling via JAK1 and JAK2. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref></s><s>We investigated the impact of H pylori on the integrity of lipid rafts by assessing potential alterations in the assembly of functional IFNGR.</s><s>According to immunofluorescence analysis, surface accumulation of glycosphingolipid ganglioside GM1, a constituent marker of lipid rafts, is lost after infection with P12 wt and P12DcagA (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>, quantification of the relative membrane GM1 signal in Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2F</ref>).</s><s>In contrast, infection with P12Dcgt did not notably alter GM1 distribution (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref> and Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2F</ref>).</s><s>In addition, we performed a membrane fractionation to separate lipid rafts as detergent-resistant membranes.</s><s>In control cells, fractions containing cholesterol-rich micro-domains, identified by the presence of raft markers GM1 or caveolin, partitioned in top fractions (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2G</ref>).</s><s>Combining these fractions for Western blot analysis showed that GM1 as well as IFNGR1 were lost in detergent-resistant membranes upon infection with wild-type P12 but not P12Dcgt, regardless of IFNG treatment (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2E</ref>).</s><s>In total lysates, IFNGR1 and IFNGR2 were detected in all conditions (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2H</ref>).</s><s>Finally, we performed immunoprecipitation of IFNGR subunit 2 to test co-precipitation of IFNGR1.</s><s>Immunoprecipitation specificity was controlled for by absence of the transferrin receptor CD71, a protein not associated with lipid rafts or the IFNGR complex (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2I</ref>).</s><s>In line with recent findings, 11 MKN45 cells showed constitutive oligomerization of IFNGR subunits even in the absence of IFNG (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2F</ref>).</s><s>Despite this, prolonged wt H pylori infection but not  P12Dcgt abolished assembly of receptor subunits.</s><s>Coating H pylori with exogenous cholesterol prior to infection restored assembly of IFNGR subunits (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2G</ref>).</s><s>Together, these data suggest that subversion of JAK/STAT1 signaling by H pylori takes place at the very top of the pathway, by preventing assembly of IFNG receptor subunits through lipid raft destruction.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H pylori Blocks the IFNG Response In Vivo in a Cgt-Dependent Manner</head><p><s>Reportedly, H pylori cgt mutants are unable to colonize mice. <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">21,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref></s><s>Because Cgt activity is required for the block of the IFNG response, which in turn protects against H pylori in vivo, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> we investigated whether the IFNG response is linked to bacterial clearance.</s><s>After 3 days of infection PMSS1Dcgt was already undetectable in wild-type mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A</ref>).</s><s>Mice infected with PMSS1 or PMSS1Dcgt presented similar IFNG levels in the stomach; however, the induction of the IFNG downstream response gene IRF1 was substantially higher in PMSS1Dcgt-infected mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3B</ref>).</s><s>Next, we infected mice for 2 weeks with PMSS1 to allow a stronger Th1 response to develop.</s><s>We observed a corpus-predominant gland occupation by H pylori in all analyzed mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C</ref>).</s><s>Notably, the IFNG expression (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>, left) was higher compared with the less colonized antrum.</s><s>However, IRF1 expression remained at similar levels (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3D</ref>, right).</s><s>Infection with wild-type H pylori thus leads to increased levels of IFNG, but fails to increase expression of interferon response genes, consistent with the notion of a Cgt-dependent block.</s><s>Finally, although we reasoned that H pylori PMSS1Dcgt might be able to infect Ifngr1-knock out mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A</ref>, right), this was not the case.</s><s>Knockout mice did show increased colonization by wild-type PMSS1, indicating that additional defense-related pathways apart from IFNG might contribute to the clearance of PMSS1Dcgt.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cholesterol Depletion by H pylori Inhibits Type I IFN, IL6, and IL22 Signaling and Downstream hBD3 Response</head><p><s>Lipid raft integrity is also known to be required for type I IFNs and IL6 signaling. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28</ref></s><s>In congruence, we observed that H pylori P12 also inhibited IFNB-induced STAT1 signaling in MKN45 cells, and this effect was dependent on the presence of cgt but not cagA or cagPAI (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4A</ref>).</s><s>Also, mbCD treatment inhibited IFNB signaling in a dosedependent manner (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3A</ref>).</s><s>Similarly, wild-type infection and mbCD treatment, but not infection with the cgt mutant, prevented STAT3 phosphorylation upon IL6 treatment (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B</ref>).</s><s>IL22 is a crucial cytokine for mediating the epithelial defense against mucosal pathogens.</s><s>Binding to receptors in epithelial cells triggers STAT3 activation, inducing expression of antimicrobial factors. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref></s><s>gain, 24-hour infection with wt P12 but not a P12Dcgt mutant strain inhibited IL22 signaling transduction in epithelial cells (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4C</ref>); the block was also observed upon mbCD treatment (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4C</ref>).</s><s>Genetic rescue of the cgt mutant partially restored the bacterial capacity to block IL22 signaling (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3B</ref>).</s><s>Because IL22 signaling has not previously been reported to depend on cholesterol, we demonstrated restoration of IL22 signaling by adding PEG-cholesterol to MKN45 cells before IL22 stimulation (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3C</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Because IFNG and IL22 are reported to induce epithelial expression of hBD3, <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref> a potent defensin against H pylori, 15,19 we tested the impact of infection on the cytokine-induced hBD3 response.</s><s>Infection of MKN45 cells for 24 hours with P12Dcgt but not P12 wt, followed by treatment with IFNG for 5 hours, induced a significant increase of hBD3 transcription (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4D</ref>, left), which was even more dramatic after 24-hour IFNG treatment (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4D</ref>, right).</s><s>In contrast, the increase over time in non-infected and P12 wt-infected cells was minimal.</s><s>Similarly, IL22 treatment also induced hBD3 expression in P12Dcgt-infected cells, albeit to a lower extent, following a similar time course as IFNG (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4E</ref>).</s><s>In summary, H pylori blocks the production of hBD3 in epithelial cells stimulated with IFNG or IL22.</s><s>Interestingly, co-stimulation with a cgt-deficient strain induced substantially higher hBD3 expression compared with cytokine treatment alone.</s><s>Overall, these data confirm that cholesterol depletion by H pylori not only inhibits the response to IFNG, but also type I IFNs, IL6, and IL22.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Inhibition of JAK/STAT Signaling in Human Primary Gastric Epithelial Cells</head><p><s>We next used human gastric primary cultures <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">31</ref> to validate our observations during authentic host-pathogen interaction.</s><s>Cells derived from primary gastric antral organoids were seeded on plastic and infected with H pylori under serum starvation before IFNG or IFNB treatment for 30 minutes.</s><s>Similar to results obtained with MKN45, H pylori P12, but not P12Dcgt, prevented JAK1/STAT1 phosphorylation (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5A</ref>).</s><s>These differences were also observed at higher MOI and in cells isolated from the corpus region (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4A</ref>), independent of donors (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4B</ref>).</s><s>In contrast to cancer cell lines, primary gastric epithelial cells did not exhibit constitutive JAK1 activation (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5A</ref>).</s><s>Block of IFNG signaling was observed at 24 hours post-infection, but not at earlier time points (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4C</ref>) or with a low MOI (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4D</ref>).</s><s>Cholesterol-coated bacteria, however, failed to block JAK/STAT1 signaling (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5B</ref>).</s><s>Further, block of IFN signaling, as determined by the up-regulation of the type II IFN-activated gene CXCL9 in response to IFNG stimulation, was observed in H pylori P12 wt, P12DcagA, P12DcagPAI, or P12DvacA, but not in P12Dcgt-infected cells (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4E</ref>).</s><s>Moreover, H pylori P12 wt, but not P12Dcgt, inhibited STAT3 phosphorylation upon IL22 treatment at 24 hours postinfection (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5C</ref>).</s><s>Genetic rescue of P12Dcgt restored its capacity to block the response to IFNG and IL22 in primary epithelial cells (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4F and G</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To assess the global cellular response to infection with H pylori P12 wt or P12Dcgt, we performed microarray analysis with human primary gastric cells infected with P12 wt or P12Dcgt.</s><s>Gene Ontology term enrichment analysis revealed responsiveness for genes involved in 'response to external stimuli,' 'signal transduction,' and 'immune response,' which was similar for both wt and P12Dcgtinfected cells (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5D</ref>, and data not shown).</s><s>Many of the pro-inflammatory genes up-regulated upon infection with either strain are related to NF-kB signaling (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5E</ref>).</s><s>Therefore, while H pylori effectively blocks the response to IFNG, IFNB, and IL22 in normal human gastric epithelial cells, initial sensing of the pathogen by NF-kB 3 remains largely unaffected.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H pylori Generates Micro-Niches of Diminished Inflammatory Response</head><p><s>To spatially resolve the effects H pylori exerts, we examined the resulting cellular phenotypes over longer periods of time using a novel infection model of human gastric primary cells in air-liquid interphase culture. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32</ref></s><s>This model enables longer infection times and resembles the in vivo situation more closely because it features greater cell type diversity, a protective layer of mucin, and cell polarization (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5A</ref>).</s><s>After 3 days of infection with P12 wt at MOI 100, cells were treated with IFNG for 30 minutes and analyzed by immunofluorescence.</s><s>Interestingly, IFNG treatment led to nuclear translocation of phospho-STAT1 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6A</ref>, middle panel).</s><s>Micro-colonies of spiral-shaped bacteria (red) formed infection foci (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6B</ref> and Supplementary Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5A and B</ref>) correlating with areas of reduced phospho-STAT1 exhibition (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6A</ref>, bottom panel).</s><s>At lower magnification, areas of reduced STAT1 activation appeared to clearly correlate with infected areas,  while non-infected areas of the same filter responded normally to IFNG (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6B</ref>).</s><s>Next, we quantified the number of phospho-STAT1-positive cells in infected compared with non-or less well-infected microscopic fields of the same filter.</s><s>The vast majority of infected areas displayed phospho-STAT1 levels below the activation threshold, while non-infected fields exhibited a robust IFNG response (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5C</ref>).</s><s>Infection with the P12Dcgt mutant at MOI 200 led to similar colonization densities, yet the infected monolayer exhibited full STAT1 phosphorylation upon IFNG similar to non-infected cells (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">5D</ref>).</s><s>Similarly, H pylori infection also hampered STAT3 phosphorylation upon IL22 treatment in infected areas (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">6C</ref>).</s><s>Thus, using an advanced epithelial cell culture model, we demonstrate that H pylori prevents infected cells from responding to IFNG or IL22.</s><s>This favors the formation of micro-colonies at micro-niches devoid of STAT1 or STAT3 activation.</s><s>Although non-infected sites of the same culture retain full responsiveness, this does not halt micro-colony formation at protected sites.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>A hallmark of gastric infections with H pylori is the strong NF-kB-driven response of the epithelium.</s><s>This initiates a chronic inflammatory condition fueled by the recruitment of immune cells, which produce IFNs <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> and other cytokines, including IL22. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref> These cytokines trigger a second wave of epithelial responses, characterized by the release of defensins and other bactericidal factors, to restrict pathogen growth. <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">29</ref></s><s>As we report here, H pylori evolved a powerful means to prevent infected epithelial cells from responding to this cytokine burstshutting down bactericidal activity right at the site of infection.</s><s>This intriguing phenomenon, exerted by the bacterial enzyme Cgt, is in line with previous observations that point to an unexplained inhibition of IFNG-induced nuclear translocation of STAT1 during H pylori infection. <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">33</ref></s><s>Our findings now provide the mechanistic clue to our earlier characterization of cgt as a critical determinant of H pylori immune evasion. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref></s><s>he gastric mucosa of patients exhibits a marked prevalence of pro-inflammatory cytokines and mediators that provoke innate and Th1-, Th17-, and Th22-driven immune responses. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">34,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">35</ref></s><s>However, IFNG and IL17 merely control, rather than clear, established infections.</s><s>Similarly, IL22 induces the production of relevant antimicrobial factors in gastric epithelial cells, but surprisingly IL22 knockout and wt mice show similar H pylori colonization rates. <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18</ref></s><s>Previous work identified the H pylori factors VacA and GGT as immune modulators that impair the activation and proliferation of T cells. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">36</ref></s><s>They skew normal T-cell maturation from Th1 and Th17 toward a Treg phenotype and thereby elicit a considerable degree of local and systemic tolerance. <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">37</ref></s><s>Although this deficit of T-cell maturation can be rescued by vaccination, vaccine-driven T-cell activation normally achieves only a reduction of the bacterial load concomitant with an increased inflammation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">38</ref></s><s>This paradox points to a block of the T-cell-mediated immunity at the effector side of host epithelial defense, which can be explained by the action of Cgt.</s><s>Because Cgt acts only on infected cells, this gives rise to an intriguing scenario: while inflammation prevails in the infected tissue, Cgt generates protected islands of diminished defense, promoting pathogen survival.</s><s>Indeed, this notion is corroborated by observations with chronically infected mice challenged with a secondary H pylori infection 39 : newly incoming bacteria were unable to colonize infected mice except for a few glands already occupied by the primary infection, pointing toward an overall anti-microbial environment in the infected stomach.</s><s>Together these observations suggest that H pylori forms protected micro-niches surrounded by an otherwise inflamed and microbicidal milieu (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">7</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Amongst the T-cell chemotactic factors affected by Cgt are MIG and IP-10, which contribute to protection against H pylori. 7,40 Homeostasis of the mucosal colonization by H pylori, avoiding an excessive bacterial load, is thought to be achieved through secretion of a variety of innate factors, including defensins, mucins, and oxidative metabolites. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">41,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">42</ref></s><s>Many of these are produced by the epithelium in response to IFNG and IL22. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17</ref></s><s>hBD3, one of the most potent factors against H pylori, is induced in an IFNGdependent manner in the context of chronic gastrointestinal inflammation. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref></s><s>We have previously observed that EGFR-dependent induction of hBD3 is down-regulated upon translocation of H pylori CagA via the activation of SHP-2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref> and CagA-dependent activation of SHP-2 also interferes with IFNG signaling. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref></s><s>Thus, CagA acts synergistically with Cgt in preventing IFN signaling and hBD3 synthesis, with Cgt expressed also in strains that lack the cagPAI T4SS.</s><s>Our results, however, show a minimal contribution of CagA in blocking JAK/STAT signaling, possibly because of variations in the active motifs of CagA proteins in our European strain as compared with Asian strains, <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">43</ref> such as the one used by Wang and colleagues. <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">25</ref></s><s>Consistently, biopsies from European patients exhibited poor bactericidal activity against H pylori and lack of hBD3, regardless of whether they were cagPAI/cagA positive or negative. <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19</ref></s><s>ipid rafts are also targeted by other pathogens known to block IFN signaling (such as West Nile virus), which modifies the distribution of lipid rafts in the membrane <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44</ref> and Leishmania donovani, which disrupts lipid rafts in macrophages to inhibit assembly of IFNGR subunits. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref></s><s>Here, using H pylori, we achieve striking mechanistic insights into microbial cholesterol depletion from host cells, an apparently common, yet little appreciated virulence strategy.</s><s>Accordingly, cholesterol depletion prevents the partitioning of IFNGR1 to lipid rafts and association with IFNGR2 subunits. <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref></s><s>In MKN45 cells, we observed an association of IFNGR2 and IFNGR1 subunits even in the absence of infection, consistent with the abnormal, constitutive JAK1/2 activation.</s><s>However, this association collapsed upon H pylori infection, rendering these cells unresponsive, independently of the presence of interferons.</s></p><p><s>Our in vivo experiments confirmed a Cgt-dependent block of the IFNG response, with the results obtained in Ifngr1 knockout mice indicating that additional pathways contribute to preventing colonization with the PMSS1Dcgt mutant.</s><s>This finding is consistent with the inhibitory action of Cgt on multiple lipid raft-dependent pathways, including IL6 and IFNB, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">28,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">44</ref> and IL22, in addition to IFNG.</s><s>Vice versa, Cgt may also cause receptor activation such as for EGFR and TGFBR, where cholesterol depletion increases the number of molecules available for ligand binding. <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">45,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">46</ref></s><s>part from this, many signaling routes, particularly those involving the pro-inflammatory pathway NF-kB, appear to function normally in H pylori-infected cells, even at a time when cholesterol depletion has progressed.</s></p><p><s>We have substantiated our findings in primary epithelial cells from different donors.</s><s>Importantly, the use of cells from human gastric organoids allowed us to address biological questions in a mutation-free background. <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">30</ref></s><s>Although primary cell models are increasingly used to address questions of infection biology, <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">47</ref> little data related to H pylori are available yet.</s><s>Here, we also utilized an advanced ALI model, which offers several improvements: (i) cultures grow under the influence of Wnt to maintain stemness; (ii) cells differentiate toward a diversity of cells, including pit, neck, chief, parietal, and neuroendocrine cells; (iii) cell polarization and secretion of a protective mucus layer supports an authentic equilibrium between cells and bacteria, enabling long-term infection. <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">32</ref></s><s>s we have previously shown, dietary cholesterol supplementation significantly reduces the H pylori burden in mice. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref></s><s>The decreased colonization came at the cost of substantially increased IFNG-driven inflammation.</s><s>Our current results, together with the established link between lipid rafts and IFN signaling, <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">27</ref> are in complete agreement with previous in vivo findings. <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">22</ref></s><s>Accordingly, cholesterol supply in the context of H pylori infection enhances JAK/STAT signaling together with the release of antibacterial effectors.</s><s>Such increased Th1 responses, however, are also thought to promote preneoplastic lesions. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b47">48</ref></s><s>This notion, in turn, is consistent with the situation in patients suffering from increased blood cholesterol levels, especially in the form of low-density lipoprotein-cholesterol, who often exhibit severe H pylori-induced gastritis. <ref type="bibr" target="#b48">49</ref></s><s>Accordingly, a lowcholesterol diet may reduce the pathology of H pylori gastric infections.</s><s>This places Cgt function, cholesterol metabolism, and inflammation at the crossroads of gastric pathogenesis and cancer.</s><s>= Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</s><s>(A) Time course analysis of IFNG induced STAT1 phosphorylation by immunoblot.</s><s>MKN45 cells were infected with H pylori P12 wild type at MOI 50 or non-infected (NI).</s><s>After indicated infection times, cells were treated (þ) with IFNG (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes).</s><s>(B) Immunoblot analysis of IFNG induced STAT1 phosphorylation in AGS gastric epithelial cell line upon infection with indicated H pylori strain at MOI 50 and in non-infected cells.</s><s>After 24 hours of infection, cells were treated (þ) with IFNG (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes).</s><s>(C) MOI titration analysis of IFNG induced STAT1 phosphorylation by immunoblot.</s><s>MKN45 cells were infected with H pylori P12 wild type at indicated MOIs or non-infected (NI).</s><s>After 24 hours of infection, cells were treated (þ) with IFNG (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes).</s><s>(D) Analysis of JAK2 phosphorylation (red) by confocal IF at low magnification, confocal section.</s><s>Cells were non-infected (NI), or infected with indicated H pylori strains (bacteria labeled in green).</s><s>In all cases, cells were treated with IFNG (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes).</s><s>Scale bar: 10 mm.</s><s>The result is representative of 3 independent experiments.</s><s>(E) Cellular viability of MKN45 cells infected with indicated H pylori strains, or heat-killed P12 (P12 HK) at indicated MOIs for 24 hours.</s><s>Viability was measured via a fluorescence-based ATP assay (Promega, Madison, WI).</s><s>All readings were normalized against non-infected (NI) cells.</s><s>Cells treated for 5 minutes with Triton X-100 serve as control.</s><s>Data shows mean ± SD of 2 independent biological experiments.</s><s>SD is derived from 3 technical replicates.</s><s>(F) Immunoblot analysis of IFNG induced JAK1 and STAT1 phosphorylation in MKN45 gastric epithelial cells after 48 hours of infection with indicated H pylori strains at MOI 50 and in non-infected cells.</s><s>At the end of infection, cells were treated (þ) or mock-treated (-) with IFNG (10 ng/mL) for 30 minutes.</s><s>Quantification shows band intensity ratio of STAT1pY:actin.</s><s>(G) Immunoblot analysis of CGT expression after genetic complementation of CGT mutant strain.</s><s>4x10 6 bacteria of H pylori P12 wt, P12Dcgt, DcagA, DcagPAI, and 2 clones of the recomplemented strains Dcgt/cgt were lysed in Laemmli buffer and checked for CGT expression by using an in-house created monoclonal anti-CGT antibody.</s><s>(H) Response to IFNG for genes IRF1, CXCL9, and CXCL10 quantified by RT-qPCR analysis.</s><s>MKN45 cells were non-infected or infected with indicated H pylori strains for 24 hours.</s><s>IFNG (10 ng/mL) was then added to selected wells for the specified times.</s><s>To represent the net response to IFN, results were normalized against relative gene expression of corresponding non-infected, P12 and P12Dcgt infected cells.</s><s>Data are represented as mean ± SD; ns, non-significant, *P &lt; .05,</s><s>**P &lt; .01. = Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>. Experiment performed in 2D primary gastric human cells from different donors infected with indicated H pylori strains at MOI 20 or 50 for 24 hours or non-infected (NI).</s><s>(A) Immunoblot analysis of STAT1 pathway activation.</s><s>Cells from the corpus region were infected with indicated H pylori strains at different MOIs.</s><s>After infection time cells were mock-treated or treated with IFNG (5 ng/mL).</s><s>(B) Immunoblot analysis of the activation of JAK1/STAT1 pathway.</s><s>After infection, cells were mock-treated or treated 30 minutes with IFNG (g) (5 ng/mL) or IFNB (b) (2300 U/mL).</s><s>(C) Time course analysis of IFNG-induced STAT1 phosphorylation by immunoblot.</s><s>Cells were infected with H pylori P12 wt at MOI 20 or noninfected (NI).</s><s>After indicated infection times, cells were treated (þ) with IFNG (5 ng/mL, 30 minutes).</s><s>(D) Immunoblot analysis of STAT1 phosphorylation.</s><s>Cells were infected with H pylori wild type at different MOIs or left uninfected.</s><s>After infection time cells were mock-treated or treated with IFNG (5 ng/mL).</s><s>(E) Response to 2.5-hour treatment with IFNG (5 ng/mL) after infection with indicated H pylori strains or non-infected (NI).</s><s>CXCL9 mRNA levels obtained by qRT-PCR were normalized against respective GAPDH mRNA levels, and further normalized against non-infected (NI) cells.</s><s>Data show mean ± SD of 4 independent biological experiments (performed with cells from 2 different donors) with 2 technical replicates each.</s><s>For statistical analysis, infected samples were compared with uninfected, IFNG-treated controls: ns non-significant, **P &lt; .01.</s><s>Immunoblot analysis of STAT1 (F) or STAT3 (G) phosphorylation of primary cells mock-infected (NI) or infected with H pylori P12 wt, P12Dcgt or 2 clones of the recomplemented strains Dcgt/cgt for 24 hours at MOI 50, followed by treatment with (F) IFNG (5 ng/mL, 30 minutes) or (G) IL22 (50 ng/mL, 30 minutes).</s><s>Quantification of (F) shows band intensity ratio of STAT1pY:actin.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Prolonged infection prevents IFNG-induced activation of JAK1, JAK2, and STAT1 through Cgt activity.</s><s>MKN45 cells were infected with the indicated strains (HK, heat killed) at MOI 50 and treated (þ) or mock-treated (-) with IFNG (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes) at the indicated times post-infection (p.i.).</s><s>(A and B) Immunoblot analysis of total protein level and phosphorylation of JAK1 or STAT1, respectively.</s><s>(C) Analysis of JAK2 phosphorylation (red) by confocal IF, maximum projection.</s><s>Cells were noninfected (NI) or infected with indicated H pylori strains (green) and treated with IFNG (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes).</s><s>Scale bar ¼ 5 mm.</s><s>(D and E) Immunoblot analysis JAK1 and STAT1 phosphorylation and total protein levels of MKN45 cells infected or mockinfected (NI) for 24 hours at MOI 50 with the indicated H pylori strains and treatment with IFNG (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,48.93,65.37,497.51,402.46" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Cholesterol depletion by H pylori blocks IFNG signaling by disrupting lipid rafts, impairing IFNGR complex assembly.(A)</s><s>Immunoblot analysis of JAK1/STAT1 phosphorylation after 5 hours mbCD treatment at indicated concentrations or in nontreated cells (-), with or without IFNG treatment (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes).</s><s>(B) Immunoblot analysis of JAK1 and STAT1 phosphorylation upon IFNG treatment (þ).</s><s>MKN45 cells were infected for 24 hours with the indicated strains or non-infected, then treated with IFNG (þ) (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes).</s><s>Cholesterol-coating of bacteria was started 1 hour before infection and applied to non-infected cells accordingly.</s><s>(C) Immunoblot analysis of STAT1 phosphorylation upon IFNG and/or PEG-cholesterol treatment.</s><s>MKN45 cells were infected for 24 hours with H pylori wt or non-infected.</s><s>In selected wells (þ), PEG-cholesterol (5 mg/mL) was added during the final hour of infection.</s><s>Then, cells were treated with IFNG (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes) (þ) or mock-treated (-).</s><s>Quantification: band intensity ratio STAT1pY:actin.</s><s>(D) Confocal microscopy analysis (x-y sections with lateral views along dotted lines: x-z, bottom; y-z right) of the lipid raft marker GM1 (green) in membranes of cells non-infected or infected for 24 hours with indicated strains.</s><s>Nuclei stained with DAPI (blue).</s><s>Scale bar: 5 mm.</s><s>(E) Immunoblot analysis of detergent-resistant membranes for IFNGR1, IFNGR2, caveolin, or dot blot analysis with CTxB-HRP.</s><s>Cells were non-infected or infected for 24 hours with indicated strains, followed by treatment (þ) or mock-treatment (-) with IFNG (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes).</s><s>(F and G) Immunoprecipitation (IP) and immunoblot analysis of IFNGR subunits 1 and 2. IFNGR2 was pulled down using IFNGR2 antibody.</s><s>MKN45 cells were infected with H pylori P12 wt or coated with water-soluble cholesterol before infection.</s><s>Results representative of 2 independent experiments.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,48.93,65.37,497.51,415.11" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>=Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. IFN response triggered by H pylori in vivo is ineffective.</s><s>(A) Bacterial clearance in C57BL6 wt and Ifngr1 -/-mice orally infected with PMSS1 wt or PMSS1Dcgt.</s><s>Each point represents CFU counts for individual mice.</s><s>Mean ± SD is also represented.</s><s>**P &lt;.01.</s><s>(B) RT-qPCR analysis of IFNG and IRF1 expression in stomachs of infected wt and Ifngr1 -/-mice, shown as fold-change to respective expression of mGAPDH.</s><s>Data represented as mean ± SD. ns, non-significant, *P &lt;.05.</s><s>(C) Confocal microscopy image of longitudinal stomach sections of mice orally infected with PMSS1 for 2 weeks, labelled for actin (phalloidin, red), H pylori (green), and nuclei (DAPI, blue).</s><s>Scale bars: 1000 mm (upper) and 100 mm (lower).</s><s>(D) RT-qPCR analysis of IFNG and IRF1 expression in samples taken from corpus or antrum of the mice used in (C), results represented as in (B).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. Cgt prevents IFNB-, IL6-, and IL22-induced signaling in epithelial cells upon prolonged infection and impairs hBD3 expression.</s><s>(A) Immunoblot analysis of STAT1 pathway activation in MKN45 cells.</s><s>Cells were infected for 24 hours with indicated strains or non-infected, then treated (þ) or mock-treated (-) with IFNB (2300 U/mL) for 30 minutes.</s><s>(B and C)Immunoblot analysis of STAT3 activation in MKN45 cells infected for 24 hours with indicated strains or treated with mbCD (5 mg/mL) for 5 hours, followed by 30 minutes with (B) IL6 (100 ng/mL) or (C) IL22 (50 ng/mL).</s><s>(D and E) RT-qPCR analysis of hBD3.</s><s>MKN45 cells were non-infected or infected with indicated strains for 24 hours.</s><s>IFNG (10 ng/mL) (D) or IL22 (50 ng/mL) (E) were then added to selected wells for the specified times.</s><s>To represent the net response to cytokines, results are normalized against relative gene expression of corresponding non-infected, P12 wt and P12Dcgt infected cells.</s><s>Data represented as mean ± SD. ns, non-significant, **P &lt;.01.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,48.93,65.37,497.51,289.42" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. Cgt blocks IFN signaling in primary gastric epithelial cells.</s><s>Human primary gastric cells were infected with indicated strains at MOI 20 for 24 hours or non-infected.</s><s>(A) Immunoblot analysis of JAK1/STAT1 pathway activation.</s><s>After infection cells from antrum were mock-treated or treated for 30 minutes with IFNG (5 ng/mL) or IFNB (2300 U/mL).</s><s>Quantification: band intensity ratio STAT1pY: actin.</s><s>(B) Cholesterol-coating of bacteria was started 1 hour before infection and applied to non-infected cells accordingly.</s><s>Afterwards cells were mock-treated or treated for 30 minutes with IFNG (5 ng/mL).</s><s>Result representative of 2 independent experiments.</s><s>(C) Immunoblot analysis of STAT3 activation.</s><s>Cells from antrum were infected for 24 hours with indicated strains and after infection treated for 30 minutes with IL22 (50 ng/mL).</s><s>(D and E) Primary human cells were infected with H pylori P12 wt or P12Dcgt for 26.5 hours and microarray results compared with those obtained in non-infected (n.i.) cells.</s><s>Results shown are from 2 independent experiments with cells obtained from 2 independent donors.</s><s>(D) Gene Ontology processes enrichment (Panther) from up-regulated genes in n.i. vs. P12 wt data set.</s><s>In all cases P &lt; .05. (E) NF-kB-response genes differentially modulated in n.i. vs. P12 wt and n.i.</s><s>vs P12Dcgt datasets.</s><s>In all cases, fold change &gt; 1.5 and P value &lt;.05.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,48.93,65.37,497.51,368.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6.</s><s>Block of cytokine responses in infected ALI cultures.</s><s>Primary human cells grown on filters were infected with P12 wt at MOI 100 for 3 days or mock-infected (NI), then mock-treated or treated for 30 minutes with IFNG (10 ng/mL) (A and B) or IL22 (50 ng/mL) (C) and fixed with PFA.</s><s>Filters were labelled with DAPI (DNA, blue) and antibodies against H pylori (red) and analyzed by whole-mount IF. (A) Analysis of STAT1 phosphorylation.</s><s>Filters were labelled with phalloidin (green) and STAT1-pY (white).</s><s>Scale bar: 20 mm.</s><s>(B) Analysis of STAT1 phosphorylation, lower magnification.</s><s>Filters were labelled with antibodies against STAT1-pY (white).</s><s>Scale bar: 50 mm.</s><s>(C) Analysis of STAT3 phosphorylation.</s><s>Filters were labelled with antibodies against STAT3-pY (white).</s><s>Scale bar: 20 mm.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,48.93,65.37,497.51,550.94" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 7. Summary of cholesterol-dependent subversion of immune response.</s><s>Extraction of host cell cholesterol by H pylori's Cgt disrupts lipid rafts and thereby prevents assembly of IFNG receptors.</s><s>In infected cells this leads to a shutdown of JAK/STAT1 signaling, inhibiting the production of T-cell chemo-attractants and antimicrobial peptides like hBD3.</s><s>With this mechanism, H pylori creates micro-niches of locally diminished inflammation, despite a marked global immune response.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="11,162.43,65.37,377.74,470.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="1,74.10,273.15,445.87,179.26" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="19,102.73,65.37,388.51,275.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1404">.e4 Morey et al Gastroenterology Vol. 154, No. 5</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p><s>The authors thank Jörg Angermann, Kirstin Hoffmann, Stefanie Mülllerke, and Ina Wagner for technical assistance, Robert Hurwitz for generating the Cgt antibody, Toni Aebischer, Bianca Bauer, Michael Fehlings, June Ghosh-Guha, and Eric Perret for fruitful discussions, and Rike Zietlow for expert editing of the manuscript.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary Material</head><p><s>Note: To access the supplementary material accompanying this article, visit the online version of Gastroenterology at www.gastrojournal.org,</s><s>and at https://doi.org/10.1053/</s><s>j.gastro.2017.12.008.</s></p><p><s>Author contributions P.M., E.P., and L.P. designed and performed the experiments and analyzed the data; V.D. and M.K. performed the in vivo experiments; H.-J.M. analyzed the microarray data; P.S., F.B., M.S., A.I.M., M.K, and T.F.M. provided experimental guidance during the study; P.M., L.P., and T.F.M. wrote the manuscript; T.F.M. conceived the study and provided conceptual guidance.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflicts of interest</head><p><s>The authors disclose no conflicts.</s></p><p><s>Grant support P.M. was supported by the People Programme (Marie Curie Actions) of the European Union's Seventh Framework Programme FP7/2007-2013/ under REA grant agreement no.</s><s>316682; E.P. and L.P. received support from the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft through grant SFB633 to T.F.M.; M.S. was funded as a clinician scientist by the Berlin Institute of Health (BIH).</s><s>The funders played no role in the design of the study or the collection, analysis, and interpretation of the data.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Transcript profiling</head><p><s>Microarray data have been deposited in the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO; www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/) of the National Center for Biotechnology Information and can be accessed with the GEO accession number GSE76589.</s><s>= Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref>. (A) Cholesterol quantification of MKN45 upon H pylori infection.</s><s>Cells were non-infected (NI) or infected with indicated strains of H pylori for 24 hours at MOI 50.</s><s>After this period, cholesterol was quantified using Amplex kit (Invitrogen Carlsbad, CA).</s><s>All readings were normalized against protein content and further normalized against cholesterol levels in non-infected cells.</s><s>Data show mean ± SD of 2 independent biological experiments with 2 technical replicates each.</s><s>(B) Cellular viability of MKN45 cells treated with mbCD (5 mg/mL) for 6 hours.</s><s>Viability was measured via a fluorescence-based ATP assay (Promega).</s><s>All readings were normalized against the NI and mock-treated cells.</s><s>Cells treated for 5 minutes with TritonX-100 served as control.</s><s>Data show mean ± SD of 2 independent biological experiments with 2 technical replicates each.</s><s>(C) Response to 2.5-hour treatment with IFNG (10 ng/mL) after mock treatment or treatment with myriocin (72 hours, 50 mmol/ L) plus zaragozic acid (18 hours, 50 mmol/L) (MZ).</s><s>IRF1 mRNA levels obtained by qRT-PCR were normalized against respective GAPDH mRNA expression, and further normalized against non-infected (NI) cells.</s><s>Data show mean ± SD of 2 independent biological experiments with 2 technical replicates each.</s><s>For statistical analysis, MZ-treated samples were compared with mock, IFNG-treated controls: ns non-significant, **P &lt;.01.</s><s>(D) Response to 2.5-hour treatment with IFNG for IRF1 gene in cells infected with bacteria with or without cholesterol coating.</s><s>MKN45 cells were non-infected or infected with indicated H pylori strains for 24 hours.</s><s>IFNG (10 ng/mL) was then added to selected wells for the 2.5 hours.</s><s>To represent the net response to IFN, results were normalized against relative gene expression of respective corresponding non-infected, P12 and P12Dcgt infected cells.</s><s>Data are represented as mean ± SD; ns, non-significant, **P &lt; .01. (E) Viability of cholesterol-coated bacteria.</s><s>Bacteria (10 8 /mL) in serum-free medium were coated or mock-coated with exogenous cholesterol (1 mg/mL) for 1 hour.</s><s>Colony forming units (CFU)/mL were quantified 3 days later.</s><s>Data are expressed as percentage bacterial survival relative to the untreated P12 (without cholesterol coating).</s><s>Data show mean ± SD of 2 independent biological experiments with 2 technical replicates each.</s><s>(F) Confocal microscopic analysis of the lipid raft marker GM1 (stained with CTxB-Alexa488, green) in cellular membranes of cells non-infected (NI) or infected for 24 hours with indicated H pylori strains.</s><s>Left panel corresponds to the quantification of relative superficial GM1 signal.</s><s>Results are shown as a box-plot (2nd and 3rd quartiles, median represented as horizontal line inside the box) of the ratio between cellular membrane and correspondent cytoplasm average intensities and further normalized to the average intensity ratio of non-infected cells of each corresponding experiment.</s><s>Data correspond to 3 independent experiments; n ¼ number of analyzed cells; **P &lt; .01.</s><s>Right panel, representative images used for quantification.</s><s>Scale bar: 10 mm.</s><s>(G) Immunoblot analysis of detergent resistant membrane fractions (1-10, from top to bottom) of uninfected MKN45 cells after density gradient centrifugation for distribution of caveolin or GM1 distribution detected by dot blot with cholera toxin B conjugated to HRP.</s><s>Fractions inside the box were pooled for further analysis.</s><s>(H) Immunoblot analysis of whole cell lysate of MKN45 cells for IFNGR1, IFNGR2, or caveolin.</s><s>Cells were non-infected (NI) or infected for 24 hours with indicated H pylori strains.</s><s>After infection time, cells were treated (þ) or mock-treated (-) with IFNG (10 ng/mL, 30 minutes).</s><s>(I) Immunoprecipitation (IP) and immunoblot analysis of IFNGR subunits 1, 2, and CD71.</s><s>IFNGR2 was pulled down using anti-IFNGR2 antibody.</s><s>Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref>. (A) Immunoblot analysis of STAT1 phosphorylation after 5 hours mbCD treatment at the concentrations indicated or in non-treated cells (-).</s><s>IFNB treatment (2300 U/mL, 30 minutes) was applied in selected wells.</s><s>The result is representative of 3 independent experiments.</s><s>Quantification shows band intensity ratio of STAT1pY:actin (B) Immunoblot analysis of STAT3 phosphorylation of MKN45 cells infected with indicated H pylori strains or mock-infected (NI) for 24 hours at MOI 50 with the indicated H pylori strains, followed by treatment with IL22 (50 ng/mL) for 30 minutes.</s><s>(C) Immunoblot analysis of STAT3 activation in MKN45 cells.</s><s>Cells were infected for 24 hours with H pylori P12 wild type or mock infected.</s><s>In selected wells PEG-cholesterol was added during the final hour of infection.</s><s>Cells were then treated with IL22 (50 ng/mL, 30 minutes) (þ) or mock-treated (-).</s><s>Quantification shows band intensity ratio of STAT1pY:actin.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The human gastric pathogen helicobacter pylori and its association with gastric cancer and ulcer disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ulcers</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2011</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Helicobacter pylori activates and expands Lgr5(þ) stem cells through direct colonization of the gastric glands</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sigal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Rothenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Logan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gastroenterology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1392" to="1404" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>e21</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ALPK1-and TIFA-dependent innate immune response triggered by the helicobacter pylori type IV secretion system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zimmermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Pfannkuch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Al-Zeer</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Bartfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2384" to="2395" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lymphocytes in the human gastric mucosa during Helicobacter pylori have a T helper cell 1 phenotype</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bamford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Fan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Crowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gastroenterology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="482" to="492" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Life in the human stomach: persistence strategies of the bacterial pathogen Helicobacter pylori</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Salama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hartung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Muller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="385" to="399" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The CD4þ T cellmediated IFN-gamma response to Helicobacter infection is essential for clearance and determines gastric cancer risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sayi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kohler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hitzler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">182</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7085" to="7101" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">NOD1 contributes to mouse host defense against Helicobacter pylori via induction of type I IFN and activation of the ISGF3 signaling pathway</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Watanabe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Asano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fichtner-Feigl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1645" to="1662" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IL-23 Contributes to control of chronic Helicobacter pylori infection and the development of T helper responses in a mouse model</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Horvath</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Washington</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cope</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">56</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A pro-inflammatory role for Th22 cells in Helicobacter pylori-associated gastritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhuang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gut</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1368" to="1378" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cross talk between interferon-gamma and -alpha/beta signaling components in caveolar membrane domains</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Takaoka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Mitani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Suemori</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">288</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2357" to="2360" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glycosylationdependent IFN-gammaR partitioning in lipid and actin nanodomains is critical for JAK activation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Blouin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hamon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gonnord</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">166</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="920" to="934" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulation of type I interferon responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ivashkiv</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Donlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Interleukin-22 mediates early host defense against attaching and effacing bacterial pathogens</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Valdez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Danilenko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="282" to="289" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Helicobacter pylori virulence effector CagA abrogates human beta-defensin 3 expression via inactivation of EGFR signaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Holland</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Host Microbe</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="576" to="586" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gastric antimicrobial peptides fail to eradicate Helicobacter pylori infection due to selective induction and resistance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nuding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gersemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hosaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e73867</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">beta-Defensin-3 and -4 in intestinal epithelial cells display increased mRNA expression in ulcerative colitis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fahlgren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hammarstrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Danielsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Exp Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="379" to="385" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation between beta-defensin expression and induction profiles in gingival keratinocytes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Joly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Organ</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1073" to="1084" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IL-17a and IL-22 induce expression of antimicrobials in gastrointestinal epithelial cells and may contribute to epithelial cell defense against Helicobacter pylori</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Dixon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Radin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Piazuelo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e0148514</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential expression of human beta defensin 2 and 3 in gastric mucosa of Helicobacter pylori-infected individuals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wex</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kuester</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Helicobacter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="12" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloning of a cholesterol-alpha-glucosyltransferase from Helicobacter pylori</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lebrun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wunder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hildebrand</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">281</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27765" to="27772" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Helicobacter pylori cholesteryl glucosides interfere with host membrane phase and affect type IV secretion system function during infection in AGS cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="84" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cholesterol glucosylation promotes immune evasion by Helicobacter pylori</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wunder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Churin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Winau</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1030" to="1038" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modulation of the CD4þ T-cell response by Helicobacter pylori depends on known virulence factors and bacterial cholesterol and cholesterol alpha-glucoside content</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Beigier-Bompadre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Moos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Belogolova</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">204</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1339" to="1348" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cholesterol glucosylation by Helicobacter pylori delays internalization and arrests phagosome maturation in macrophages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Microbiol Immunol Infect</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="636" to="645" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Helicobacter pylori infection activates Src homology-2 domain-containing phosphatase 2 to suppress IFN-gamma signaling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Sheu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">193</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4149" to="4158" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Orchestration of membrane receptor signaling by membrane lipids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Arish</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Husein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kashif</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochimie</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Restoration of IFN-gammaR subunit assembly, IFNgamma signaling and parasite clearance in Leishmania donovani infected macrophages: role of membrane cholesterol</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mukherjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Pathog</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1002229</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cytokine signaling: STATS in plasma membrane rafts</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Sehgal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Shah</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">277</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12067" to="12074" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antimicrobial peptides and gut microbiota in homeostasis and pathology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ostaff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Stange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wehkamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO Mol Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1465" to="1483" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel human gastric primary cell culture system for modelling Helicobacter pylori infection in vitro</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schlaermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Toelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Berger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gut</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="202" to="213" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vitro expansion of human gastric epithelial stem cells and their responses to bacterial infection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bartfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bayram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Van De Wetering</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gastroenterology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="126" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>e6</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Polarised epithelial monolayers of the gastric mucosa reveal insights into mucosal homeostasis and defence against infection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Boccellato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Woelffling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Imai-Matsushima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/gutjnl-2017-314540</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1136/gutjnl-2017-314540" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gut</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Epub ahead of print</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chronic exposure to Helicobacter pylori impairs dendritic cell function and inhibits Th1 development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mitchell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Germain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Fiori</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Infect Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="810" to="819" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cytokine gene polymorphisms influence mucosal cytokine expression, gastric inflammation, and host specific colonisation during Helicobacter pylori infection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dossumbekova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Neu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gut</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1082" to="1089" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inflammatory gene profiles in gastric mucosa during Helicobacter pylori infection in humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Felley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bouzourene</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">172</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2595" to="2606" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Helicobacter pylori vacuolating cytotoxin inhibits T lymphocyte activation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gebert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Fischer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">301</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1099" to="1102" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Helicobacter pylori gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase and vacuolating cytotoxin promote gastric persistence and immune tolerance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oertli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Noben</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Engler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3047" to="3052" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inflammation, immunity, vaccines for Helicobacter pylori infection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Moss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Helicobacter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial and temporal shifts in bacterial biogeography and gland occupation during the development of a chronic infection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Keilberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zavros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Shepherd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">MBio</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mucosal vaccination increases local chemokine production attracting immune cells to the stomach mucosa of Helicobacter pylori infected mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Flach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mozer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sundquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vaccine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1636" to="1643" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immunization of mice with urease vaccine affords protection against Helicobacter pylori infection in the absence of antibodies and is mediated by MHC class II-restricted responses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ermak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Giannasca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nichols</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Exp Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">188</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2277" to="2288" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Natural antibiotic function of a human gastric mucin against Helicobacter pylori infection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kawakubo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Okimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">305</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1003" to="1006" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influence of EPIYA-repeat polymorphism on the phosphorylationdependent biological activity of Helicobacter pylori CagA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Naito</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yamazaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Tsutsumi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gastroenterology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1181" to="1190" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cholesterol manipulation by West Nile virus perturbs the cellular immune response</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mackenzie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Khromykh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Parton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Host Microbe</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="229" to="239" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cholesterol depletion results in site-specific increases in epidermal growth factor receptor phosphorylation due to membrane level effects. Studies with cholesterol enantiomers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Westover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Covey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Brockman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">278</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="51125" to="51133" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cholesterol suppresses cellular TGF-beta responsiveness: implications in atherogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fliesler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cell Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3509" to="3521" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Modeling infectious diseases and hostmicrobe interactions in gastrointestinal organoids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bartfeld</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">420</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="262" to="270" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transgenic expression of interferon-gamma in mouse stomach leads to inflammation, metaplasia, and dysplasia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Syu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>El-Zaatari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Eaton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Pathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">181</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2114" to="2125" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The relationship between updated Sydney System score and LDL cholesterol levels in patients infected with Helicobacter pylori</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kucukazman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Yavuz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sacikara</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dig Dis Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="604" to="607" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
