<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Galleria mellonella larvae allow the discrimination of toxic and non-toxic chemicals</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-02-06">6 February 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Enrico</forename><surname>Allegra</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Envigo Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Huntingdon, Cambridgeshire</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Titball</surname></persName>
							<email>r.w.titball@exeter.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Biosciences University of Exeter</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>EX4 4QD</postCode>
									<settlement>Exeter</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Carter</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Envigo Ltd</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Huntingdon, Cambridgeshire</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Olivia</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Champion</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Biosystems Technology Ltd Colleton Crescent</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>EX2 4DG</postCode>
									<settlement>Exeter</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Galleria mellonella larvae allow the discrimination of toxic and non-toxic chemicals</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-02-06">6 February 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5A11726C129E97D3E6ACB04C1CD720CA</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2018.01.175</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 20 December 2017 Received in revised form 22 January 2018 Accepted 31 January 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:17+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Galleria mellonella Toxicity testing Cell culture Globally Harmonised system</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>The version presented here may differ from the published version.</s><s>If citing, you are advised to consult the published version for pagination, volume/issue and date of publication</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p><s>Estimating the toxicity of chemicals, biocides, pesticides and cosmetics is essential to reduce the risk of the exposure of humans to hazardous materials that could cause illness <ref type="bibr">(European Union, 2006)</ref>.</s><s>Apart from cosmetic testing, tests are typically carried out using mammals, providing an LD50 value.</s><s>Increasingly, there are initiatives to reduce the use of mammals for testing.</s><s>In vitro toxicity data towards cultured cells can be used to estimate the dose for subsequent rodent acute toxicity tests, and this methodology forms the basis of the acute toxicity Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) 129 method (Environment directorate joint meeting of the chemicals committee and the working party on chemicals, 2010).</s><s>This allows the use of mammals to be reduced, as a consequence of refined dose estimations.</s><s>However, although cytotoxicity tests can reveal intrinsic cell sensitivity to the toxicity of chemicals, factors associated with metabolism of the compound such as rates of absorption, biotransformation, distribution and excretion may not be simulated in cell culture systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Schrage et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">van Vliet, 2011)</ref>.</s><s>Consequently, the toxicity of some chemicals in mammals is not well predicted from cell culture data (Environment directorate joint meeting of the chemicals committee and the working party on chemicals, 2010; <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Schrage et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">van Vliet, 2011)</ref>.</s><s>Furthermore, differences occur between cytotoxicity test results in different laboratories.</s><s>This may reflect differences in the cell line used, preservation and culture methods and passage number.</s><s>These limitations are highlighted in the OECD 129 guidance document (Environment directorate joint meeting of the chemicals committee and the working party on chemicals, 2010) which states "The limitations of the in vitro methods are largely due to the differences between whole animal and cell culture systems" Consequently there is a requirement for tests that can better predict toxicity in mammals.</s><s>Galleria mellonella (wax moth) larvae are considered to be non-animal technologies.</s><s>However, they reflect aspects of the complexity present in mammals and are accepted as an ethical alternative for research <ref type="bibr">(Lionakis, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Champion et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Tsai et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>For example, G. mellonella possess an innate immune system that is structurally and functionally similar to that of mammals <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Browne et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Wojda, 2017)</ref>.</s><s>In the UK and other countries studies using G. mellonella larvae are not regulated, reducing the costs associated with studies and enabling the system to be used flexibly.</s><s>In addition, the ability to use large groups of larvae can increase the statistical power of studies.</s><s>The larvae used are 6th instar stage and do not feed.</s><s>Therefore maintenance is simple.</s><s>G. mellonella are being used widely to investigate mechanisms of bacterial and fungal pathogenicity, and the efficacy and pharmacokinetics of antimicrobials <ref type="bibr">(Lionakis, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Champion et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Tsai et al., 2016)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>More recently there are preliminary reports that G. mellonella can be used to test the toxicity of chemicals <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Megaw et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Dolan et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Maguire et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>In one study, G. mellonella larvae were used to measure the relative toxicity of 8 food preservatives and a correlation between the LD50 values in G. mellonella larvae and in rats was demonstrated <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Maguire et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>Here we set out to test the potential to use G. mellonella larvae to predict the acute toxicity of a panel of compounds in mammals.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Material and methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Chemicals</head><p><s>Most chemicals were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (Poole, UK).</s><s>Acetonitrile, glycerol, sodium dichromate dehydrate, sodium hypochlorite and xylene were obtained from Fisher Scientific (Loughborough, UK).</s><s>Chloramphenicol was obtained from Acros Organics (Loughborough, UK).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Injection of Galleria mellonella larvae</head><p><s>G. mellonella larvae (TruLarvTM) were purchased from Biosystems Technology (Exeter, UK) <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Champion et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Wand et al., 2011)</ref>.</s><s>Larvae (0.2 g) were injected with 10 mL of chemical into the front proleg using a micro-syringe (Hamilton Ltd).</s><s>For each chemical 6 dilutions were made and each dilution injected into a groups of 10 larvae.</s><s>Larvae were incubated at room temperature (20e25 C) and mortality scored at 24 h, 48 h and 72 h.</s><s>Death was defined as complete loss of mobility including following a physical stimulus using a plastic pipette.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Calculation of LD50</head><p><s>In order to analyse mortality, a probit Model was used: y ¼ F(aþb *Log10(conc)), where conc is concentration, F is the standard normal distribution and y is the proportion of events which occurred.</s><s>Parameters a and b were estimated as well as Log10 (LD50) ¼ -a/b.</s><s>To evaluate the dose response relationship, the 95% confidence interval for b (slope) was determined.</s><s>The calculation of LD50 provides a value in mg/mL, the LD50 in mg kg-1 was determined by multiplying by 50, assuming a typical weight of 0.2 g per larvae.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Cytotoxicity and oral toxicity in mammals</head><p><s>The toxicities of chemicals in human epidermal keratinocyte cells (NHK cells), in murine fibroblast cells (3T3 cells) or oral toxicity in rats was taken from the OECD Guidance on using cytotoxicity tests to estimate starting doses for acute oral systemic toxicity tests (Environment directorate joint meeting of the chemicals committee and the working party on chemicals, 2010).</s><s>The LD50 doses of chemicals in mammals, extrapolated from IC50 values in cell culture, were calculated as previously described (Environment directorate joint meeting of the chemicals committee and the working party on chemicals, 2010).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results and discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Effects of solvents on G. mellonella larvae</head><p><s>We first tested the responses of G. mellonella larvae to ethanol, water or DMSO solvents.</s><s>No deaths were recorded in larvae dosed with SDW.</s><s>All larvae were killed after the injection of 80% DMSO but not 50% DMSO.</s><s>30% (v/v) ethanol was tolerated, but 2 of 10 larvae dosed with 40% ethanol died.</s><s>For subsequent studies we ensured that the concentrations of solvents given to larvae did not exceed 50% (v/v) DMSO or 30% (v/v) ethanol.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Testing chemical toxicity in G. mellonella larvae</head><p><s>We selected 30 chemicals for toxicity testing in G. mellonella larvae.</s><s>Three chemicals selected for testing (5-aminosalicylic acid, propylparaben and xylene) could not be solubilised and could therefore not be injected.</s><s>The toxicity of 8 chemicals could only be estimated due to limited solubility (Table <ref type="table">1A</ref>).</s><s>A dilution series of the remaining 19 chemicals was made to provide concentrations bracketing the expected LD50 dose.</s><s>Each dilution was injected into a group of G. mellonella larvae, mortality recorded and the LD50 values calculated (Table <ref type="table">1B</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Prediction of toxicity from studies in G. mellonella larvae and in cell cultures</head><p><s>We next considered toxicities according to the GHS categorisation of chemicals.</s><s>This system places chemicals into one of five categories (Fig. <ref type="figure">1a</ref> and Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>) ranging from low toxicity (GHS category 5, LD50 2000e5000 mg kg-1) to highly toxic (GHS category 1, LD50 &lt; 5 mg kg-1).</s><s>For the 9 chemicals tested which had been assigned to GHS category 5, the toxicity measured in G. mellonella larvae was consistent with the GHS categorisation (Fig. <ref type="figure">1b</ref>).</s><s>In comparison, cytotoxicity measured using 3T3 or NHK cells predicted 4 out of 9 chemicals in GHS category 5 as having low toxicity with the remaining 5 chemicals being predicted as weakly toxic or very toxic.</s><s>A previous study <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Schrage et al., 2011)</ref> where 79 GHS category 5 chemicals were tested also highlighted the poor correlation of oral toxicity in rats with in vitro cytotoxicity.</s><s>In this previous study, of the 79 chemicals tested only 6 (8%) were found to have low toxicity towards cell cultures, the remainder being more toxic.</s><s>This might reflect the inability of cell cultures to detoxify or excrete cytotoxic chemicals.</s><s>These findings are important, because the incorrect assessment of these chemicals could trigger studies using mammals to evaluate oral toxicity and could result in the unnecessary testing of compounds in mammals.</s></p><p><s>For chemicals tested in this study where acute oral LD50 values were less than 2000 mg kg-1 (GHS categories 1e4), testing in G. mellonella larvae showed 8 out of 10 chemicals to be correctly predicted.</s><s>In comparison, cytotoxicity methods predicted 10 out of 10 chemicals as being classified in GHS categories 1e4.</s></p><p><s>Overall, testing in G. mellonella larvae classified 11 out of 19 chemicals (58%) in the same GHS class as measured in rats.</s><s>Cytotoxicity towards NHK cells classified 11 out of 19 chemicals (58%) in the same hazard class as measured from acute oral LD50 tests in rats.</s><s>Cytotoxicity towards 3T3 cells classified 9 out of 19 chemicals (47%) in the same hazard class.</s></p><p><s>Some chemicals are converted into other toxins as a consequence of mammalian metabolism, and especially via the cytochrome P450 enzymes.</s><s>There is some data indicating that the cytochrome P450 enzymes from insects behave like their counterparts in mammals <ref type="bibr">(Feyereisen, 1999)</ref>.</s><s>For example, converting caffeine into theobromine, paraxanthine and theophylline <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Coelho et al., 2015)</ref>.</s><s>However, there are also examples of differences.</s><s>For example, in mammals acetonitrile is metabolised to cyanide by cytochrome P450 enzymes <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Pozzani et al., 1959)</ref>, but this chemical was essentially non-toxic in G. mellonella.</s><s>Since insects are susceptible to killing by cyanide <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Bond, 1962)</ref> this suggests that they do not metabolise this chemical in the same was as mammals.</s><s>Toxicity measurements in cell cultures or in G. mellonella larvae both have limitations.</s><s>However, there are differences in the ease with which the tests can be carried out.</s><s>Significant preparation time is required for the propogation of cells in the laboratory before use, whereas G. mellonella larvae can be purchased and used on the same day.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusions</head><p><s>This study investigated the suitability of G. mellonella larvae to measure the acute toxicity of chemicals compared to cell culture systems.</s><s>In general, cell culture systems overestimated the toxicity of chemicals, especially low toxicity chemicals.</s><s>In contrast, toxicity testing in G. mellonella larvae was found to be a reliable predictor for low toxicity chemicals.</s><s>We believe that a more robust assessment of the likely toxicity of chemicals in mammals could be made by measuring toxicity in both cell culture and in G. mellonella larvae.</s><s>Further studies in G. mellonella larvae to establish repeatability and reproducibility of tests and to investigate a wider panel of chemicals are warranted.</s></p><p><s>Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</s><s>Linear trendlines showing the relationship of oral toxicity in rats (x axis) with oral toxicity measured in rats (C), in G. mellonella larvae (-) or extrapolated from toxicity data in 3T3 (A) or NHK (:) cell cultures.</s><s>The panels below the X-axis show the range of toxicity of GHS category 1 (&lt;5 mg kg -1 ); GHS category 2 (5e50 mg kg-1); category 3 (50e300 mg kg -1 ); category 4 (300e2000 mg kg-1); category 5 (&gt;2000 mg kg -1 ).</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="1,262.15,479.73,333.12,362.16" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,44.50,472.42,247.90,211.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Appendix A. Supplementary data</head><p><s>Supplementary data related to this article can be found at https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2018.01.175.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of oxygen on cyanide poisoning in insects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Bond</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">193</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1002" to="e1003" />
			<date type="published" when="1962">1962</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An analysis of the structural and functional similarities of insect hemocytes and mammalian phagocytes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Browne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Heelan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kavanagh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Virulence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="597" to="e603" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Galleria mellonella as an alternative infection model for Yersinia pseudotuberculosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Champion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>James</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Karlyshev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Duffield</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Oyston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Titball</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Microbiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1516" to="e1522" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Galleria mellonella as a model host for microbiological and toxin research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Champion</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wagley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Titball</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Virulence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="840" to="e845" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cytochrome P450-dependent metabolism of caffeine in Drosophila melanogaster</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Coelho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fraichard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Le Goff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Faure</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Artur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Ferveur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Heydel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. e0117328</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synthesis, antibacterial and anti-MRSA activity, in vivo toxicity and a structureactivity relationship study of a quinoline thiourea</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Dolan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gavin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Eshwika</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kavanagh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcginley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Stephens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioorg Med Chem Letts</title>
		<editor>Directorate, E.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="630" to="e635" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2016. 2010</date>
			<publisher>Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Guidance document on using cytotoxicity tests to estimate starting doses for acute oral systemic toxicity tests</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">concerning the registration, evaluation, authorisation and restriction of chemicals (REACH), establishing a European Chemicals Agency, amending directive 1999/45/EC and repealing Council regulation (EEC) no 793/93 and Commission regulation (EC) no 1488/94 as well as Council directive 76/769/EEC and Commission directives 91/155/EEC, 93/67/ EEC, 93/105/EC and 2000/21/EC. Off J Eur Union L 396, 1e520. Feyereisen, R., 1999. Insect P450 enzymes</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">507e533. Lionakis, M.S., 2011. Drosophila and Galleria insect model hosts: new tools for the study of fungal virulence, pharmacology and immunology</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>European Union</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1907-12-18">2006. 1907. 18 December 2006</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="521" to="e527" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of Galleria mellonella larvae as an in vivo model for assessing the relative toxicity of food preservative agents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Maguire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Duggan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kavanagh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Biol. Toxicol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="209" to="e216" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Galleria mellonella as a novel in vivo model for assessment of the toxicity of 1-alkyl-3-methylimidazolium chloride ionic liquids</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Megaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lafferty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gilmore</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chemosphere</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015. 197e201</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An investigation of the mammalian toxicity of acetonitrile</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Pozzani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Carpenter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Palm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Weil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Nair 3rd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Occup. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="634" to="e642" />
			<date type="published" when="1959">1959</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Refinement and reduction of acute oral toxicity testing: a critical review of the use of cytotoxicity data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schrage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hempel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schulz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Kolle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Van Ravenzwaay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Landsiedel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ATLA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="e295" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Galleria mellonella infection models for the study of bacterial diseases and for antimicrobial drug testing. Virulence 7, 214e229</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Loh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Proft</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">; M E</forename><surname>Van Vliet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Muller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Titball</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Michell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Microbiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2016. 2011. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ALTEX</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Immunity of the greater wax moth Galleria mellonella</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Wojda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Insect Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="342" to="e357" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
