<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Sillem</surname></persName>
							<email>martin.sillem@t-online.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Praxisklinik am Rosengarten</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Mannheim</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Juhasz-Böss</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Frauenklinik Homburg</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Uniklinikum Saarland</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Homburg, Saar</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Klausmeier</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">DC Physiotherapie</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Universitätsmedizin Mannheim</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Mannheim</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mechsner</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Benjamin Franklin</addrLine>
									<settlement>Gynäkologie, Charité, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Siedentopf</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Klinik für Gynäkologie und Geburtshilfe</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Martin-Luther-Krankenhaus</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Solomayer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Frauenklinik Homburg</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Uniklinikum Saarland</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Homburg, Saar</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Praxisklinik am Rosengarten</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>7-11 68165</postCode>
									<settlement>Augustaanlage, Mannheim</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">0016-5751</idno>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">6475E9FE0B1EF8A25945E26C1ED1F73B</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1055/s-0042-111010</idno>
					<note type="submission">received 29. 3. 2016 revised 15. 5. 2016 accepted 22. 6. 2016</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:18+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>No accurate epidemiological data on the incidence of chronic pelvic pain in women, an ill-defined term, have been published to date.</s><s>In a review of the international literature, Latthe et al.</s></p><p><s>[1] state a prevalence of 2-24 % for chronic, non-cyclical pelvic pain; estimates for the USA and Germany are between 7 and 15 % [2-4].</s><s>In gynaecological practice the question often arises as to whether clinical, imaging or endoscopic findings adequately explain reported pain symptoms <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>.</s><s>For example, endometriosis has been found in at least 20 % of women undergoing laparoscopic tubal ligation.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Introduction: Pelvic pain is a common problem in gynaecological practice.</s><s>It is often unclear whether definite causality exists between reported symptoms and objective clinical findings of the female genital tract, and medical or operative treatments do not always achieve long-term resolution of symptoms.</s><s>Methods: This pilot study investigated 28 patients (age 20-65, median 36.5 years) from a gynaecology practice whose only clinical finding was painful pelvic floor muscle tightness.</s><s>Following standardised gynaecological and physiotherapist examination, all patients received osteopathic treatment.</s><s>Pain had been present for a median of 3 years (range 1 month to 20 years).</s><s>14 patients had previously confirmed endometriosis.</s><s>Treatment success was evaluated on consultation with patients in person or in writing.</s><s>Results: 22 of the 28 participants completed the treatment according to plan.</s><s>Overall, 17 reported symptom improvement, while 10 of the 14 patients with endometriosis did.</s><s>Conclusion: Osteopathy is well received by women with painful pelvic floor muscle tightness and appears to be an effective treatment option.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Zusammenfassung</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Osteopathy for Endometriosis and Chronic Pelvic Paina Pilot Study</head><p><s>Osteopathie bei Endometriose und chronischen Unterbauchschmerzeneine Pilotstudie dian interval from endometriosis diagnosis to onset of symptoms is 10.4 years <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref>.</s><s>This highlights the unsatisfactory situation these patients find themselves in, however this particular study sheds no light on whether available treatments are effective.</s><s>Women with chronic pelvic pain very often have painful pelvic floor muscle tightness <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[7]</ref> a rare finding in healthy, symptomfree women <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[8]</ref>.</s><s>Significant comorbidity with musculoskeletal diseases exists, a fact that is not widely acknowledged <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[9]</ref>.</s><s>The term "osteopathy" describes a school of diagnosis and treatment developed by the American Andrew Taylor Still.</s><s>Its central focus is on musculo-fascial structures and their influence on somatic symptoms.</s><s>Three forms of practice have evolved: parietal osteopathy, visceral osteopathy and craniosacral therapy.</s><s>Evidence exists to different degreesin descending ordersupporting the efficacy of each of the three subdivisions of osteopathy <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[10]</ref>.</s><s>Osteopathy describes causality between numerous symptoms and diseases due to the fascial connections between the musculoskeletal system and the internal organs.</s><s>Thus, inflammation of internal organs can cause musculoskeletal symptoms and vice versa (e.g.</s><s>injuries of the axial skeleton can cause abdominal symptoms).</s><s>Also, functional limitation at one skeletal level may cause symptoms at a different level.</s><s>These interconnections are described as "lesion chains" <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[11]</ref>.</s><s>This pilot study investigates the efficacy of osteopathic diagnosis and treatment for women with chronic pelvic pain and painful pelvic floor muscle tightness not related to the menstrual cycle.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials and Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patients</head><p><s>28 women presented to our clinic at a certified endometriosis centre with chronic lower abdominal symptoms not clearly related to the menstrual cycle.</s><s>14 of these patients had previously confirmed endometriosis.</s><s>In the control group of 14 patients without known endometriosis, 7 had previous abdominal surgery for other reasons (uterine fibroids, appendicectomy, cholecystectomy, Crohnʼs disease, ileus during infancy); specific, endoscopic exclusion of endometriosis was however not carried out since dysmenorrhea and infertility did not feature as prominent symptoms in this group (l " Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>Group allocation was on the basis of clinical history.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gynaecological examination</head><p><s>Apart from the gynaecological history, particular note was taken of symptoms, diseases and injuries of the axial skeleton.</s><s>All patients underwent a standard gynaecological examination by the same investigator (M.</s><s>Sillem).</s><s>Additional transvaginal digital palpation of the levator ani and internal obturator muscles was performed.</s><s>Bony landmarks were the inferior pubic ramus and the ischial spine (l " Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>).</s><s>A diagnosis of painful muscle tightness was made if there was tenderness on careful palpation.</s><s>All patients also underwent transvaginal ultrasound examination.</s><s>All patients were offered further investigation with (repeat) laparoscopy and/or medication as alternatives to osteopathic treatment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study inclusion</head><p><s>Only patients with painful tightness of the pelvic floor musculature were included in the study.</s><s>Patients with concurrent pathological findings on clinical or ultrasound examination of the genital tract (cysts, fibroids) were treated accordingly and excluded from the study.</s><s>After selection, patients were presented to a physiotherapist with osteopathy training (I.</s><s>Klausmeier).</s><s>A clinical history was taken, with particular attention to musculoskeletal and abdominal symptoms/injuries, followed by a systematic examination (sacroiliac joint mobility, tenderness on abdominal palpation, posture, range of motion of the hips, spine).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Osteopathic treatment</head><p><s>A standardised approach was used starting with release of musculoskeletal blocks, particularly of the sacroiliac joints.</s><s>Depending on clinical findings, this was followed by mobilisation of the diaphragm and abdominal organs using standard techniques.</s><s>The pelvic floor was released using the so-called "grand manoeuvre" (movement of the abdominal organ compartment in a cranial direction).</s><s>The treatment was concluded in many cases with mobilisation of the temporomandibular joints and cervical spine.</s><s>Each patient was prescribed 6 treatment sessions, of which a median of 6 were carried out (range 1-24), usually at weekly intervals.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Evaluation</head><p><s>A few weeks after treatment completion, patients were questioned in person or in writing on their satisfaction with the treatment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical history</head><p><s>Duration of symptoms ranged from a few weeks up to 20 years, median 3 years.</s><s>21 patients had previously had an abdominal operation: 9 had one previous laparoscopy or laparotomy, 8 patients had 2, one patient 3, and 3 patients 4 previous laparoscopies and/or laparotomies.</s><s>10 of the patients with endometriosis were taking or had previously taken hormonal treatment, in 6 cases dienogest mono.</s><s>Four of these patients had had no improvement of symptoms.</s><s>11 patients reported injuries or diseases of the axial skeleton/ musculoskeletal system or specifically the lower limbs (3 motor vehicle accidents, 3 sacral injuries, 2 knee injuries, and 1 each for scoliosis, pelvic ring fracture and multiple fractures).</s><s>Six patients had had psychotherapy, which had been recommended for a further two patients.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Osteopathic treatment</head><p><s>Patients underwent a median of 6 (range 1-24) osteopathic treatment sessions each lasting 30 minutes.</s><s>22 patients com-pleted treatment as planned with only two patients discontinuing after a single session.</s><s>The median of repeat prescriptions was 2.5 (range 0 to 5).</s><s>The group of 14 patients with endometriosis differed significantly from the rest of the participants as follows: longer duration of symptoms, more previous operations and both better treatment compliance and outcome (l " Tables <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2  to 4</ref>).</s><s>In contrast there was no difference in comorbidity between the groups.</s><s>Five out of 11 cases with musculoskeletal diseases/injuries benefitted from osteopathic treatment, whereas all 5 patients with endometriosis and psychiatric comorbidity did.</s><s>Three patients without any symptom improvement after osteopathic treatment re-presented to the gynaecology clinic: One, with a history of previous endometriosis, required surgery for a newly diagnosed ovarian endometrioma; two were receiving and had benefitted from psychotherapy.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>This feasibility study presents our experience with osteopathy for the treatment of endometriosis and pelvic pain on the basis of muscular tightness.</s><s>There is little scientific data on the use of osteopathy in general, and available data often has limited validity.</s><s>In a PubMed search only one study on the described techniques for the treatment of endometriosis was found.</s><s>Daraï and colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[12]</ref> used osteopathy to treat 20 patients with deep infiltrating endometriosis, of whom one third had already been operated and 70% were receiving medication.</s><s>Physical wellbeing improved in 80 % of patients and 60 % had improved psychological wellbeing.</s><s>In a Cochrane Review, however, Proctor et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[13]</ref> concluded that spinal    manipulation (a parietal osteopathic technique) was of no benefit for dysmenorrhea.</s><s>Chronic pain arising from areas bordering the internal genital organs includes backache/low-back pain and urinary tract pain syndromes.</s><s>A systematic review of osteopathy for lower back pain found numerous studies of which only two were high-quality: One showed an effect no better than placebo, the other found similar effects for osteopathy, conventional physiotherapy and physical/sporting activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[14]</ref>.</s><s>However, a prospective, doubleblind, randomised trial of 455 patients, which was published soon thereafter and included a control arm receiving a sham treatment, showed a highly significant positive effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[15]</ref>.</s><s>A systematic review of osteopathy in women with lower urinary tract symptoms also showed a statistically significant positive effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[16]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Endometriosis is a disease prone to recurrence, with recurrence rates estimated at 20 and 50 % respectively two and five years after primary treatment <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[17]</ref>.</s><s>However, it has also been found in at least 20 % of women undergoing routine tubal ligation for family planning <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[18]</ref>.</s><s>This means that other causes of pain and alternative treatment approaches must be considered, especially when proven effective treatments fail.</s><s>Endometriosis patients in our study were burdened by long histories of suffering and multiple operations.</s><s>These women were more likely to benefit from osteopathy and had better compliance than women without known endometriosis.</s><s>A history of injury or disease of the musculoskeletal system with consequent tension of the pelvic floor musculature was common among our study patients.</s><s>Psychopathological comorbidity was considerable, as shown by the number of women being recommended or already receiving psychotherapy.</s><s>Osteopathy was well received as a treatment option by participants in our study and proved effective in this heterogenous group with multiple previous treatments.</s><s>On the one hand, the validity of this pilot study is limited by small population size and the lack of systematic follow-up, on the other hand all patients were examined and treated in a standardised fashion by the same two investigators.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>We consider osteopathy to be a valuable additional treatment method as part of the multimodal approach to the treatment of endometriosis and chronic pelvic pain.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>!Einleitung:</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Unterbauchschmerzen sind ein häufiges Problem in der gynäkologischen Praxis.</s><s>Der Kausalzusammenhang zwischen objektivem Befund am inneren Genitale und den geklagten Beschwerden ist oft nicht eindeutig und nicht immer führen medikamentöse oder operative Therapien zu einer dauerhaften Beschwerdefreiheit.</s><s>Methodik: Im Rahmen einer Pilotstudie wurden 28 Patientinnen (Alter 20-65, Median 36,5 Jahre) einer gynäkologischen Praxis untersucht.</s><s>Als einziger klinisch auffälliger Befund fanden sich schmerzhafte Verspannungen des muskulären Beckenbodens.</s><s>Nach einer standardisierten gynäkologischen und physiotherapeutischen Untersuchung wurden diese Patientinnen osteopathisch behandelt.</s><s>Die Schmerzen bestanden seit 3 Jahren (Median, Bereich 1 Monat bis 20 Jahre).</s><s>Bei 14 Patientinnen war in der Vorgeschichte eine Endometriose gesichert worden.</s><s>Der Behandlungserfolg wurde durch Befragung evaluiert.</s><s>Ergebnisse: 22 von 28 Patientinnen schlossen die Therapie planmäßig ab.</s><s>17 Patientinnen gaben an, die Beschwerden hätten sich durch die Behandlung gebessert.</s><s>Bei den Patientinnen mit Endometriose gaben 10 von 14 eine Besserung an.</s><s>Schlussfolgerung: Osteopathie wird von Frauen mit muskulären Verspannungen des Beckenbodens gut angenommen und scheint eine wirksame Therapie darzustellen.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1 Palpation of the pelvic floor muscles.</s><s>1: inferior pubic ramus, 2: int.</s><s>obturator muscle, 3: ischial spine, 4: levator ani muscle.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Summary of differences between patients with and without endometriosis.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Number</cell><cell>Duration of symptoms in years</cell><cell>Number of laparoscopies/-tomies</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>median (range)</cell><cell>median (range)</cell></row><row><cell>Known endometriosis</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>8 (2-20)</cell><cell>2 (1-4)</cell></row><row><cell>No known endometriosis</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>0.1 (0.1-5)</cell><cell>0.5 (0-3)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Treatment success as a function of previously diagnosed endometriosis.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Number</cell><cell>Improved</cell><cell>Repeat prescription</cell><cell>Did not improve</cell><cell>Therapy stopped</cell><cell>No follow-up</cell></row><row><cell>Endometriosis</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>No known endometriosis</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Treatment success as a function of known/previous musculoskeletal diseases/injuries.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Number</cell><cell>Improved</cell><cell>Repeat prescription</cell><cell>Did not improve</cell><cell>Therapy stopped</cell><cell>No follow-up</cell></row><row><cell>Positive history</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>Negative history</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Comorbidity.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Number</cell><cell>Musculoskeletal 1</cell><cell>Psychosomatic</cell></row><row><cell>Known endometriosis</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>No known endometriosis</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>3</cell></row></table><note><p><s>1Previous history of musculoskeletal disease/injury.</s></p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of Interest</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>The authors declare that no conflict of interest exists.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WHO systematic review of prevalence of chronic pelvic pain: a neglected reproductive health morbidity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Latthe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Latthe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Say</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Public Health</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">177</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The prevalence of dysmenorrhea, dyspareunia, pelvic pain, and irritable bowel syndrome in primary care practices</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Jamieson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Steege</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Chronic pelvic pain: prevalence, health-related quality of life, and economic correlates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mathias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kuppermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Liberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">87</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="321" to="327" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Beutel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Weidner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Brähler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Chronic pelvic pain of women and its co-morbidity</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geburtsh Frauenheilk</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Chronischer Unterbauchschmerz der Frau. AWMF-Leitlinie Reg</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hrsg</forename><surname>Awmf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>Nr. 016/001. 2009</idno>
		<ptr target="http://www.awmf.org/leitlinien/detail/ll/016-001.html" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>last access: 25.07.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diagnostic delay for endometriosis in Austria and Germany: causes and possible consequences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hudelist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fritzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum Reprod</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3412" to="3416" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Importance of pelvic muscle tenderness evaluation in women with chronic pelvic pain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Montenegro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Mateus-Vasconcelos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rosa</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pain Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="224" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pelvic floor muscle tenderness in asymptomatic, nulliparous women: topographical distribution and reliability of a visual analogue scale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kavvadias</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Pelikan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int Urogynecol J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="281" to="286" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sociodemographic characteristics and gynecological disease in 40-42 year old women reporting musculoskeletal disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ostensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schei</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scand J Rheumatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="426" to="434" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wissenschaftliche Bewertung osteopathischer Verfahren</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Bundesärztekammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dtsch Arztebl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1941">2009. 1997/C-1941</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Langer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hebgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hrsg</forename><forename type="middle">Lehrbuch</forename><surname>Osteopathie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<pubPlace>Stuttgart: Haug</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of osteopathic manipulative therapy on quality of life of patients with deep infiltrating endometriosis with colorectal involvement: results of a pilot study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Daraï</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Deboute</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zacharopoulou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">188</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="70" to="73" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spinal manipulation for primary and secondary dysmenorrhoea</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Proctor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">D002119</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Osteopathic intervention in chronic non-specific low back pain: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Orrock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Myers</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Musculoskelet Disord</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">129</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Outcomes of osteopathic manual treatment for chronic low back pain according to baseline pain severity: results from the OSTEOPATHIC Trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Licciardone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kearns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Minotti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Man Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="533" to="540" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Osteopathic manipulative treatment (OMT) for lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) in women</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Franke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hoesele</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Bodyw Mov Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Recurrence of endometriosis and its control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum Reprod Update</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="441" to="461" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Endometriosis in women at interval sterilization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Moen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="451" to="454" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
