<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Epidemiologic analysis of families with isolated anorectal malformations suggests high prevalence of autosomal dominant inheritance</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Gabriel</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Dworschak</surname></persName>
							<email>gabriel.dworschak@uni-bonn.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bonn</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bonn</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatrics, Children&apos;s Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bonn</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Sigmund-Freud-Str. 25</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-53127</postCode>
									<settlement>Bonn</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bonn</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bonn</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nadine</forename><surname>Zwink</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Eberhard</forename><surname>Schmiedeke</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kiarasch</forename><surname>Mortazawi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Stefanie</forename><surname>Märzheuser</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Konrad</forename><surname>Reinshagen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Johannes</forename><surname>Leonhardt</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Barbara</forename><surname>Gómez</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Patrick</forename><surname>Volk</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anke</forename><surname>Rißmann</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ekkehart</forename><surname>Jenetzky</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Heiko</forename><surname>Reutter</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bonn</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bonn</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bonn</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bonn</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Epidemiologic analysis of families with isolated anorectal malformations suggests high prevalence of autosomal dominant inheritance</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">7284B924570C16C7993EBE390D18A6BD</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s13023-017-0729-7</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 8 August 2017 Accepted: 30 November 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:19+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Anorectal malformation</term>
					<term>ARM</term>
					<term>Inheritance</term>
					<term>Recurrence risk</term>
					<term>Genetic counseling</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Background: Anorectal malformations (ARM) are rare abnormalities that occur in approximately 1 in 3000 live births with around 40% of patients presenting with isolated forms.</s><s>Multiple familial cases reported, suggest underlying genetic factors that remain largely unknown.</s><s>The recurrence in relatives is considered rare, however transmission rates of ARM by affected parents have never been determined before.</s><s>The inheritance pattern of ARM was investigated in our database of patients with isolated ARM.</s><s>Results: Within our cohort of 327 patients with isolated ARM we identified eight adult patients from eight families who had in total 16 children with their healthy spouse.</s><s>Of these ten had ARM, resulting in a recurrence risk of approximately one in two live births (10 of 16; 62%).</s><s>From 226 families with 459 siblings we found two affected siblings in five families.</s><s>Hence, the recurrence risk of ARM among siblings is approximately one in 92 live births (5 of 459; 1.0%).</s><s>Conclusions: Comparing the observed recurrence risk in our cohort with the prevalence in the general population, we see a 1500-fold increase in recurrence risk for offspring and a 32-fold increase if a sibling is affected.</s><s>The recurrence risk of approximately 62% indicates an autosomal dominant mode of inheritance.</s><s>Reliable figures on recurrence of ARM are becoming increasingly important since improved surgical techniques are able to maintain sexual function resulting in more offspring of patients with ARM.</s><s>These data allow more precise counseling of families with ARM and support the need for genetic studies.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Background</head><p><s>Anorectal malformations (ARM) comprise a broad spectrum, ranging from mild anal anomalies to complex cloacal malformations.</s><s>The estimated birth prevalence amount to 1 in 3000 live births, with a male to female ratio of 1.7 <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>Around 60% of ARM occur within the context of defined genetic syndromes or complex multiple congenital anomalies or in association with chromosomal aberrations <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>.</s><s>The remaining 40% are isolated ARM with its etiology remaining largely unknown.</s></p><p><s>Although we previously identified 59 ARM families from the literature with at least two affected members <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, the condition is usually sporadic, with low risk of recurrence among first degree relatives <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>In the first report on the risk of recurrence from Anderson and Reed the likelihood for recurrence of ARM in a sibling has been depicted with 1 in 100 (1%) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s><s>However, this figure is based on surveillance of not further described patients from unquoted reports.</s><s>In 2007 Falcone et al. calculated the risk of recurrence in a large cohort of 1606 patients with ARM with 1.4% without specifying between risk for siblings or risk for offspring <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s><s>Here we present inheritance data on a cohort of 619 ARM patients and demonstrate evidence for monogenic inheritance in at least a subset of patients.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p><s>In 2009 the last two authors initiated a nationwide German study of the genetic causes of urogenital and anorectal malformations (CURE-Net, Network for Congenital Uro-REctal malformations).</s><s>Patients and their families have been contacted through the German self-help organization for patients with anorectal malformations (SoMA e.V.) and various German pediatric surgical departments.</s><s>The CURE-Network comprises 23 pediatric surgical departments in Germany.</s><s>Recruiting physicians are experienced in the field of congenital anomalies and are encouraged to contribute any case, regardless of sporadic or multiple occurrence of the ARM.</s><s>Cases underwent a clinical investigation and ARM was classified according to the Krickenbeck-Classification <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</s><s>Despite major efforts to collect comprehensive data in Germany, it cannot be claimed that the cohort represents population-based data.</s></p><p><s>Data on multiple affected family members was compiled using a standardized questionnaire.</s><s>Information regarding the type of ARM, associated malformations and family history were evaluated.</s><s>In order to avoid overestimation of recurrence risk and to exclude any form of non-isolated ARM, strict criteria have been applied to identify isolated cases for further analysis: If any malformation outside the anorectal developmental field was noted, the case was flagged as "non-isolated" and excluded.</s><s>Anomalies within the anorectal developmental field include anomalies of the upper and lower urinary tract as well as the genitalia and the os sacrum.</s><s>In contrast, patients presenting with any of the following features were defined as non-isolated cases and excluded from the analysis: Chromosomal or single gene disorders; any defined clinical syndrome; congenital malformations of the esophagus, the heart, the limbs, mental retardation; and facial anomalies (e.g., orofacial clefts or hemifacial macrosomia).</s><s>If it was uncertain whether the patient should be classified isolated or non-isolated, the patient was subsequently excluded from the analysis.</s></p><p><s>At the time of data analysis (2009-2016) the study sample comprised of 619 ARM patients and their families.</s><s>After exclusion of all syndromic patients (n = 292) 327 patients with isolated ARM (53%) remained.</s><s>From these remaining 327 patients with isolated ARM data on first degree relatives were evaluated to identify multiple affected families.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Multiplex ARM families with affected first degree relatives Affected parents with affected children (parent-offspring families)</s></p><p><s>Within our cohort of 327 patients with isolated ARM we identified only eight patients from eight families who had in total 16 children with their healthy spouse (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, Additional file 1: Figure <ref type="figure">S1</ref>).</s><s>This low number of patients with children is due to the fact, that the majority of patients in our cohort are underage.</s><s>Here, four men with isolated ARM fathered five affected and one healthy child.</s><s>Four women with isolated ARM had five affected and five healthy children.</s><s>Hence, the recurrence risk of ARM among 16 offspring is approximately one in two live births (10 of 16; 62%; 95%-CI: 35% -85%).</s><s>Noteworthy, in two of these nine families have been further affected family members (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, Additional file 1: Figure <ref type="figure">S1</ref>): In family 1 another relative of the affected father (anal atresia) had unspecified ARM.</s><s>The grandparents and the sister of the affected father of family 4 had unspecified ARM.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phenotypic description of ARM subphenotypes among parent-offspring families</head><p><s>Of the four fathers with isolated ARM one had anal atresia and another had a stenosis of the anal canal; the type of ARM in the other two fathers is unspecified.</s><s>In their offspring we recorded five perineal fistula.</s><s>Of the four mothers with isolated ARM two had a perineal fistula, another one had a vestibular fistula and one had an ectopic anus (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>, Additional file 1: Figure <ref type="figure">S1</ref>).</s><s>One of the families has been published before (family 6) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In their offspring we observed two perineal fistula, one vestibular fistula, one atresia without fistula (aganglionic blind-loop) and one ectopic anus.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Healthy parents with two affected children</head><p><s>In 226 families (69%) we found 459 siblings.</s><s>In five of these families two siblings were affected with ARM (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>, Additional file 1: Figure <ref type="figure">S1</ref>).</s><s>Hence, the recurrence risk of ARM among siblings is approximately one in 92 live births (5 of 459; 1.0%; 95%-CI: 0.3% -2.3%).</s><s>Affected siblings with affected parents have been excluded for this analysis, but included in the figures for vertical transmission.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phenotypic description of ARM subphenotypes among families with affected siblings</head><p><s>Of the five families with two affected children (five female and five male) five children showed perineal fistula, one with a recto-urethral fistula, one had a cloacal malformation, one with an anal atresia and one unspecified ARM.</s><s>Additionally, there have been three healthy siblings (families 11, 12 and 13).</s><s>In family 10 a history of ARM with a maternal second cousin with unspecified ARM has been reported.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recurrence risk in families with specific subphenotypes</head><p><s>Of the 197 patients with perineal or vestibular fistula 17 had at least one further family member affected with ARM (8.6%; 95%-CI: 5.1% -13.5%), resulting in a 260-fold increase in risk to the general population.</s><s>From 29 patients with a prostatic fistula only one had an affected family member (3.5%; 95%-CI: 0.1% -17.8%), resulting in a 103fold increased risk compared to the general population.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Data on recurrence risk for genetic counseling is sparse for ARM and is mostly limited to reports of familial occurrence.</s><s>Reliable figures however will become increasingly important, since improved surgical techniques are able to maintain sexual function resulting in more offspring of patients with ARM.</s><s>Here, we present data on the recurrence risk in a large cohort for isolated ARM and determine the recurrence risk in offspring of parents with ARM, which has not been investigated previously.</s></p><p><s>The first report on the recurrence risk in families with ARM estimated the recurrence risk for siblings to be 1% <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s><s>Although this figure is based on unknown and unquoted reports, it is often used as a reference.</s><s>In 2007 Falcone et al. identified in 2.4% of 1606 ARM patients an additional family member with a congenital malformation, which was an ARM in 1.4% <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s><s>Comparing the recurrence risk we observed in the studied cohort with the estimated prevalence in the general population of 1 in 3000 we see a 1500-fold increase in recurrence risk for offspring and a 32-fold increase if a sibling is affected.</s><s>The recurrence risk of 62% (10 affected of 16 offspring in 8 families) indicates an autosomal dominant mode of inheritance.</s><s>However, we have to emphasize that the estimation of recurrence risk is not precise due to the low number of cases.</s><s>Not only larger populationbased cohorts will be necessary to refine exact figures but also further genetic studies are needed to identify explicit genetic factors.</s><s>In spite of this impressive increased risk, we have to consider that the number of parents is still low in our cohort with mainly underage patients.</s><s>This is due to the fact that pediatric surgeries could recruit only underage patients, and parents in our cohort were mainly recruited through the German self-help group.</s><s>There may be an increased motivation for an affected parent Previous findings reported epidemiologic differences among the various types of anal anomalies suggesting different embryological or genetic origins <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>Notably, Falcone et al. found patients with a perineal or vestibular fistula having an increased risk to have a relative with ARM.</s><s>In those families ARM recurred in 3% of families, resulting in a 90-fold increase in risk compared with the general population (based on a frequency in the general population of 1 in 3000).</s><s>In contrast, in patients with cloacal malformations or prostatic fistula they observed a significantly lower risk of recurrence among family members <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s><s>According to this data, we confirmed that there is a higher risk of recurrence in the presence of a perineal or vestibular fistula among first degree relatives.</s><s>Unlike Falcone et al. we did not find a difference in sex ratios, namely a female predominance, in the group of ARM patients with at least one affected family member.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>Our data in a large cohort of isolated ARM indicates a higher recurrence risk of ARM than previously reported.</s><s>Especially for offspring of affected patients with ARM we demonstrate a recurrence risk of approximately 62% suggesting an autosomal dominant mode of inheritance.</s><s>However, research has yet only identified a minority of the monogenic factors.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Phenotypic description of parents with isolated ARM</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="5">Family Affected parent Phenotype of parent Unaffected offspring Affected offspring</cell><cell>Additionally affected family members</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>Father</cell><cell>NS</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>2 (male, perineal fistula;</cell><cell>One further relative in paternal family</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>male perineal fistula)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>Father</cell><cell>NS</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1 (male, perineal fistula)</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>Father</cell><cell>Anal stenosis</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>1 (male, perineal fistula)</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>Father</cell><cell>NS</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>1 (male, perineal fistula)</cell><cell>Grandparents and the sister of the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>affected father had unspecified ARM</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>Mother</cell><cell>Anterior ectopy</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>2 (male, perineal fistula;</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>female, anterior ectopy)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>Mother</cell><cell>Perineal fistula</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>2 (female, perineal fistula;</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>male, anal atresia without</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>fistula and aganglionic blind-loop)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>Mother</cell><cell>Vestibular fistula</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1 (female, vestibular fistula)</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>8</cell><cell>Mother</cell><cell>Perineal fistula</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row></table><note><p><s>NS not specified</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Phenotypic description of affected siblings with non-syndromic ARM from unaffected parents</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Family</cell><cell>Unaffected offspring</cell><cell>Affected offspring</cell><cell>Additionally affected family members</cell></row><row><cell>9</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>2 (female, perineal fistula;</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>female, perineal fistula)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>10</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>2 (male, perineal fistula;</cell><cell>Maternal second cousin with</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>female, cloacal malformation)</cell><cell>not specified ARM</cell></row><row><cell>11</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 (male, perineal fistula;</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>male, NS)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>12</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 (female, perineal fistula;</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>male, anal atresia without</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>fistula)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>13</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2 (male, prostatic fistula;</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>female, vestibular fistula)</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Acknowledgments CURE-Net would not exist without numerous diligent pediatric surgeons in Germany, who participate in this nationwide register.</s><s>We thank all patients and their families for their participation, as well as the German self-help organization for individuals with anorectal malformations (SoMA e.V.) for their assistance with recruitment.</s></p><p><s>2 Department of Pediatrics, Children's Hospital, University of Bonn, Sigmund-Freud-Str.</s><s>25, D-53127 Bonn, Germany. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> Division of Clinical Epidemiology and Aging Research, German Cancer Research Center, Heidelberg, Germany. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry, University Medical Center of the Johannes Gutenberg University Mainz, Mainz, Germany. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref></s><s>Department of Pediatric Surgery and Urology, Center for Child and Adolescent Health, Hospital Bremen-Mitte, Bremen, Germany.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional file</head><p><s>Additional file 1:</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Availability of data and materials</head><p><s>Please contact authors for data requests.</s></p><p><s>Authors' contributions GCD, NZ, EJ and HR designed the study.</s><s>GCD and NZ performed the data analysis.</s><s>GCD wrote the manuscript draft and HR supervised the entire process of manuscript preparation.</s><s>ES, KM, SM, KR, JL, BG, PV, AR and HR recruited the included patients and families and made contributions to the draft of the manuscript.</s><s>All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethics approval and consent to participate</head><p><s>The study has been conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki, and ethical approval has been obtained from the local ethic committee (reference number 146/12).</s><s>Written informed consent has been obtained from patients, parents or the patients' by-proxy prior to study entry.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Consent for publication</head><p><s>Not applicable.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Competing interests</head><p><s>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Publisher's Note</head><p><s>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Descriptive epidemiology of isolated anal anomalies: a survey of 4.6 million births in Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cuschieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Eurocat Working</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Group</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Med Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="207" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prevalence estimation of anorectal malformations using German diagnosis related groups system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Jenetzky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatr Surg Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1161" to="1165" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anorectal malformations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Levitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Peña</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Orphanet J Rare Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">33</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Associated malformations in patients with anorectal anomalies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Stoll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Alembik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Dott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Med Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="281" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anorectal anomalies associated with or as part of other anomalies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cuschieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Med Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="122" to="130" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Autosomal-dominant non-syndromic anal atresia: sequencing of candidate genes, array-based molecular karyotyping, and review of the literature</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Schramm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Draaken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tewes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bartels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Schmiedeke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Märzheuser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Pediatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">170</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="741" to="746" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The likelihood of recurrence of congenital malformations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Reed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="175" to="176" />
			<date type="published" when="1954">1954</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increased heritability of certain types of anorectal malformations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Falcone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Levitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Peña</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bates</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pediatr Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="127" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preliminary report on the international conference for the development of standards for the treatment of Anorectal malformations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Holschneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hutson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Peña</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Beket</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chatterjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Coran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pediatr Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1521" to="1526" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A de novo paradigm for mental retardation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Lelm</forename><surname>Vissers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>De Ligt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gilissen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Janssen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Steehouwer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>De Vries</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1109" to="1112" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
