<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Fitting homocysteine to disease models, as well as adjusting the models to the disease</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-05-09">9 May 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Friedrich</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Luft</surname></persName>
							<email>luft@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Experimental and Clinical Research Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Charité Medical Faculty</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Max Delbrück Center for Molecular Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Lindenbergerweg 80</addrLine>
									<postCode>13125</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Fitting homocysteine to disease models, as well as adjusting the models to the disease</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-05-09">9 May 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F74EC3CC43BD7769ADDFEE9087622B38</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00109-015-1293-z</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:19+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Homocysteine is a nonprotein α-amino acid and differs from cysteine by having an additional methylene bridge.</s><s>Homocysteine is not present in the diet, and all homocysteine in the body is biosynthesized from the essential amino acid methionine.</s><s>Homocysteine is a product of methionine demethylation and is recycled into methionine or alternatively converted into cysteine with the assistance of B vitamins.</s><s>Homocysteine is metabolized through two pathways, namely remethylation and transsulfuration.</s><s>Much information has been generated from mouse models.</s><s>A summary of this model information, as presented by Dayal and Lentz <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, is shown (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>).</s><s>The remethylation pathway requires vitamin B 12 , folate, and the enzyme 5,10-methylene-tetrahydrofolate reductase (MTHFR).</s><s>In the kidney and liver, homocysteine is also remethylated by the enzyme betaine homocysteine methyltransferase (BHMT), which transfers a methyl group to homocysteine via the demethylation of betaine to dimethylglycine (DMG).</s><s>The transsulfuration pathway requires the enzyme cystathionine beta-synthase (CBS) and vitamin B 6 (pyridoxal-5′-phosphate).</s><s>Once formed from cystathionine, cysteine can be utilized in protein synthesis and glutathione (GSH) production.</s></p><p><s>Genetics has contributed greatly to our understanding of homocysteine, its metabolism, and cardiovascular risk.</s><s>Classical homocystinuria, an autosomal-recessive disease, is caused by CBS deficiency.</s><s>The defect leads to a multisystem disorder involving connective tissue, muscle, the central nervous system, and the cardiovascular system <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s>Genetic var-iation in the MTHFR gene influences the susceptibility to occlusive vascular disease, neural tube defects, Alzheimer's disease and other dementias, colon cancer, and acute leukemia <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s>Thus, homocysteine, its metabolism, and the enzymes involved are of great interest in biomedical research.</s></p><p><s>Homocysteine contributes to endothelial injury and subsequent atherosclerosis and is a specific risk factor for cardiovascular disease.</s><s>As a result, much effort has been expended in clinical trials for various vascular diseases in the hopes that by reducing homocysteine levels, cardiovascular endpoints could be ameliorated.</s><s>For instance, an updated Cochrane review found no evidence to suggest that homocysteinelowering interventions in the form of supplements of vitamins B 6 , B 9 , or B 12 given alone or in combination should be used for preventing cardiovascular events <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4]</ref>.</s><s>Neither has the supplementation of dietary folic acid to lower homocysteine levels led to more favorable outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>.</s><s>Nevertheless, folic acid supplementation has a major impact on reducing neural tube defects <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>J Mol Med this month features a homocysteine-based hypothesis in a complicated animal model.</s><s>Muthuramu et al. point out that a Bcausal role of homocysteine in myocardial biology and function cannot be proven since residual confounding in multivariable models may occur^ <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s><s>How very true!</s><s>They studied Cbs heterozygous gene-deleted (Cbs +/−) mice.</s><s>These mice were crossed with low-density lipoprotein receptor (Ldlr −/−) gene-deleted mice to generate Cbs +/−/ Ldlr −/− mice.</s><s>The mice were divided into three groups and fed regular chow, folic acid-depleted chow, or methionineenriched chow.</s><s>Three weeks after diet initiation, the mice were intravenously injected with a hepatocyte-specific adenoviral vector expressing Cbs (AdCBS), with the same dose of control vector, or with saline buffer.</s><s>Two weeks after that, the mice were subjected to thoracic aortic constriction (TAC), an experimental aortic coarctation, or sham operation to induce heart disease.</s><s>Adenoviral transfer lowered homocysteine values in TAC mice and sham controls.</s><s>Hemodynamic measurements were performed with a Millar pressure catheter.</s><s>In short, replacing the CBS function made the mice better.</s><s>Survival was improved after TAC, compared to untreated mice, and the end-diastolic pressure was reduced to almost sham values and reflectors of diastolic function were improved.</s><s>The authors monitored antioxidant defense mechanisms and found that replacing CBS function reduced myocardial oxidative stress.</s></p><p><s>The animal model, complex and confounded as it is, is convincing.</s><s>However, what do we carry away that is really new here?</s><s>More than 200 articles in the literature underscore the relationship between hyperhomocysteinemia and heart failure.</s><s>More than 1000 papers are concerned with hyperhomocysteinemia and increased oxidative stress.</s><s>Viral gene transfer of Cbs to replace Cbs in Cbs-heterozygous genedeficient mice is a nice touch and eliminates variables imposed by dietary manipulation.</s><s>However, the results were largely predictable.</s><s>Will we encounter patients with CBS deficiency that simultaneously have familial hypercholesterolemia and then happen to have developed coarctation of the aorta?</s><s>The studies underscore what must be done to mice to make them sick; the relevance to any human disease is uncertain.</s></p><p><s>Actually, MFTR polymorphisms have been studied in patients with familial hypercholesterolemia (LDLR +/−).</s><s>Indeed, the homocysteine levels in patients with the risk variant (TT) were higher and their high-density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol levels were lower than persons not carrying this MFTR variant <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</s><s>The mechanism of interaction between plasma homocysteine and lipid metabolism is unknown.</s><s>Interestingly, coarctation of the aorta has also been associated with MFTR the TT polymorphism <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, so perhaps the authors' model is not so far-fetched after all.</s></p><p><s>In terms of Btranslational research,^the fact that all the intervention trials directed at reducing homocysteine have invariably failed is certainly disappointing.</s><s>However, perhaps the human conditions have very little to do with the animal studies.</s><s>Thus, it is not clear whether or not homocysteine actually plays a causal role in many diseases with which it is associated.</s><s>An alternative possibility could be that homocysteine is instead a marker for some other underlying mechanism.</s><s>A large body of data links hyperhomocysteinemia and folate status with oxidant stress.</s><s>The authors of the current studies also made oxidative stress their focus.</s><s>Hoffmann recently reviewed data suggesting that homocysteine not only promotes cellular and protein injury via oxidant mechanisms but also serves as a marker for the presence of pathological oxidant stress <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</s><s>Of course, the antioxidant trials to reduce cardiovascular disease were as disappointing as the homocysteine trials <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s><s>Humans just seem to be a stubborn, outbred, heterogeneous animal model that has little utility in explaining diseases in rodents.</s></p><p><s>Respectfully</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacological inhibitor</head><p><s>Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> Homocysteine is an intermediate metabolite of the methionine cycle.</s><s>Homocysteine can be metabolized to cystathionine by cystathionine beta-cystathionine synthase (CBS), requiring the cofactor vitamin B 6 .</s><s>Homocysteine can also be remethylated to methionine by methionine synthase (MS) with vitamin B 12 .</s><s>This reaction uses a methyl group from 5-methyl tetrahydrofolate (THF) and links the methionine cycle with the folate cycle.</s><s>The activity of methylene tetrahydrofolate reductase (MTHFR) derives 5-methyl THF.</s><s>Methionine synthase reductase (MSR) is required to maintain MS in its active conformation.</s><s>The liver and kidney homocysteine can be remethylated to methionine by betaine/homocysteine methyltransferase (BHMT).</s><s>This reaction uses betaine, which is derived from choline, as a methyl donor.</s><s>Hyperhomocysteinemia can be induced in mice by administering methionine or homocysteine, dietary deficiency of folate, vitamin B 6 , vitamin B 12 , or choline (yellow); by a genetic deficiency of CBS (as in the current study), MTHF R, MS, or MSR (blue); or by pharmacologically inhibiting BHMT (red).</s><s>Scheme adapted from Dayal and Lentz <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref></s></p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Murine models of hyperhomocysteinemia and their vascular phenotypes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dayal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Lentz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1596" to="1605" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular biology of 5,10-methylenetetrahydrofolate reductase</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fodinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Horl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sunder-Plassmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Nephrol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="33" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homocysteine-lowering interventions for preventing cardiovascular events</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Marti-Carvajal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lathyris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Karakitsiou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Simancas-Racines</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">D006612</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homocysteinelowering interventions for preventing cardiovascular events</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Marti-Carvajal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lathyris</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">D006612</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Homocysteine lowering interventions for preventing cardiovascular events</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Marti-Carvajal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Lathyris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Salanti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">D006612</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Effect of homocysteine interventions on the risk of cardiocerebrovascular events: a meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Mei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Rong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Jinming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Yongjun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Hui</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Clin Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="208" to="215" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Folic acid to reduce mortality from neural tube disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Blencowe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cousens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Modell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lawn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="110" to="121" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Selective homocyseine-lowering gene transfer attenuates pressure-overloadinduced cardiomyopathy via reduced oxidative stress</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Muthuramu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Amin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Nefyodova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Debasse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Horenbeeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Jacobs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Geest</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00109-015-1281-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Mol Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Association of C677T polymorphism in MTHFR gene, high homocysteine and low HDL cholesterol plasma values in heterozygous familial hypercholesterolemia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Real</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Martinez-Hervas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Garcia-Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Chaves</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Civera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Ascaso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Carmena</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Atheroscler Thromb</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="815" to="820" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Association of congenital cardiovascular malformations with 33 single nucleotide polymorphisms of selected cardiovascular disease-related genes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kuehl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Loffredo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Iovannisci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shaw</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Birth Defects Res A Clin Mol Teratol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hypothesis: hyperhomocysteinemia is an indicator of oxidant stress</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hoffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Hypotheses</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1088" to="1093" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antioxidants and coronary artery disease: from pathophysiology to preventive therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Leopold</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Coron Artery Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="176" to="183" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Mol Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="585" to="587" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
