<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Polymer-free sirolimus-eluting stents in a large-scale all-comers population</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-06-06">6 June 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Florian</forename><surname>Krackhardt</surname></persName>
							<email>florian.krackhardt@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Virchow-Klinikum Charité</addrLine>
									<settlement>Kardiologie, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Viktor</forename><surname>Kočka</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital Královské Vinohrady</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Prague</settlement>
									<country key="CZ">Czech Republic</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Matthias</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Waliszewski</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical Scientific Affairs</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">B. Braun Melsungen AG</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Utech</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Ambulantes Herzzentrum Kassel</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Kassel</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Meik</forename><surname>Lustermann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Kardiologie</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Sudharz Klinikum Nordhausen gGmbH</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nordhausen, Thüringen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Hudec</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">SUSCCH a.s</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Banská Bystrica</settlement>
									<country key="SK">Slovakia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Studenčan</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="institution">Cardiocentre of Teaching Hospital of J.A. Reiman</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Prešov</settlement>
									<country key="SK">Slovakia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Markus</forename><surname>Schwefer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Kardiologie</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Elblandklinikum Riesa</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Riesa</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jiangtao</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Kardiologie</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Helmut-G.-Walther-Klinikum Lichtenfels</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Lichtenfels</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Myung</forename><forename type="middle">Ho</forename><surname>Jeong</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff10">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chonnam National University Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Gwangju</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Taehoon</forename><surname>Ahn</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff11">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Gil Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Gachon University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Incheon</settlement>
									<country key="KR">Republic of Korea</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wan</forename><surname>Azman</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wan</forename><surname>Ahmad</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff12">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Division Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Malaya Medical Centre</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Kuala Lumpur</settlement>
									<country key="MY">Malaysia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Boxberger</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Medical Scientific Affairs</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">B. Braun Melsungen AG</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">André</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff13">
								<orgName type="institution">Klinik für Kardiologie</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Klinikum Esslingen</addrLine>
									<settlement>Angiologie, Pneumologie, Esslingen, Baden-Württemberg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Matthias</forename><surname>Leschke</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff13">
								<orgName type="institution">Klinik für Kardiologie</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Klinikum Esslingen</addrLine>
									<settlement>Angiologie, Pneumologie, Esslingen, Baden-Württemberg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Interventional cardiology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Polymer-free sirolimus-eluting stents in a large-scale all-comers population</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2017-06-06">6 June 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">47F9DE070797658D6DE2870C30DF3D27</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1136/openhrt-2017-000592</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 11 January 2017 Revised 9 March 2017 Accepted 21 March 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:38+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Objective The objective of this study was to assess the safety and efficacy of a polymer-free sirolimus coated, ultrathin strut drug-eluting stent (PF-SES) in an unselected patient population with a focus on acute coronary syndrome (ACS).</s><s>Furthermore, stable coronary artery disease (CAD) with short (≤6 months) versus long (&gt;6 months) dual antiplatelet therapy (DAPT) were also studied.</s><s>Methods Patients who received PF-SES were investigated in an unselected large-scale international, single-armed, multicenter, 'all comers' observational study.</s><s>The primary endpoint was the 9-month target lesion revascularisation (TLR) rate, whereas secondary endpoints included the 9-month major adverse cardiac events (MACE) and procedural success rates.</s><s>A priori defined subgroups such as patients with ACS, diabetes, lesion subsets and procedural characteristics relative to DAPT were investigated.</s></p><p><s>Results A total of 2877 patients of whom 1084 had ACS were treated with PF-SES (1.31±0.75</s><s>stents per patient).</s><s>At 9 months, the accumulated overall TLR rate was 2.3% (58/2513).</s><s>There was no significant difference between ACS and stable CAD (2.6% vs 2.1%, p=0.389).</s><s>However, the overall MACE rate was 4.3% (108/2513) with a higher rate in patients with ACS when compared with the stable CAD subgroup (6.1%, 58/947 vs 3.2%, 50/1566, p&lt;0.001).</s><s>Conclusions PF-SES angioplasty is safe and effective in the daily clinical routine with low rates of TLR and MACE in an unselected patient population.</s><s>Our data are in agreement with prior clinical findings that extended DAPT duration beyond 6 months do not improve clinical outcomes in patients with stable CAD ( ClinicalTrials.</s><s>gov Identifier NCT02629575).</s><s>Trial registration number NCT02629575.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IntroductIon</head><p><s>Drug-eluting stents (DES) have greatly reduced the need for repeat revascularisation despite studies revealing that first-generation DES were associated with stent thrombosis (ST) rates that were less favourable when compared with bare-metal stents. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> The theoretical advantage of new coating technologies such as bioabsorbable polymers or non-polymer coating and the potential patient benefit of a shortened dual-antiplatelet therapy (DAPT) may herald a new milestone in DES development.</s><s>This, in turn, may enable patients to undergo other non-coronary treatments with a reduced risk of bleeding.</s></p><p><s>Currently, there are polarised opinions regarding the length of DAPT which range from an extended DAPT duration beyond 12 months with more favourable long-term ► Sirolimus-coated drug-eluting stents can deliver a sufficient drug dose from a polymer and nonpolymer stent coating.</s><s>► Safety and efficacy for a sirolimus-probucol coating was already demonstrated in the ISAR-TEST 5 trial with long follow-up in diabetics and in patients with ST elevation myocardial infarction.</s></p><p><s>What does this study add?</s></p><p><s>► Our data suggest that well-known cardiovascular and lesion morphological risk factors, such as vessel diameter, lesion length and B2/C lesions, do not seem to impact the clinical results in an all-comers setting after polymer-free sirolimuseluting stenting.</s><s>► To date, this study is the largest 'all comers' registry in 2877 patients dedicated to the routine use of ultrathin-strut, polymer-free sirolimusprobucol coated stents, which can be safely and effectively used with very favourable rates of target lesion revascularisation (TLR) and major adverse cardiac events (MACE).</s><s>► Our data are in agreement with other large studies that patients who were not able to receive antiplatelet preloading in all-comers patients or extended dual anti-platelet therapy (DAPT) beyond 6 months in patients with stable coronary artery disease (CAD) do not have higher rates of TLR or MACE at 9 months.</s></p><p><s>clinical outcomes 2 to a greatly shortened DAPT duration. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s>he polymer-free matrix of the investigational device in this large-scale study consists of sirolimus and its matrix builder probucol which was initially studied in the ISAR-TEST 5 trial comparing a polymer-free sirolimus-eluting stent (PF-SES) to a zotarolimus-eluting stent (ZES) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref> with similar safety and efficacy.</s></p><p><s>The objective of the study was to assess the safety and efficacy of PF-SES for the treatment of 'real-world' de novo and restenotic lesions in native coronary arteries and coronary bypass grafts.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods end points and definitions</head><p><s>The international ISAR 2000 all-comers registry ( Clin-icalTrials.</s><s>gov Identifier NCT02629575) prospectively enrolled patients in Europe and Asia.</s><s>The study protocol was approved by all relevant ethics committees prior to patient recruitment.</s><s>The primary endpoint was the 9-month target lesion revascularisation (TLR) rate, whereas secondary endpoints were the 9-month major adverse cardiac events (MACE) rate, the in-hospital MACE rate and the corresponding rates of myocardial infarction (MI) and TLR (coronary artery bypass grafting and re-PCI (percutaneous coronary intervention).</s><s>Cardiac death was only defined inhospital, whereas the all-cause death rate was used to define MACE at 9 months (MI, TLR, inhospital cardiac death and all deaths post discharge).</s><s>The Academic Research Consortium (ARC) criteria <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> were used to define acute/subacute stent thrombosis.</s></p><p><s>Renal insufficiency was defined with a glomerular filtration rate (GFR) of &lt;90 mL/min/1.73</s><s>m 2 with a cut-off GFR rate for mandatory dialysis of &lt;15 mL/min/1.73</s><s>m 2 .</s><s>Severe tortuosity had to meet the angulation criterion of &gt;45°.</s><s>centres Patients were prospectively enrolled in 26 Asian (South Korea and Malaysia) and 36 European (Czech Republic, France, Germany, Slovakia and Spain) cardiac centres (see online supplementary appendix I).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MAterIAls</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PF-SES (Coroflex ISAR, B. Braun Melsungen, Melsungen%20AG,%20Germany)</head><p><s>were implanted according to each institution's guidelines and in accordance with proper indications for national reimbursement.</s><s>Briefly, the bare-metal backbone of the PF-SES has been investigated previously by Leschke et al, <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> whereas the sirolimus matrix coating was extensively studied in the ISAR-TEST 5 trial 4 with very favourable clinical outcomes up to 5 years <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> and in various subgroups such as patients with ST-elevation myocardial infarction <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref> and diabetics. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref></s><s>The polymer-free stent platform consists of a premounted, thin strut (50/60 µm) cobalt-chromium stent whose abluminal surface only is sandblasted to permit a microporous surface for the polymer-free matrix consisting of sirolimus and probucol.</s><s>The concentration of sirolimus is 1.2 µg/mm 2 on the abluminal stent surface only.</s><s>Sirolimus is the active antiproliferative drug, and probucol is an excipient controlling the release of the drug.</s><s>Probucol mimics the function of a polymer by retarding the release of sirolimus.</s><s>Non-clinical testing showed that traces of sirolimus or probucol can be detected beyond 8 weeks.</s><s>Different from drug-coated polymer-free stents without an excipient, the release of sirolimus over time is comparable to polymer-coated DES.</s><s>This matrix coating concept has been evaluated in the aforementioned clinical trials on a different stent platform (Yukon stent, Translumina, Hechingen, Germany).</s><s>Non-inferiority of the polymer-free sirolimus-probucol coated stent has been demonstrated in comparison to the ZES. <ref type="bibr">4 6-9</ref> The device is available in lengths of 8-32 mm and has a crossing profile (0.79 -0.93 mm).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</head><p><s>Patients ≥18 years of age with stable angina or objective proof of ischaemia or patients with acute coronary syndrome (ACS) had to meet the requirements forPCI. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10</ref></s><s>ingle or multiple vessel stenting was allowed in de novo or restenotic lesions with reference diameters from 2.0 to 4.0 mm.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Procedural approach</head><p><s>Femoral or radial vascular access was permitted with recommended introducer sheaths of at least 5 Fr in diameter.</s><s>Moreover, operators could predilate with a balloon catheter of their preference or chose direct stenting at their discretion.</s><s>Intravenous heparin (70 IU/kg) was given to all patients and supplemented when required.</s><s>If possible platelet aggregation inhibitor loading was recommended prior to the procedure according to the institutional preferences of the cardiac centre.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Postprocedural medication</head><p><s>Due to the international characteristic of this study, it was permissible to use various antiplatelet inhibition agents (≥6 months) such as clopidogrel 75 mg/day, prasugrel 10 mg/day or ticagrelor 2×90 mg/day as recommended by the treating physician while acetylsalicylic acid 100-325 mg/day was prescribed life long.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>data collection</head><p><s>A dedicated and established electronic data capture systemwas used, which immediately informed the investigator of data quality issues.</s><s>This database was used in prior large-scale unselected patient cohorts. <ref type="bibr">6 11</ref></s><s>The accuracy of the data sets on a national level was verified by the national principal investigators in each country when the routinely performed web-based plausibility checks indicated discrepancies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>statistical analysis</head><p><s>For all tests, the significance level α was 0.05.The two-sided Fisher's exact test or the χ 2 statistic was used whenever Interventional cardiology applicable to evaluate dichotomous variables.</s><s>Continuous variables were compared with the unpaired t-test or the Mann-Whitney U test in case the Shapiro-Wilk test revealed a strong deviation from a normal distribution.</s></p><p><s>On the basis of previously published results with a predecessor device, 4 a literature value of 10.3% for TLR was assumed for comparison.</s><s>A 9-month TLR rate of 6.0% was postulated for the investigational device in this study.</s><s>It was determined that the one group χ 2 test 90% power to detect the difference between the null hypothesis proportion, π 0 , of 6.0% and the alternative proportion, π A , of 10.3% when the sample size is 396.</s><s>With an expected follow-up rate of at least 80%, a minimum of 495 patients would have to be recruited to reject the null hypothesis that the 9-month TLR rate is non-inferior to the assumed TLR rate of the ISAR-TEST 5 trial.</s></p><p><s>Statistical analyses were conducted with SPSS V.24.0, whereas the biometric estimate was calculated with nQuery/nTerim V.2.0.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>results</head><p><s>Between November 2014 and December 2015, a total of 2877 patients were recruited to receive PF-SES.</s><s>Patient demographics are detailed in table 1.</s><s>The rate of diabetes mellitus (DM) was 37.9% (1090/2877) in the overall population, whereas 1084 patients or 37.6% were treated for ACS.</s><s>Dialysis-dependent patients amounted to 1.7% (48/2877) in the overall cohort.</s><s>Most patients were recruited in Europe (70.4%,</s><s>2025/2877) while the frequency of ACS between regions was not significantly different (p=0.612).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>lesion morphologies</head><p><s>Overall, 3254 lesions were treated with 3858 PF-SES (table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>) primarily for de novo lesions (96.7%, 3146/3254).</s><s>Significant differences in lesion characteristics between patients with stable coronary artery disease (CAD) and those with ACS were observed in the rates of thrombotic occlusions (3.6% vs 24.5%, p&lt;0.001), thrombus burden (7.6% vs 25.2%, p&lt;0.001), in-stent restenosis (ISR, 4.1% vs 2.0%, p=0.002) and the degree of stenosis (85.0%±10.7%</s><s>vs 89.9%±11.0%,</s><s>p&lt;0.001).</s><s>The average use of PF-SES was significantly higher in the non-ACS group (1.36±0.79</s><s>vs 1.29±0.67,</s><s>p=0.031).</s><s>The technical success rate to implant the PF-SES was not different between groups (98.4% vs 98.0%, p=0.411).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>comedication</head><p><s>In terms of the preprocedural drug therapy (table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>), the new antiplatelet inhibitors prasugrel and ticagrelor were more frequently used in patients with ACS (p&lt;0.001).</s><s>Patients without preloading amounted to 10 The recommended duration DAPT (table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">4</ref>) was significantly longer in patients with ACS (p group &lt;0.001), for example, the percentage of patients who underwent 12 months of DAPT was 70.4% (763/1084) versus 42.4% (761/1793).</s><s>The number of patients with unknown length of DAPT was considerable (17.1%, 493/2877) in the total study population.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>clinical results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Inhospital events</head><p><s>Inhospital clinical MACE (table 5) was significantly higher in patients with ACS when compared with those with non-ACS (2.8% vs 0.6%, p&lt;0.001), which were driven by MI (1.8% vs 0.3%, p&lt;0.001), cardiac death (1.2% vs 0.2%, p&lt;0.001) and TLR (0.8% vs 0.3%, p=0.039).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Nine-month events</head><p><s>The follow-up rate for the entire cohort was 87.3% (2513/2877).</s><s>χ 2 statistics and t-tests revealed that the risk profile (demographic and lesion morphological) was not different between those patients with and without 9-month follow-up (see online supplementary appendix II).</s><s>At 9 months, the primary endpoint TLR was not significantly different between both groups (ACS: 2.6% vs stable CAD: 2.1%, p=0.389).</s><s>However, the 9-month MACE rate was almost twice as high as in patients with ACS when compared</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Interventional cardiology</head><p><s>with the stable CAD group (6.1% vs 3.2%, p&lt;0.001) due to MI and overall mortality.</s><s>The Kaplan-Meier (K-M) analysis for the primary endpoint (figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>) did not indicate a significant difference between ACS and non-ACS patients (log-rank p=0.141).</s><s>In contrast, the K-M curves (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref>) for freedom of MACE in the ACS and non-ACS patient subgroups were different (log-rank p&lt;0.001), that is, patients with ACS have significantly higher MACE rates, which manifests itself in an early divergence of the K-M curves.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Nine-month MACE subgroup analyses</head><p><s>Additional χ 2 analyses were conducted for 9-month MACE in a number of subgroups (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>), which did not reveal differences in terms of preloading (p=0.878),</s><s>diabetes (p=0.995),</s><s>dialysis (p=0.429) and region (Europe vs Asia, p=0.317).</s><s>However, the presence of ISR in bare-metal stent (BMS) or DES at baseline led to numerically higher 9-month MACE rates (8.3% vs 4.2%, p=0.064) when compared with patients with de novo lesions.</s><s>Finally, in the patient with stable CAD subgroup, the clinical event rates at 9 months were not different between patients who received 6 months of DAPT and those who had more than 6 months of DAPT (table <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">6</ref>).</s><s>In these patients with stable CAD, there were no significant differences in terms of cardiovascular and lesion morphological risk factors at baseline between the short and long DAPT subgroups with the exception of   Interventional cardiology renal insufficiency, which was higher in the short DAPT subgroup (10.9% vs 4.9%, p&lt;0.001).</s></p><p><s>For comparison purposes, a subgroup of patients with a follow-up closer to 12 months (11.8±1.3 months) was also investigated.</s><s>Their event rates were equally low with a stent thrombosis rate of 1.7% (2/115), MACE 4.3% (5/115), TLR 1.7% (2/115), MI 2.6% (3/115) and all-cause death rate of 0.9% (1/115).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bleeding complications</head><p><s>The accumulated rate of bleeding complications (Bleeding Academic Research Consortium (BARC) 1-5) was1.8%</s><s>(33/1793) in the stable CAD group and 2.4% (26/1084) in the ACS group (p=0.306).</s><s>There were no differences in bleeding frequency among patients who received different antithrombotic agents  in either group.</s><s>However, patients who were on triple therapy in the stable CAD group had significantly more bleeding events when compared with those with DAPT only (15.0%, 6/40 vs 1.5%, 27/1753, p&lt;0.001).</s><s>In the ACS group, triple therapy was also associated with a higher rate of bleeding events (14.3%, 2/14 vs 2.2%, 24/1070; p=0.003).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>dIscussIon</head><p><s>The analogue BMS backbone and the PF-SES 6 had similar procedural/technical success rates.</s><s>This can be rationalised with similar lesion crossing profiles of the crimped stents with identical stent architectures and identical delivery catheters.</s><s>In terms of clinical outcomes, however, there is a pronounced clinical benefit of the sirolimus-probucol coating used in this study since the 9-month MACE and TLR rates <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref> were significantly lower for the PF-SES (BMS analogue MACE 10.2%, TLR 4.4% vs PF-SES MACE 4.3% and TLR 2.3%).</s><s>A propensity score matching with the BMS database seems the only ethically feasible avenue to determine the exact added value of the sirolimus-probucol coating.</s><s>This comparison of uncoated versus coated stents of identical design does not have the lustre of a clinical game changer but may certainly confirm the finding of the Norwegian Coronary Stent Trial (NORSTENT), that is, a significant difference in TLR rates.</s></p><p><s>Basically, the LEADERS-FREE trial <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> with the availability of the 2-year data <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">12</ref> could not demonstrate non-inferiority for BMS to DES as the default treatment strategy even in recognised indication niches such as patients with increased bleeding risks.</s></p><p><s>In reference to the ISAR-TEST 5 trial, the TLR rates in this registry were quite different, that is, 2.3% at 9 months versus 10.3% at 12 months in the ISAR trial despite a comparable all-comers population in both studies.</s><s>One explanation for this finding is the angiographic follow-up in the ISAR-5 trial which was most likelyassociated with the recently reconfirmed 'occulo-stenotic reflex' or spontaneously conducted PCI without objective proof of ischaemia measurements, for example, fraction flow reserve. <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">13</ref></s><s>This, in turn, may have contributed to higher TLR rates in the ISAR-5 trial.</s><s>However, this single-armed study included patients with long lesions and ISR, which were excluded in the ISAR-5 trial.</s><s>Given that the lesion subsets in this registry appear to be more challenging to treat, our 2.3% TLR rate at 9 months fares well with previous findings considering the framework of a registry with potential under-reporting.</s></p><p><s>Iqbal et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">14</ref> reported MACE rates in an all-comers population treated with either ZES or everolimus-eluting stents (EES).</s><s>At 9 months, the MACE rates were in the 6%-8% range without significant differences between EES and ZES.</s><s>Because interstudy comparison is always plagued by methodological challenges, we can merely state that MACE rates in this study are comparable.</s></p><p><s>Colombo et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">15</ref> conducted a single-armed study in an Italian all-comers population which demonstrated similar efficacy of a polymer-free sirolimus-eluting stent by usingorganic acids to modulate the drug release.</s><s>They found target vessel failure rates of 10.1% (62/615) in the overall population.</s><s>Despite the fact that the clinical event rates in this study are numerically lower, it allows the critical question whether diabetes can be considered as a true cardiovascular risk factor for increased MACE and TLR rates in modern DES.</s><s>In this regard, our registry data did not reveal a significant difference in terms of MACE between diabetics and non-diabetics (4.3% vs 4.3%, p=0.995) which is in agreement with the ISAR-TEST 5 diabetic subgroup study <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> and the findings of Colombo et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">15</ref> A more relevant question which seems to drive the current opinion is the debate whether DAPT can be discontinued if the need should arise, for example, an unplanned surgery.</s><s>As pointed out by Stefanini et al, <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">16</ref> there is no class effect of modern DES, that is, different coating and release characteristics hinder the bridging of clinical benefits between devices of different design and coating technology.</s></p><p><s>Out of the myriad of potential explanatory variables in our χ 2 analyses, only the ACS status (p&lt;0.001)</s><s>seems to have an impact on our 9-month MACE (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Interventional cardiology</head><p><s>Established risk factors such as diabetes, stent length or multivessel disease do not seem to increase MACE in patients with ACS and those with stable CAD.</s><s>Because of the non-polymer matrix, the PF-SES used in this assessment is transformed into a BMS once the sirolimusprobucol matrix is fully released.</s><s>Recently published meta-analyses by D'Ascenzo et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">17</ref> and Savarese et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">18</ref> investigated the effect of DAPT duration in first-generation and second-generation DES.</s><s>D'Ascenzo et al concluded that DAPT for up to 6 months can be justified in patients receiving EES and ZES.</s><s>However, the observed decreased risk of major bleeding must be balanced at a higher risk of MI if the shorter DAPT is chosen. <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">17</ref></s><s>Savarese et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">18</ref> reported that prolonged DAPT did not reduce mortality rates.</s><s>Our results, nevertheless, indicate that a shorter DAPT duration up to 6 months did not show higher event rates in the elective patient cohort.</s><s>Elective patients who received up to 6 months of DAPT had comparable rates for MACE (3.1% vs 3.2%, p=0.931) and TLR (2.1% vs 2.1%, p=0.970).</s><s>We also investigated the 9-month MACE rates of patients with stable CAD in subgroups of 0-3, 3-6s, 6-12 months and beyond 12 months which yielded 5.4%, 2.9%, 3.3% and 0.0%, respectively, whereas patients with unknown DAPT duration had a 9-month MACE rate of 3.1%.</s><s>In this analysis we could not detect a difference among these subgroups (p=0.937).</s><s>Despite the fact that this analysis was not powered to detect differences, this finding warrants further investigations.</s><s>Mauri et al 2 who concluded that longer DAPT had clinical benefits for patients with stable CAD and those with ACS could not be demonstrated in our study since our follow-up horizon was substantially shorter than the one reported in the DAPT study.</s></p><p><s>The recently published results of the NORSTENT study <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">19</ref> revealed that DES implantations had no benefit over BMS in terms of the combined rate of all-cause mortality and non-fatal MI (16.6% vs 17.1%, p=0.66) within a follow-up period of 6 years.</s><s>In contrast, the 6-year TLR rates were clearly in favour of DES angioplasty (16.5% vs 19.8%, p&lt;0.001) which is in agreement with our results and the findings of the uncoated analogue BMS backbone. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6</ref></s><s>inally, a careful ramification based on our findings can be made relative to balancing the bleeding risks and DAPT duration.</s><s>As proposed by Yeh et al, <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">20</ref> a benefit:risk ratio for extended DAPT could be quantified on a 'penalty' point system.</s><s>In future subgroup analyses of this large-scale study, the application of this proposed rating system is highly desirable.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>limitations</head><p><s>Intrinsic to an observational study of this size, the less stringent control in terms of data collection and study monitoring may have introduced event under-reporting.</s><s>Furthermore, the follow-up rate of 87.3% is not ideal; however, the 2513 patients with a clinical follow-up provided a wealth of data for meaningful subgroup analyses.</s><s>Moreover, patients with 9-month follow-up did not have an 'easier' cardiovascular risk profile when compared with those lost to follow-up, which would have skewed the clinical results.</s><s>We suspect that this large patient base may compensate for some of the inaccuracies that were introduced by the aforementioned lack of 100% on-site monitoring.</s><s>Another shortcoming of our work is the fact that reliable dyslipidemia data could not be obtained and the smoking status was not determined at baseline.</s><s>This established risk factor would have been very desirable for our exploratory logistic regression analyses.</s><s>Although we could not detect increased rates of MACE in the absence of preloading or shorter DAPT in our data set, our findings are hypothesis generating and do, therefore, not replace a properly designed non-inferiority trial with primary endpoint ST rate as described by Waliszewski and Rittger <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">21</ref> with patient numbers in the 2000-8000 patient range per treatment group.</s><s>conclusIon PF-SES angioplasty was safe and effective in ACS patients with low rates of TLR and MACE which are comparable to reports of other polymer-free DES technologies.</s><s>Patients who were not able to receive antiplatelet preloading do not have higher rates of TLR or MACE at 9 months.</s><s>Established risk factors such as diabetes, lesion length, vessel diameter or presence of B2/C lesions do not seem to increase TLR in patients with ACS and those with stable CAD.</s><s>The impact of shortened DAPT remains to be speculative; however, stable CAD patients with a DAPT duration of up to 6 months did not have higher TLR rates when compared with those with DAPT durations longer than 6 months.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2 Kaplan-Meier curve for freedom from MACE of patients with stable CAD and those with ACS.</s><s>ACS, acute coronary syndrome; CAD, coronary artery disease; MACE, major adverse cardiac events.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,113.32,49.50,368.43,265.58" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3 MACE rates in subgroups of the overall cohort.</s><s>ACS, acute coronary syndrome; CAD, coronary artery disease; ISR, in-stent restenosis; MACE, major adverse cardiac events.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,113.34,480.11,368.40,237.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>on May 17 ,</head><label>17</label><figDesc><div><p><s>2022 by guest.</s><s>Protected by copyright.</s><s>http://openheart.bmj.com/</s><s>Open Heart: first published as 10.1136/openhrt-2017-000592 on 6 June 2017.</s><s>Downloaded from</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,113.32,453.57,368.43,264.14" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Patient demographics</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>http://openheart.bmj.com/</cell></row><row><cell>on May 17, 2022 by guest. Protected by copyright.</cell></row></table><note><p><s>Bold values are statistically significant.</s><s>ACS, acute coronary syndrome; CAD, coronary artery disease; DES, drug-eluting stents; NSTEMI, non-ST segment elevation myocardial infarction; ST, stent thrombosis; STEMI, ST-elevation myocardial infarction.</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>.5% (302/2877) in the overall cohort.</s><s>Postprocedural DAPT use was different between patient groups.</s><s>Patients with stable CAD received more frequently clopidogrel (80.9% vs 51.7%, p group &lt;0.001) and less often prasugrel (5.0% vs 19.4%) and ticagrelor (11.8% vs 26.7%) when compared with patients with ACS.</s><s>Lesion characteristics and procedural data</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>http://openheart.bmj.com/</cell></row><row><cell>on May 17, 2022 by guest. Protected by copyright.</cell></row></table><note><p><s>ACC, American College of Cardiology; ACS, acute coronary syndrome; AHA, American Heart Association; atm, atmosphere; CAD, coronary artery disease; CX, circumflex; DES, drug-eluting stents; LAD, left anterior descending artery; RCA, right coronary artery.</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>on May 17, 2022 by guest.</s><s>Protected by copyright.</s><s>http://openheart.bmj.com/</s><s>Open Heart: first published as 10.1136/openhrt-2017-000592 on 6 June 2017.</s><s>Downloaded from Periprocedural drug therapy</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>p-Value</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Stable CAD vs</cell></row><row><cell>Drug type</cell><cell></cell><cell>Drug</cell><cell cols="3">All patients (%) Stable CAD (%) ACS (%)</cell><cell>ACS</cell></row><row><cell>Pre-PCI</cell><cell>APT</cell><cell>Clopidogrel</cell><cell>1529 (53.1)</cell><cell>1061 (59.2)</cell><cell>468 (43.2)</cell><cell>&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Prasugrel</cell><cell>328 (11.4)</cell><cell>162 (9.0)</cell><cell>166 (15.3)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ticagrelor</cell><cell>383 (13.3)</cell><cell>156 (8.7)</cell><cell>227 (20.9)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ticlopidine</cell><cell>19 (0.7)</cell><cell>9 (0.5)</cell><cell>10 (0.9)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Aspirin only</cell><cell>316 (11.0)</cell><cell>205 (11.4)</cell><cell>111 (10.2)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>No preloading</cell><cell>302 (10.5)</cell><cell>200 (11.2)</cell><cell>102 (9.4)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>OAC</cell><cell>All OAC</cell><cell>54 (1.9)</cell><cell>40 (2.2)</cell><cell>14 (1.3)</cell><cell>0.072</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>VKA</cell><cell>33 (1.1)</cell><cell>25 (1.4)</cell><cell>8 (0.7)</cell><cell>0.188</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>NOAC, eg,</cell><cell>21 (0.7)</cell><cell>15 (0.8)</cell><cell>6 (0.5)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>rivaroxaban</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Post-PCI</cell><cell>APT</cell><cell>Clopidogrel</cell><cell>2010 (69.9)</cell><cell>1450 (80.9)</cell><cell>560 (51.7)</cell><cell>&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Prasugrel</cell><cell>300 (10.4)</cell><cell>90 (5.0)</cell><cell>210 (19.4)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ticagrelor</cell><cell>501 (17.4)</cell><cell>212 (11.8)</cell><cell>289 (26.7)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Aspirin only</cell><cell>28 (1.0)</cell><cell>16 (0.9)</cell><cell>12 (1.1)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Unknown</cell><cell>38 (1.3)</cell><cell>25 (1.4)</cell><cell>13 (1.2)</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>ACS, acute coronary syndrome; APT, antiplatelet therapy; CAD, coronary artery disease; NOAC, new oral anticoagulative; OAC, oral anticoagulatives; PCI, percutaneous coronary intervention; VKA, vitamin k antagonist.</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Recommended duration of dual antiplatelet therapy during follow-up</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>p Value</cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>All patients</cell><cell>Stable CAD</cell><cell>ACS</cell><cell>Stable CAD vs ACS</cell></row><row><cell>No of patients</cell><cell>2877</cell><cell>1793</cell><cell>1084</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>DAPT duration in months</cell><cell>10.0±2.8</cell><cell>9.4±2.9</cell><cell>11.0±2.2</cell><cell>&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell>1 month, n (%)</cell><cell>24 (0.9)</cell><cell>17 (0.9)</cell><cell>7 (0.6)</cell><cell>&lt;0.001</cell></row><row><cell>1-3 months, n (%)</cell><cell>34 (1.2)</cell><cell>24 (1.3)</cell><cell>10 (0.9)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>3-6 months, n (%)</cell><cell>12 (0.4)</cell><cell>8 (0.4)</cell><cell>4 (0.4)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>6 months, n (%)</cell><cell>503 (17.5)</cell><cell>416 (23.2)</cell><cell>87 (8.0)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&gt;6-12 months, n (%)</cell><cell>282 (9.8)</cell><cell>210 (11.7)</cell><cell>72 (6.6)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>12 months, n (%)</cell><cell>1524 (53.0)</cell><cell>761 (42.4)</cell><cell>763 (70.4)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&gt;12 months, n (%)</cell><cell>5 (0.2)</cell><cell>3 (0.2)</cell><cell>2 (0.2)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Unknown status, n (%)</cell><cell>493 (17.1)</cell><cell>354 (19.7)</cell><cell>139 (12.8)</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>ACS, acute coronary syndrome; CAD, coronary artery disease; DAPT, dual-antiplatelet therapy.</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Clinical outcomes</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>http://openheart.bmj.com/</cell></row><row><cell>on May 17, 2022 by guest. Protected by copyright.</cell></row></table><note><p><s>ACS, acute coronary syndrome; CABG, coronary artery bypass grafting; CAD, coronary artery disease; MACE; major adverse cardiac events; MI, myocardial infarction; re-PCI, re-percutaneous coronary intervention; TLR, target lesion revascularisation.Figure 1 Kaplan-Meier curve for freedom from TLR of patients with stable CAD and those with ACS.</s><s>ACS, acute coronary syndrome; CAD, coronary artery disease; TLR, target lesion revascularisation.</s><s>on May 17, 2022 by guest.</s><s>Protected by copyright.</s><s>http://openheart.bmj.com/</s><s>Open Heart: first published as 10.1136/openhrt-2017-000592 on 6 June 2017.</s><s>Downloaded from</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Nine-month clinical outcomes in patients with stable CAD on short vs long DAPT</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Longer than</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Less or equal to</cell><cell>6 months of</cell><cell>p Value</cell></row><row><cell>Variable</cell><cell>All patients</cell><cell>6 months of DAPT</cell><cell>DAPT</cell><cell>long vs short DAPT</cell></row><row><cell>No of patients</cell><cell>1566</cell><cell>384</cell><cell>1182</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>9-month MACE, n (%)</cell><cell>50 (3.2)</cell><cell>12 (3.1)</cell><cell>38 (3.2)</cell><cell>0.931</cell></row><row><cell>9-month TLR</cell><cell>33 (2.1)</cell><cell>8 (2.1)</cell><cell>25 (2.1)</cell><cell>0.970</cell></row><row><cell>(re-PCI, CABG), n (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>9-month MI, n (%)</cell><cell>17 (1.1)</cell><cell>4 (1.0)</cell><cell>13 (1.1)</cell><cell>0.924</cell></row><row><cell>9-month death all causes, n (%)</cell><cell>14 (0.9)</cell><cell>4 (1.0)</cell><cell>10 (0.8)</cell><cell>0.723</cell></row><row><cell>9-month accumulated definite/probable stent thrombosis,</cell><cell>9 (0.6)</cell><cell>3 (0.8)</cell><cell>6 (0.5)</cell><cell>0.538</cell></row><row><cell>n (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>CABG, coronary artery bypass grafting; CAD, coronary artery disease; DAPT, dual-antiplatelet therapy; MACE, major adverse cardiac events; MI, myocardial infarction; re-PCI, re-percutaneous coronary intervention; TLR, target lesion revascularisation.</s></p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Acknowledgements The authors express their sincere thanks to Dr Ralf Degenhardt at the Cardiovascular Center in Rotenburg, Germany for his essential statistical expertise.</s><s>Furthermore, the authors would like to express their gratitude to the following Medical AffairsTeam members Denny Herberger (Germany), Dr Ghislaine Martin and Ms Aude Michaud (France), Dr Ricard Rosique (Spain), Ms Zoey Hooi (Malaysia) and Ms Yoonmi Lee (South Korea) for their regulatory and logistic support to conduct this study.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long-term safety of drug-eluting and bare-metal stents: evidence from a comprehensive network meta-analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Palmerini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Benedetto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Biondi-Zoccai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jacc.2015.04.017</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2496" to="2507" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Twelve or 30 months of dual antiplatelet therapy after drug-eluting stents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mauri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kereiakes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/NEJMoa1409312</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med Overseas Ed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">371</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2155" to="2166" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Polymer-free drug-coated coronary stents in patients at high bleeding risk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Urban</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Meredith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Abizaid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/NEJMoa1503943</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">373</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2038" to="2047" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Polymer-free sirolimusand probucol-eluting versus new generation zotarolimus-eluting stents in coronary artery disease: the Intracoronary stenting and angiographic results: test efficacy of sirolimus-and probucol-eluting versus zotarolimus-eluting stents (ISAR-TEST 5) trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Massberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Byrne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kastrati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.111.026732</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">124</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="624" to="632" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical end points in coronary stent trials: a case for standardized definitions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cutlip</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Windecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mehran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.106.685313</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">115</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2344" to="2351" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thin strut bare metal stents in patients with atrial fibrillation: is there still a need for BMS?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Leschke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Waliszewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/ccd.26261</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Catheter Cardiovasc Interv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="358" to="366" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Randomized trial of polymerfree sirolimus-and probucol-eluting stents versus durable polymer zotarolimus-eluting stents: 5-year results of the ISAR-TEST-5 trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kufner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sorges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mehilli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcin.2016.01.009</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JACC Cardiovasc Interv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="784" to="792" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Five-year follow-up of polymerfree sirolimus-and probucol-eluting stents versus new generation zotarolimus-eluting stents in patients presenting with st-elevation myocardial infarction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Colleran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kufner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Harada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/ccd.26597</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Catheter Cardiovasc Interv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="367" to="374" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Five-year clinical outcomes in patients with diabetes mellitus treated with polymer-free sirolimusand probucol-eluting stents versus second-generation zotarolimuseluting stents: a subgroup analysis of a randomized controlled trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Harada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Colleran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kufner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12933-016-0429-y</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cardiovasc Diabetol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">124</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">ESC/EACTS guidelines on myocardial revascularization: the task force on myocardial revascularization of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and the European Association for Cardio-Thoracic Surgery (EACTS)developed with the special contribution of the European Association of Percutaneous Cardiovascular Interventions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Windecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kolh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Alfonso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>EAPCI</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/eurheartj/ehu278</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2541" to="2619" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SeQuentPlease World Wide Registry: clinical results of SeQuent please paclitaxel-coated balloon angioplasty in a large-scale, prospective registry study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wöhrle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zadura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Möbius-Winkler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jacc.2012.07.040</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1733" to="1738" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">2-year outcomes of high bleeding risk patients after polymer-free drug-coated stents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Garot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Morice</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Tresukosol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jacc.2016.10.009</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Coll Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="162" to="171" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Outcomes of the largest multi-center trial stratified by the presence of diabetes mellitus comparing sirolimus-eluting stents (SES) and paclitaxel-eluting stents (PES) in patients with coronary artery disease. The Japan drug-eluting stents evaluation: a</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nakamura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Muramatsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yokoi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>randomized trial (J-DESsERT</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s12928-014-0279-z</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cardiovasc Interv Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="114" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of zotarolimusand everolimus-eluting coronary stents: final 5-year report of the RESOLUTE all-comers trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Iqbal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Serruys</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Silber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1161/CIRCINTERVENTIONS.114.002230</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circ Cardiovasc Interv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e002230</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">One-year clinical outcome of amphilimus polymer-free drug-eluting stent in diabetes mellitus patients: insight from the ASTUTE registry (AmphilimuS iTalian mUlticenTre rEgistry)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Colombo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Godino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Donahue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ijcard.2016.03.088</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">214</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="120" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Will LEADERS-FREE change my practice? A randomised double-blind comparison of the BioFreedom™ drug-coated stent vs. the Gazelle™ bare metal stent in patients at high bleeding risk using a short (1 month) course of dual antiplatelet therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Stefanini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Behan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Valgimigli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.4244/EIJV12I6A129</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EuroIntervention</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="798" to="800" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Meta-analysis of the duration of dual antiplatelet therapy in patients treated with secondgeneration drug-eluting stents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>D'ascenzo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Moretti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bianco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.amjcard.2016.03.005</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1714" to="1723" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficacy and safety of prolonged dual antiplatelet therapy: a meta-analysis of 15 randomized trials enrolling 85 265 patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Savarese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Savonitto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/ehjcvp/pvw011</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Heart J Cardiovasc Pharmacother</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="218" to="228" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drug-eluting or bare-metal stents for coronary artery disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Bønaa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mannsverk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wiseth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/NEJMoa1607991</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">375</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1242" to="1252" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Development and validation of a prediction rule for benefit and harm of dual antiplatelet therapy beyond 1 year after percutaneous coronary intervention</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Secemsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kereiakes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1001/jama.2016.3775</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JAMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">315</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1735" to="1749" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Surrogate and clinical endpoints in interventional cardiology: are statistics the brakes?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Waliszewski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Rittger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1177/1753944716656150</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ther Adv Cardiovasc Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="314" to="326" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/openhrt-2017-000592on6</idno>
		<ptr target="http://openheart.bmj.com/OpenHeart" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-06">June 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
