<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Long-Term Analysis of Ab-2 (Clone SN3b) Immunoreactivity as a Prognostic Factor in Breast Carcinoma</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-03-26">March 26, 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Klaus-Jürgen</forename><surname>Winzer</surname></persName>
							<email>klaus-juergen.winzer@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Breast Cancer Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Joachim</forename><surname>Bellach</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Comprehensive Cancer Centre Charité</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Glen</forename><surname>Kristiansen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Pathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Rheinische Friedrich-Wilhelms-Universität Bonn</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Breast Cancer Centre Charité -Universitätsmedizin Berlin Charité</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Long-Term Analysis of Ab-2 (Clone SN3b) Immunoreactivity as a Prognostic Factor in Breast Carcinoma</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-03-26">March 26, 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">1EEF53C0B1A0B051D3115D14C7104F55</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1159/000377654</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:38+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>In 2003, our group established that overexpression of CD24 in invasive breast carcinoma is prognostically unfavourable <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>Our initial study used the monoclonal CD24 antibody Ab-2 (clone SN3b, Neomarkers (Fremont, CA, USA)), which was technically very robust and subsequently employed by innumerable groups to detect CD24, even though its precise epitope was -and still iselusive.</s><s>In a later study <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, we compared the CD24 immunoreactivity patterns of clone SN3b with those of clone SWA11, which have been well characterised as specific for the CD24 protein core.</s><s>This comparison revealed only a partial overlap between both antibodies.</s><s>It is probable that clone SN3b detects sialic acid on Olinked glycans, which can also occur independently of the CD24 protein backbone.</s><s>This implies that mAb SN3b is not strictly a CD24-specific antibody, which explains discrepancies with other studies, although it presumably accounts for the major component of 'CD24' immunoreactivity.</s><s>This is even more of interest since SWA11 failed to show a statistically significant prognostic value, although a weak positive trend was discernible.</s></p><p><s>Our original study published in 2003 had several minor shortcomings.</s><s>First, it encompassed patients from different clinics who had been diagnosed at the pathology institute of the Charité; secondly, it was based on patient data covering an average follow-up observation period of only 65 months (5-129 months); and thirdly, it lacked access to additional information on secondary tumours, etc.</s><s>The acquisition of markedly prolonged follow-up data and additional patient information prompted us to reanalyse the original CD24/SN3b expression data of the patients from a single centre (Breast Cancer Centre Charité).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Keywords</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">Breast cancer • Prognostic factor • Ab-2 (clone SN3b) • CD24, Survival</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary</head><p><s>Background: CD24 expression has been described as a significant prognostic factor in multiple solid tumours.</s><s>Most of these studies have, however, been undertaken using the Ab-2 antibody (clone SN3b), which detects a CD24-associated carbohydrate, and not the CD24 protein itself.</s><s>Although its biological identity remains unclear, its prognostic significance means that detection of this carbohydrate may, nonetheless, be clinically relevant.</s><s>Methods: 133 breast carcinomas were selected (pT1-2 pN0-2 M0, no secondary carcinoma, no contralateral carcinoma) from a previous SN3b expression study on a larger cohort of breast carcinomas.</s><s>After updating data on follow-up observations, we carried out univariate and multivariate analysis of the prognostic significance of SN3b for total and breast cancer-specific survival.</s><s>Results: A statistically significant correlation between cytoplasmic SN3b immunoreactivity and positive node status was found.</s><s>Cytoplasmic SN3b also has node status-independent prognostic significance.</s><s>Total survival exhibits a statistically significant dependency on cytoplasmic SN3b even for pN0 cases.</s><s>Conclusion: The independent prognostic value of CD24 as detected by Ab-2/ clone SN3b could replace the diagnostic axillary dissection in breast carcinoma patients if this was confirmed in further studies.</s><s>Also, clarifying the exact epitope of this interesting antibody is more than warranted.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patients and Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patients</head><p><s>From our previous study, we identified 139 cases with primary breast carcinoma.</s><s>These had undergone surgery in the surgical unit on the central Charité campus and were diagnosed at the Institute of Pathology of the Charité. 2 of these cases had other previous or concurrent malignancies and were therefore excluded from the analysis.</s><s>5 patients who subsequently developed other malignant tumours remained in the analysis.</s><s>A further 4 patients who had previously been diagnosed with a contralateral breast carcinoma prior to the breast carcinoma under investigation were also excluded from the study.</s><s>4 patients who developed a simultaneous (i.e.</s><s>within 6 months) contralateral breast carcinoma and 7 patients who subsequently developed a contralateral breast carcinoma were not excluded from the study.</s><s>In total, 133 cases remained in the analysis.</s><s>Of these, 127 cases were M0 and 6 cases were M1.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Follow-Up Data</head><p><s>Total survival up to a cut-off date of 30.06.2007 was analysed.</s><s>The death rates of a previously published analysis of all patients between 1984 and 1998 were underestimated since they were exclusively based on follow-up data from a single clinical tumour register that contained data established solely on further consultations with patients.</s><s>These data were, therefore, supplemented with data on survival times from the Joint Cancer Register of the States of Berlin, Brandenburg, Mecklenburg-West Pomerania, Saxony-Anhalt and the Free States of Saxony and Thuringia (GKR) and from the Berlin Resident Registration Office <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Since no data on continued survival were available from the resident registration offices in the other German states, in particular those in the former East Germany, the number of deaths of patients from these states was weighted more heavily despite the identical recording period.</s><s>This is because data from other resident registration offices, if they had been available, would have supplemented data from the clinical register prior to the cut-off date for the analysis for those patients who were no longer attending hospital consultations.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Immunohistochemistry</head><p><s>CD24 immunostaining was conducted as described previously <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>Briefly, freshly cut paraffin sections were dewaxed with xylene and gradually hydrated.</s><s>Antigen retrieval was achieved by pressure cooking in 0.01 M citrate buffer for 5 min.</s><s>The primary CD24 antibody (clone SN3b; Neomarkers, Fremont, USA) was diluted 1: 100 and incubated at room temperature for 2 h.</s><s>The conventional labelled streptavidin-biotin method was used for detection with alkaline phosphatase as the reporting enzyme and chromogenic development with Fast-Red.</s><s>Finally, the slides were briefly counterstained and mounted.</s></p><p><s>In the initial study we kept our scoring system of the CD24 staining as simple as possible to enhance the reproducibility of our findings in future studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>We evaluated the membranous and the cytoplasmic staining intensity of CD24 separately and scored the staining intensity as negative (0), or weakly (1+), moderately (2+) or strongly (3+) positive.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>The mean observation period was 96.1 months (minimum 1 month, maximum 192 months).</s><s>Follow-up data received from the clinical cancer registry were supplemented with data from Berlin Resident Registration Office records and the cancer registry of the new federal states of Germany (GKR).</s><s>In total, 40 deaths were recorded.</s><s>Because the first event (death) occurred after 6 months, 2 cases for which the follow-up period was only 1 month and 1 case for which it was 5 months were discarded, leaving 130 patients in our analysis.</s><s>Due to missing data the number of cases analysed for some individual parameters was lower.</s><s>We found a significant association of CD24 expression with a positive nodal status (table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>This association between pN and cytoplasmic SN3b was further tested using the gamma statistics, which is suitable for analysing associations between ordinal-scaled variables.</s><s>The corresponding cross-table (table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>) showed a positive association between cytoplasmic SN3b and pN.</s><s>A gamma test for no association between cytoplasmic SN3b and pN (gamma test) was rejected with a significance level of p = 0.013.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Survival Analyses</head><p><s>We conducted a univariate Cox regression to determine the prognostic value for overall survival of CD24 and the standard prognostic parameters (pT, pN, G and oestrogen receptor) (table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">2</ref>).</s><s>The prognostic significance of CD24/SN3b was further confirmed in a Kaplan Meier analysis (fig.</s><s><ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>; p = 0.023 (log rank test)).</s></p><p><s>To approach a multivariate setting, backward stepwise (Wald) Cox regression analysis using the above prognostic parameters was employed: of the 130 cases, 15 were omitted due to missing data, leaving 115 cases and 34 events.</s><s>In the resulting model, cytoplasmic CD24/SN3b immunoreactivity was the strongest independent prognostic parameter (table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">3</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Despite the small number of cases, we considered it of interest to examine total survival time as a function of cytoplasmic SN3b for pN0 cases only (table 4).</s><s>As with the above calculations, 60 cases (64 minus 2 cases censored before the earliest event in the stratum and 2 cases with missing values) with 12 deaths were included in the calculation, which yielded a significance of p = 0.045 (backwards stepwise Cox regression).</s><s>The same calculation for all pT1pN0 cases shows that the number of cases remains too small (data not shown).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Our reanalysis revealed that cytoplasmic CD24/SN3b immunoreactivity is found to improve the prognostic accuracy further in terms of breast cancer-specific survival, even compared to nodal status.</s><s>We are well aware that calculating breast cancer-specific survival is controversial due to diagnostic uncertainty in death statistics -as a result, for example, of death certificates not always being filled out correctly <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> or of treatment-induced premature deaths not directly caused by breast cancer.</s><s>For this reason we deliberately used overall patient survival times.</s><s>The results for the pN0 cases appear to support the validity of this method.</s></p><p><s>The increase in events detected using our data collection methodology of incorporating data from additional cancer registries is beneficial for this comparative analysis.</s><s>Although the appropriateness of the Kaplan-Meier method can be questioned in cohorts with complex follow-up compositions like ours <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, we have still utilized this widely applied technique for approximation and the subsequent Cox analyses confirmed the prognostic value of CD24/ SN3b.</s><s>These results for cytoplasmic CD24/SN3b are even more interesting in light of recent data that led to discussions on the value of axillary lymph node dissection in cases in which several sentinel  lymph nodes (up to 2) are positive <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</s><s>This could imply that the quantity of lymph node involvement would no longer be available as a prognostic factor.</s></p><p><s>Unfortunately, the number of cases in this study is too low to identify putative pT1pN0 cases by an evaluation of cytoplasmic CD24/SN3b.</s><s>If this were possible, it would identify a subgroup of small tumours with no lymph node involvement that still have a poor prognosis.</s><s>In addition, currently the idea that local lymph node dissection is not significant for further survival is under considerable discussion <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Clearly, a much larger study of well-characterized breast cancer cases is not only warranted but also urgently needed to elucidate the promising prognostic value of SN3b immunoreactivity, ideally in direct comparison to an antibody that recognizes the CD24 protein core (e.g.</s><s>SWA11).</s><s>CD24 began to attract the attention of can-cer researchers a decade ago.</s><s>It is overexpressed in the majority of human carcinomas and is often associated with a poorer prognosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</s><s>Many of these studies were carried out with the SN3b antibody; therefore, it is time to investigate and annotate the SN3b epitope to understand its tumour-biological functions.</s></p><p><s>In conclusion, CD24/Ab-2 (clone SN3b) immunoreactivity is a strong prognostic factor in node-negative primary breast carcinomas and provides useful information supplementing that obtained from lymph node involvement.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disclosure Statement</head><p><s>We declare that we have no conflict of interest.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1.</s><s>Survival times from the Joint Cancer Register of the federal states of Berlin, Brandenburg, Mecklenburg-West Pomerania, Saxony-Anhalt, the free states of Saxony and Thuringia (GKR) and from the Berlin resident registration office.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,37.97,62.66,259.22,263.18" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Association of CD24 (clone SN3b) with clinicopathological parameters</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Characteristic</cell><cell cols="4">CD24/SN3b cytoplasmic</cell><cell>Approx.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>significance a</cell></row><row><cell>pT</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>pT1 pT2</cell><cell>22 6</cell><cell>30 17</cell><cell>24 12</cell><cell>10 7</cell><cell>0.256</cell></row><row><cell>pT3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>pT4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>pN</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>pN0</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>7</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>pN1</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0.013</cell></row><row><cell>pN2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Histological grade</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>G1</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>5</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>G2</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0.366</cell></row><row><cell>G3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Oestrogen receptor</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Negative</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>0.126</cell></row><row><cell>Positive</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>28</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>9</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>a Ordinal by ordinal gamma</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Univariate Cox regression for single prognostic parameters (overall survival)</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Prognostic</cell><cell>Statistical</cell><cell cols="2">For the analysis:</cell><cell></cell><cell>Exp(B)</cell></row><row><cell>parameter</cell><cell>significance</cell><cell>Cases</cell><cell>Censored</cell><cell>Available</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>with</cell><cell>cases</cell><cell>deaths</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>missing</cell><cell>before the</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>data</cell><cell>earliest</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>event in a</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>stratum</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>pT</cell><cell>0.007</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>1.569</cell></row><row><cell>pN</cell><cell>0.002</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>39</cell><cell>2.208</cell></row><row><cell>G</cell><cell>0.014</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>37</cell><cell>1.765</cell></row><row><cell>ER</cell><cell>0.082</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>0.566</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">CD24/SN3b 0.003</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>40</cell><cell>1.661</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">ER = oestrogen receptor, Exp(B) = hazard ratio.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>Ab-2 (clone SN3b) -Prognostic Factor Breast Care 2015;10:273-276 275</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Multivariate Cox regression of CD24 expression and clinicopathological parameters -overall survival</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Sig.</cell><cell>Exp(B)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Multivariate</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Cox regression of</cell></row><row><cell>CD24/SN3b expression</cell></row><row><cell>and clinicopathological</cell></row><row><cell>parameters (pN0) -</cell></row><row><cell>overall surviva</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CD24 expression is a new prognostic marker in breast cancer</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kristiansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Winzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mayordomo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4906" to="4913" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Molecular and clinical dissection of CD24 antibody specificity by a comprehensive comparative analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kristiansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Machado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bretz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lab Invest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1102" to="1116" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wertigkeit der routinemäßig erfassten Nachsorgedaten bei Brustkrebspatientinnen</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Winzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bellach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Zentralbl Chir</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">135</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="261" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Todesursachen sowie Häufigkeit pathologisch-anatomischer Befundkomplexe und Diagnosen einer mittelgroßen Stadt bei fast 100 prozentiger Obduktionsquote -Eine Obduktionsanalyse unter Einbeziehung histologischer Untersuchungen zum gegenwärtigen Stellenwert der Pathologie (Görlitzer Studie</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Modelmog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986/ 1987. 1993</date>
			<publisher>Hänsel-Hohenhausen</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Egelsbach, Köln, New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Accuracy of death certificates: A population-based, complete-coverage, one-year autopsy study in East Germany</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Modelmog</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rahlenbeck</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Trichopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Causes Control</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="541" to="546" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Studie zur Verbesserung der Validität und Reliabilität der amtlichen Todesursachenstatistik</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Jahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K-H</forename><surname>Bocter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Schriftenreihe des Bundesministeriums für Gesundheit</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Baden-Baden</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Nomos Verlagsgesellschaft</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Axillary dissection vs no axillary dissection in women with invasive breast cancer and sentinel node metastasis: A randomized clinical trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Giuliano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Ballman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JAMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">305</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="569" to="575" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Locoregional recurrence after sentinel lymph node dissection with or without axillary dissection in patients with sentinel lymph node metastases: The American College of Surgeons Oncology Group Z0011 randomized trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Giuliano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mccall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Beitsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">252</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="426" to="432" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Positive sentinel nodes without axillary dissection: Implications for the radiation oncologist</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Haffty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Hunt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Buchholz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4479" to="4481" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Positive lymph nodes do not metastasize</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Engel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Emeny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hölzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Metastasis Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="246" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tumour biological aspects of CD24, a mucin-like adhesion molecule</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kristiansen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sammar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Altevogt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Mol Histol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="255" to="262" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
