<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Pyoderma outbreak among kindergarten families: Association with a Panton-Valentine leukocidin (PVL)-producing S. aureus strain</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-12-19">December 19, 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Rasmus</forename><surname>Leistner</surname></persName>
							<email>rasmus.leistner@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Hygiene and Environmental Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">PVL Workgroup</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Axel</forename><surname>Kola</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Hygiene and Environmental Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Petra</forename><surname>Gastmeier</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Hygiene and Environmental Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Renate</forename><surname>Kru ¨ger</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">PVL Workgroup</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatric Pulmonology and Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Pia-Alice</forename><surname>Hoppe</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">PVL Workgroup</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatric Pulmonology and Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sylke</forename><surname>Schneider-Burrus</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">PVL Workgroup</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Dermatology and Allergy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Irina</forename><surname>Zuschneid</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Charlottenburg-Wilmersdorf Health Department</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nicoletta</forename><surname>Wischnewski</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Charlottenburg-Wilmersdorf Health Department</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jennifer</forename><surname>Bender</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Robert Koch Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Wernigerode, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Franziska</forename><surname>Layer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">PVL Workgroup</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Robert Koch Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Wernigerode, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michaela</forename><surname>Niebank</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">PVL Workgroup</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Internal Medicine/Infectious Diseases and Pulmonary Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Carmen</forename><surname>Scheibenbogen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Medical Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Leif</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hanitsch</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">PVL Workgroup</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Medical Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´Universita ¨tsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="institution">Universitatsklinikum Munster</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DE">GERMANY</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Pyoderma outbreak among kindergarten families: Association with a Panton-Valentine leukocidin (PVL)-producing S. aureus strain</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2017-12-19">December 19, 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">825A550B94C9B400007F0274897C5D04</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0189961</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: July 11, 2017 Accepted: December 5, 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:23+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Objectives</head><p><s>We report on an outbreak of skin and soft tissue infections (SSTI) among kindergarten families.</s><s>We analyzed the transmission route and aimed to control the outbreak.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p><s>The transmission route was investigated by nasal screening for Panton-Valentine leukocidin (PVL)-producing Staphylococcus aureus (PVL-SA), subsequent microbiological investigation including whole genome sequencing and a questionnaire-based analysis of epidemiological information.</s><s>The control measures included distribution of outbreak information to all individuals at risk and implementation of a Staphylococcus aureus decontamination protocol.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Individuals from 7 of 19 families were either colonized or showed signs of SSTI such as massive abscesses or eye lid infections.</s><s>We found 10 PVL-SA isolates in 9 individuals.</s><s>In the WGS-analysis all isolates were found identical with a maximum of 17 allele difference.</s><s>The clones were methicillin-susceptible but cotrimoxazole resistant.</s><s>In comparison to PVL-SAs from an international strain collection, the outbreak clone showed close genetical relatedness to PVL-SAs from a non-European country.</s><s>The questionnaire results showed frequent travels of one family to this area.</s><s>The results also demonstrated likely transmission via direct contact between families.</s><s>After initiation of Staphylococcus aureus decontamination no further case was detected.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Staphylococcus aureus is the most common cause of community-acquired skin and soft tissue infections (SSTI) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>In particular, the development of massive skin abscesses in otherwise healthy individuals is associated with certain strains of community-acquired S. aureus <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref>.</s><s>These strains very often carry a gene-encoding Panton-Valentine leukocidin (PVL).</s><s>PVL is a porin-like exotoxin that lyses leukocytes and is associated with dermonecrosis in the animal model <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>In the USA, most isolates from outbreaks resulting from community-acquired Methicillin-resistant S. aureus (CA-MRSA) carry the PVL gene.</s><s>In Europe, similar outbreaks are often associated with strains of Methicillin-susceptible S. aureus (CA-MSSA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s>However, both types of outbreaks occur within similar settings.</s><s>They generally include close physical contact, the sharing of clothes such as sports or work clothes, or sauna visits <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref>.</s><s>Here, we report an outbreak of pyoderma resulting from PVL-positive MSSA and its control among children in an urban kindergarten and their families in Berlin, Germany.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p><s>This work evolved from a cooperation during an outbreak investigation.</s><s>Only secondary data from the outbreak scenario was used to conduct this analysis.</s><s>Written informed consent was obtained from all participants.</s><s>The provided data was strictly anonymized for analysis and publication.</s></p><p><s>Exclusively RL and LH had access to the original data from the questionnaires and access to identifying information.</s><s>As this work arose from routine infection control analyses, the Charite ´institutional review board waived the necessity of a previous ethics approval (Ethikausschuss 4 Campus Benjamin Franklin, process number EA4/112/17).</s></p><p><s>In March 2016, we were informed of a cluster of pyoderma cases among children who attended the same kindergarten.</s><s>We established a multidisciplinary outbreak team to treat affected individuals and started a comprehensive investigation to control the outbreak.</s><s>We arranged an information meeting with all families in order to discuss transmission routes and possible control measures.</s><s>We performed a screening for nasal PVL-positive S. aureus (PVL-SA) colonization on all the kindergarten children and teachers.</s><s>PVL-SA was detected by bacterial culture and subsequent PCR <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The genetical relatedness of the PVL-SA strains was investigated by whole genome sequencing (WGS) at the German National Reference Center (NRC) for Staphylococci and Enterococci at the Robert Koch Institute.</s><s>Illumina short read sequencing and subsequent bioinformatics analyses using the SeqSphere+ software suite (Ridom, Mu ¨nster, Germany) were utilized for this analysis.</s></p><p><s>DNA was isolated utilizing the DNeasy Blood 48 and Tissue Kit (Qiagen), followed by library preparation (Nextera XT Library Prep Kit, Illumina) and Illumina short read sequencing in paired-end on a MiSeq instrument (2x300 bp).</s><s>Trimmed reads were assembled de novo using the a5-miseq algorithm (Coil et al., Bioinformatics, 2015) and contigs were analyzed by the SeqSphere+ software suite (Ridom, Mu ¨nster, Germany).</s><s>Strain relatedness based on core genome MLST (cgMLST) data was inferred from 1790 loci.</s><s>Allelic differences are defined as novel alleles allocated due to the presence of SNPs, insertions or deletions.</s></p><p><s>We developed a questionnaire that was distributed among all families of children in the kindergarten (S1 Questionnaire).</s><s>We inquired about the following subjects: skin infections among family members, chronic skin diseases or other underlying diseases, age, sex, contact with other kindergarten families outside of the kindergarten, pets, and travel abroad.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Initially, we knew of three symptomatic children who had had severe abscesses during the previous weeks.</s><s>This included recurrent abscesses on fingers, necks, knees, thighs, or ears.</s><s>In all cases, S. aureus expressing resistance to cotrimoxazole was isolated.</s><s>The production of PVL in the S. aureus isolates was examined only in one case and found positive.</s><s>We suspected an outbreak and notified the local health authorities.</s><s>Twenty-three children from 19 families attended the kindergarten.</s><s>We found two asymptomatic children carrying PVL-positive S. aureus.</s><s>All isolates were methicillin-susceptible but cotrimoxazole-resistant.</s><s>In addition, all household contacts of symptomatic children or children with PVL-SA carriage were contacted and screened for nasal or pharyngeal colonization.</s></p><p><s>The response rate of the questionnaire was 79% (15 of 19 families).</s><s>The answers showed that within the previous 12 months, members of two additional families had been diagnosed with eyelid abscesses.</s><s>We defined families with either PVL-SA-colonized or symptomatic members as affected or case families.</s><s>Based on the questionnaire's information on play dates outside the kindergarten, we created a social network visualization (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>) (The figure was created using open access software (http://cuttlefish.sourceforge.net/).</s><s>The illustration shows the frequency of contacts between affected and unaffected families.</s><s>It describes a cluster of play dates among case families and suggests that the predominant transmission route was most likely direct contact between the children.</s></p><p><s>We initiated a 5-day course of S. aureus decolonization for the affected families (symptomatic regardless colonization status or PVL-SA carrier) that included all of the family members who shared a single apartment.</s><s>The core decolonization protocol consisted of nasal mupirocin or octenidine ointment three times per day; twice-daily mouthwash with octenidine or chlorhexidine; and, daily washing of the body with octenidine or chlorhexidine.</s><s>Moreover, we recommended changing all personal care products including toothbrushes, combs and skin care products, and washing all clothes, towels and bed linens at 60˚C.</s><s>However, in the control screening-one week after the first decolonization-we found one positive child and one positive kindergarten teacher.</s><s>We repeated the decolonization protocol for the remaining carriers a second time, followed by a control screening (2 weeks later) and a third repetition followed by a screening only for the remaining carriers (S1 Table <ref type="table">)</ref>.</s><s>During a follow-up period of ten months, the affected families did not report any further skin or soft tissue infections.</s><s>No additional cases occurred in the kindergarten.</s></p><p><s>Whole genome sequencing (WGS) was performed on 10 screening isolates of 9 individuals from 5 families.</s><s>Sequence type (ST) 1633 and spa-type t355 was verified for all outbreak isolates.</s><s>While MLST is based on 7 housekeeping genes only, further sub-differentiation with enhanced discriminatory power was achieved by extracting cgMLST types (CT) considering a total of 1790 loci.</s><s>Thereby, CT 3142 was determined for the outbreak isolates which strengthens the hypothesis of strain transmission between various family members and unrelated individuals.</s><s>As an example and as inferred from pairwise comparisons of the outbreak isolates, a maximum of 11 allele difference was detected between child A from fam#1 and adult A from fam#2 (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</s><s>In order to infer evolutionary relatedness, we completed the sample set with isolates from the strain collection of the German NRC for Staphylococci.</s><s>They were acquired from pyoderma cases from 5 different countries on 2 continents, exhibiting the following characteristics: MSSA, PVL-positive, spa-type t355.</s><s>The outbreak cluster was clearly separated from the closest relative by 68 alleles (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</s><s>This strain (ST152) originated from country A, outside of Europe.</s><s>Interestingly, and concordant to the answers given in the above mentioned questionnaire survey, members of family #1 travel several times per year to this country.</s><s>The hypothesis was further examined by comparing PVL-encoding genes and flanking genetic regions hence verifying a close relationship between country A and the outbreak isolates (not shown).</s><s>Unfortunately, due to data protection of the respective family we are obliged to use a pseudonym for the respective country.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>This outbreak of PVL-SA-associated skin infection was most likely following introduction of the pathogen via international travel and subsequent transmission via direct contact.</s><s>WGS of the screening isolates showed a genetically close relationship between the outbreak strain and an often-visited country of one family (family #1).</s><s>International travel has been described as risk factor of PVL-SA acquisition and introduction into communities <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>.</s><s>Whereas skin infections on trunk and extremities are the most common sites, some patients showed signs of periorbital skin infection.</s><s>This is rare, but has been previously described as PVL-SA-associated infections <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s>Direct contact is the most likely route of PVL-SA transmission <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s>As our data showed a clustering pattern of PVL-SA cases among children that often met for play dates, our data underlines this assumption.</s></p><p><s>Our results also show that some colonized individuals can develop serious cases of pyoderma while others merely remain colonized without signs of skin infection (e.g.</s><s>family #1).</s><s>This goes along with the meta-analysis by Shallgross et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s>Moreover, our survey did not reveal any association with preexisting skin conditions in this family.</s><s>This indicates a distinct pathogen-host interaction that allows for infection in some individuals.</s><s>However, a study by Hermos et al. showed that simply high levels of antibodies to PVL components LukF and LukS are not associated with resistance to SSTI <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</s><s>Future studies on PVL-SA colonized individuals without history of skin infection are necessary to provide explanations for this phenomenon.</s></p><p><s>S. aureus decolonization treatments interrupted further transmission and enabled control of the outbreak.</s><s>This is reported to be highly effective in clinical patients while having a reduced effect in outpatients <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>We investigated an outbreak of skin infections among families of kindergarten children.</s><s>WGS analysis together with the results of a questionnaire showed the introduction of a PVL-SA strain into a kindergarten.</s><s>This occurred likely as a result of international travel and further transmission by direct contact.</s><s>The implementation of a S. aureus decolonization protocol for affected families led to the control of the outbreak.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig 1. Visualization of the social network among kindergarten families outside of the kindergarten.</s><s>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0189961.g001</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,48.02,78.01,527.92,322.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig 2. Allele-based neighbor-joining (NJ) tree, using cgMLST profiles of S. aureus from the suspected outbreak (10 isolates from 9 individuals) and from the NRCs strain collection (countries A-D).</s><s>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0189961.g002</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,48.02,78.01,527.92,231.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">PLOS ONE | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0189961 December 19, 2017</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p><s>We thank the kindergarten and the affected families for their close cooperation.</s><s>We also thank Dr. Mariska Janssen for her excellent cooperation with our working group.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Host-pathogen interactions between the skin and Staphylococcus aureus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Krishna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.mib.2011.11.003</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22137885</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mib.2011.11.003" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2012. 2011/12/06</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="28" to="35" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Current opinion in microbiology</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The role of the Panton-Valentine leucocidin toxin in staphylococcal disease: a systematic review and meta-analysis. The Lancet Infectious diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Shallcross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fragaszy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hayward</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S1473-3099(12)70238-4</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">23103172</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="54" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pragmatic management of Panton-Valentine leukocidin-associated staphylococcal diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Gillet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Dumitrescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Tristan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Dauwalder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Javouhey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Floret</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2011.05.003</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">21733661</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2011.05.003" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International journal of antimicrobial agents</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="457" to="464" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-07-08">2011. 2011/07/08</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Staphylococcal toxin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Panton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Valentine</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">222</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="506" to="508" />
			<date type="published" when="1932">1932</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global distribution and evolution of Panton-Valentine leukocidin-positive methicillin-susceptible Staphylococcus aureus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Rasigade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Laurent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Meugnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Vandenesch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1086/652008</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">20367458</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1086/652008" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of infectious diseases</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">201</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1589" to="1597" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981-2007. 2010. 2010/04/07</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Relationships between Staphylococcus aureus genetic background, virulence factors, agr groups (alleles), and human disease. Infection and immunity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jarraud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mougel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Thioulouse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Meugnier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Forey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1128/IAI.70.2.631-641.2002</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">11796592</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1128/IAI.70.2.631-641" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002. 2002/01/18. 2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="631" to="641" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Skin and soft tissue infections in intercontinental travellers and the import of multi-resistant Staphylococcus aureus to Europe. Clinical microbiology and infection: the official publication of the European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Nurjadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Friedrich-Janicke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schafer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Genderen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goorhuis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Perignon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cmi.2015.01.016</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">25753191</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmi.2015.01.016" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-03-11">2015. 2015/03/11</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="567" to="e568" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Outbreak of a South West Pacific clone Panton-Valentine leucocidin-positive meticillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus infection in a UK neonatal intensive care unit. The Journal of hospital infection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Nash</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kearns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Pichon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vasu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Nixon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jhin.2011.12.019</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22361299</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhin.2011.12.019" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-03-01">2012. 2012/03/01</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">80</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="298" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">High levels of antibody to panton-valentine leukocidin are not associated with resistance to Staphylococcus aureus-associated skin and soft-tissue infection. Clinical infectious diseases: an official publication of the Infectious Diseases Society of America</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hermos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Yoong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Pier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1086/656742</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">20946065</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1086/656742" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010. 2010/10/16</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1138" to="1146" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
