<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Anti-ET A R and anti-AT 1 R autoantibodies are elevated in patients with endstage cystic fibrosis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014-08-02">2 August 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Budding</surname></persName>
							<email>k.budding@umcutrecht.nl</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Translational Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Medical Center Utrecht</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Utrecht</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Van De Graaf</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Respiratory Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Medical Center Utrecht</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Utrecht</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hoefnagel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Translational Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Medical Center Utrecht</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Utrecht</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kwakkel-Van Erp</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Respiratory Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Medical Center Utrecht</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Utrecht</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Van Kessel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Center of Interstitial Lung Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">St. Antonius Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nieuwegein</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dragun</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Nephrology and Intensive Care Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Medical Faculty of Charité</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hack</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Translational Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Medical Center Utrecht</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Utrecht</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Rheumatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Medical Center Utrecht</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Utrecht</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Dermatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Medical Center Utrecht</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Utrecht</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Otten</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Translational Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Medical Center Utrecht</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Utrecht</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory of Translational Immunology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Medical Center Utrecht</orgName>
								<address>
									<postBox>F.03.821, P.O. Box 85500</postBox>
									<postCode>3508 GA</postCode>
									<settlement>Utrecht</settlement>
									<country key="NL">The Netherlands</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Anti-ET A R and anti-AT 1 R autoantibodies are elevated in patients with endstage cystic fibrosis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2014-08-02">2 August 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">07F096AED34E436CCEB3F48D7AA00AFC</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcf.2014.07.007</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 27 May 2014; received in revised form 17 July 2014; accepted 22 July 2014</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:49+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>AT 1 R</term>
					<term>Autoantibodies</term>
					<term>Cystic fibrosis</term>
					<term>ET A R</term>
					<term>Lung transplantation</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Autoantibodies against endothelin-1 type A receptor (ET A R) are present in systemic sclerosis complicated by lung fibrosis and pulmonary hypertension.</s><s>As increased serum levels and local overproduction of endothelin-1 in the airways are reported in cystic fibrosis (CF) patients, we reasoned that anti-ET A R antibodies could be prevalent in endstage CF patients prior to lung transplantation (LTx).</s><s>Also, ET A R autoantibodies are frequently associated with autoantibodies against the angiotensin II type 1 receptor (AT 1 R).</s><s>We analyzed the presence of anti-ET A R and anti-AT 1 R autoantibodies in 43 LTx patients (chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), n = 20; CF, n = 13; interstitial lung disease (ILD), n = 1).</s><s>We observed overall higher anti-ET A R and anti-AT 1 R autoantibody titers in sera taken prior to LTx in the CF patient group as compared to COPD.</s><s>No difference was found in autoantibody levels between patients with CF versus ILD.</s><s>In sera taken post-LTx we found the same difference in anti-ET A R and anti-AT 1 R autoantibody titers between patients with CF versus COPD.</s><s>No difference was found in antibody titers between sera taken prior to or 6 months after LTx.</s><s>There was no association between autoantibody levels and other relevant demographic parameters, and we found no association between autoantibody titers and the development of the bronchiolitis obliterans syndrome.</s><s>Both autoantibody titers were strongly correlated.</s><s>We hypothesize that due to prolonged exposure to bacterial infection, increased levels of AT 1 R and ET A R result in a deregulated immune response causing autoantibody formation.</s><s>Further research is expedient to elucidate the occurrence of autoantibodies against ET A R and AT 1 R and their role in disease progression.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p><s>Cystic fibrosis (CF) is an autosomal recessive disorder, which mainly occurs in the Caucasian population.</s><s>Patients are often confronted with chronic infections of Gram-negative bacteria in the lungs, in particular Pseudomonas aeruginosa, which results in the influx of both neutrophils and macrophages to the site of infection <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>In addition, CF is associated with manifestations of autoimmunity including primary sclerosing cholangitis, arthropathy and vasculitis.</s><s>Multiple autoantibodies are prevalent in CF, such as anti-bactericidal/permeabilityincreasing protein (BPI), anti-Saccharomyces cerevisiae antibodies, anti-Kα1 tubulin, anti-collagen-V, rheumatoid factors and antinuclear antibodies <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref>, but not anti-proline-glycineproline or antielastin autoantibodies <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>A delineation of autoimmunity of CF may provide biomarkers used to identify patients at risk for developing lung damage, as has been shown for anti-BPI which is associated with a poor prognosis of CF disease <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Endothelin-1 is a protein secreted primarily by both lung endothelial and epithelial cells and, in addition to its vasoconstrictor activity, it has proinflammatory capacities such as priming and stimulating neutrophils, activating mast cells, and macrophage stimulation that results in proinflammatory cytokine production.</s><s>Increased serum levels and local overproduction of endothelin-1 in the airways are reported in CF patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</s><s>In addition, the overexpression of endothelin-1 is associated with the bronchiolitis obliterans syndrome and bacterial infection in lung transplant recipients <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>.</s><s>Endothelin-1 acts via binding to its type A or type B receptor and autoantibodies against endothelin-1 type A receptor (ET A R) have already been identified in systemic sclerosis commonly complicated by lung fibrosis and pulmonary hypertension.</s><s>ET A R autoantibodies are frequently associated with autoantibodies against the angiotensin II type 1 receptor (AT 1 R) <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</s><s>We reasoned that, beside increased levels of endothelin-1, anti-ET A R and/or AT 1 R autoantibodies could be prevalent in patients with endstage CF.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Patients &amp; methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Patients</head><p><s>We included 43 patients in this pilot study that underwent LTx between January 2004 and May 2011 at our center.</s><s>This study was approved by the medical ethics committee and from all patients informed consent was obtained.</s><s>Several hours prior to and monthly after LTx blood was obtained from each patient, processed, and stored as serum aliquots at − 80 °C until analysis.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Determination of anti-ET A R and anti-AT 1 R concentrations in serum</head><p><s>A solid phase sandwich ELISA kit (CellTrend GmbH, Luckenwalde, Germany) was used to measure both anti-ET A R and anti-AT 1 R antibody levels in serum according to protocol <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s><s>The inter-and intra-assay CVs are 8.3% and 6.3% for the ET A R-and 11.5% and 6.9% for the AT 1 R-ELISA kit.</s><s>The lower limit of detection was 1 U/ml.</s><s>Serum samples were thawed and centrifuged for 10 min at 1800 rpm prior to analysis.</s><s>All samples were subjected to identical freeze-thaw cycles and analyzed in the same experiment.</s><s>The OD450 measurement was conducted using a Multiskan EX Microplate Photometer (ThermoScientific, Rockford, IL).</s><s>Data analysis was performed using AT 1 R/ET A R analysis software provided by the manufacturer.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Patient demographics</head><p><s>The analyzed patient cohort consisted of 43 LTx patients of which 20 suffered from chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), 13 from CF, and 10 from interstitial lung disease (ILD), including idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (n = 3), lymphangioleiomyomatosis (n = 2), non-specific interstitial pneumonia (n = 1), pulmonary Langerhans cell histiocytosis (n = 2), progressive systemic sclerosis (n = 1) and sarcoidosis (n = 1).</s><s>Nineteen of these patients developed the bronchiolitis obliterans syndrome (BOS), among which 6 had CF as a primary disease, during follow-up, defined according to ISHLT criteria <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s>After transplantation immunosuppression consisted of basiliximab, tacrolimus, mycofenolate and prednisolone.</s><s>Treatment with valganciclovir was initiated when a patient was considered to be at risk for CMV.</s><s>Further demographic parameters are summarized in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>.</s><s>Both significant differences, mean age of inclusion and high risk for CMV reactivation, can be explained by the younger age of CF patients at the time of transplantation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Anti-ET A R and AT 1 R autoantibody titers are elevated in CF patients</head><p><s>We observed overall higher anti-ET A R and anti-AT 1 R autoantibody titers pre-LTx in CF patients as compared to COPD (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1A and C</ref>).</s><s>No significant difference was found in autoantibody levels between patients with CF versus ILD.</s><s>In post-LTx sera we found the same difference in anti-ET A R and anti-AT 1 R autoantibody titers between patients with CF versus COPD (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1B and D</ref>).</s><s>Unfortunately, no post-LTx serum samples were available from three COPDs, one ILD, and on CF patient, and could thus not be analyzed.</s><s>No significant difference was found in antibody titers between sera taken prior to or post-LTx.</s><s>There was no association between autoantibody levels and other relevant demographic parameters: age, gender, type of graft, BOS incidence, ischemic time, lung function, Pseudomonas infection, CFTR mutation, or CF related diabetes mellitus.</s><s>Anti-ET A R and anti-AT 1 R autoantibody titers were strongly correlated (p b 0.0001, r = 0.756, data not shown).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p><s>In this pilot experiment we show that autoantibodies against both ET A R and AT 1 R are present in endstage lung diseases, particularly CF.</s><s>Like AT 1 R, ET A R is a G-protein coupled receptor to which both an endogenous ligand, endothelin-1, and autoantibodies may simultaneously bind resulting in a more prolonged and detrimental biologic response.</s></p><p><s>The levels of endothelin-1 are elevated in CF patients' sputum, compared to healthy controls and COPD patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>, and endothelin-1 is detectable in both the peripheral blood and bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) fluid of COPD patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s><s>In our study we did not have an access to BAL fluid, since surveillance bronchoscopy was not performed, which would allow simultaneous analysis of endothelin-1 and autoantibody levels, and their correlation with disease progression.</s></p><p><s>Besides being elevated in the sputum of CF patients, endothelin-1 is also a biomarker for the detection of BOS in serum <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s><s>The authors postulate that high endothelin-1 levels arise due to an inflammatory response after lung tissue damage.</s><s>Autoantibodies against ET A R and AT 1 R are associated with Table <ref type="table">1</ref> Clinical and demographic profile of lung transplant patients.</s><s>Patients are divided in three diagnostic clusters, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), cystic fibrosis (CF), and interstitial lung disease (ILD).</s><s>Categorical data (gender, risk for CMV/EBV, BOS) were analyzed by the Fisher's exact test, continuous variables (mean age, follow up, and the onset of BOS) by the ANOVA test, and influence of the type of graft (bilateral or single) by the Pearson's χ 2 test (SPSS version 20, IBM Corp., Armon, NY).</s><s>Significant intergroup variants are displayed in italics.</s><s>Eleven out of the 13 CF patients were colonized with P. aeruginosa.</s><s>One patient was colonized with S. aureus and one patient was colonized with Stenotrophomonas maltophilia.</s><s>Before transplantation infections were treated with antibiotics according to the sputum cultures.</s><s>Eleven out of 13 patients were analyzed for CFTR mutation status.</s><s>Nine patients were genotyped with ΔF508, one with a homozygous 1998+5GT, and one with a G542x/R347P mutation.</s><s>Two CF patients were diagnosed by sweat test.</s><s>Five patients were diagnosed with cystic fibrosis related diabetes before transplantation.</s><s>Six patients were on steroids because of a diagnosed allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis or to reduce inflammation.</s><s>All patients were given best clinical care, had a BMI higher than 18.5, and had a lung function b 35% (range 13%-34%) prior to transplantation.</s><s>systemic sclerosis with fibrotic complications <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</s><s>In this study we could not find a correlation between autoantibody titers and development of BOS, which is hallmarked by fibrotic development in the lungs <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s>Also, both anti-ET A R and anti-AT 1 R autoantibodies have been identified in episodes of cellular and antibody-mediated rejection after heart transplantation, and anti-AT 1 R autoantibodies are associated with antibody mediated rejection after kidney transplantation <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>All</head><p><s>However in our study we were unable to distinguish cellular and antibody mediated rejection due to the absence of lung biopsy material.</s><s>We show for the first time that autoantibodies against both ET A R and AT 1 R are elevated in endstage CF patients.</s><s>Although both receptors are involved in a common vasocontrictive pathway, their natural ligands differ in functional capacities.</s><s>AT 1 R autoantibodies are agonistic <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, but we can only speculate on the role of both ET A R and AT 1 R autoantibodies and their part in CF pathology.</s><s>We hypothesize that due to prolonged exposure to bacterial infection, increased levels of AT 1 R and ET A R result in a deregulated immune response causing autoantibody formation.</s><s>The development of these autoantibodies would then be a consequence of disease progression.</s><s>Anti-ET A R and anti-AT 1 R autoantibodies could thus have an additive value in disease prognosis for young CF patients, which is desired, since besides genetic background, more factors can contribute to their respective clinical outcome <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s>However, we only analyzed endstage lung disease patients, indicating that further research is expedient in a follow-up cohort of different lung diseases, to elucidate the occurrence of autoantibodies against ET A R and AT 1 R and their role in disease progression.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig.1.</s><s>ET A R and AT 1 R autoantibody titers pre-and post-lung transplantation.</s><s>Pre-(A and C) and post-transplantation (B and D) antibody levels against ET A R (A and B) and AT 1 R (C and D) are displayed in U/ml.</s><s>Cut-off levels to define positivity were set according to previously described healthy control values (see Patients and methods).</s><s>Each dot represents the result from 1 serum sample.</s><s>No significant differences between CF and ILD were found between pre-and post-LTx anti-ET A R, p = 0.31 and p = 0.38, and pre-and post-LTx anti-AT 1 R autoantibodies, p = 0.28 and p = 0.58 respectively.</s><s>A Mann-Whitney rank-sum test was used for statistical analysis (GraphPad Prism version 5.03, GraphPad Software Inc., San Diego, CA).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prediction of mortality in patients with cystic fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kerem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Reisman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Corey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Canny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Levison</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">326</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1187" to="1191" />
			<date type="published" when="1992-04-30">Apr 30 1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pretransplant antibodies to Kα1 tubulin and collagen-V in lung transplantation: clinical correlations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Tiriveedhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Gautam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sarma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Askar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Budev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Aloush</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Heart Lung Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="807" to="814" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-08">Aug 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prevalence and clinical significance of autoantibodies in adults with cystic fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Lachenal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nkana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nove-Josserand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Fabien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Durieu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Respir J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1079" to="1085" />
			<date type="published" when="2009-11">Nov 2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anti-proline-glycineproline or antielastin autoantibodies are not evident in chronic inflammatory lung disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Low</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>O'neill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mcelvaney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">181</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-01-01">Jan 1 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Autoantibody response to BPI predict disease severity and outcome in cystic fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Carlsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Eriksson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Pressler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kornfalt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mared</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cyst Fibros</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="228" to="233" />
			<date type="published" when="2007-05">May 2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Plasma immunoreactive endothelin levels in children with cystic fibrosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Siahanidou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Nicolaidou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Doudounakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Georgouli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Papadimitriou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Karpathios</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Paediatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="915" to="920" />
			<date type="published" when="2000-08">Aug 2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increased endothelin-1 associated with bacterial infection in lung transplant recipients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Charpin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lebrun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Aubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Grenet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Israel-Biet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transplantation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1840" to="1847" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-06-27">Jun 27 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Distribution of endothelin-1 in transplanted human lungs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jeppsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Tazelaar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Mcgregor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transplantation Sep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="806" to="809" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Involvement of functional autoantibodies against vascular receptors in systemic sclerosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Riemekasten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Philippe</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nather</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Slowinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Muller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Heidecke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Rheum Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">70</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="530" to="536" />
			<date type="published" when="2011-03">Mar 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A working formulation for the standardization of nomenclature and for clinical staging of chronic dysfunction in lung allografts. International Society for Heart and Lung Transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cooper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Billingham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Egan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Hertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Higenbottam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lynch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Heart Lung Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="713" to="716" />
			<date type="published" when="1993-10">Sep-Oct 1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sputum endothelin-1 is increased in cystic fibrosis and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Chalmers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Macleod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sriram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Thomson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mcsharry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Stack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Respir J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1288" to="1292" />
			<date type="published" when="1999-06">Jun 1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sputum and plasma endothelin-1 levels in exacerbations of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Roland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bhowmik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sapsford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Seemungal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Jeffries</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Warner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thorax</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-01">Jan 2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Endothelin-1 is a useful biomarker for early detection of bronchiolitis obliterans in lung transplant recipients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Salama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Jaksch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Andrukhova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Taghavi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Klepetko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Aharinejad</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">140</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1422" to="1427" />
			<date type="published" when="2010-12">Dec 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-HLA antibodies targeting vascular receptors enhance alloimmune response and microvasculopathy after heart transplantation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hiemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Wellnhofer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Schoenemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Heidecke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Lachmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transplantation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">94</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="919" to="924" />
			<date type="published" when="2012-11-15">Nov 15 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Non-HLA antibodies in solid organ transplantation: recent concepts and clinical relevance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dragun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Catar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Philippe</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Organ Transplant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="430" to="435" />
			<date type="published" when="2013-08">Aug 2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
