<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">131AD1583178DE566D9DC6AA598ACDB8</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.nmd.2016.07.008</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:50+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>When in January 2015 Anna Fidzianska, Professor of Neurology at Warsaw University, died unexpectedly the myopathological and myological community lost a highly experienced and dedicated member whose pair of keen eyes and inquisitive mind had observed, foremost by electron microscopy, and described many new findings and conditions.</s><s>Embedded, raised and grown in the myology-devoted Department of Neurology at Warsaw Medical School, first under the mentorship and then the directorship of Professor Irena Hausmanowa-Petrusewicz, since the inception of her career to her official retirement when she switched from Warsaw University to the Polish Academy of Medical Sciences until her death, Anna Fidzianska had chosen early on the then fledgling discipline of electron microscopy as her path to academic reputation, and this she gained as an expert in the Warsaw Myology team as well as in the international myology community.</s></p><p><s>Her interests and achievements were broad: she studied the various levels between the spinal cord, in spinal muscular atrophy, the peripheral nerves, the motor endplates and the skeletal muscle itself, not only the muscle fibres, but capillaries and interstitial cells, likewise, especially during development, neurogenic atrophy, apoptosis, autophagy, and protein aggregation.</s><s>Her major target was the human tissue obtained by biopsy, but she did not shun post mortem tissues.</s><s>She was one of the first (1973) to suspect viral infection in polymyositis based on having observed peculiar virus-like structures, the viral nature of which, however, could not be further demonstrated.</s><s>She discovered Cap Disease and contributed to its genetic elucidation, she described Mallory body-like myopathy, earlier called and entered in OMIM as the Eichsfeld type of muscular dystrophy, simply because she took a second, more thorough look than the earlier author, and she, thereby, paved the way for the molecular identification of selenoproteinopathy.</s><s>The ultrastructure of the myonucleus was another one of her objects of investigation where she emphasized its abnormalities in laminopathies and in apoptosis.</s><s>She covered the entire myopathological spectrum by electron microscopy; she wrote on inflammatory, dystrophic, congenital, and metabolic myopathies.</s><s>Later she expanded her studies to include cardiomyocytes, also becoming an expert in normal and pathological cardiac ultrastructure.</s><s>She authored and co-authored more than 180 papers and book chapters related to myopathology, the last one written by herself (2015) appearing posthumously.</s><s>She had always been productive and quick to publish what she had uncovered.</s></p><p><s>Among the congenital myopathies, a particular field of study for her as the myopathologist, she described, proposed as such and left as her legacy, four new conditions: lipid raft disease, congenital myopathy with tubular aggregates and IBM-type inclusions, ring fibre myopathy, and congenital myopathy with desmin and dystrophin plaques, the molecular clarification and nosological significance of which remain to be demonstrated by her heirs in myopathology.</s></p><p><s>Born and raised in Piotrkow, Poland, her father Adam and her mother Leona were both medical doctors.</s><s>She earned her MD degree from the Medical Academy in Warsaw in 1957.</s><s>After graduation she started to work at the Department of Neurology of the Medical University of Warsaw going through all the steps of an academic career and became an emerita in 2003.</s></p><p><s>In 1989, she was appointed at the newly established Neuromuscular Unit of the Polish Academy of Sciences and continued to work there until her death.</s></p><p><s>In 1970-71 she spent 12 months at the Istituto Patologia Generale in Padua working on muscle regeneration (with Professor Massimo Aloisi).</s><s>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.nmd.2016.07.008</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="1,65.67,184.79,189.12,281.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Neuromuscular Disorders 26 (2016) 634-635 www.elsevier.com/locate/nmd</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ScienceDirect</head><p><s>On several <ref type="bibr">occasions, i.e. 1980-1981</ref> for 12 months in Göttingen and as visiting professor for 12 months in 1988 and for another 3 months in Mainz, she did extensive electron microscopic studies on varying subjects which resulted in numerous papers.</s></p><p><s>She was a dedicated teacher, and her myopathological contributions, presented with verve and clarity, always beautifully illustrated, were highly appreciated by students and conference attendees.</s><s>Although a warm-hearted lady, in private professional dialogues she could be a fierce and persistent discussant.</s></p><p><s>She received several honours from the Medical University of Warsaw, the Ministry of Health, and the Polish Neurological Society.</s><s>She was also awarded the Golden Cross of Merit in 1983 by the President of the Republic of Poland.</s></p><p><s>She is survived by her son Adam, her daughter-in-law Ewa and two grandchildren whilst her husband of many years had died several years earlier.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Anna Kaminska</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
