<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Efficacy and safety of levosimendan in Chinese elderly patients with Takotsubo syndrome</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yi</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hainan Branch of Chinese People&apos;s Liberation Army General Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>572013</postCode>
									<settlement>Sanya</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Chaofei</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hainan Branch of Chinese People&apos;s Liberation Army General Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>572013</postCode>
									<settlement>Sanya</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Xia</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese People&apos;s Liberation Army General Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100853</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Chinese People&apos;s Liberation Army General Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Fuxing Road 28</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Haidian District</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100853</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Efficacy and safety of levosimendan in Chinese elderly patients with Takotsubo syndrome</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">ECBFC423C661F41285ED9A575EAFC1F4</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.21037/atm.2018.10.15</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted Jun 01, 2018. Accepted for publication Sep 21, 2018.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:50+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Chinese elderly</term>
					<term>levosimendan</term>
					<term>Takotsubo syndrome</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Background: Takotsubo syndrome has a low global incidence, but it is observed more and more in clinical practice.</s><s>Only case reports and series have been published, while prospective studies are still necessary.</s><s>This study aimed to explore the efficacy and safety of levosimendan in elderly with Takotsubo syndrome.</s><s>Methods: This study followed a prospective, randomized and double-blinded design.</s><s>All 200 consecutive patients (&gt;65 years) with Takotsubo syndrome were randomly assigned into a levosimendan group (n=100) and a control group (n=100).</s><s>The control group underwent regular treatment, and the levosimendan group was additionally administrated with levosimendan.</s></p><p><s>Results: Age of all patients was 71 [66-85] years, and there were 138 females (69%).</s><s>Baseline characteristics between the two groups had no significant difference before treatment (P&gt;0.05 for all).</s><s>In the levosimendan group on the 30 and 180 days after treatment, left ventricular ejection fraction was significantly higher, and New York Heart Association class and N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide levels were significantly lower, than those in the control group (P&lt;0.05 for all).</s><s>Systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, heart rate and serum creatinine levels had no significant difference between the two groups (P&gt;0.05 for all).</s></p><p><s>Conclusions: Levosimendan showed reliable efficacy and safety in Chinese elderly patients with Takotsubo syndrome, supporting the idea that levosimendan has the potential to be an essential drug applied for patients with Takotsubo syndrome.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Although Takotsubo syndrome has a low global incidence, it is observed more and more in current clinical practice <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2)</ref>.</s><s>Levosimendan is a new type of Ca 2+ sensitizer that can improve cardiac function without severely affecting stable hemodynamics and renal function <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4)</ref>.</s><s>However, to date there has hardly been any prospective study to observe the application of levosimendan in patients with Takotsubo syndrome, and there are only controversial results based on the clinical experience <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</s><s>As advised by the current position statement from the Heart Failure Association of European Society of Cardiology, the published literature on the Takotsubo syndrome only consists of case reports and series, while prospective studies to probe the efficacy and safety of levosimendan in patients with Takotsubo syndrome are still necessary <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>China, the largest developing country in the world, has become an aging society, and there are increased morbidity and mortality rates in the elderly <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6)</ref>.</s><s>Clinical data on the levosimendan application in Chinese elderly patients with Takotsubo syndrome remain very rare, and it is essential to analyze the efficacy and safety of levosimendan in these patients.</s><s>The current study aimed to explore the efficacy and safety of levosimendan in patients with Takotsubo syndrome.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study participants</head><p><s>The current study followed a prospective, randomized and double-blinded design  <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study procedures</head><p><s>Patients were randomly assigned into a levosimendan group (n=100) and a control group (n=100) using random numbers in a randomized block design.</s><s>Random numbers were generated by Statistic Package for Social Science (SPSS) version 17.0 software (SPSS Inc., Chicago, USA).</s></p><p><s>After diagnosed with Takotsubo syndrome and assigned into the two groups, the control group underwent regular treatment, and the levosimendan group was administrated with levosimendan (Qilu Pharmaceutical, Jinan, China; Specifications: 5 mL, 12.5 mg) at continuously intravenous infusion of 0.1 μg/kg/min without loading dose for 24 hours in addition to regular treatment (1,10 on the Hitachi 7600 autoanalyzer (Hitachi, Tokyo, Japan).</s><s>All patients were followed up on the 30 and 180 days after treatment <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11)</ref>.</s><s>All patients were not re-hospitalized after discharge from hospital.</s><s>They received follow-up and reexamination in the Outpatient Department in our hospital.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical analyses</head><p><s>Continuous variables with normal distribution were reported using mean and standard deviation, and the difference between the two groups was compared using Student's t-test.</s><s>Continuous variables with abnormal distribution were reported using median and interquartile range, and the difference between the two groups was compared using Mann-Whitney U test.</s><s>Categorical variables were reported with number and percentage, and the difference between the two groups was compared with Chi-square test.</s><s>All analyses were carried out by SPSS version 17.0 software (SPSS Inc., Chicago, USA), and P value &lt;0.05 was accepted as statistically significant.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Age of all patients was 71 [66-85] years, and there were 138 females (69%).</s><s>Baseline characteristics between the two groups had no significant difference before treatment (P&gt;0.05 for all; Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1</ref>).</s><s>Comparison between the two groups on the 30 and 180 days after treatment is shown in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">2</ref>.</s><s>In the levosimendan group, LVEF was significantly higher, and New York Heart Association (NYHA) class and serum NT-proBNP levels were significantly lower, than those in the control group (P&lt;0.05 for all).</s><s>Systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, heart rate and serum creatinine levels had no significant difference between the two groups (P&gt;0.05 for all).</s><s>Other kinds of side effects were not found in the two groups.</s><s>Compared with the control group, mortality was significantly lower in the levosimendan group (P&lt;0.05).</s><s>All patients died of circulatory failure.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Takotsubo syndrome has a low global incidence <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</s><s>The treatment of Takotsubo syndrome in elderly patients should be taken into special consideration <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</s><s>As advised by the current position statement from the Heart Failure Association of European Society of Cardiology, inotropes, including dobutamine and dopamine, should be forbidden in patients with Takotsubo syndrome, as further activation of catecholamine receptors or other molecular pathways might aggravate their condition <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13)</ref>.</s><s>Levosimendan is one of the limited options that is left, but there have been rare case reports and series to observe the application of levosimendan in patients with Takotsubo syndrome, and prospective studies to probe the efficacy and safety of levosimendan are still necessary, especially in Chinese elderly patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</s><s>The current study found that levosimendan improved cardiac function and reduced mortality in elderly patients, which suggests that levosimendan is effective in treating Takotsubo syndrome in Chinese elderly patients.</s><s>Meanwhile, these elderly patients in the current study exhibited no distinction of blood pressure, heart rate and renal function with the treatment of levosimendan or not, which suggests that levosimendan is safe in treating Takotsubo syndrome in Chinese elderly patients.</s><s>Therefore, levosimendan is very appropriate for Chinese elderly patients with Takotsubo syndrome.</s></p><p><s>Levosimendan is a new type of Ca 2+ sensitizer that can improve cardiac function without severely affecting stable hemodynamics and renal function <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4)</ref>.</s><s>Levosimendan has provided beneficial cardioprotective and hemodynamic effects in cardiac surgery field and patients with septic shock <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15)</ref>.</s><s>However, there has hardly been any prospective studies analyzing the application of levosimendan in patients with Takotsubo syndrome.</s><s>The current study proved favorable efficacy and safety of levosimendan in Chinese elderly patients with Takotsubo syndrome.</s></p><p><s>It is not surprising that levosimendan has beneficial effects on the elderly patients with cardiac troponin C insensitive to Ca 2+ .</s><s>Levosimendan can be combined with cardiac troponin C for the greater sensitivity to Ca 2+ , leading to myocardial contraction even at the same or lower Ca 2+ concentration <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p><s>The current study demonstrated that levosimendan showed reliable efficacy and safety in Chinese elderly patients with Takotsubo syndrome, supporting the idea that levosimendan has the potential to be an essential drug applied for patients with Takotsubo syndrome.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>We are grateful to all study participants for their participation in the study.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Footnote</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflicts of Interest:</head><p><s>The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Baseline characteristics of elderly patients with Takotsubo syndrome in the levosimendan and control group ARB, angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitor/angiotension receptor blocker; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; NT-proBNP, N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide; NYHA, New York Heart Association; LVEF, left ventricular ejection fraction; SBP, systolic blood pressure.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Characteristics</cell><cell>Levosimendan group (n=100)</cell><cell>Control group (n=100)</cell><cell>P</cell></row><row><cell>Age (year)</cell><cell>72 [68-76]</cell><cell>71 [68-77]</cell><cell>0.498</cell></row><row><cell>Females, n (%)</cell><cell>71 (71.0)</cell><cell>67 (67.0)</cell><cell>0.541</cell></row><row><cell>Hypertension, n (%)</cell><cell>21 (21.0)</cell><cell>17 (17.0)</cell><cell>0.471</cell></row><row><cell>Diabetes mellitus, n (%)</cell><cell>11 (11.0)</cell><cell>13 (13.0)</cell><cell>0.663</cell></row><row><cell>SBP (mmHg)</cell><cell>136 [120-145]</cell><cell>129 [121-140]</cell><cell>0.389</cell></row><row><cell>DBP (mmHg)</cell><cell>70 [64-72]</cell><cell>68 [64-74]</cell><cell>0.573</cell></row><row><cell>Heart rate (time/minute)</cell><cell>93 [89-103]</cell><cell>97 [90-102]</cell><cell>0.232</cell></row><row><cell>NYHA class, n [%]</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1.000</cell></row><row><cell>IV</cell><cell>100 [100]</cell><cell>100 [100]</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>LVEF [%]</cell><cell>29 [27-31]</cell><cell>29 [25-32]</cell><cell>0.473</cell></row><row><cell>NT-proBNP (pg/mL)</cell><cell>2,040.8 (1,543.2-3,856.1)</cell><cell>2,358.5 (1,760.8-3,539.8)</cell><cell>0.398</cell></row><row><cell>Serum creatinine (μmol/L)</cell><cell>79.0 (71.0-98.5)</cell><cell>85.6 (75.9-92.5)</cell><cell>0.353</cell></row><row><cell>ACEI/ARB, n (%)</cell><cell>29 (29.0)</cell><cell>23 (23.0)</cell><cell>0.333</cell></row><row><cell>Beta-blockers, n (%)</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1.000</cell></row><row><cell>Diuretics, n (%)</cell><cell>83 (83.0)</cell><cell>87 (87.0)</cell><cell>0.428</cell></row><row><cell>ACEI/</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Efficacy and safety of elderly patients with Takotsubo syndrome in the levosimendan and control group</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Characteristics</cell><cell>Levosimendan group (n=100)</cell><cell>Control group (n=100)</cell><cell>P</cell></row><row><cell>30 days</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>NYHA class, n (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.041</cell></row><row><cell>II</cell><cell>68 (68.7)</cell><cell>48 (52.2)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>III</cell><cell>29 (29.3)</cell><cell>38 (41.3)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>IV</cell><cell>2 (2.0)</cell><cell>6 (6.5)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>LVEF [%]</cell><cell>47 [44-55]</cell><cell>47 [41-51]</cell><cell>0.035</cell></row><row><cell>NT-proBNP (pg/mL)</cell><cell>759.3 (545.5-1,116.9)</cell><cell>897.6 (660.8-1,118.2)</cell><cell>0.044</cell></row><row><cell>Serum creatinine (μmol/L)</cell><cell>83.6 (73.6-103.0)</cell><cell>88.3 (71.1-99.0)</cell><cell>0.596</cell></row><row><cell>SBP (mmHg)</cell><cell>124 [121-132]</cell><cell>125 [114-136]</cell><cell>0.852</cell></row><row><cell>DBP (mmHg)</cell><cell>61 [58-65]</cell><cell>61 [59-64]</cell><cell>0.848</cell></row><row><cell>Heart rate (time/minute)</cell><cell>79 [75-84]</cell><cell>77 [74-81]</cell><cell>0.135</cell></row><row><cell>Mortality, n (%)</cell><cell>1 (1.0)</cell><cell>8 (8.0)</cell><cell>0.041</cell></row><row><cell>180 days</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>NYHA class, n (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.042</cell></row><row><cell>I</cell><cell>68 (68.7)</cell><cell>50 (54.3)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>II</cell><cell>31 (31.3)</cell><cell>42 (45.7)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>LVEF [%]</cell><cell>49 [47-57]</cell><cell>49 [47-53]</cell><cell>0.040</cell></row><row><cell>NT-proBNP (pg/mL)</cell><cell>476.7 (245.5-664.6)</cell><cell>542.5 (360.8-748.7)</cell><cell>0.032</cell></row><row><cell>Serum creatinine (μmol/L)</cell><cell>83.0 (73.7-101.0)</cell><cell>86.3 (69.1-97.7)</cell><cell>0.669</cell></row><row><cell>SBP (mmHg)</cell><cell>119 [117-130]</cell><cell>121 [110-132]</cell><cell>0.871</cell></row><row><cell>DBP (mmHg)</cell><cell>59 [55-64]</cell><cell>62 [56-64]</cell><cell>0.563</cell></row><row><cell>Heart rate (time/minute)</cell><cell>72 [68-77]</cell><cell>71 [67-77]</cell><cell>0.249</cell></row><row><cell>Mortality, n (%)</cell><cell>1 (1.0)</cell><cell>8 (8.0)</cell><cell>0.041</cell></row></table><note><p><s>DBP, diastolic blood pressure; NT-proBNP, N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide; NYHA, New York Heart Association; LVEF, left ventricular ejection fraction; SBP, systolic blood pressure.</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">© Annals of Translational Medicine. All rights reserved.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Ethical Statement: The study protocol has been approved by Ethics Committee of Chinese People's Liberation Army General Hospital (Beijing, China; ID: 301hn11201601) and it conforms to the Helsinki Declaration.</s><s>Each participant provided written informed consent to be included in the study.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Current state of knowledge on Takotsubo syndrome: a position statement from the task force on Takotsubo syndrome of the Heart Failure Association of the European Society of Cardiology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Lyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Bossone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Heart Fail</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The emerging role of small non-coding RNAs in the failing heart: big hopes for small molecules</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cardiovasc Drugs Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">149</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Levosimendan: current data, clinical use and future development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Nieminen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fruhwald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Heunks</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Heart Lung Vessel</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="245" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Perioperative use of levosimendan: best practice in operative settings</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Toller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Algotsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Guarracino</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="361" to="366" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Analysis of determinants of population longevity at county level in China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Popul Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">146</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Aging and heart failure: changing demographics and implications for therapy in the elderly</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Jugdutt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Heart Fail Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="401" to="405" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Apical ballooning syndrome (Tako-Tsubo or stress cardiomyopathy): a mimic of acute myocardial infarction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Prasad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rihal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="408" to="417" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ESC Guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of acute and chronic heart failure: The Task Force for the diagnosis and treatment of acute and chronic heart failure of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC). Developed with the special contribution of the Heart Failure Association (HFA) of the ESC</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ponikowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Voors</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Anker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2129" to="2200" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Australian Medicines Handbook</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Safety and feasibility of levosimendan administration in takotsubo cardiomyopathy: a case series</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Santoro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ieva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ferraretti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cardiovasc Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="e133" to="137" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficacy and safety of intravenous levosimendan compared with dobutamine in severe low output heart failure (the LIDO study): a randomised double-blind trial</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Follath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cleland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Just</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">360</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="196" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Use of vasopressors in Takotsubo cardiomyopathy: a cautionary tale</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Redmond</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Knapp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Salim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shanbhag</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Jaumdally</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Anaesth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="487" to="488" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A mouse model reveals an important role for catecholamine-induced lipotoxicity in the pathogenesis of stress-induced cardiomyopathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Redfors</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Stahlman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Heart Fail</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rationale and design of the multicentre randomized trial investigating the efficacy and safety of pulsed infusions of levosimendan in outpatients with advanced heart failure (LevoRep study)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Altenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Parissis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Ulmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Poelzl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Heart Fail</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="192" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Levosimendan in perioperative and critical care patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Salmenpera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Eriksson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Anaesthesiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="496" to="501" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Levosimendan improves clinical outcomes of refractory heart failure in elderly Chinese patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Med Sci Monit</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2439" to="2445" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Levosimendan: from basic science to clinical practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Parissis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rafouli-Stergiou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Paraskevaidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Heart Fail Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="275" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
