<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Key Amino Acids in the Bacterial (6-4) Photolyase PhrB from Agrobacterium fabrum</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-10-21">October 21, 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Dominik</forename><surname>Graf</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Botanical Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kaiserstr. 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-76131</postCode>
									<settlement>Karlsruhe</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Janine</forename><surname>Wesslowski</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Botanical Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kaiserstr. 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-76131</postCode>
									<settlement>Karlsruhe</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Hongju</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Botanical Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kaiserstr. 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-76131</postCode>
									<settlement>Karlsruhe</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Patrick</forename><surname>Scheerer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Medical Physics and Biophysics (CC2)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Charité-University Medicine Berlin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">AG Protein X-ray Crystallography and Signal Transduction</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Norbert</forename><surname>Krauß</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">School of Biological and Chemical Sciences</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Queen Mary University of London</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>E1 4NS</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Inga</forename><surname>Oberpichler</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Botanical Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kaiserstr. 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-76131</postCode>
									<settlement>Karlsruhe</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Fan</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<email>fanzhangscu@hotmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Botanical Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kaiserstr. 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-76131</postCode>
									<settlement>Karlsruhe</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tilman</forename><surname>Lamparter</surname></persName>
							<email>tilman.lamparter@kit.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Botanical Institute</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Kaiserstr. 2</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-76131</postCode>
									<settlement>Karlsruhe</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Cape Town</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">SOUTH AFRICA</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Key Amino Acids in the Bacterial (6-4) Photolyase PhrB from Agrobacterium fabrum</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-10-21">October 21, 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">73DA5BE574E3155F885C8B34CD1C7E5C</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0140955</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: April 13, 2015 Accepted: October 3, 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:23+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Photolyases can repair pyrimidine dimers on the DNA that are formed during UV irradiation.</s><s>PhrB from Agrobacterium fabrum represents a new group of prokaryotic (6-4) photolyases which contain an iron-sulfur cluster and a DMRL chromophore.</s><s>We performed site-directed mutagenesis in order to assess the role of particular amino acid residues in photorepair and photoreduction, during which the FAD chromophore converts from the oxidized to the enzymatically active, reduced form.</s><s>Our study showed that Trp342 and Trp390 serve as electron transmitters.</s><s>In the H366A mutant repair activity was lost, which points to a significant role of His366 in the protonation of the lesion, as discussed for the homolog in eukaryotic (6-4) photolyases.</s><s>Mutants on cysteines that coordinate the Fe-S cluster of PhrB were either insoluble or not expressed.</s><s>The same result was found for proteins with a truncated C-terminus, in which one of the Fe-S binding cysteines was mutated and for expression in minimal medium with limited Fe concentrations.</s><s>We therefore assume that the Fe-S cluster is required for protein stability.</s><s>We further mutated conserved tyrosines that are located between the DNA lesion and the Fe-S cluster.</s><s>Mutagenesis results showed that Tyr424 was essential for lesion binding and repair, and Tyr430 was required for efficient repair.</s><s>The results point to an important function of highly conserved tyrosines in prokaryotic (6-4) photolyases.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Photolyases are flavoproteins that repair UV-damaged DNA in a light-dependent fashion, cryptochromes are related proteins without repair activity that serve as photoreceptors or compounds of the inner clock.</s><s>The family of photolyases and cryptochromes may be divided into seven major phylogenetic groups: CPD photolyases class I, II and III, Cry-DASH proteins, eukaryotic  photolyases and animal cryptochromes, plant cryptochromes and prokaryotic FeS-BCP (Fe-S bacterial cryptochromes and photolyases) proteins <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">2]</ref>.</s><s>The terms CPD-and  photolyases refer to the kind of lesions that are repaired by these proteins, which are cyclo pyrimidine dimers and (6-4) photoproducts, respectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[3]</ref>.</s><s>Both kinds of repair are triggered by a rapid electron transfer from the excited flavin adenine dinucleotide (FAD) chromophore to the DNA lesion.</s><s>A second light reaction, termed photoreduction, results in the transition of oxidized or semi-reduced FAD to fully reduced FAD in photolyases or from oxidized to semi reduced FAD in plant cryptochromes.</s><s>During photoreduction, electrons are transmitted from the surface via Trp or Tyr residues of the protein to the FAD chromophore <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[4]</ref>.</s><s>The classical photoreduction pathways in which electrons travel via three conserved Trp residues is realized in most photolyases and in cryptochromes <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>.</s><s>Additional pathways have been described in class I and class III CPD photolyases <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">7]</ref>.</s><s>In class II CPD photolyases, where the Trp residues of the classical pathway are missing, another Trp triad is involved in photoreduction <ref type="bibr">[8]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The group of FeS-BCP proteins is most distantly related to the other members of the cryptochrome / photolyase family.</s><s>Two members of this group, CryB from Rhodobacter sphaeroides and PhrB from Agrobacterium fabrum (formerly A. tumefaciens C58), have been studied and their crystal structures have been determined <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">10]</ref>.</s><s>FeS-BCP proteins are bacterial  photolyases, although they are phylogenetically not related to eukaryotic  photolyases.</s><s>The antenna chromophore of PhrB and CryB is 6,7-dimethyl-8-ribityl-lumazine (DMRL), the last intermediate of the flavin biosynthesis pathway before the formation of riboflavin <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[12]</ref>.</s><s>Other members of the photolyase or Cry-DASH group of proteins have methenyltetrahydrofolate, 8-hydroxy-5-deazariboflavin or flavin mononucleotide as antenna chromophore <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[13]</ref>.</s><s>Another specific feature of FeS-BCP members is their iron-sulfur (Fe-S) cluster that is missing in all other photolyases or cryptochromes.</s><s>PriL, the large subunit of eukaryotic and archaeal primases, and photolyases share a common protein fold.</s><s>PriL also contains an Fe-S cluster, which is located within the common fold at the same position as the Fe-S cluster of FeS-BCP proteins <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[10]</ref>.</s><s>Indeed, phylogenetic studies place PhrB next to PriL, indicating an early branchpoint of FeS-BCP and other cryptochrome / photolyase family members <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[10]</ref>.</s><s>Therefore, the Fe-S cluster is regarded as an ancient feature.</s><s>In photosynthesis, respiration and many other processes, Fe-S clusters are involved in electron transfer.</s><s>Either one of the two electron transfer processes of FeS-BCPs, photoactivation or DNA repair, could be linked to electron reactions involving the Fe-S cluster.</s></p><p><s>Among FeS-BCP members, amino acid residues in the active center are highly conserved.</s><s>His366 of PhrB is among the few residues that are conserved in both FeS-BCP proteins and eukaryotic (6-4) photolyases.</s><s>A co-crystal structure of Drosophila (6-4) photolyase with damaged DNA showed that this residue is in contact with the DNA lesion.</s><s>Mutagenesis studies for Drosophila and Arabidopsis eukaryotic (6-4) photolyases showed that this residue is essential for DNA repair.</s><s>It is thought that this His delivers a proton to the lesion, following lightinduced electron transfer from FAD to the lesion <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">15]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In this study, we elucidate the role of particular amino acid residues of the prokaryotic (6-4) photolyase PhrB from Agrobacterium fabrum during photoreduction and photorepair.</s><s>We identified Trp342 and Trp390 as electron transmitters.</s><s>The replacement of the highly conserved His366 results in loss of DNA repair activity.</s><s>Leu370, which is also highly conserved, is not essential for repair; the L370M mutant has a lower repair activity.</s><s>We also mutagenized Tyr residues between the FeS cluster and the DNA lesion.</s><s>Tyr424 is essential for lesion binding and DNA repair activity.</s><s>Mutants in which Tyr430 is replaced are characterized by a lower DNA repair activity.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials and Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mutagenesis, expression and purification</head><p><s>For conservation studies, the selection of FeS-BCP proteins and the alignment of an earlier publication was used <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[10]</ref>.</s><s>A PhrB expression vector based on the pET21 (Novagen) with a C-terminal poly-His-tag was used <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">10]</ref> for protein expression.</s><s>Site-directed mutagenesis was performed according to the Quik Change Site-Directed Mutagenesis protocol of Stratagene.</s><s>The primers used for each mutant are given in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>.</s><s>Expression vectors for truncated versions of PhrB were made by PCR using the wild-type PhrB expression vector and the primer pairs PhrB-Nt426-fw / PhrB-Nt426-rev for the N-terminal 426 amino acids and PhrB-Nt476-fw / PhrB-Nt476-rev for the N-terminal 476 amino acids of PhrB.</s><s>Protein expression and purification of PhrB and mutants was performed as described before <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">10]</ref>.</s><s>For optimization of expression recombinant E. coli harboring the pET21 based expression vector were cultivated at different temperatures (28°C, 33°C or 37°C) after IPTG induction.</s><s>For Western Blot assays, different cultures were grown in parallel until the same OD 600 nm of 1.5 was reached.</s><s>Before extraction, each liter bacterial culture was centrifuged and the cells were brought into 20 ml extraction buffer.</s><s>After extraction and centrifugation, each pellet was suspended in 10 ml extraction buffer to get an estimate of the insoluble fraction of each PhrB mutant.</s><s>Analyses by SDS-PAGE and Western blot were performed with 100 μl aliquots that were mixed with 50 μl SDS-PAGE sample-buffer, heated and cleared by centrifugation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Photoreduction</head><p><s>In all photoreduction studies, 10 mM DTT were added to the sample just before the onset of the measurements.</s><s>UV/vis spectra of PhrB were scanned with a Jasco V550 photometer.</s><s>Between these scans, samples were irradiated with blue light from light emitting diodes (λ max = 470 nm, fluence rate = 55 μmol m -2 s -1 ).</s><s>Total irradiation times were usually 0, 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 5, 10, 15, 20, 30, 45, 60 and 90 min.</s></p><p><s>Purification of (6-4) photoproducts and DNA repair Four ml oligonucleotides "t_repair", "EMSA_1" or "EMSA_2" (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>), adjusted to 100 μM, were irradiated under argon atmosphere with a G15T8-lamp (GE, 15 W, λ max = 254 nm).</s><s>The DNA containing the lesion was thereafter purified by HPLC on a "series 1200" Agilent Technologies system using a Nucleodur 100-5 C18ec (250x10) column from Macherey &amp; Nagel.</s><s>The flow rate was adjusted to 5 ml/min.</s><s>Buffer A (0.1 M triethylaminoacetate in H 2 O) was passed through the column for 45 min, thereafter a gradient of 4-18% buffer B (0.1 M (triethylaminoacetate) in H 2 O / acetonitrile (20:80)) was applied over 20 min.</s><s>The eluate was monitored by a diode array detector, the (6-4) photoproduct is characterized by an absorbance maximum at 325 nm.</s><s>Relevant fractions were sampled and stored at -20°C until further use.</s><s>The photorepair reaction mixture contained 4 μM of the purified (6-4) photoproduct of t-repair1 (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>) and 12 μM protein in repair buffer 1 (50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.0, 1 mM EDTA, 100 mM NaCl, 5% (w/v) glycerol, 20 mM DTT).</s><s>In some cases, repair buffer 2 (50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 1 mM EDTA, 100 mM NaCl, 5% (w/v) glycerol, 10 mM DTT) was used.</s><s>After 30 min pre incubation in darkness at 20°C, aliquots were irradiated with 470 nm light emitting diodes (55 μmol m -2 s -1 ) for the given time.</s><s>The reactions were stopped by heating to 95°C.</s><s>The obtained samples were then centrifuged (4°C, 15000 × g, 10 min) and the supernatants analyzed by HPLC.</s><s>To this end, the same Agilent system with a Nukleosil 100-5 C18ec (250x4) column from Macherey &amp; Nagel was used.</s><s>The flow rate was 0.5 ml/min and a gradient of 0-17% buffer B over 45 min was applied.</s><s>The repair efficiency was estimated from the peak areas corresponding to photoproduct DNA and repaired DNA.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Protein-DNA interaction</head><p><s>The single-stranded EMSA_1 (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>) oligonucleotide or its purified (6-4) photoproduct were labeled with γ-32 P-ATP by viral T4 polynucleotide kinase (NEB Biolabs) according to the instructions of the manufacturer.</s><s>γ-32 P-ATP was added in a fivefold molar excess.</s><s>The sample was incubated at 37°C for 3 h and the reaction was stopped by raising the temperature to 67°C for 20 min.</s><s>Free γ-32 P -ATP was separated on a G25 gel filtration column according to the manufacturer's instructions.</s></p><p><s>The interaction between protein and single-stranded DNA was monitored by electrophoretic mobility shift assay (EMSA).</s><s>The FAD of photolyase was first photoreduced for 12 h at 4°C under oxygen-free conditions.</s><s>The concentration of DNA was always 28 nM, the protein concentration was varied as given in the Results section.</s><s>Protein and DNA were mixed in repair buffer.</s><s>Electrophoresis was carried out in a 10% TBE-polyacrylamide-gel (acrylamide/ bisacrylamide 19:1) at 70-100 V and 4°C in darkness.</s><s>Images were taken by a phosphoimager (BIO-Imaging-Analyzer BAS-1500).</s><s>The fraction of bound DNA was determined and plotted versus protein concentration.</s><s>For each condition these data were fitted with the program Origin 8.6 to (function 2) which is derived from the dissociation constant formula (function 1).</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">K D ¼ ðy À x Á DÞ Á D À x Á D x Á D<label>ð1Þ</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">y ¼ ððK D þ x þ DÞ AE ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ðK D þ x þ DÞ 2 À 4 Á D Á xÞ q 2 Á D<label>ð2Þ</label></formula><p><s>In these formulae, K D is the dissociation constant, y the total concentration of the protein, D the total concentration of the ligand DNA and x the fraction of protein-bound DNA.</s><s>The parameters y, x and D are given by the experiment; K D is obtained from the fit.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results and Discussion Photoreduction</head><p><s>The classical electron pathway for photoreduction consisting of three Trp residues which are conserved in most cryptochromes and photolyases is absent in FeS-BCPs.</s><s>Based on the PhrB crystal structure, two Trp/Tyr pathways can be proposed.</s><s>One pathway involves Trp342, Trp390 and Tyr391, edge-to-edge distances between aromatic systems of amino acid side chains and isoalloxazine of FAD are 3.9, 3.8 and 3.7 Å, respectively (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>These amino acids are conserved in most FeS-BCP proteins.</s><s>The other pathway involves Tyr40 and Tyr399 with edge-to-edge distances of 6.3 and 5.8 Å, respectively.</s><s>To study the role of these amino acids, we generated the mutants Y399F, W390F, Y391F, W342F, Y399F and the double mutant W390F/ Y391F and measured their photoreduction.</s><s>In wild-type PhrB, the transition from the oxidized to the semi-reduced form of FAD is characterized by absorbance decreases at around 450 nm and 370 nm, and an increase at 580 nm.</s><s>During the transition of the semi-reduced to the fully-  photorepair in PhrB, in contrast to CryB, where the homologous mutant has a slower photoreduction than the wild type <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[9]</ref>.</s><s>There is also no other Trp or Tyr residue between Trp342 and FAD that could form a bridge.</s><s>Therefore, electrons must tunnel directly from Trp342 to FAD via a distance of 7.9 Å.</s><s>The observation that Tyr391 is not involved in electron transfer is consistent with the fact that there is no nearby basic group in the crystal structure of PhrB that could abstract a proton from the Tyr hydroxyl group as would be required for the oxidation of the Tyr side chain <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[11]</ref>.</s><s>There is no evidence for electron transfer via Tyr40.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The distinct role of His366</head><p><s>PhrB and eukaryotic (6-4) photolyases have only 30 identical amino acids.</s><s>Most of these are not specific for (6-4) photolyases but also present in other CPF members <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[10]</ref>.</s><s>His366 of PhrB is one of two amino acids that are specifically present in FeS-BCPs, eukaryotic (6-4) photolyases and in animal cryptochromes.</s><s>This histidine residue is located at the bottom end of the lesion binding cavity and is in close distance to the lesion and to FAD (see also <ref type="bibr">Fig 1)</ref>.</s><s>It is stabilized by Leu370 and Met410 via van der Waals contacts <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[10]</ref>.</s><s>These residues are conserved to 100% and 99% in FeS-BCP, but not in eukaryotic (6-4) photolyases, where a hydrogen bonding network stabilizes the homologous His residue <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[14,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">15]</ref>.</s><s>We generated the H366N and L370M mutants and the corresponding double mutant H366N/L370M of PhrB and tested these mutants for photoreduction and repair of (6-4) photoproducts.</s><s>The wild-type amino acids are thereby replaced by their CPD photolyase counterparts.</s><s>The photoreduction of H366N was slightly slower than that of the wild type (Fig <ref type="figure">3B</ref>).</s><s>Quite unexpectedly, the photoreduction of L370M was faster than that of the wild type during the first 10 min of irradiation, but slower thereafter.</s><s>The absorbance at 450 nm reached stable intermediate levels after 90 min (Fig <ref type="figure">3B</ref>).</s><s>This incomplete photoreduction points to a heterogeneity of this sample.</s><s>The photoreduction of the H366M/L370M double mutant was still slower (Fig 3B <ref type="figure">)</ref>, apparently because the effects of both mutations are additive.</s><s>Leu370 is close to the chromophore with a distance of 4.0 Å; the role of this residue in photoreduction could be a subtle one in helping to define the precise position and orientation of FAD by van der Waals interactions or by shielding the chromophore from water.</s><s>The smaller size and higher polarity of the mutant residue could slightly displace the chromophore or provide space for a water molecule.</s></p><p><s>A single experiment was performed in which damaged DNA and PhrB or mutants thereof were incubated for varying times periods under blue light irradiation.</s><s>In this experiment, wildtype PhrB repaired 90% of (6-4) photoproducts after 90 min incubation.</s><s>The mutant L370M was less efficient, the repair was 28% after 30 and 60% after 90 min.</s><s>No repair activity could be found for H366N or the H366N/L370M double mutant and the PhrA from A. fabrum (a class III CPD photolyase) as a control (Fig <ref type="figure">4</ref>).</s><s>Repeated repair assays were performed in a slightly different buffer (repair buffer 2 with pH 7.5 instead of repair buffer 1 with pH 7.0), different irradiation conditions (400 nm, 200 μmol m -2 s -1 ) and a fixed irradiation time of 30 min (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).</s></p><p><s>The overall repair efficiency in these experiments was lower but the differences between the proteins remained: no repair activity was found for PhrA, H366N and the double mutant H366N/L370M.</s><s>The repair activity of L370M with 10% was intermediate, whereas the highest repair activity was obtained for PhrB wild type.</s><s>It is therefore clear that His366 is essential for DNA repair, a property that is shared with the homologous amino acids in eukaryotic photolyases.</s><s>These results suggest functional identity of this His residue in prokaryotic and eukaryotic  photolyases.</s><s>The lower repair activity of L370M could also originate from displaced FAD as discussed above for photoreduction.</s><s>It is clear, however, that Leu370 is not essential for DNA repair, despite its high degree of conservation within the FeS-BCP group.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fe-S cluster</head><p><s>To study the role of the Fe-S cluster, several attempts were undertaken to remove this cluster from the protein.</s><s>Three point mutants in which Cys residues of the Fe-S cluster were replaced by Ser, C438S, C350S and C441S, were generated.</s><s>These mutant proteins were not expressed in E. coli under conditions where the wild-type protein was expressed as soluble protein (S2 Fig) <ref type="figure">.</ref></s><s>Temperature increase during cultivation resulted in a weak expression, but the mutant proteins were insoluble (S1 Fig) <ref type="figure">.</ref></s><s>Two truncated versions of PhrB, designated PhrB-C and PhrB-D, were also generated which consist of amino acids 1-432 and 1-476, respectively.</s><s>In PhrB-C, three of the Fe-S coordinating Cys residues are missing, in PhrB-D, all Cys residues are present but the two C-terminal helices are missing.</s><s>PhrB-C was insoluble under all tested conditions, whereas PhrB-D was partially soluble (Fig <ref type="figure">5</ref>).</s><s>In the context of Mössbauer experiments <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[16]</ref>, we tested the expression of PhrB by E. coli cells growing in minimal medium without iron.</s><s>Under these conditions, PhrB was also insoluble (data not shown).</s><s>Thus, all conditions that might lead to a protein without Fe-S cluster result in very poor protein expression or insoluble protein.</s><s>We therefore propose that the Fe-S cluster is required for structural stability, integrity and correct folding of PhrB.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conserved Tyr residues between Fe-S cluster and lesion</head><p><s>In order to identify a possible electron donor / acceptor function of the Fe-S cluster, we screened the PhrB structure for nearby Tyr or Trp residues that could serve as electron  <ref type="table">3</ref>).</s><s>The dissociation constant for PhrB and undamaged DNA was estimated as K D = 25±3 μM and the values for the mutants were similar (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>).</s><s>The affinity of the wild-type protein for damaged DNA was found to be much higher; the dissociation constant decreased to K D = 13±2 nM.</s><s>The mutants Y430F and Y460F had slightly higher K D values (Table <ref type="table">3</ref>), whereas Y424F had a dissociation constant of K D = 18±2 μM, a value in the range of the undamaged DNA (see Table <ref type="table">3</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Fig 8)</ref>.</s><s>Apparently, the Tyr residue is important for the high affinity towards (6-4) lesions, although we did not expect that the replacement of one amino acid could result in a complete loss of lesion binding.</s><s>The repair of (6-4) photoproducts by Y460F was comparable to that of the wild type.</s><s>The Y424F mutant did not show repair activity, whereas the activity of Y430F was 30% as compared to the wild type (Fig <ref type="figure">9</ref> and Table <ref type="table">3</ref>).</s><s>The loss of repair activity in Y424F correlates with the loss of lesion binding.</s><s>However, no such correlation could explain the low repair activity of Y430F, which has wild type-like lesion binding properties.</s><s>Its position between the lesion and the Fe-S cluster could point to an effect of the Fe-S cluster on the repair process.</s><s>Their surface exposed positions are consistent with the potential involvement of Tyr424 and Tyr430 in electron transfer reactions, since their accessibility to the solvent would enable protonation and deprotonation of their side chain oxygen atoms during redox processes.</s></p><p><s>These studies must be regarded as a first step towards the function of the Fe-S cluster in PhrB.</s><s>The loss of the cluster during the early evolution of the other photolyases can be much better understood if the function of the Fe-S cluster is known.</s><s>Other DNA interacting proteins like primases, DNA polymerase or helicases can also have Fe-S clusters; in most cases their function is unclear.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusions</head><p><s>Site-directed mutagenesis has shown that photoreduction in PhrB involves two Trp residues.</s><s>There are thus four different photoreduction pathways for photolyases, the classical one with the Trp-triad as described for E. coli photolyase, the pathway of class II CPD photolyases in which a Trp and a Tyr are involved, a dual pathway as described for the class III CPD photolyase PhrA and the pathway of FeS-BCP proteins described here in which two Trp residues are involved.</s><s>It was also shown that the same His residue is required for photorepair of (6-4) photoproducts as in eukaryotic photolyases.</s><s>Tyr424, highly conserved in the FeS-BCP proteins, is required for lesion binding and repair.</s><s>Tyr430, also highly conserved, plays a role in the repair process, but is not involved in lesion binding.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig 1. Orientation of FAD and amino acids that might be relevant for photoreduction in the structure of PhrB (PDB entry 4DJA).</s><s>The ribbon representation shows the α/β-domain (N-terminal domain; green) and the helical domain (catalytic domain; blue) connected by an inter-domain linker (orange).</s><s>FAD chromophore (yellow), DMRL ligand (pink) and relevant amino acids are shown as stick models.</s><s>Trp342 is located close to the surface.</s><s>Distances are given in Å. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0140955.g001</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,200.01,426.10,254.61,219.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig 2 .Fig 3 .</head><label>23</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig 2. Photoreduction of wild-type PhrB.</s><s>UV/vis spectra during irradiation with 470 nm LED light.</s><s>Above: absorbance spectra, below: difference spectra in which the dark spectrum is taken as reference.</s><s>Insets: The spectra or difference spectra &gt; 500 nm are shown in an enlarged y-axis.</s><s>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0140955.g002</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,36.00,223.03,432.23,450.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig 4 .Fig 5 .Fig 6 .</head><label>456</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig 4. Repair activity of PhrB and its mutants H366N, L370M and H366N/L370M.</s><s>The percentage remaining (6-4) photoproduct after irradiation with 470 nm is plotted against the time.</s><s>Data are for repair buffer 1. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0140955.g004</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,200.01,78.01,239.98,187.65" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig 7 .Fig 8 .μM 2 5 Fig 9 .</head><label>7859</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig 7. Photoreduction of PhrB and its mutants Y424F, Y430F and Y460F.</s><s>Spectra were measured as in Fig 2. Difference spectra (obtained by subtractions of the dark spectrum) after 470 nm irradiation.</s><s>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0140955.g007</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="11,36.00,78.01,527.98,438.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,200.01,464.94,251.95,199.28" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="12,36.00,78.01,532.29,174.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="12,200.01,453.83,239.98,219.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Primers for DNA repair studies, site-directed mutagenesis, or PCR.</s><s>The TT pair that yields the (6-4) photoproduct is printed in bold.</s><s>The triplet of the mutation site is printed in bold.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>EMSA_1</cell></row></table><note><p><s>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0140955.t001</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">PLOS ONE | DOI:10.1371/journal.pone.0140955 October 21, 2015</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p><s>We gratefully acknowledge Sybille Wörner, Jennifer Welschhof, and Ernst Heene for technical assistance.</s><s>This work was supported by Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) Grant 799/</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supporting Information</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Karlsruhe House of Young Scientists (to F. Z.), and DFG Cluster of Excellence &quot;Unifying Concepts in Catalysis</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">and SFB 740-B6 and SFB 1078-B6 (to P. S.), and grants from the China Scholarship Council</title>
				<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Research Field D3/E3 (to P. S.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A photolyase-like protein from Agrobacterium tumefaciens with an iron-sulfur cluster</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Oberpichler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pierik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wesslowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pokorny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rosen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vugman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0026775</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22066008</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Plos One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e26775</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011. 2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A prokaryotic (6-4) photolyase with a DMRL chromophore and an iron-sulfur cluster</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lamparter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Graf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wesslowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Oberpichler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Encyclopedia of Inorganic and Bioinorganic Chemistry</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Ltd</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Formation and direct repair of UV-induced dimeric DNA pyrimidine lesions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kneuttinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Kashiwazaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Prill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Heil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Carell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Photochemistry and Photobiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="14" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reaction mechanisms of DNA photolyase</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Brettel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Byrdin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.sbi.2010.07.003</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">20705454</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Struct Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="693" to="701" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Searching for a photocycle of the cryptochrome photoreceptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zhong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.pbi.2010.09.005</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">20943427</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Plant Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="578" to="586" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Determining complete electron flow in the cofactor photoreduction of oxidized photolyase</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sancar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zhong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.1311073110</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">23882080</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12966" to="12971" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The class III cyclobutane pyrimidine dimer photolyase structure reveals a new antenna chromophore binding site and alternative photoreduction pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Scheerer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kalms</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Von Stetten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Krauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Oberpichler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1074/jbc.M115.637868</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">25784552</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">290</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11504" to="11514" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crystal structures of an archaeal class II DNA photolyase and its complex with UV-damaged duplex DNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kiontke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Geisselbrecht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pokorny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Carell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Batschauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Essen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/emboj.2011.313</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">21892138</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4437" to="4449" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CryB from Rhodobacter sphaeroides: a unique class of cryptochromes with new cofactors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Geisselbrecht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Fruhwirth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Schroeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pierik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Klug</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Essen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/embor.2012.2</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">22290493</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="223" to="229" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crystal structure of a prokaryotic (6-4) photolyase with an Fe-S cluster and a 6,7-dimethyl-8-ribityllumazine antenna chromophore</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Scheerer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Oberpichler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lamparter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Krauss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.1302377110</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">23589886</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="7217" to="7222" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Further comments on the redox potentials of tryptophan and tyrosine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Harriman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Physical Chemistry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">91</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6102" to="6104" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Riboflavin analogs and inhibitors of riboflavin biosynthesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Grill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">16607521</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="265" to="275" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure and function of DNA photolyase and cryptochrome blue-light photoreceptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Sancar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="PMID">12797829</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chem Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2203" to="2237" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crystal structure and mechanism of a DNA (6-4) photolyase</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Maul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Barends</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Glas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cryle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Domratcheva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/anie.200804268</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">18956392</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Angew Chem Int Ed Engl</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10076" to="10080" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008. 200804268</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional motifs in the (6-4) photolyase crystal structure make a comparative framework for DNA repair photolyases and clock cryptochromes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hitomi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ditacchio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Arvai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yamamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Todo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1073/pnas.0809180106</idno>
		<idno type="PMID">19359474</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6962" to="6967" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterization of the photolyase-like iron sulfur protein PhrB from Agrobacterium tumefaciens by Mössbauer spectroscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Bauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Graf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lamparter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Schünemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hyperfine Interactions</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">226</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="445" to="449" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
