<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Actin Nucleator Cobl Is Critical for Centriolar Positioning, Postnatal Planar Cell Polarity Refinement, and Function of the Cochlea</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Natja</forename><surname>Haag</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biochemistry I</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jena University Hospital -Friedrich Schiller University Jena</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>07743</postCode>
									<settlement>Jena</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Susann</forename><surname>Sch€ Uler</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biochemistry I</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jena University Hospital -Friedrich Schiller University Jena</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>07743</postCode>
									<settlement>Jena</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sandor</forename><surname>Nietzsche</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">EM Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jena University Hospital -Friedrich Schiller University Jena</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>07743</postCode>
									<settlement>Jena</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Christian</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>H€ Ubner</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nicola</forename><surname>Strenzke</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Otolaryngology</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">InnerEarLab</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Go ¨ttingen</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>37075</postCode>
									<settlement>Go ¨ttingen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Britta</forename><surname>Qualmann</surname></persName>
							<email>britta.qualmann@med.uni-jena.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biochemistry I</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jena University Hospital -Friedrich Schiller University Jena</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>07743</postCode>
									<settlement>Jena</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
							<email>michael.kessels@med.uni-jena.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Biochemistry I</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jena University Hospital -Friedrich Schiller University Jena</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>07743</postCode>
									<settlement>Jena</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Lead Contact</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Christian</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>H€</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Jena University Hospital -Friedrich Schiller University Jena</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>07743</postCode>
									<settlement>Jena</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Human Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital RWTH Aachen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Aachen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Actin Nucleator Cobl Is Critical for Centriolar Positioning, Postnatal Planar Cell Polarity Refinement, and Function of the Cochlea</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B6D88A6C7E8AF9691C928E5AE51BB59B</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.celrep.2018.07.087</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:23+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Highlights d Cobl is critical for cochlear amplification in hearing d Cobl is a critical effector of postnatal planar cell polarity refinement d Cobl KO led to reduction of cuticular plate F-actin beneath the sensory apparatus d Cobl KO disrupts F-actin-dependent PCM organization and the PCM-stereocilia alignment</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>In Brief <ref type="bibr">Haag et al.</ref> identify the actin nucleator Cobl as a crucial effector of postnatal planar cell polarity refinements and for cochlear amplification during hearing.</s><s>The authors show that F-actin-dependent PCM organization, centriolar positioning, kinocilium regression, PCM/kinociliar alignment with stereocilia, and sensory apparatus orientation are cellular mechanisms derailed upon Cobl KO.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p><s>Establishment and changes of cell morphology and polarity depend on forces created by actin and microtubule cytoskeletal structures.</s><s>Early embryonic planar cell polarity (PCP) plays a central role in tissue patterning <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Montcouquiol et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Curtin et al., 2003)</ref>.</s><s>PCP signaling, for example, brings about a preliminary alignment of outer hair cells (OHCs) in the inner ear and of their stereocilia bundles serving as mechanosensors.</s><s>Auditory perception in mice starts about 2 weeks after birth <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Song et al., 2006)</ref>.</s><s>Sound-evoked basilar membrane vibrations cause stereociliar deflections and open mechanotransduction channels <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Fettiplace and Hackney, 2006)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>While microtubule-based ciliary structures are indicative of PCP and also the orientation of OHC stereociliar bundles in the cochlea precisely reflects PCP in the tissue <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Kelley et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Ezan and Montcouquiol, 2013)</ref>, little is known about PCP effectors and about postnatal processes subsequent to classical embryonic PCP signaling.</s></p><p><s>Stereocilia of OHCs are organized as V-shaped bundles inserted into the cortical actin network, the cuticular plate <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Tilney et al., 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kitajiri et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Szarama et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>They show tight correlation with the microtubule-based kinocilium intimately associated with the tip of the stereocilia bundle.</s><s>The kinocilium originates from a mother centriole-derived basal body and may play some guiding role in PCP and stereocilia positioning, as it migrates to the distal (i.e., abneural) hair cell side during embryonic development.</s><s>Recent work in simplified systems suggested some, albeit not yet fully understood F-actin cross talk with centrosomes and centrioles <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Farina et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Carvajal-Gonzalez et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Obino et al., 2016)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Here, we demonstrate at the whole-animal level that Cobl (Cordon-Bleu) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Ahuja et al., 2007</ref>)-a WH2 domain-based actin nucleator <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Qualmann and Kessels, 2009)</ref>-is critical for cross talk of microtubule-based and F-actin-based structures in OHCs of the cochlea.</s><s>Cobl knockout (KO) hereby specifically impaired F-actin structures and functions in the cuticular plate beneath stereocilia and the kinocilium.</s><s>Cobl KO disrupted the organization of the pericentriolar material (PCM) and its intimate spatial alignments with the kinocilium and the stereocilia bundle.</s><s>Interestingly, the associated stereociliar positioning defects mostly manifested postnatally, that is, were not related to classical embryonic PCP signaling.</s><s>Cobl KO phenotypes thereby unveiled postnatal refinements and also revealed that PCP has to be actively maintained during adulthood.</s><s>Physiological studies uncovered that Cobl-mediated functions in the cochlea are important for the OHC amplifier function in hearing.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head><p><s>Cobl KO Mice Show a Lack of a Specific Cortical Subset of Actin Filaments Cobl promotes F-actin formation and is critical for dendrite formation and branching in neurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Ahuja et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Hou et al., 2015</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hou et al., , 2018))</ref>.</s><s>In situ hybridizations of zebrafish larvae suggested an additional role in the auditory system.</s><s>Strong Cobl signals also occurred in the developing ear (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>).</s><s>In mice, cochlear Cobl expression was detected, too (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>).</s><s>Cobl was prominent in OHCs and enriched in their cuticular plates <ref type="bibr">(Figures 1C and 1D)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>To analyze its functional importance, we generated Cobl KO mice.</s><s>The murine Cobl gene comprises 15 exons (GenBank: NM_172496.3).</s><s>Database analyses predict that besides the actin nucleator Cobl also a splice variant lacking exons 10-15, that is, all WH2 domains, may exist (CoblDE10-15).</s><s>Antibodies against the N-terminal part of Cobl (anti-Cobl ARA ; <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Schwintzer et al., 2011)</ref>, which would detect both Cobl and the putative truncated variant not representing an actin nucleator, did not yield any immunosignals in samples from up to ten pooled cochleae due to the minimal tissue amounts (not shown).</s><s>Therefore, these analyses could not exclude that a CoblDE10-15 protein may exist.</s><s>RT-PCRs could also not rule out that indeed some actin nucleation-incompetent DE10-15 variant may exist, as some weak mRNA trace was obtained with E9 and I9 primers (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1A-S1C</ref>).</s></p><p><s>To eradicate specifically all actin nucleating products of the Cobl gene but not the putative truncated form, which lacks all actin-binding WH2 domains and thus would have functions unrelated to actin nucleation, we targeted exon 11 (Cre/lox).</s><s>Using mice ubiquitously expressing Cre <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Schwenk et al., 1995)</ref>, we removed exon 11 together with the selection cassette yielding a mouse line with an ubiquitous and constitutive Cobl .</s></p><p><s>RT-PCRs demonstrated that exon 11 deletion affected Cobl mRNA stability in cochlea and brain <ref type="bibr">(Figures 1I and 1J)</ref>.</s><s>Western blotting as well as immunofluorescence analyses of cochleae and brain material with antibodies against a C-terminal epitope (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1A</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Haag et al., 2012)</ref> confirmed that the actin nucleator Cobl was successfully knocked out (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1K-1N</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Theoretically, a residual fragment of 549 aa (544 + 5 non-Cobl amino acids due to frameshift; $60 kDa) could result from exon 11 deletion (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1B</ref>).</s><s>Whereas antibodies against Cobl 175-324  (anti-Cobl ARA ) did successfully detect Cobl in brains of wild-type (WT) mice, neither the putative DE10-15 variant nor any truncated protein resulting from exon 11 deletion was detected in KO samples (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1N</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Homozygous Cobl KO mice displayed normal viability during &gt;1 year of monitoring.</s><s>Body weights of both sexes were unaltered.</s><s>Litter sizes were significantly reduced when homozygous mice were bred.</s><s>These impairments, however, did not seem to reflect a critical role of Cobl during embryonic development, as suggested by work in zebrafish <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Ravanelli and Klingensmith, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Sch€ uler et al., 2013)</ref>, because genotypes did not differ from Mendelian distribution (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1D-S1G</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Cobl KO embryos did not display any obvious defects in embryogenesis, in body laterality establishment (data not shown), or in neural tube closure, and did also not lead to exencephaly, which would have been an obvious readout for defects in cerebrospinal fluid movements through the ventricular system (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1H and S1I</ref>).</s><s>Thus, although Cobl is expressed in the floor plate and in the notochord of the neural tube at embryonic day 9.5 (E9.5) (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1J-S1M</ref>), as demonstrated before at the mRNA level <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Gasca et al., 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Carroll et al., 2003)</ref>, Cobl KO mice did not show any phenotypes reflecting impairments of motile cilia or defects in early development based on the parameters examined.</s></p><p><s>To address a putative Cobl role in the cochlea, we first examined the F-actin-rich cuticular plates of OHCs (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1O-1U</ref>).</s><s>Their width increases during cochlear maturation <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Szarama et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>This was not affected upon Cobl KO (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1O-1Q</ref>).</s><s>However, specifically areas beneath the sensory apparatus showed a significantly reduced F-actin content in Cobl KO OHCs (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1R-1U</ref>).</s><s>The overall reduction across the entire line scan was about 10% (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1R</ref>).</s><s>Interestingly, distribution analyses showed that the F-actin loss occurred specifically in an about 1-mm-thick apical layer underneath OHC stereocilia.</s><s>In this substereociliar layer, the F-actin loss reached $20% (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1S</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Altered Organization of PCM in Cobl KO Cochleae</head><p><s>The cell cortex embeds both stereocilia and kinocilium base structures.</s><s>Three-dimensional (3D) surface models computed from postnatal day 8 (P8) cochleae immunostained for pericentrin, a marker for the PCM surrounding the centrioles at the kinocilium base <ref type="bibr">(Doxsey et al., 1994)</ref>, showed a dramatically increased volume of the pericentriolar scaffold.</s><s>In all three OHC rows, it more than doubled (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2A-2E</ref>).</s><s>The sum intensity of the anti-pericentrin labeling was also increased (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2F</ref>).</s><s>This may reflect an increased pericentrin recruitment in Cobl KO mice, an improved immunodetection upon a loss of PCM compression, or both.</s><s>Since the density of the anti-pericentrin labeling in the enlarged PCM was decreased (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2G</ref>), PCM organization clearly was impaired.</s><s>Similar defects-albeit not yet as pronounced-were seen in newborn mice (P2) (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S2A-S2G</ref>).</s></p><p><s>In contrast to the defects in PCM organization, the centrioles encased by the PCM (marked by immunolabeling of g-tubulin; <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Jones et al., 2008)</ref> did not show any significant defects <ref type="bibr">(Figures S2H and S2I)</ref>.</s><s>Cobl KO thus specifically disrupted the organization of the pericentrin-marked PCM around centrioles.</s><s>Proper PCM Organization in OHCs Depends on Actin Filament Formation and Ca 2+ /CaM Signaling To address whether the PCM organization defects observed upon KO of the actin nucleator Cobl reflect a critical role of F-actin formation, we applied 1 mM latrunculin A to freshly dissected cochlear whole mounts of P8 WT animals.</s><s>Strikingly, this resulted in an increase in PCM volume and sum anti-pericentrin signal (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2H-2M</ref>) as well as in a decrease of anti-pericentrin immunolabeling density (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2N</ref>).</s><s>Thus, suppression of F-actin formation by latrunculin A mirrored the defects observed in Cobl KO mice very well</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(Figures 2A-2G versus Fig- ures 2H-2N).</formula><p><s>Cobl's actin functions in neurons depend on Ca 2+ /CaM signaling <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Hou et al., 2015)</ref>.</s><s>Strikingly, CaM inhibitors CGS9343B and W7 both also led to a dramatic loss of PCM organization reminiscent of the Cobl KO phenotypes.</s><s>The PCM volume more than doubled and the sum anti-pericentrin signal increased strongly (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2O-2T</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Together, these experiments demonstrate that Cobl and proper F-actin formation play key roles in organizing the PCM surrounding the centrioles, that is, the kinociliar base, and that this cell biological process is dependent on Ca 2+ /CaM signaling.</s></p><p><s>The Defects in PCM Organization Coincide with Impaired Centriole Positioning Proper positioning of centrioles is considered key in the development of organized cellular arrays.</s><s>Three consequences of PCM disorganization for the OHC sensory array seemed plausible: First, since the PCM harbors the two centrioles, their positioning to each other could be affected.</s><s>Second, impairments of the PCM at the base of the kinocilium may affect kinocilium organization and stability.</s><s>Third, consequences for the stereocilia bundle that is linked to the kinocilium during development seemed possible-especially, if the tight alignment of the mother centriole (basal body) and/or of the PCM with the tip position of the stereocilia bundle would be disrupted.</s></p><p><s>First, Cobl KO indeed coincided with impaired centriole positioning.</s><s>3D analyses of immunolabelings of g-tubulin showed that the intercentriolar distance was increased in P2 Cobl KO OHCs (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3A-3C and S3A</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Cobl KO Impairs PCM-Kinocilium Alignment and Causes Premature Kinocilium Retraction prior to Hearing Onset Second, we addressed whether the PCM disorganization would coincide with impairments in kinocilium linkage and subsequently with defects in kinocilium stability.</s><s>Strikingly, 3D recon-structions of OHCs of P2 cochlea stained for pericentrin and for acetylated tubulin (axoneme marker; Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">S3B and S3C</ref>) showed that basal body docking to the axoneme of the kinocilium was affected upon Cobl KO.</s><s>Specifically in the more mature OHC1 and OHC2 cells, the PCM-to-kinocilium base distance was increased by about 25% (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3D-3I</ref>).</s></p><p><s>The fate of kinocilia was examined next.</s><s>Cobl KO animals showed a premature kinocilium retraction.</s><s>While at P2 and P6 invariably every OHC still had a kinocilium and at P15 the kinocilium had disappeared from almost all WT and Cobl KO OHCs, we observed significantly fewer kinocilia-bearing OHC3s in Cobl KO cochleae during the critical time window of cochlear maturation prior to hearing onset (P8) (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3J-3T</ref>).</s><s>At P9, premature kinocilium retraction was even more severe.</s><s>Now, all three OHCs rows of the apico-medial turn of Cobl KO cochleae showed significantly fewer remaining kinocilia (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3P, 3Q,  and 3T</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Cobl KO Leads to Disrupted Spatial Correlation of the Kinocilium with the Stereocilia Bundle We then addressed the third possibility and explored whether the Cobl-and actin filament formation-dependent defects in PCM organization may disrupt the normally tight kinocilium/stereocilia bundle alignment.</s><s>As the kinocilium showed premature regression at P8 and P9 in Cobl KO mice and both PCM as well as centriole positioning defects were already observable in newborn Cobl KO mice (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">2 and 3</ref>), we addressed this question in newborn mice.</s><s>Strikingly, scanning electron microscopy (EM) revealed that the tight spatial correlation of the kinociliar base and the stereocilia bundle was disrupted upon Cobl KO (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4A and 4B</ref>).</s><s>Analyses of images with the same rotational positioning of the cochlear array (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4C and 4D</ref>) showed that the distance of the kinociliar base to the stereocilia bundle was significantly increased.</s><s>In Cobl KO OHC3s, the distance increased by almost 30% (to &gt;420 nm) when compared to WT-a significant disruption of the normally very intimate assembly of the kinocilium with the tip of the stereocilia bundle (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4E</ref>).</s></p><p><s>3D analyses of surface-rendered anti-pericentrin immunostained PCMs and of phalloidin-highlighted stereocilia bundles demonstrated that also the PCM and the base of the stereocilia bundle tip were misaligned in all three OHC rows (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4F-4J</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Interestingly and in accordance with the relatively symmetrical positioning of the kinocilia at the tip of the V-shaped stereocilia bundles (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4A-4D</ref>), we did not observe any shift of the   PCM to one side of the stereocilia bundle (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4K</ref>), as described for defects in classical embryonic PCP signaling <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Gegg et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>Instead, the disruption of the alignment of the PCM (i.e., the kinocilia base) with the stereocilia bundle occurred along the symmetry axis.</s></p><p><s>The fact that the proportion of OHCs that showed a disorganized PCM as well as structural defects in kinocilia docking to the stereocilia bundle tip was about 80% suggests that these Cobl KO phenotypes do not occur separately from each other but may be correlated (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4L</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Cobl KO Leads to Rotational Defects in OHC Arrays of Adult Cobl KO Cochleae that Reflect Impairments of Postnatal PCP Refinements and Maintenance Considering that proper ciliary functions and a tight coupling of kinocilia to stereocilia are thought to be linked to PCP signaling and/or establishment in some way <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Frolenkov et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kelley et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Ezan and Montcouquiol, 2013)</ref>, the Cobl KO phenotypes identified thus far could have consequences for stereocilia bundle positioning.</s><s>Scanning EM analyses indeed showed that the sensory arrays of OHCs were  altered upon Cobl KO (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5</ref>).</s><s>Whereas neither individual stereocilia in the bundles nor the bundles themselves showed any obvious defects (erect, normal three-row staircase pattern, normal height gradation, all three rows with normal extent and undisturbed packing and no distortions in the row linearity or any gaps; Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">S4</ref>), we observed a broader range of orientation angles of OHC stereocilia bundles in cochlea of young adult Cobl KO mice (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5A and 5B</ref>).</s><s>Quantitation of orientation angles of stereocilia bundles according to literature procedures (absolute deviations from 0 ) (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Dabdoub et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Copley et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ezan et al., 2013)</ref> showed a less regular alignment in Cobl KO cochleae when compared to WT.</s><s>The orientation deviations reached 13 (OHC3) and were 40%-70% above WT and highly statistically significant in all three OHC rows (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5D</ref>).</s><s>Interestingly, Cobl KO hereby led to a superimposition of two effects (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5E-5G and  S5</ref>).</s><s>First, the ranges of orientations of OHC stereocilia were increased, as shown by measuring the total range of angle distributions.</s><s>In absolute numbers, the ranges of deviations from the corresponding means were 18-20 , that is, 37%-69% larger than in WT (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5H and S5</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Second, in contrast to the often erratically directed deviations found upon disrupting embryonic PCP signaling (e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Copley et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ezan et al., 2013)</ref>, the orientation deficits in Cobl KO mice showed directionality of the deviations.</s><s>Cobl KO OHCs showed a general rotational distortion of stereocilia bundles toward the apical turn of the cochlea (+).</s><s>This rotation was in clear contrast to WT, which rather displayed rotations toward the basal turn (À) (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5I-5K</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Kinocilia and/or basal body disruptions in, for example, Kif3a, Bbs8, and Ift20 KO coincided with impairments in cochlear development and were linked to grossly misoriented stereocilia bundles indicative of disrupted embryonic PCP signaling <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Sipe and Lu, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">May-Simera et al., 2015)</ref>.</s><s>It was therefore of utmost importance to clarify whether the stereociliar orientation defects seen in young adult Cobl KO mice represent defects in classical embryonic PCP.</s><s>Interestingly, this was not the case.</s><s>Scanning EM demonstrated that OHC stereocilia bundles in newborn (P2) Cobl KO pups were correctly located, orientated, and aligned after the completion of embryonic development (Figures S6A-S6I).</s></p><p><s>Only row 3 OHCs showed a widened range of distributions, which may reflect the fact that OHC maturation follows a gradient from OHC1 to OHC3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Frolenkov et al., 2004</ref>) (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">S6F-S6I</ref>).</s><s>However, in average, the OHCs of all three rows were orientated around 0 in both Cobl KO and WT newborns (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">S6J-S6L</ref>).</s><s>This average orientation is in line with a report describing a minor, postnatal minus-directed rotation of specifically OHC3 stereocilia bundles between P0 and P4 with OHC3s being orientated close to 0 at P4 <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Copley et al., 2013)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Consistent with undisturbed classical embryonic PCP signaling and successful distinction between distal and proximal sides, also the PCP markers Par6b and aPKC <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Ezan and Montcouquiol, 2013)</ref> were properly localized to the proximal side in both WT and Cobl KO OHCs (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">S6M and S6N</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Taken together, classical embryonic PCP signaling seems not to be affected by Cobl KO.</s><s>This provided an excellent opportunity to unveil postnatal processes important for stereocilia bundle orientation.</s><s>Our examinations clearly unveiled two PCP refinement processes that operate postnatally, general narrowing of angle deviations and directed rotation.</s><s>The postnatal narrowing of the orientation ranges from 33.2 in P2 to only 25.9 in adult WT OHC1s was completely impaired in Cobl KO mice (P2, 40.0 ; adult OHC1s, 43.8 ; Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">S6I</ref> versus Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5H</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Furthermore, orientations already successfully obtained by classical embryonic PCP signaling were not maintained in Cobl KO cochleae after birth.</s><s>The orientation range of 42.4 for newborn Cobl KO OHC2s subsequently widened to 62.3 in adult OHC2s.</s><s>OHC2 in adult Cobl KO cochleae thereby reached levels of misalignment almost as severe as those observed for OHC3s (67.7 ) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">S6I</ref> versus Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5H</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cobl-Dependent Postnatal PCP Refinements Are Executed during Cochlear Maturation Preceding Hearing Onset</head><p><s>Since PCP has to be actively maintained lifelong instead of being a robust tissue achievement provided by embryonic PCP signaling, we asked whether phenotypes seen in adult mice exclusively reflect maintenance defects during hearing or reflect impairments of postnatal refinements.</s><s>We therefore conducted scanning EM analyses of P8 cochleae.</s><s>At this stage, the auditory canal is still closed (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6A and 6B</ref>) and the middle ear still filled with fluid.</s><s>Interestingly, although not yet exposed to the physical stresses of sound, the ranges of stereocilia bundle deviations were already increased in the OHCs of Cobl KO pups (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6C</ref>).</s><s>Also, stereocilia bundle orientations in all three P8 OHC rows already showed a directed shift toward positive directions as in adult cochleae.</s><s>The absolute differences were less  pronounced (about 2 each) than at later times.</s><s>However, already at P8, they were statistically highly significant in all rows (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">6D-6I</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Cobl therefore plays an important role in postnatal PCP refinements that are part of a cochlear maturation program initiated prior to hearing onset.</s></p><p><s>Cobl KO Mice Show Hearing Impairments Reflecting Defects in the Cochlear Amplifier Finally, we addressed whether the defects in the orientations of OHC stereocilia bundles may be associated with any defects in integrity and functionality of the cochlea.</s><s>The OHC arrays of cochleae from WT and Cobl KO mice showed that Cobl KO cochleae were not marked by array distortions by insertions of extra OHCs.</s><s>Also distortions by lacking OHCs (free positions in array, gaps) were not frequent (2%-4%) and mostly comparable to irregularities also occurring in WT cochlear arrays.</s><s>Only in OHC row 3, an increased frequency of gaps (1.5% in WT versus 4% in KO) became statistically significant in Cobl KO mice .</s><s>Since these findings were correlated with OHC3 also showing the severest early misrotations (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">S6F-S6I</ref>), the slightly increased gap frequency in row 3 may suggest that misorientations of the sensory apparatus are mechanically detrimental for hair cell integrity.</s><s>The observed gaps indeed reflected a lack of the entire OHC at the respective array position (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">S7E and S7F</ref>), as it, for example, also occurs during age-related hearing loss <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Bowl and Dawson, 2015)</ref>.</s><s>A trend toward a loss of hair cells was also observed for IHCs, whereas insertions again were at WT levels (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">S7G and S7H</ref>).</s></p><p><s>At P2, however, no hair cell gaps were observed (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">S7I</ref>).</s><s>The gaps observed in adult Cobl KO cochleae are thus unrelated to classical embryonic PCP signaling defects but represent lowfrequency deletions from previously properly patterned arrays.</s></p><p><s>Whereas Cobl KO did not seem to have effects on the integrity of hair cells that go much beyond the slow hair cell loss that also occurs with age, distortions in the carefully aligned cochlear array are more likely to have direct physiological consequences for hearing.</s><s>To address this, we first excluded that Cobl KO mice may suffer from general hearing loss.</s><s>The general waveform of evoked responses in auditory brainstem response (ABR) measurements was unaffected (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">7A</ref>).</s><s>Also the latencies and the amplitudes of the individual ABR waves were not significantly different between Cobl KO and WT littermates for click stimulation ranging from 10 to 80 dB (not shown).</s><s>ABR thresholds to tone burst stimulation were only mildly elevated, especially for low-frequency stimuli, such as 4 kHz (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">7B</ref>).</s><s>Thus, general sound detection was not strongly impaired but at low frequencies showed some defects.</s></p><p><s>We next analyzed cochlear amplification.</s><s>In the healthy cochlea, electromotility of OHCs leads to enhanced basilar membrane vibrations, which are back-propagated through the middle ear and can be measured as otoacoustic emissions.</s><s>Over the entire frequency range, the intensities of distortion product otoacoustic emissions (DPOAEs) from adult (12-14 weeks) Cobl KO mice consistently were significantly lower than those of WT mice (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">7C</ref>).</s><s>Cobl may contribute to shaping the tonotopic spread of cochlear amplification, for which distorsion product otoacoustic emissions are a sensitive measure.</s><s>Taken together, the Cobl KO-mediated defects in cochlear arrays are accompanied by defective cochlear amplification.</s><s>Together, our data unveil that Cobl is critical for in part previously unnoticed, postnatal PCP refinement processes and for correlated structural organizations beneath stereocilia, which are important for proper functioning of the cochlear amplifier during hearing (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">7D</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>The organ of Corti is a highly organized array of sensory cells generated by different developmental cell polarity programs.</s></p><p><s>Here, we report that KO of the actin nucleator Cobl leads to defects in postnatal PCP refinement and to impaired OHC amplifier function in hearing.</s></p><p><s>Analyses of Cobl KO mice unveiled the existence of a specialized, Cobl-dependent F-actin subset in OHCs.</s><s>F-actin formation in OHCs was required for proper PCM organization.</s><s>The specific Cobl function identified is in line with Cobl being an evolutionary young, vertebrate-specific actin nucleator.</s><s>In addition, Cobl functions may be backed up by its distant relative Cobl-like <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Izadi et al., 2018)</ref>.</s><s>In contrast to the specialized functions of Cobl beneath the sensory structures of OHCs, the general F-actinrich cell cortex represents a very basic cell-biological structure and can be expected to depend on actin nucleators, which are evolutionarily much older and less specialized.</s></p><p><s>The identified Cobl-dependent substereociliar F-actin subset seemed to be distinct from the F-actin bundles in OHC stereocilia, which protrude into the cell cortex as rootlets conferring stereocilia stability and proper morphology <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Tilney et al., 1980;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">Kitajiri et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">Vranceanu et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">Szarama et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>Stereociliar length is sensitive to changes in F-actin bundling and dynamics.</s><s>Loss of F-actin-bundling proteins localized to the stereocilia core usually causes stereocilia degeneration.</s><s>Interference with actin cytoskeletal components localized to the tips of stereocilia, such as the myosin XVa/whirlin/eps8 complex, reduces stereociliar length and diminishes the height differences between stereocilia rows <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Manor et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Ebrahim et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>Interferences with proteins at the stereociliar base, such as CLIC5 and ERM proteins, lead to stereocilia enlargement and fusion <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Salles et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>Finally, deletion of band g-actin severely shortened stereocilia and led to losses of individual stereocilia, respectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Perrin et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b31">McGrath et al., 2017)</ref>.</s><s>At the physiological level, such defects are associated with fast progressive hearing loss or deafness at birth.</s><s>Our analyses showed that Cobl KO did not lead to any of such more classical phenotypes.</s><s>Instead, Cobl KO phenotypes affected the cuticular plate actin cytoskeleton and structures embedded in it (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">7D</ref> for summary).</s></p><p><s>The identified, very specific role of Cobl in OHCs is in line with Cobl's relatively high abundance in inner ear OHCs and especially in the cuticular plate.</s><s>The decrease of Cobl-dependent, substereociliar F-actin in the cuticular plate was accompanied with several hair cell phenotypes.</s><s>Cobl KO led to an impaired organization of the PCM of OHCs.</s><s>These impairments were observed both prior and during the critical postnatal period of structural and functional maturation of the cochlea prior to onset of hearing (P8).</s><s>Importantly, they were F-actin formation dependent as demonstrated by latrunculin A-mediated inhibition of F-actin formation in WT cochleae.</s><s>Interestingly, proper PCM organization furthermore turned out to be dependent on Ca 2+ /calmodulin signaling.</s><s>That both different inhibitors are phenocopying the PCM organization defects in Cobl KO is consistent with Cobl being (1) an actin nucleator <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Ahuja et al., 2007)</ref> and (2) Ca 2+ /calmodulin controlled <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Hou et al., 2015)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>These defects were accompanied by a loss of the spatial correlation of the centrioles, which are encased by the disorganized PCM.</s><s>This Cobl KO phenotype may be in line with a suggested role of F-actin in centriole positioning <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Tang and Marshall, 2012)</ref> and maybe also with recent reports describing some cross talk of centrosomes with the actin cytoskeleton-at least in less adherent cells, such as Jurkat, RPE1 cells and lymphocytes <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Farina et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Obino et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>We demonstrate the importance of the actin nucleator Cobl for the spatial organization of the PCM encasing the centriole-derived basal body of OHC kinocilia in the cochlea.</s></p><p><s>Mechanistically, it seems likely that Cobl-dependent, rather dynamic F-actin structures beneath the sensory apparatus help to encase and thereby spatially constrain the PCM.</s><s>A rather static F-actin scaffold directly in the PCM to properly build the PCM or prevent the PCM from fragmentation seems unlikely because no F-actin can be observed in the PCM volume.</s><s>It will therefore be interesting to evaluate whether Cobl has interaction partners in the PCM and/or at the basal body that may help to promote Cobl-mediated F-actin formation around the PCM.</s><s>The PCM relations to cortical F-actin that we observed may furthermore relate to recent reports describing some sort of structural connections emanating from microtubular structures in the cuticular plate <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Antonellis et al., 2014)</ref>, some cross talk of the actin cytoskeleton with cilia during their embryonic migration <ref type="bibr">(Ezan et al., 2013)</ref>, RNAi against the PCM component PCM1 affecting the cloud-like F-actin mesh around related microtubule-based structures (centrosomes) in Jurkat cells, and the ability of isolated centrosomes to grow actin asters in vitro <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Farina et al., 2016)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>While the physiological relevance of the latter findings for centrosomes await further examinations, our data clearly show that Cobl-mediated disruption of cortical F-actin and of pericentriolar organization is linked to cell-biological processes that underlie the proper spatial arrangement of the sensory structures of OHCs.</s><s>First, the distance of the disorganized PCM to the axoneme of the kinocilium was increased.</s><s>Second, the distance of the PCM to the stereocilia bundle tip was increased.</s><s>Accordingly, these defects coincided with an impaired spatial correlation of the normally intimately linked kinocilium base and the stereocilia bundle in Cobl KO mice.</s><s>It seems possible that the defects in basal body docking of the kinocilium with the stereocilia lead to the observed premature loss of kinocilia in Cobl KO mice during the critical time period prior to hearing onset (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">7D</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Cobl KO-mediated defects in kinocilium maintenance were observed at P8 and P9.</s><s>This is in line with the observation that the Cobl KO defects in stereocilia bundle orientation also did not occur during classical embryonic PCP signaling, which is critical for PCP establishment and rough alignment of sensory cells prior to birth, but almost exclusively manifested postnatally.</s><s>This provided an excellent possibility to specifically unveil thus far largely unknown postnatal planar polarity processes occurring subsequent to embryonic PCP establishment.</s><s>In mutant mice lacking the functions of classical core PCP components, such as Frizzled or Celsr1, postnatal refinements are difficult to reveal because they are masked by the severe embryonal defects <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(Wang et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Curtin et al., 2003)</ref>.</s><s>Comparisons of WT and Cobl KO cochleae from P2 and adult mice at ultra-high resolution clearly demonstrated that stereocilia bundle positioning angles are refined after birth to reach an even more aligned status in mature cochleae.</s><s>An existence of postnatal refinement processes has already been suggested in earlier studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Dabdoub et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Copley et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Our work shows that postnatal refinement narrowing the spread of orientation angles is completely disrupted upon Cobl KO.</s></p><p><s>Interestingly, all Cobl KO defects manifested before hearing onset, that is, between P2 and P8.</s><s>During this time frame, hair cells are just probing transmission by self-activation <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Johnson et al., 2013)</ref>, but the hearing channel is still closed, the middle ear is still filled with fluid, and outside sounds cannot reach the inner ear.</s><s>Thus, all forms of postnatal refinement we identified studying Cobl KO mice thus seem to be cochlea-autonomous processes independent of the physical pressures of sound.</s></p><p><s>Our analyses of Cobl KO mice furthermore revealed that the angle deviation status successfully reached by the embryonic PCP program has to be actively maintained after birth.</s><s>The fact that both maintenance of embryonic PCP achievements and further postnatal refinements (angle fine-tuning and rotational refinement) are Cobl dependent strongly suggests that these processes are mechanistically related (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">7D</ref>).</s></p><p><s>The existence of postnatal planar polarity refinement and maintenance processes independent from classical embryonic PCP unraveled by Cobl KO is further supported by a previous observation of unknown, Vangl2-independent patterning mechanisms operating postnatally in cochleae from mice lacking the PCP core component Vangl2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Montcouquiol et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Copley et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Parallel, somewhat related, but independent functions of Vangl2 and Cobl may finally also provide an explanation for Vangl2's genetic interaction with the Coblc101 gene trap mutation <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Carroll et al., 2003)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The finding that misorientation of stereocilia bundles in Cobl KO worsened after hearing onset suggests that Cobl-mediated processes actively counteract the mechanical stress occurring during mechanotransduction and thereby prevent rotational shifts of the tip of the V-shaped bundle toward the apical turn of the cochlea.</s><s>Thus, the achievements of embryonic PCP signaling have to be both refined and actively maintained after birth.</s></p><p><s>Two findings underscore the physiological importance of the postnatal processes executed by Cobl in the inner ear.</s><s>First, OHC3, which showed the strongest defect in rotational refinement and premature kinocilium retraction during the critical time window of hearing onset, also showed the highest frequency in hair cell deletions in adult Cobl KO mice.</s><s>Cobl-dependent postnatal refinements thus seem important for withstanding the mechanical stress during mechanotransduction after the onset of hearing and thereby ensure the integrity of the organ of Corti.</s><s>It is therefore likely that defects in refinement and maintenance processes, such as those dependent on Cobl, are one of the cellular causes underlying the insidious loss of hair cells in age-related hearing loss.</s></p><p><s>Second, our analyses of otoacoustic emissions of Cobl KO mice showed that distortions of stereocilia bundle orientations caused by impaired, Cobl-dependent planar polarity refinement processes, which were linked to impaired PCM organization, were accompanied with disrupted alignment of the kinocilium with the stereociliar bundle, and with premature kinocilia retraction, and coincided with defects in the cochlear amplifier.</s></p><p><s>Thus, the ability to execute Cobl-dependent processes, which precisely fine-tune stereocilia bundle orientations postnatally to ensure a correct patterning of the inner ear sensory epithelium, is essential for cochlear amplification during hearing.</s><s>STAR+METHODS Doxsey, S.J., <ref type="bibr">Stein, P., Evans, L., Calarco, P.D., and Kirschner, M. (1994)</ref>.</s><s>Pericentrin, a highly conserved centrosome protein involved in microtubule organization.</s><s>Cell 76, 639-650.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>STAR+METHODS KEY RESOURCES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONTACT FOR REAGENT AND RESOURCE SHARING</head><p><s>Further information and requests for resources and reagents should be directed to and will be fulfilled by the Lead Contact, Michael Kessels (Michael.Kessels@med.uni-jena.de).</s></p><p><s>EXPERIMENTAL MODEL AND SUBJECT DETAILS E. coli Strain XL10 Gold E. coli strain XL10 Gold (Stratagene/Agilent) (genomic information: endA1 glnV44 recA1 thi-1 gyrA96 relA1 lac Hte D(mcrA)183 D(mcrCB-hsdSMR-mrr)173 tet R F'[proAB lacI q ZDM15 Tn10(Tet R Amy Cm R )]) was used for DNA plasmid amplifications.</s><s>The strain was grown in LB-medium (Carl Roth GmbH &amp; Co.KG) or on LB-agar (Carl Roth GmbH &amp; Co.KG) with or without the respective antibiotics, which the strain carries resistances for (10 mg/ml tetracycline, 30 mg/ml chloramphenicol) or (if transformed) which the strain obtained resistances for by plasmid uptake (usually either 100 mg/ml ampicillin or 25 mg/ml kanamycin).</s><s>The strain was usually either grown at 37 C or at RT. Ubiquitously Cre recombinase expressing mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Schwenk et al., 1995)</ref> were used for Cobl exon11 deletion.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. coli</head><p><s>Cobl KO mouse generation and backcrossings were done using C57BL/6J mice.</s></p><p><s>Cobl KO C57BL/6J::129/SvJ mice (99.7::0.3)</s><s>were analyzed for cochlear defects.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHOD DETAILS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Generation of Cobl KO Mice</head><p><s>The targeting vector was generated using a clone isolated from a 129/SvJ mouse genomic l library (Agilent).</s><s>An approximately 10 kb EcoRV fragment of this clone including exons 11-12 of the Cobl gene (GenBank: NC_000077.5,</s><s>Mus musculus, chromosome 11) was cloned into the SmaI site of the pKO-DTA plasmid (Lexicon Genetics) with a phosphoglycerate kinase promoter-driven diphtheria toxin A cassette as a negative selection marker.</s><s>A phosphoglycerate kinase promoter-driven neomycin resistance cassette (positive selection marker) flanked by frt sites and a loxP site was inserted into the AflII site of intron 10.</s><s>A second loxP site together with an additional BamHI site was inserted into the SwaI site of intron 11.</s><s>R1 mouse embryonic stem (ES) cells were electroporated with the NotI-linearized targeting vector.</s><s>Genomic DNA of 288 Neomycin-resistant ES cell clones was screened by Southern blot with a P 32labeled DNA probe (379 bp, nt 213457-213835, GenBank: NC_000077.5)</s><s>after BamHI restriction (WT fragment: 9.3 kbp, nt 205809-215151; transgene fragment: 6.2 kbp, 208983-215151).</s><s>One correctly targeted ES cell clone (B8) was injected into C57BL/6 blastocysts to generate chimeras.</s><s>Cobl KO mice were obtained via mating with mice ubiquitously expressing Cre recombinase <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Schwenk et al., 1995)</ref> to remove exon11 together with the selection cassette.</s><s>Germline transmission successfully gave rise to a mouse line lacking the actin nucleator Cobl.</s></p><p><s>For genotyping, DNA of mouse tail biopsies was extracted with 10 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 100 mM NaCl, 0.4 mg/ml proteinase K.</s><s>After inactivation (10 min, 95 C), a high-speed supernatant was analyzed by PCR (fwd-primer F1 acacagccctggcatcat, rev-primers R1 (atacgggcaatcacgttttc) and R2 (tgctccacactgaggtgttc)). Primer combination F1/R1 amplified a 388 bp WT allele and primer combination F1/R2 a 235 bp KO allele.</s></p><p><s>The generation of Cobl KO mice and initial characterization was performed in strict compliance with the EU guidelines for animal experiments and was approved by the local government (permission number: 02-011/10; Th€ uringer Landesamt, Bad Langensalza; Germany).</s></p><p><s>Hearing physiological animal procedures were approved by the Niedersa ¨chsiches Landesamt f€ ur Verbraucherschutz und Lebensmittelsicherheit Oldenburg (permission number 33.9-42502-04-11/0415).</s></p><p><s>Experiments were done with both male and female mice 3-16 weeks (body weight) and with 12-14 weeks old male and female mice (hearing physiology), respectively.</s></p><p><s>Animals were kept in a C57BL/6J::129/SvJ (99,7::0,3) genetic background, bred heterozygously and housed under 14 h light/10 h dark conditions with ad libitum access to food and water.</s><s>KO cochleae costained with anti-pericentrin antibodies (PCM marker) and phalloidin (stereocilia marker) were evaluated in a blinded manner.</s><s>The evaluations of the presence or absence of anti-acetylated tubulin-stained kinocilium were done in 3D.</s><s>n-numbers of OHCs evaluated: P2, 407 <ref type="bibr">WT and 463 KO OHCs,</ref><ref type="bibr">8 WT and 8 KO images,</ref><ref type="bibr">4 WT and 4 KO animals. P6,</ref><ref type="bibr">387 WT and 280 KO OHCs,</ref><ref type="bibr">25 WT and 17 KO images,</ref><ref type="bibr">2 animals each. P8,</ref><ref type="bibr">692 WT and 769 KO OHCs,</ref><ref type="bibr">20 WT and 22 KO images,</ref><ref type="bibr">5 animals each. P9,</ref><ref type="bibr">444 WT and 557 KO OHCs,</ref><ref type="bibr">29 WT and 33 KO images,</ref><ref type="bibr">2 animals each. P15,</ref><ref type="bibr">120 WT and 175 KO OHCs,</ref><ref type="bibr">11 WT and 17 KO images,</ref><ref type="bibr">3 WT and 6 KO animals.</ref></s><s>PCM analyses in WT and Cobl KO mice (P2, P8) were conducted by quantitative determinations of volume, sum intensity of anti-pericentrin labeling (i.e., integration of all fluorescence signals in the volume defined by 3D surface rendering) and density of anti-pericentrin labeling (average fluorescence signal per mm 3 ) in computed so-called 3D-surfaces (which represent the volume of the anti-pericentrin-marked PCM) that were obtained by surface rendering of confocal z stacks of the apico-medial turn of whole-mount preparations of P2 and P8 WT and Cobl KO cochleae costained with anti-acetylated tubulin antibodies (to correlate pericentrin PCM localization with the adjacent kinocilium) and with phalloidin (to mark the stereocilia bundle) using Imaris software (Bitplane) (absolute intensity, smooth 0.1).</s><s>The n-numbers of kinociliar base structures evaluated were as follows: P2, 367 WT and 391 KO OHCs, 7 WT and 7 KO images, 4 WT and 4 KO animals.</s><s>P8, 692 WT and 769 KO OHCs, 20 WT and 22 KO images, 5 animals each.</s></p><p><s>For further mechanistic analyses, P8 WT cochleae were incubated with the CaM inhibitors W7 (10 mM, 2 h, 0.1% DMSO final), CGS9343B (CGS, 10 mM, 2 h, RT, 0.1% DMSO final) and latrunculin A (LatA) (1 mM, 30 min, RT, 0.02% DMSO final), respectively, in DMEM/10% FCS (37 C, 5% CO2) prior to fixation.</s><s>Evaluated were n = 63 OHCs (0.1%-DMSO-treated), 44 OHCs (W7) and 269 OHCs (CGS) from 3 P8 WT animals/cochleae per CaM inhibitor condition.</s><s>In the LatA-treatments, n = 191 OHCs (DMSO) and 223 OHCs (LatA) from 4 P8 WT animals/cochleae per condition were evaluated.</s></p><p><s>Intercentriolar distances were analyzed in confocal z stacks of anti-g-tubulin, anti-pericentrin and phalloidin-stained P2 cochleae subjected to anti-g-tubulin surface rendering.</s><s>The n-numbers of OHCs evaluated were: WT OHC3, 31; KO OHC3, 50; WT OHC2, 21; KO OHC2, 27; WT OHC1, 9; KO OHC1, 20 from 3 animals/cochleae each.</s><s>The analyses were conducted by independent researchers in a fully blinded manner.</s></p><p><s>Measurements of the distance between the apical pole of the pericentrin-marked PCM and the base of the kinocilium (PCM-KC base distance) were also done in 3D surface renderings based on stacks of confocal images from mouse cochlear whole-mounts using IMARIS software.</s><s>Cochleae were costained with phalloidin to visualize the stereocilia bundle and with anti-acetylated tubulin antibodies marking the kinocilium.</s><s>Control experiments (coimmunolabelings) showed that anti-acetylated tubulin antibodies marked the kinocilium of OHCs similar to antibodies directed against the ciliary marker Arl13b.</s><s>The n-numbers of PCM-KC base distance determinations were: 56-75 OHCs/row; total, 175 WT OHCs, 219 KO OHCs from 4 animals/genotype.</s></p><p><s>The distance from the PCM to the base of the stereocilia (SC) bundle tip was determined in 3D surface renderings of anti-pericentrin and phalloidin-stained cochlear whole-mounts (surface to surface measurements, as above, using IMARIS software).</s><s>The n-numbers were: 49-75 OHCs/row; total, 171 WT OHCs, 224 KO OHCs; 4 animals/genotype.</s></p><p><s>The PCM distance from the symmetry axis of the stereocilia bundle was evaluated using the same 3D surface renderings.</s><s>Top views were imaged and two perpendicular lines were drawn to mark the base of the V-shaped bundle and the perpendicular symmetry axis going through the tip of the stereocilia bundle.</s><s>Distances between PCM (surface) and symmetry axis were determined in (in absolute values; using ImageJ).</s><s>The n-numbers were: 221 WT OHCs, 234 KO OHCs from 4 animals/each genotype.</s></p><p><s>For frequency analyses of different phenotypes, the proportion of KO OHCs with data above the WT mean was plotted.</s></p><p><s>For neural tube and floor plate immunostainings, E9.5 WT and KO embryos were fixed with PFA (4% in PBS pH 7.4, 2 h at 4 C), cryoprotected (10% and 30% sucrose, o/n, 4 C), embedded in Tissue-Tek O.C.T. Compound (Sakura Finetek), cut transversely (section thickness, 16 mm) and subjected to immunohistochemistry as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Haag et al., 2012)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scanning EM and Quantitative Analyses of Hair Bundle Morphology</head><p><s>Dissected cochleae were immediately perfused with PBS and with pre-warmed fixative (2.5% glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M sodium cacodylate buffer pH 7.4).</s><s>Cochleae were then immersion-fixed in the same fixative at RT (2 h) and at 4 C (o/n).</s><s>Subsequently, the cochlear blocks were washed, dehydrated (ethanol series), critical point dried with liquid CO2 (CPD300, Leica), mounted on sample holders and post-dissected (removal of the bony shell as well as Reissner's and tectorial membranes) to expose the organ of Corti.</s></p><p><s>The specimen were sputtered with gold (SCD005 BAL-TEC) and examined with a field emission scanning EM (LEO1530, Zeiss; operated at 10 keV).</s><s>All quantitative analyses were conducted in a fully blinded manner.</s></p><p><s>The number of inserted and deleted IHCs and OHCs were determined per 1000.</s><s>Adult animals (12-15 weeks): WT, n = 7 animals/ cochleae; KO n = 6 animals/cochleae (each with 17-53 pictures/cochlea and 101-356 IHCs/animal, 352-1129 OHCs/animal).</s><s>P2 animals: n = 4 animals/cochleae per genotype (each with 11-57 pictures/cochlea and 20-250 IHCs/animal, 320-1651 OHCs/animal).</s></p><p><s>Scanning EM fine structure analyses of adult stereocilia bundles comprised assessments of the number of stereocilia per outer row (i.e., the tallest row) of the V-shaped bundle, row organization (number of stereocilia rows; supposed to be invariantly 3), missing stereocilia (visible as gaps), packing densities and positioning patterns (stacking) of stereocilia within the bundles, stereociliar heights (in tilts of the samples in the scanning EM; heights evaluated i) in absolute values (longest row) and ii) relative from row to row (gradation)).</s><s>n = 32 WT and 31 KO OHC stereocilia bundles were evaluated.</s><s>Measurements of length were done in n = 301 (WT) and n = 246 (KO) tallest-row stereocilia (from 4 WT and 4 KO mice and 2-10 stereocilia bundles/animal).</s></p><p><s>To measure OHC bundle orientation, the two ends of each individual V-shaped cilia bundle were connected and the deviation of this line from the 0 axis defined by the cell borders of row 1 OHCs and the Inner Pillar cells (0 axis, see scheme in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">5C</ref>) was determined.</s></p><p><s>Averaged stereocilia bundle orientations (bundle deviations from 0 C) were calculated by using the modulus of the orientation angles, i.e., irrespective of direction.</s><s>This literature procedure was complemented by additional analyses, in which the direction of deviation was considered, too.</s></p><p><s>The distributions of stereocilia bundle orientations in adult WT and Cobl KO cochleae were plotted as percentage of hair cell bundles in a given deviation angle class with steps of 5 (considering the direction of deviation from 0 C).</s></p><p><s>Quantitative determinations of the ranges of stereocilia orientation angles were calculated considering 98% of the angles closest to mean.</s></p><p><s>For all the above detailed stereociliar orientation analyses, the n-numbers for adult mice (12-15 weeks) were n = 4 animals/ cochleae each genotype, 17-53 pictures/cochlea, 141-916 OHCs/animal and 705-874 hair cell bundles/row.</s><s>For P8 pups, the n-numbers were n = 5 WT/3 KO P8 animals/cochleae, 14-51 images/cochleae, 302-1246 OHCs/animal and 1172-1354 hair cell bundles/row.</s><s>For P2 pups, the n-numbers were n = 4 animals/cochleae each genotype, 11-57 pictures/cochleae, 111-413 OHCs/animal and 382-437 hair cell bundles/row.</s></p><p><s>The spatial correlation of the kinocilium position in relation to the stereocilia bundle of was addressed for P2 OHCs by measuring the distances between the bases of the kinocilium and the first side stereocilium of the V-shaped structure in top views of cochlear arrays.</s><s>Although this type of measurement may grossly under-evaluate increases in the distance between kinocilium and the central tip stereocilia of the bundle (the V-shaped bundles usually show indented tips, i.e., do not exhibit a pointed V shape) -e.g., a doubling of the distance may only lead to about 30% in the measurements of the neighboring side of the triangle formed between central ''tip'' stereocilium, kinocilium and the first side stereocilium when tips are broad -these measurements were most useful, as the distance between first side stereocilium and kinocilium could always reliably be addressed, whereas sight on the base of the central tip stereocilium is often blocked due to the tip indention of the stereocilia bundle.</s><s>Analyzed were n = 60 OHCs/row from 4 animals/cochleae each genotype.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recordings of Auditory Brainstem Response and DPOAE</head><p><s>The physiological examinations of hearing thresholds and cochlear amplification were essentially done as described before <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Jing et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>In brief, 12-14 weeks old animals (male and female) were anesthetized intraperitoneally with a combination of ketamine (125 mg/kg) and xylazine (2.5 mg/kg).</s><s>The heart rate was monitored constantly and the core temperature was maintained constant at 37 C using a rectal temperature-controlled heating blanket (Hugo Sachs Elektronik; Harvard Apparatus).</s></p><p><s>For stimulus generation, presentation, and data acquisition a TDT System II (Tucker-Davis Technologies) run by BioSig32 software (TDT) was used.</s><s>Sound pressure levels are provided in dB SPL RMS (tonal stimuli) or dB SPL peak equivalent (PE, clicks) and were calibrated using a 1/4 00 microphone (Br€ uel &amp; Kjaer).</s><s>Tone bursts (12 kHz, 10 ms plateau, 1 ms cos2 rise/fall) or clicks of 0.03 ms were presented at 20 Hz or 100 Hz in the free field ipsilaterally using a JBL 2402 speaker <ref type="bibr">(JBL &amp; Co.)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The difference potential between vertex and mastoid subdermal needles was amplified (50,000 times), filtered (low pass: 4 kHz, high pass: 400 Hz) and sampled at a rate of 50 kHz for 20 ms, 2 3 2000 times to obtain two mean auditory brainstem responses (ABRs) for each sound intensity.</s></p><p><s>Hearing thresholds were determined with 10 dB precision as the lowest stimulus intensity that evoked a reproducible response waveform in both traces by visual inspection.</s></p><p><s>For DPOAEs, MF1 speakers (Tucker-Davis) were used to generate two primary tones (frequency ratio f2/f1: 1.2, intensity f2 = intensity f1 + 10 dB).</s><s>Primary tones were coupled into the ear canal by a custom-made probe containing an MKE-2 microphone (Sennheiser) and adjusted to the desired sound intensities at the position of the ear drum as mimicked in a mouse ear coupler.</s></p><p><s>The microphone signal was amplified and digitalized (DMX 6 Fire; Terratec) and analyzed by fast Fourier transformation (MATLAB; MathWorks).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>QUANTIFICATION AND STATISTICAL ANALYSIS</head><p><s>No statistical methods were used to predetermine sample size.</s><s>All quantitative data shown represent mean and SEM.</s><s>Statistical analyses were done using GraphPad Prism software using the tests specified in the figure legends.</s><s>Comparisons of two conditions were tested by either D'Agostino normality test/Mann Whitney U or unpaired t test (normal data distribution).</s><s>Multiple comparisons were tested by two-way-ANOVA with post-test (Tukey's, Sidak's, Bonferroni's).</s><s>Connected datasets were analyzed using 1way ANOVA with post-test (Dunnett's, Dunn's).</s></p><p><s>Statistical significances were marked by * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01 and *** p &lt; 0.001 throughout.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DATA AND SOFTWARE AVAILABILITY</head><p><s>Original datasets are available at https://data.mendeley.com</s><s>(https://doi.org/10.17632/rypw3jv8mj.1).</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Cobl KO Mice Show a Lack of a Specific Cortical F-Actin Subset Residing beneath the Sensory Apparatus of OHCs in the Inner Ear</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,89.01,101.59,418.28,469.53" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>(N) Anti-Cobl ARA antibodies detect Cobl but no putative truncated protein or DE10-15 variant (see Figures S1A-S1C) in brain.</s><s>(O-U) Blinded F-actin analyses in WT (O) and Cobl KO cochlear whole-mount preparations (P8) (P) using line scans across the cuticular plate at substereociliar (line 1) and stereocilia-free positions (line 2).</s><s>Dashed lines, cuticular plate borders (O).</s><s>Bar, 2 mm.</s><s>(Q) OHC3 cuticular plate thicknesses.</s><s>(R-U) Mean phalloidin intensities (R and T) and distribution of phalloidin intensities (S and U) in line 1 (R and S) and in line 2 scans (T and U) of n = WT/KO 33/33 OHC3s; 3/4 animals.</s><s>Data, mean and SEM.</s><s>(R) ***p &lt; 0.001 (unpaired, two-tailed t test).</s><s>(S) *p &lt; 0.05 (two-way ANOVA/Sidak's test).</s><s>See also Figure S1.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Cobl KO Causes an Impaired Kinociliar Base Organization that Is Phenocopied by Inhibition of F-Actin Formation and Ca 2+ /CaM Signaling in WT Cochlea</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>A-D) MIPs of whole-mount preparations (A and C) and corresponding 3D surface renderings (B and D) of P8 WT (A and B) and Cobl KO (C and D) cochleae (green, pericentrin; blue, phalloidin).</s><s>(E-G) Analyses of PCMs for volume (E), sum intensity (F), and density (sum intensity/volume) (G) of anti-pericentrin labeling.</s><s>n = WT/KO 692/769 OHCs, 20/22 images, 5 animals each.</s><s>(H-T) Corresponding analyses with cochleae of P8 WT mice incubated with DMSO (control) (H, I, L-N, O, and R-T), latrunculin A (LatA) (J-N), and with the CaM inhibitors CGS9343B (CGS) (P and R-T) and W7 (Q-T).</s><s>Bars, 1 mm (A, C, H, J, and O-Q) and 5 mm (B, D, I, and K).</s><s>(L-N and R-T) Quantitative analyses of anti-pericentrin signals.</s><s>n = 44-269 OHCs and 3-4 WT P8 cochleae/condition.</s><s>Data, mean + SEM.</s><s>***p &lt; 0.001.</s><s>Two-way ANOVA/Tukey's (E-G and L-N) and one-way ANOVA/Dunnett's (R-T).</s><s>White arrowheads (A, C, H, J, and O-Q) mark PCMs (confirmed by associated kinociliar anti-acetylated tubulin labeling; not shown).</s><s>See also Figure S2.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. Cobl KO Leads to Increased Intercentriolar Distance, Disrupted PCM-to-Kinocilium Base Alignment, and Premature Kinocilium Regression prior to Hearing Onset (A-C) Analyses of intercentriolar distances in 3D reconstructions of antig-tubulin labelings (centriolar marker) costained for PCMs (anti-pericentrin) and stereocilia bundles (phalloidin) in P2 Cobl KO OHCs compared to WT (A and B).</s><s>(C) Quantitative analyses of n = WT/KO 61/97 OHCs; 3/3 cochleae and mice.</s><s>(D-I) Analyses of PCM-to-kinocilium (PCM-KC) base distances in 3D surface renderings of anti-acetylated tubulin (marker for the axoneme of kinocilia), anti-pericentrin and phalloidin-stained P2 cochleae of WT (D) and Cobl KO mice (E).</s><s>Panels in (D) and (E) show both a top view (left) and a corresponding side view (right).</s><s>Bars, 0.5 mm (A-D).</s><s>(F-I) Quantitations of OHCs overall (n = WT/KO 175/219 OHCs; 4/4 mice) (F) and row for row (G-I) (n = 56-75 each row).(J-S)</s><s>MIPs of confocal z stacks of P2 (J and K), P6 (L and M), P8 (N and O), P9 (P and Q), and P15 (R and S) WT (J, L, N, P, and R) and Cobl KO cochleae (K, M, O, Q, and S) stained with anti-acetylated tubulin antibodies (red; kinocilia) and phalloidin (blue; stereocilia bundles).</s><s>White asterisks, hair cells without kinocilium.</s><s>Bars, 10 mm.</s><s>(T) Quantitation of kinocilium-bearing WT and Cobl KO OHCs at P2, P6, P8, P9, and P15 (120-769 OHCs; 8-33 images; 2-6 animals/each stage and genotype).</s><s>Data, mean and SEM.</s><s>Unpaired two-tailed t test.</s><s>*p &lt; 0.05; **p &lt; 0.01; ***p &lt; 0.001.</s><s>See also FigureS3.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,53.12,101.71,257.46,608.54" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. Cobl KO Leads to a Disruption of the Spatial Correlation between the Kinocilium and the Stereocilia Bundle</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,96.27,101.59,417.34,361.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>(A-D) High-resolution scanning EM images showing a disrupted correlation of the kinocilium with the stereocilia bundle in Cobl KO OHC3s (A and B) and example of top views of cochlear arrays in similar overall specimen orientation used to quantitatively evaluate the spatial correlations between kinocilia and stereocilia bundles (C and D).</s><s>Arrows marks the significantly widened gap between kinociliar base and stereocilia bundles.</s><s>Bars, 1 mm.</s><s>(E) Distances of kinociliar base to first stereocilium of one side of the bundle.</s><s>n = 60 OHCs/row and genotype (4 cochleae and animals each).</s><s>Data, mean + SEM; two-way ANOVA/Bonferroni's.</s><s>(F and G) Anti-pericentrin and phalloidin-stained P2 cochleae of WT (F) and Cobl KO mice (G) analyzed for PCM-to-stereocilium docking (left 3D surface renderings show orientation for lateral deviation determination; right panels visualize examples of increased distance of PCM and stereocilia bundle).</s><s>(H-J) Distances between PCM (apical point) to the base of the stereocilia bundle tip in OHC1 (H), OHC2 (I), and OHC3 (J) (n = WT/KO 171/224 OHCs; 49-75 OHCs/row).</s><s>(K) Deviation of PCM positions from the stereocilia bundles symmetry axis (perpendicular blue line in left panels of F and G) (n = WT/KO 221/234 OHCs) (both 4/4 animals).</s><s>Data, mean + SEM.</s><s>Unpaired, two-tailed t test.</s><s>(L) Comparison of the proportions of OHCs with indicated phenotypes (percentage of cells above WT mean).</s><s>**p &lt; 0.01; ***p &lt; 0.001.</s><s>See also Figure S4.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. Defective Planar OHC Polarity and Directed Rotational Shift of Stereocilia Bundles in Adult Cobl KO OHCs (A and B) Scanning EM of stereocilia bundles of adult (12-15 weeks) WT (A) and Cobl KO cochlea (B) for orientation evaluations.</s><s>Bar, 2 mm.</s><s>(C) Scheme depicting the determinations.</s><s>0 , horizontal position, that is, alignment to apicobasal axis (blue line); rotations, +, turned toward apical turn; À, turned toward basal turn of the cochlea.</s><s>(D) The absolute values of stereocilia bundle deviations from 0 (irrespective of direction of misalignment).</s><s>(E-G) Distributions of stereocilia bundle orientations (classes shown represent the 5 around indicated values) in OHC3 (E), OHC2 (F), and OHC1 (G) of adult WT and Cobl KO cochleae.</s><s>Arrows, middle of three highest groups for each genotype.</s><s>(H) Ranges of stereocilia bundle orientation angles (red, extended ranges).</s><s>(I-K) Averaged orientation angles of OHC1 (I), OHC2 (J), and OHC3 (K).</s><s>Note the orientation of Cobl KO OHC stereocilia bundles toward the apical turn of the cochlea, that is, opposite to WT. n = 705-874 hair cell bundles/row; 17-53 images/ cochlea; 4 animals and cochleae/genotype.</s><s>Data, mean and SEM.</s><s>***p &lt; 0.001; two-way ANOVA/Bonferroni's (D) and D'Agostino normality/Mann-Whitney U (E-G and I-K).</s><s>See also Figure S5.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,53.12,101.71,322.79,425.93" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6.</s><s>Cobl KO Leads to Defects in Postnatal Directed Rotational Refinement (A and B) Heads of WT (A) and Cobl KO pups (B) with ears still closed at P8. (C-I) Quantitative scanning EM analyses of OHC stereocilia bundle orientations directly prior to hearing onset (P8).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,83.74,101.59,191.27,573.22" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>(C) Absolute values of deviations from 0 (irrespective of direction of misalignment).</s><s>(D-F) Angle distribution analyses of OHC3 (D), OHC2 (E), and OHC1 (F).</s><s>Note the already widened deviation ranges and the directed rotational defects.</s><s>(G-I) Directional evaluations of orientation angle deviations of OHC1 (G), OHC2 (H), and OHC3 (I).</s><s>Data, mean and SEM.</s><s>n = 1,172-1,354 hair cell bundles/row; 14-51 images/ cochlea; WT/KO 5/3 animals and cochleae.</s><s>**p &lt; 0.01; ***p &lt; 0.001.</s><s>Two-way ANOVA/Bonferroni's (C) and D'Agostino normality test/Mann-Whitney U (D-I), respectively.</s><s>See also Figure S6 for P2 data.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 7. Cobl KO Mice Show Hearing Impairments (A) Averaged ABR waveforms evoked by 80-dB click stimulation in WT and Cobl KO mice (n = 11 WT and 11 KO mice; age, 12-14 weeks).</s><s>(B) ABR thresholds in Cobl KO mice compared to WT littermates.</s><s>(C) DPOAE intensities recorded from 11 WT and 11 KO mice in response to pairs of sine waves at different frequencies f1 and f2 unveiling an OHC amplifier defect.</s><s>SPL, sound pressure level.</s><s>Data, mean ± SEM. (B) Mann-Whitney U: 4 kHz, *p = 0.0212; (C) two-way ANOVA across all intensities: 8 kHz, *p = 0.021; 11.3 kHz, **p = 0.001; 16 kHz, *p = 0.014; 22.7 kHz, **p = 0.001.</s><s>(D) Schematic illustrations of the apical pole of an OHC and of Cobl KO phenotypes.</s><s>Red double-headed arrow (small panel) indicates the increased orientation variations observed for Cobl KO OHC stereociliar bundles.</s><s>Black double arrows represent directly experimentally demonstrated causal relationships between (1) impairment of actin filament formation by LatA and PCM disorganization and (2) Cobl KO and each of the different phenotypes (numeration indicated by ''+'' signs).</s><s>See also Figure S7.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="1,55.16,194.51,285.82,285.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Continued</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>REAGENT or RESOURCE</cell><cell>SOURCE</cell><cell>IDENTIFIER</cell></row><row><cell>NucleoSpin Plasmid</cell><cell>Macherey-Nagel</cell><cell>Cat#740.588.250</cell></row><row><cell>Rediprime II Random Prime Labeling System</cell><cell>GE Healthcare</cell><cell>Cat#RPN1633</cell></row><row><cell>RNase-free DNase kit</cell><cell>QIAGEN</cell><cell>Cat#79254</cell></row><row><cell>Deposited Data</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>REAGENT or RESOURCE Original data</cell><cell>SOURCE This paper</cell><cell>IDENTIFIER https://data.mendeley.com/datasets/</cell></row><row><cell>Antibodies</cell><cell></cell><cell>https://doi.org/10.17632/rypw3jv8mj.1</cell></row><row><cell>Mouse monoclonal anti-acetylated tubulin Experimental Models: Organisms/Strains</cell><cell>Sigma</cell><cell>RRID:AB_609894</cell></row><row><cell>Mouse monoclonal anti-Arl13b Mouse strain C57BL/6J (WT and background for</cell><cell>Neuromab Jackson Labs</cell><cell>RRID:AB_2341543 IMSR_JAX:000664</cell></row><row><cell>Guinea pig polyclonal anti-Cobl DBY Cobl KO line)</cell><cell>Haag et al., 2012</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Guinea pig polyclonal anti-Cobl ARA Mouse strain Cobl KO C57BL/6J::129/SvJ (99,7::0,3</cell><cell>Schwintzer et al., 2011 This paper</cell><cell>N/A N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Rabbit polyclonal anti-oncomodulin after speed congenics and backcrossing) (WT, KO and Rabbit polyclonal anti-Par6b (M-64) heterozygous littermates thereof) Guinea pig polyclonal anti-parvalbumin Ubiquitously Cre recombinase expressing mice Rabbit polyclonal anti-pericentrin Oligonucleotides Rabbit polyclonal anti-aPKCz (C-20) Genotyping Cobl KO mice (WT; 388 bp): forward primer F1, 5 0 -acacagccctggcatcat-3 0</cell><cell>Swant Santa Cruz Swant Schwenk et al., 1995 Abcam Santa Cruz</cell><cell>RRID:AB_2313681 RRID:AB_2267889 N/A RRID:AB_2665495 RRID:AB_304461 RRID:AB_2300359</cell></row><row><cell>Rabbit polyclonal anti-b-tubulin</cell><cell>Synaptic Systems</cell><cell>RRID:AB_10637424</cell></row><row><cell>Mouse monoclonal anti-g-tubulin (GTU-88)</cell><cell>Sigma</cell><cell>RRID:AB_477584</cell></row><row><cell>Alexa Fluor 488-labeled goat anti-guinea pig</cell><cell>Molecular Probes</cell><cell>RRID:AB_142018</cell></row><row><cell>Alexa Fluor 568-labeled goat anti-guinea pig</cell><cell>Molecular Probes</cell><cell>RRID:AB_141954</cell></row><row><cell>Alexa Fluor 488-labeled donkey anti-mouse</cell><cell>Molecular Probes</cell><cell>RRID:AB_141607</cell></row><row><cell>Alexa Fluor 568-labeled donkey anti-mouse</cell><cell>Molecular Probes</cell><cell>RRID:AB_2534013</cell></row><row><cell>Alexa Fluor 647-labeled goat anti-mouse</cell><cell>Molecular Probes</cell><cell>RRID:AB_141725</cell></row><row><cell>Alexa Fluor 488-labeled donkey anti-rabbit</cell><cell>Molecular Probes</cell><cell>RRID:AB_141708</cell></row><row><cell>Alexa Fluor 568-labeled goat anti-rabbit</cell><cell>Molecular Probes</cell><cell>RRID:AB_143011</cell></row><row><cell>Alexa Fluor 647-labeled goat anti-rabbit</cell><cell>Molecular Probes</cell><cell>RRID:AB_141775</cell></row><row><cell>Alexa Fluor 680-labeled goat-anti-rabbit</cell><cell>Molecular Probes</cell><cell>RRID:AB_2535758</cell></row><row><cell>Alexa Fluor 680-labeled goat-anti-mouse</cell><cell>Molecular Probes</cell><cell>RRID:AB_1965956</cell></row><row><cell>DyLight800-conjugated goat anti-rabbit</cell><cell>Thermo Fisher</cell><cell>RRID:AB_2556775</cell></row><row><cell>DyLight800-conjugated goat anti-mouse</cell><cell>Thermo Fisher</cell><cell>RRID:AB_2556774</cell></row><row><cell>IRDye680-conjugated donkey anti-guinea pig</cell><cell>LI-COR Bioscience</cell><cell>RRID:AB_10956079</cell></row><row><cell>IRDye800-conjugated donkey anti-guinea pig</cell><cell>LI-COR Bioscience</cell><cell>RRID:AB_1850024</cell></row><row><cell>Bacterial and Virus Strains</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>E. coli commercial strain XL-10 Gold</cell><cell>Agilent</cell><cell>Cat#200314</cell></row><row><cell>E. coli commercial strain BL21-CodonPlus(DE3)-RIPL</cell><cell>Agilent</cell><cell>Cat#230280</cell></row><row><cell>Biological Samples</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mouse (adult C57BL/6J) (different sorts of brain</cell><cell>Charles River</cell><cell>IMSR_JAX:000664</cell></row><row><cell>and cochlear material thereof)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Chemicals, Peptides, and Recombinant Proteins</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>a P 32 dCTP, 100mCi, 3000Ci/mmol</cell><cell>Amersham</cell><cell>Cat#BLU013H100UC</cell></row><row><cell>AlexaFluor 488-conjugated phalloidin</cell><cell>Molecular Probes</cell><cell>Cat#A12379</cell></row><row><cell>AlexaFluor 647-conjugated phalloidin</cell><cell>Molecular Probes</cell><cell>Cat#A22287</cell></row><row><cell>DAPI</cell><cell>Molecular Probes</cell><cell>Cat#D1306</cell></row><row><cell>Latrunculin A</cell><cell>Tocris biosciences</cell><cell>Cat#3973</cell></row><row><cell>Calmodulin antagonist CGS9343B</cell><cell>Tocris biosciences</cell><cell>Cat#2255/10</cell></row><row><cell>Calmodulin antagonist W7 hydrochloride</cell><cell>Tocris biosciences</cell><cell>Cat#0369/100</cell></row><row><cell>Critical Commercial Assays</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>(Continued on next page) e1 Cell Reports 24, 2418-2431.e1-e6,</s><s>August 28, 2018</s></p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Strain BL21-CodonPlus (DE3)-RIPL E. coli strain BL21-CodonPlus (DE3)-RIPL (Stratagene/Agilent) (genomic information: E. coli B F-ompT hsdS(rB-mB-) dcm+ Tetr gal l(DE3) endA Hte [argU proL Camr] [argU ileY leuW Strep/Specr]) was used for preparations of recombinant fusion proteins.The strain carries a resistance for tetracycline and was therefore either grown in LB-medium or on LB-agar with either tetracycline or other antibiotics (resistance acquired by transformation with suitable plasmid).The strain was either grown at 18 C, RT or 37 C.MiceTissue material for RT-PCRs and Western blot analyses as well as brain sections and cochleae for immunohistochemistry were taken from WT (C57BL/6J) and Cobl KO mice of different developmental stages (see figure legends and Method Details).</s></p></div></figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Cell Reports24, 2418-2431, August 28, 2018 2425</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Cell Reports24, 2418-2431, August 28, 2018 2427(legend on next page)</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">e3 Cell Reports 24, 2418-2431.e1-e6, August 28, 2018</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Cell Reports24, 2418-2431.e1-e6, August 28, 2018 e4</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">e5 Cell Reports 24, 2418-2431.e1-e6, August 28, 2018</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Detailed methods are provided in the online version of this paper and include the following: Antibodies and Reagents Primary antibodies were used according to Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>.</s><s>Affinity purifications of anti-Cobl antibodies were done and validated as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Schwintzer et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Haag et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>Secondary antibodies used included Alexa Fluor 488-, Alexa Fluor 568and Alexa Fluor 647-conjugates (Molecular Probes) and antibodies coupled to IRDye680 and IRDye800 (LI-COR Biosciences), respectively.</s></p><p><s>Nuclei were visualized by co-staining with 0.1 mg/ml 4,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI; Molecular Probes) and F-actin filaments using Alexa Fluor488-and Alexa Fluor647-conjugated phalloidin (Molecular Probes).</s></p><p><s>Latrunculin A (Tocris biosciences) was used at a concentration of 1 mM to inhibit actin polymerization.</s></p><p><s>To inhibit Ca 2+ /calmodulin signaling, calmodulin antagonists W7 hydrochloride and CGS9343B (both Tocris biosciences) were used at a concentration of 10 mM in DMEM supplemented with 10% fetal calf serum (Thermo Fisher Scientific).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reverse Transcription PCR (RT-PCR)</head><p><s>RNA isolation and RevT-PCR were performed as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Haag et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>Briefly, tissue samples from cochleae and mouse brain were dissected, snap-frozen, and homogenized by grinding in liquid nitrogen and subsequently resuspended in Trizol reagent (Invitrogen).</s><s>Two micrograms of DNase-treated (RNase-free DNase kit, QIAGEN) total RNA were reversely transcribed using oligo(dT)-primers and RevertAid H Minus Reverse Transcriptase (Fermentas).</s><s>To test for the absence of contaminating genomic DNA, controls omitting the reverse transcriptase (-RevT) were run in parallel.</s></p><p><s>Cobl expression was analyzed by PCRs using the exon-spanning primers ggctcctgagaaatctgtacg (fwd-pan; exon 3/4), ctaaa catttctcttctgttgtcc (rev-pan; exon 4/5), gctccggaagactgcagaaca (fwd-WH2; exon 12/13), cgagcaagggaacctttcttagtc (rev-WH2; exon 14/15); ccgagctccctaccctcctcctgacaca (fwd-D10-15; exon 9); tgggtaccgcaattcctggacaccaact (rev-D10-15; intron 9) and GAPDH serving as control (fwd, attgacctcaactacatggtctaca; rev, ccagtagactccacgacatactc).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Zebrafish Whole-Mount In Situ Hybridization</head><p><s>Zebrafish whole mount in situ hybridizations were performed as described <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Sch€ uler et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Sequences encoding for Cobl aa1-295 (sense and antisense) were used as probes.</s><s>Images were recorded with a Zeiss Axio ZOOM.V16 microscope and analyzed with ZEN software (Zeiss).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Western Blot Analyses of Cochlea and Brain Lysates</head><p><s>Up to 10 cochleae from postnatal mice per genotype were dissected in protease inhibitor-containing 10 mM HEPES pH 7.4, pooled, collected and homogenized in lysis buffer (10 mM HEPES pH 7.4, 1 mM EGTA, 0.1 mM MgCl2, 1 mM EDTA, 1x protease inhibitor Complete) by sonication.</s><s>Lysis was completed by addition of Triton X-100 (1% final) and incubation for 30 min at 4 C.</s><s>After centrifugation (5000 3 g, 10 min, 4 C), supernatants were precipitated with 4 volumes of 100% acetone at À20 C, washed with 80% acetone and resuspended in 2xSDS sample buffer (2% w/v SDS, 20% w/v glycerol, 10% b-mercaptoethanol, 125 mM Tris-HCl, pH 6.8, bromophenol blue).</s></p><p><s>Cochlea samples were analyzed by immunoblotting (70 mg protein/lane) with guinea pig anti-Cobl DBY antibodies, guinea pig anti-Cobl ARA antibodies (guinea pig anti-Cobl ARA , no detection of Cobl in cochlea due to low abundance of Cobl and reduced sensitivity compared to guinea pig anti-Cobl DBY antibodies) and mouse anti-b-tubulin antibodies (loading control).</s></p><p><s>Mouse brain tissue was homogenized in ice-cold homogenization buffer (5 mM HEPES, pH 7.4, 320 mM sucrose, 1x protease inhibitor Complete) using a Potter S homogenizer (Sartorius) and centrifuged (1000 3 g, 10 min at 4 C).</s><s>The supernatant S1 was kept and combined with S1' obtained by a second round of reextraction of the pellet fraction P1 and centrifugation.</s><s>The resulting supernatant (S1+S1') was centrifuged at 12000 3 g (20 min at 4 C) and analyzed as supernatant (S2) and pellet (P2) fractions by anti-Cobl immunoblotting.</s></p><p><s>Inner Ear Immunohistochemistry, Confocal Imaging and Quantitative Morphometric Analysis Animals were sacrificed, the temporal bones were removed, organs of Corti were dissected in PBS pH 7.4, and the Reissner's and tectorial membranes were carefully removed.</s></p><p><s>After fixation in 4% PFA in PBS (1 h, on ice) and washing with PBS, cochleae were blocked with 10%-15% normal goat serum in PBS containing 0.1% Triton X-100 (block solution) (1-2 h, RT).</s><s>Primary antibody incubations (see Table <ref type="table">S1</ref> for details) were done overnight at 4 C with gentle agitation.</s><s>After washing, secondary antibody incubations (in block solution, 1 h, RT) and washing, cochleae were mounted (Fluoromount G; SouthernBiotech) and confocal stacks were recorded from the apico-medial turn to ensure full developmental and morphological comparability (Leica TCS SP5; 63x/1.4 oil objective, LAS AF software).</s><s>Image processing was done with ImageJ and/or Adobe Photoshop (without changing gamma adjustments).</s></p><p><s>Cuticular plate thicknesses in P8 cochleae were measured in X-Z-projections of the apical phalloidin staining.</s><s>For this purpose, Cobl KO cochleae were stained together with WT OHCs in the same staining solution.</s><s>Cuticular plate F-actin intensity and distributions were recorded at substereociliar positions (line scans 1) and at stereociliar-free positions (line scans 2) and analyzed in a blinded manner (n = 33 OHC3s for each genotype taken from 3 WT and 4 KO animals).</s></p><p><s>For kinocilium retraction analyses, confocal z stacks of anti-acetylated tubulin (kinocilium marker <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Jones et al., 2008)</ref>; confirmed by anti-Arl13b immunolabeling) immunolabeled apico-medial turns of whole-mount preparations of P2, P6, P8, P9 and P15 WT and Cobl</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cordon-bleu is an actin nucleation factor and controls neuronal morphology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ahuja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pinyol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Reichenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Custer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Klingensmith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Qualmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="350" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Antonellis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pollock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-W</forename><surname>Chou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hassan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Geng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Alagramam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Auer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Mcdermott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ACF7 is a hair-bundle antecedent, positioned to integrate cuticular plate actin and somatic tubulin</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="305" to="312" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The mouse as a model for age-related hearing loss-a mini-review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bowl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Dawson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gerontology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="157" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cordon-bleu is a conserved gene involved in neural tube formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Carroll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gerrelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gasca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Berg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Beier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Copp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Klingensmith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">262</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="31" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Positioning of centrioles is a conserved readout of Frizzled planar cell polarity signalling</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Carvajal-Gonzalez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Roman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mlodzik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11135</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Postnatal refinement of auditory hair cell planar polarity deficits occurs in the absence of Vangl2</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Copley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Duncan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Deans</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14001" to="14016" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutation of Celsr1 disrupts planar polarity of inner ear hair cells and causes severe neural tube defects in the mouse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Curtin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Quint</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Tsipouri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Arkell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cattanach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Copp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Henderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Spurr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Stanier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1129" to="1133" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dabdoub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Donohue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Brennan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Montcouquiol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Sassoon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hseih</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Rubin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Salinas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Wnt signaling mediates reorientation of outer hair cell stereociliary bundles in the mammalian cochlea</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">130</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2375" to="2384" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternative splice forms influence functions of Whirlin in mechanosensory hair cell stereocilia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ebrahim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Ingham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J C</forename><surname>Rogers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cui</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kachar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Pass</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Steel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="935" to="943" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Revisiting planar cell polarity in the inner ear</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ezan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Montcouquiol</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semin. Cell Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="499" to="506" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ezan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lasvaux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gezer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Novakovic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>May-Simera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Belotti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lhoumeau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Birnbaumer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Beer-Hammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Borg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Primary cilium migration depends on G-protein signalling control of subapical cytoskeleton</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1107" to="1115" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The centrosome is an actin-organizing centre</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Farina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gaillard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gue ´rin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">´</forename><surname>Coute</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Sillibourne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Blanchoin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>The ´ry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The sensory and motor roles of auditory hair cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fettiplace</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hackney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="29" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic insights into the morphogenesis of inner ear hair cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Frolenkov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Belyantseva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Friedman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Griffith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="489" to="498" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterization of a gene trap insertion into a novel gene, cordon-bleu, expressed in axial structures of the gastrulating mouse embryo</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gasca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Klingensmith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rossant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="141" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Flattop regulates basal body docking and positioning in mono-and multiciliated cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gegg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bo ¨ttcher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Burtscher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hasenoeder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Van Campenhout</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aichler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Walch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Grant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lickert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e03842</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The actin nucleator Cobl is crucial for Purkinje cell development and works in close conjunction with the F-actin binding protein Abp1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Haag</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schwintzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ahuja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Grimm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Heuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Qualmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17842" to="17856" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The actin nucleator Cobl is controlled by calcium and calmodulin</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Izadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nemitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Haag</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Qualmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e1002233</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Arginine methylation by PRMT2 controls the functions of the actin nucleator Cobl</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Nemitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schopper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Qualmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="262" to="275" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>e8</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cobl-like promotes actin filament formation and dendritic branching using only a single WH2 domain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Izadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Schlobinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lahr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schwintzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Qualmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">217</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="211" to="230" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disruption of the presynaptic cytomatrix protein bassoon degrades ribbon anchorage, multiquantal release, and sound encoding at the hair cell afferent synapse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Jing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rutherford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Takago</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Frank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fejtova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Khimich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Moser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Strenzke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4456" to="4467" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Presynaptic maturation in auditory hair cells requires a critical period of sensory-independent spiking activity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kuhn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Franz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ingham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Furness</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Knipper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Steel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Adelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Holley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Marcotti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8720" to="8725" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ciliary proteins link basal body polarization to planar cell polarity regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Jones</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Roper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Foucher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Qian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Banizs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Petit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Yoder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chen</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulation of cell fate and patterning in the developing mammalian cochlea</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Driver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Puligilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Opin. Otolaryngol. Head Neck Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="381" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kitajiri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sakamoto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Belyantseva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Goodyear</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Stepanyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Fujiwara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bird</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Riazuddin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Riazuddin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ahmed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Actin-bundling protein TRIOBP forms resilient rootlets of hair cell stereocilia essential for hearing</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="786" to="798" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Regulation of stereocilia length by myosin XVa and whirlin depends on the actin-regulatory protein Eps8</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Manor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Disanza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Andrade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Di Fiore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Scita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kachar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ciliary proteins Bbs8 and Ift20 promote planar cell polarity in the cochlea</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>May-Simera</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Petralia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Montcouquiol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Szarama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Deans</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Pazour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="555" to="566" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stereocilia morphogenesis and maintenance through regulation of actin stability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcgrath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Roy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Perrin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semin. Cell Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="88" to="95" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of Vangl2 and Scrb1 as planar polarity genes in mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Montcouquiol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rachel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lanford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Copeland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Jenkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">423</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="177" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Actin nucleation at the centrosome controls lymphocyte polarity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Obino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Farina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Malbec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sa ´ez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Maurin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gaillard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Dingli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Loew</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gautreau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Yuseff</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10969</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">b-actin and g-actin are each dispensable for auditory hair cell development but required for stereocilia maintenance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Perrin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sonnemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ervasti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010. e1001158</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New players in actin polymerization-WH2-domain-containing actin nucleators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Qualmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Trends Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="276" to="285" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The actin nucleator Cordon-bleu is required for development of motile cilia in zebrafish</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ravanelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Klingensmith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">350</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CLIC5 stabilizes membrane-actin filament linkages at the base of hair cell stereocilia in a molecular complex with radixin, taperin, and myosin VI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Salles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Andrade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tanda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Plona</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gagnon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Kachar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Berryman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cytoskeleton (Hoboken)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="78" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ciliated sensory hair cell formation and function require the F-BAR protein syndapin I and the WH2 domain-based actin nucleator Cobl</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sch€ Uler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hauptmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Perner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Englert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Qualmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="196" to="208" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A cre-transgenic mouse strain for the ubiquitous deletion of loxP-flanked gene segments including deletion in germ cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Schwenk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Baron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Rajewsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nucleic Acids Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5080" to="5081" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The functions of the actin nucleator Cobl in cellular morphogenesis critically depend on syndapin I</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Schwintzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ahuja</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Grimm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kessels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Qualmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EMBO J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3147" to="3159" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Kif3a regulates planar polarization of auditory hair cells through both ciliary and non-ciliary mechanisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Sipe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3441" to="3449" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Frequency-and level-dependent changes in auditory brainstem responses (ABRS) in developing mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mcgee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Walsh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Acoust. Soc. Am</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">119</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2242" to="2257" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cytoskeletal changes in actin and microtubules underlie the developing surface mechanical properties of sensory and supporting cells in the mouse cochlea</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Szarama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Gavara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Petralia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Kelley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Chadwick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">139</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2187" to="2197" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Centrosome positioning in vertebrate development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Marshall</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4951" to="4961" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The organization of actin filaments in the stereocilia of cochlear hair cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tilney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Derosier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mulroy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="244" to="259" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Striated organelle, a cytoskeletal structure positioned to modulate hair-cell transduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Vranceanu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Perkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Terada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chidavaenzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Ellisman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lysakowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4473" to="4478" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of Frizzled3 and Frizzled6 in neural tube closure and in the planar polarity of inner-ear sensory hair cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Nathans</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2147" to="2156" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
