<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Cell-Cycle Proteins Control Production of Neutrophil Extracellular Traps Highlights d Neutrophils activate cell-cycle markers when stimulated to make NETs d Cyclin-dependent kinases CDK4/6 regulate NET formation d Cdk6 À/À mice have impaired immune response to Candida albicans Authors</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2017-11-02">November 2, 2017</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Borko</forename><surname>Amulic</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Cellular Microbiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sebastian</forename><forename type="middle">Lorenz</forename><surname>Knackstedt</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Cellular Microbiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Abed, ...,</roleName><forename type="first">Ulrike</forename><surname>Abu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Frank</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Heppner</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neuropathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´-Universit€ atsmedizin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Cluster of Excellence</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">NeuroCure</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Berlin Institute of Health (BIH)</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10178</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">German Center for Neurodegenerative Diseases (DZNE</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Philip</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hinds</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Developmental, Molecular and Chemical Biology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Tufts University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>02111</postCode>
									<settlement>Boston</settlement>
									<region>MA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Arturo</forename><surname>Zychlinsky</surname></persName>
							<email>zychlinsky@mpiib-berlin.mpg.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Cellular Microbiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="department">Lead Contact</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ulrike</forename><forename type="middle">Abu</forename><surname>Abed</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Cellular Microbiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Microscopy Core Facility</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nikolaus</forename><surname>Deigendesch</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Cellular Microbiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neuropathology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´-Universit€ atsmedizin</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Christopher</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Harbort</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Cellular Microbiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Brian</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Caffrey</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Max Planck Institute for Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>14195</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Volker</forename><surname>Brinkmann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Microscopy Core Facility</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Cell-Cycle Proteins Control Production of Neutrophil Extracellular Traps Highlights d Neutrophils activate cell-cycle markers when stimulated to make NETs d Cyclin-dependent kinases CDK4/6 regulate NET formation d Cdk6 À/À mice have impaired immune response to Candida albicans Authors</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2017-11-02">November 2, 2017</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">F1968BE530A522D91CD9DB5649B2EBBB</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.devcel.2017.10.013</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: August 17, 2016 Revised: July 12, 2017 Accepted: October 9, 2017</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:42+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Neutrophils release chromatin in the form of neutrophil extracellular traps (NETs).</s><s>Amulic et al. show that NET formation involves activation of cell-cycle markers and identify CDK4/6 as regulators of the process.</s><s>Cdk6 knockout mice, which are impaired in NET formation, are more susceptible to Candida albicans infection.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p><s>Neutrophils are the most abundant immune cells in the bloodstream.</s><s>They are essential for survival; in humans a lack of neutrophils results in severe immunodeficiency and a drastically reduced lifespan, as for example in individuals with mutations causing congenital neutropenias <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Klein, 2011)</ref>.</s><s>Neutrophils are produced in the bone marrow from dividing progenitors.</s><s>After maturing and exiting the cell cycle they move to the circulatory system where they are thought to have a short lifespan.</s><s>Upon infection or injury they migrate into affected tissues where they directly kill pathogens, as well as shaping the ensuing adaptive immune response <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Amulic et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Mantovani et al., 2011)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Neutrophils kill microbes by phagocytosis, production of reactive oxygen species (ROS), and by release of various microbicidal proteins.</s><s>Before activation, these antimicrobials are kept in intracellular storage vesicles called granules.</s><s>When the cell senses pathogens, the antimicrobials can be released by a process called degranulation, whereby the granules fuse with the plasma membrane and release their contents.</s><s>An additional antimicrobial strategy has been described, which entraps pathogens in neutrophil extracellular traps (NETs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Brinkmann et al., 2004)</ref>.</s><s>These consist of extruded chromatin bound to various antimicrobials from the granules.</s><s>By associating with NETs, the antimicrobial molecules are physically limited from diffusing away from their site of action, which may enhance their killing capacity, as well as limit collateral damage to host tissues.</s><s>NETs are triggered by large pathogens, such as hyphal forms of Candida albicans <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Branzk et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>Furthermore, excessive NET release is associated with a growing list of inflammatory and autoimmune diseases, including systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Kaplan and Radic, 2012)</ref>, atherosclerosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b59">(Warnatsch et al., 2015)</ref>, diabetes <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(Wong et al., 2015)</ref>, vasculitis <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Kaplan and Radic, 2012)</ref>, thrombosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Martinod and Wagner, 2014)</ref>, sepsis <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Camicia et al., 2014)</ref>, and cancer <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Park et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>Understanding the molecular mechanism of NET formation is thus crucial for developing therapeutics in the context of immune defense and inflammatory diseases.</s></p><p><s>NETosis is a type of neutrophil cell death, distinct from apoptosis or necrosis, which remains poorly characterized.</s><s>It is an active process characterized by internal breakdown of nuclear and granular membranes, the mixing of the contents of these compartments in the cytosol and finally, their extracellular release via plasma membrane rupture <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Fuchs et al., 2007)</ref>.</s><s>Although alternative pathways have been reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(Park et al., 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b48">Parker et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kenny et al., 2017)</ref>, the most studied NETosis program is the one in response to C. albicans and the mitogen phorbol myristate acetate (PMA).</s><s>It requires signaling through mitogen-activated protein kinases (MAPKs) <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Hakkim et al., 2011)</ref> and the production of ROS by the enzyme NADPH oxidase (NOX2) <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Fuchs et al., 2007)</ref>.</s><s>ROS are required for the permeabilization of granules by a protein complex called the azurosome, which allows translocation of a protease, neutrophil elastase, into the nucleus where it cleaves histones and leads to chromatin decondensation <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Papayannopoulos et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Metzler et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>Other mechanistic aspects remain unknown, although some forms of NET formation are associated with citrullination of histones, catalyzed by the enzyme protein arginine deiminase 4 (PAD4) <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Li et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kenny et al., 2017)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>One of the most distinctive features of NETosis is the breakdown of the nuclear envelope.</s><s>This characteristic sets it apart from apoptosis, and is highly reminiscent of nuclear envelope disintegration during mitosis in dividing cells.</s><s>This observation led us to postulate that NET induction is linked to mitogenic reactivation of cell-cycle regulators.</s><s>We show that neutrophils, which are terminally differentiated cells, upregulate Ki-67, phosphorylate retinoblastoma protein (pRb), and nuclear lamins, and separate centrosomes without replicating DNA or undergoing cytokinesis.</s><s>We demonstrate that core members of the cell-cycle machinery, cyclin-dependent kinases 4 and 6 (CDK4/6), are required for NET formation.</s><s>Taken together, the data presented here show that, in neutrophils, cell-cycle pathways are repurposed for controlling NETosis.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mitogens Induce NETs</head><p><s>Fungi and the protein kinase C agonist PMA activate a similar pathway to make NETs.</s><s>Both induce MAPK signaling <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Hakkim et al., 2011)</ref>, the activation of NOX2, and the production of ROS <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Fuchs et al., 2007)</ref>.</s><s>PMA is also a strong mitogen, a chemical with the ability to trigger cell division.</s><s>We tested if other mitogens also lead to NET release.</s><s>Concanavalin A (ConA) and phytohaemagglutinin, two plant lectins commonly used to induce proliferation of lymphocytes, both induced NETs, distinguishable by their morphology and the colocalization of nuclear and granular markers (Figures <ref type="figure">1A and 1B</ref>).</s><s>Importantly, NET induction with mitogens was also dependent on ROS production, since neutrophils isolated from chronic granulomatous disease (CGD) patients, who have deficiencies in NOX2, or those treated with diphenyleneiodonium, a NOX2 chemical inhibitor, did not undergo NETosis (Figures <ref type="figure">1A and 1B</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>NETosis Is Accompanied by Induction of Cell Division Markers</head><p><s>Neutrophils are terminally differentiated cells that have withdrawn from the cell cycle and lost their capacity to divide.</s><s>Indeed, mature neutrophils downregulate most of the genes involved in cell-cycle regulation <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Klausen et al., 2004)</ref>, a finding we confirmed by genome-wide expression analysis of peripheral blood neutrophils from healthy donors (Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>).</s><s>Despite this, mitogenic stimulation of neutrophils leads to nuclear envelope breakdown as it does in the case of mitosis in dividing cells.</s><s>Transmission electron microscopy comparing mitosis in the myeloid cell line PLB-985, and NETosis in neutrophils, revealed that the vesiculation of the nuclear envelope is common to both processes (Figure <ref type="figure">1C</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Fuchs et al., 2007)</ref>.</s><s>We were struck by this similarity and postulated that common cellular pathways are employed during NETosis and mitosis.</s></p><p><s>We first examined cell-cycle markers in neutrophils induced to make NETs.</s><s>The nuclear antigen Ki-67 is expressed in all cycling cells, irrespective of the stage of the cell cycle they are in, while it is absent in non-cycling, quiescent, or senescent cells.</s><s>Resting neutrophils were negative for Ki-67 but, surprisingly, cells stimulated to undergo NETosis transiently reactivated expression of this cell division marker, visualized by immunofluorescence (Fig- <ref type="table">ures 2A and 2B</ref>).</s></p><p><s>We examined a series of other cell-cycle markers, in the order in which they are induced in dividing cells.</s><s>Neutrophils are typically considered to be in the G 0 stage, like other terminally differentiated and quiescent cells (Figure <ref type="figure">S1</ref>).</s><s>Cells in G 0 can resume cycling after mitogenic stimulation; this is associated with phosphorylation of pRb by CDK4/6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Malumbres and Barbacid, 2009)</ref>.</s><s>Notably, neutrophils stimulated to make NETs also exhibited robust phosphorylation of pRb, indicating that activation of G1 kinases was occurring (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2C</ref>).</s><s>Importantly, pRb phosphorylation was not only triggered by PMA and ConA, but also by infection with C. albicans hyphae (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2C</ref>).</s><s>Stimuli that activate neutrophils but do not induce NETs, such as bacterial peptide analog N-formylmethionyl-leucyl-phenylalanine (fMLP), did not lead to pRb phosphorylation.</s></p><p><s>Despite activation of G1 kinases, we did not detect incorporation of the thymidine analog 5-ethynyl-2 0 -deoxyuridine (EdU) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>), indicating that DNA synthesis, the hallmark of S phase, did not occur.</s><s>As a control for EdU incorporation we used continuously cycling HEK293 cells (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>) as well as T lymphocytes, which can be induced to proliferate by treatment with PMA, analogously to our stimulation of neutrophils.</s><s>T cells stimulated with PMA/ionomycin successfully incorporated EdU, but this required a longer period of stimulation than the 3 hr it took neutrophils to make NETs (Figure <ref type="figure">S1B</ref>), highlighting an important difference in the temporal dynamic between NETosis and cell-cycle re-entry.</s><s>Similarly, we observed no induction of the S-phase transcriptional program in neutrophils making NETs.</s><s>In cycling cells, phosphorylation of pRb leads to the derepression of E2F transcription factors and expression of S-phase genes, but these were not induced in NETosis as measured by qPCR analysis (Figure <ref type="figure">S1C</ref>) and whole-genome microarray analysis (data not shown).</s></p><p><s>Our initial observation of nuclear envelope breakdown during NETosis (Figure <ref type="figure">1C</ref>) argued that mitotic pathways are also activated.</s><s>In mitosis (M phase), nuclear envelope disintegration is triggered by phosphorylation of lamins, intermediate filament proteins that form a sheet underneath the envelope called the nuclear lamina <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Heald and McKeon, 1990)</ref>.</s><s>Phosphorylation of the lamina disrupts the structural rigidity of the nucleus, allowing the nuclear envelope to disintegrate.</s><s>We tested if NET formation is also associated with phosphorylation of lamins.</s><s>Remarkably, treatment with the NET-inducing stimuli PMA, ConA, or C. albicans hyphae all led to robust phosphorylation of lamin A/C (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2C</ref>).</s><s>This was confirmed by immunofluorescence (Figures <ref type="figure">S1D and S1E</ref>).</s><s>Furthermore, NETosis was accompanied by induction of a second mitotic marker: phosphorylation of histone H3 at serine 10 (H3S10).</s><s>Neither lamin nor H3S10 phosphorylation were induced by the control stimulus fMLP (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2C</ref>), which, as mentioned above, does not induce NETs.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Induction of NETs Leads to Centrosome Separation</head><p><s>To test whether NET formation involves induction of other mitotic markers, we visualized microtubule dynamics by immunofluorescence microscopy.</s><s>During mitosis, microtubule-based structures called centrosomes, which were duplicated in the preceding S phase, separate and migrate to opposing poles of the cell where they nucleate formation of the mitotic spindle <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Mardin and Schiebel, 2012)</ref>.</s><s>In unstimulated neutrophils, immunostaining with an antibody directed against both aand b-tubulin demonstrated a ''skeletal'' or scaffold-like staining pattern with several filaments extending from a central microtubule-organizing center (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2E and S1F</ref>).</s><s>After 30 min of PMA stimulation these extended filaments were lost and rearranged into single or double dot-like structures.</s><s>Strikingly, 60 min post-stimulation, these dot-like structures had duplicated and migrated away from each other.</s><s>The structures were most fully separated from each other at 90 min post-stimulation and were no longer present by 120 min, which coincided with breakdown of the nuclear envelope.</s><s>Immunofluorescence detection of the centrosome marker g-tubulin confirmed that these structures were bona fide centrosomes (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2F and 2G</ref>).</s><s>Treatment with the control stimulus fMLP did not induce microtubule rearrangement (Figure <ref type="figure">S1G</ref>).</s><s>Centrosome separation, together with phosphorylation of lamins and histone H3S10, demonstrate that markers of a mitotic program are present just before neutrophils die and release NETs.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Neutrophils Activate Cell-Cycle Signaling In Vivo</head><p><s>Induction of cell-cycle markers in neutrophils was surprising since they are terminally differentiated cells.</s><s>To verify that this also occurs in vivo, we induced NETs by inoculating mice with C. albicans via the orotracheal route.</s><s>We then co-stained lung sections with antibodies against neutrophil markers (calgranulin A or Ly6G) and the cell division marker Ki-67.</s><s>Interestingly, we identified many Ki-67-positive neutrophils in the infected lungs <ref type="bibr">(Figures 3A and S2A)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>We also examined human histological sections from patients with brain fungal abscesses, identified by periodic acid-Schiff staining (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2B</ref>).</s><s>We observed NETs in these sections by detecting neutrophil elastase co-localizing with DNA (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2C</ref>).</s><s>Next, we co-stained sections with Ki-67 and the neutrophil marker calgranulin, and indeed were able to observe Ki-67-positive neutrophil infiltrates (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3B</ref>).</s><s>We confirmed this finding using immunohistochemical methods with a second Ki-67 antibody (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2D</ref>), as well as immunofluorescentbased detection of a second neutrophil marker (CD66b; Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2E</ref>).</s><s>Neutrophils were only Ki-67 positive when they had intact nuclei (NET precursors), as was the case with Ki-67 detection in purified neutrophils (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>).</s><s>Remarkably, we could also detect duplicated centrosomes in these cells (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3C</ref>), demonstrating the induction of mitotic pathways in neutrophils in vivo and confirming our results with isolated human cells.</s></p><p><s>The Cell-Cycle Inhibitor p21 cip Regulates NET Formation Human neutrophils are refractory to transfection and gene editing because of their short lifespans.</s><s>As an initial approach to determine whether NETosis is dependent on the cell cycle, we used cell-penetrating peptides.</s><s>In dividing cells, one class of negative cell-cycle regulators is a family of small proteins termed cip/kip (CDK interacting protein/Kinase inhibitory protein).</s><s>The prototype of this family is p21 cip1 (p21), a protein that blocks the cell cycle at several different points (Figure <ref type="figure">S1A</ref>) by inhibiting cyclin-CDK complexes.</s><s>We synthesized a peptide mimic corresponding to the CDK inhibitory domain of p21 <ref type="bibr" target="#b51">(Rousseau et al., 1999)</ref>, which was previously shown to inhibit proliferation by interfering with the activity of CDKs.</s><s>We coupled this peptide to the cell-penetrating tat sequence <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Goulvestre et al., 2005)</ref>.</s><s>A scrambled peptide served as the control.</s><s>Both peptides penetrated neutrophils with similar efficiencies (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S3A</ref>), and neither were toxic to the cells (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S3B</ref>).</s><s>Transduction of the p21 inhibitory peptide (p21inh) into human neutrophils completely blocked NET formation, while transduction of the control scrambled peptide (p21ctrl) had little effect (Figures <ref type="figure">4A  and 4B</ref>).</s><s>Interference with CDKs thus leads to inhibition of NET release, indicating that these cell-cycle regulators are necessary for NETosis.</s><s>We also examined NET formation in p21 knockout mice, whose cells have higher proliferative capacities due to increased CDK activity and loss of cell-cycle control <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Bedelbaeva et al., 2010)</ref>.</s><s>As expected, peritoneal neutrophils from p21 knockout mice made more NETs than wild-type (WT) cells (Figure <ref type="figure">4C</ref>), consistent with p21 being a regulator of both cell-cycle and NET formation.</s><s>ROS production, however, was similar in both strains (Figure <ref type="figure">4D</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Neutrophils Express CDK4/6</head><p><s>The early stages of NET formation display various cell-cycle markers and can be blocked by the CDK binding domain of the p21 cell-cycle inhibitor.</s><s>CDKs and their regulatory subunits, the cyclins, are the major drivers of the mammalian cell cycle (Figure <ref type="figure">S1A</ref>).</s><s>The CDKs are a large group of kinases, many of which have functions unrelated to the cell cycle <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Lim and Kaldis, 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Of the canonical cell-cycle regulatory kinases, the close homologs CDKs 4 and 6 regulate the transition from G 0 to G 1 phase and are considered to be largely redundant <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Malumbres and Barbacid, 2009)</ref>.</s><s>CDK2 drives progression through S phase, while CDK1 is essential for mitosis, although much functional  overlap has been reported (Figure <ref type="figure">S1A</ref>; <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Malumbres and Barbacid, 2009)</ref>.</s><s>We examined protein expression of the cell-cycle CDKs in human neutrophils and were able to detect CDK4/6 (Figure <ref type="figure">5A</ref>).</s><s>CDK4 was present at the protein level, as well as induced at the transcriptional level, after NET induction (Figure <ref type="figure">S4A</ref>), while CDK6 was only present at the protein level (Figure <ref type="figure">5A</ref>).</s><s>Neutrophils did not express CDK2 or CDK1 (Figures <ref type="figure">5A   and S4A</ref>), in agreement with previous reports <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Leitch et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Klausen et al., 2004)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>CDK4/6 are implicated in phosphorylation of pRb <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Meyerson and Harlow, 1994)</ref> and in centrosome separation <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Hussain et al., 2013)</ref> both of which occur during NET formation (Figures <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2C and 2F</ref>).</s><s>Furthermore, CDK4/6 activity can be induced via MAPK signaling and is a central link between extracellular  growth signals and induction of proliferation <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Malumbres and Barbacid, 2009)</ref>.</s><s>CDK6 localizes throughout the cytoplasm in unstimulated neutrophils and transiently accumulates in the nucleus of PMA-stimulated cells (Figure <ref type="figure">5B</ref>).</s><s>We could not determine the localization of CDK4.</s><s>Neutrophils express the CDK4/6 regulatory co-factor cyclin D2 and low levels of cyclin D3 (Figure <ref type="figure">5C</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CDK4/6 Controls NET Formation</head><p><s>To test if these G1 kinases are involved in NET formation, we incubated human neutrophils with a CDK4/6 pharmacological inhibitor (abemaciclib/LY2835219), which efficiently blocked NETs in a dose-dependent manner (Figures <ref type="figure">5D, S4D, and S4E</ref>), but did not inhibit the oxidative burst (Figure <ref type="figure">5F</ref>), phagocytosis (Figure <ref type="figure">5G</ref>), or degranulation (Figure <ref type="figure">S4F</ref>).</s><s>This was confirmed with a second Cdk4/6 inhibitor (palbociclib, Figure <ref type="figure">5E</ref>).</s><s>Both inhibitors blocked ConA-induced NETs at lower concentrations than those required for PMA, consistent with ConA being a weaker stimulus.</s><s>CDK4/6 inhibition blocked translocation of elastase to the nucleus (Figure <ref type="figure">S4G</ref>), a requirement for NET release <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(Papayannopoulos et al., 2010)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>CDK4/6 double knockout mice die at late stages of embryonic development due to severe anemia <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Malumbres et al., 2004)</ref>.</s><s>The kinases have, however, been knocked out individually.</s><s>Cdk6 knockout mice are viable and have only mild hematopoietic disturbances <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Malumbres et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Hu et al., 2009)</ref>.</s><s>We used a Cdk6 À/À mouse strain in which expression of the gene was interrupted by insertion of a floxed transcriptional stop cassette in the first exon <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Hu et al., 2009)</ref>.</s><s>We purified neutrophils from the peritoneum of Cdk6 À/À and WT mice (Figure <ref type="figure">S5A</ref>) and obtained similar yields and purities (Figure <ref type="figure">S5B</ref>).</s><s>Like human neutrophils, mouse neutrophils expressed Cdk4 as well as Cdk6 (Figure <ref type="figure">S5A</ref>).</s><s>Despite this redundancy, Cdk6-deficient neutrophils were impaired in NET production in response to both PMA and C. albicans hyphae (Figures <ref type="figure">5H and S5C</ref>).</s><s>We obtained similar results with bone marrow-purified neutrophils (Figure <ref type="figure">S5D</ref>).</s><s>The oxidative burst was unaffected in the knockout animals (Figure <ref type="figure">5I</ref>), similar to the result with the CDK4/6 inhibitor.</s><s>There was no difference in peritoneal neutrophil maturity between the two genotypes, as revealed by expression level of the surface marker Ly6G (Figure <ref type="figure">S5E</ref>) and nuclear morphology (Figure <ref type="figure">S5F</ref>).</s><s>Likewise, we observed no difference in cytokine production (Figure <ref type="figure">5J</ref>), indicating that Cdk6 deficiency specifically affects NET production, rather than generally modulating inflammatory pathways.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cdk6 Is Required for Antifungal Defense In Vivo</head><p><s>To test the effect of Cdk6 and NET deficiency in infections, we used the murine C. albicans sepsis model, which closely reflects the human disease <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Spellberg et al., 2005)</ref>.</s><s>In this model, C. albicans colonizes the kidneys leading to renal failure <ref type="bibr" target="#b54">(Spellberg et al., 2005)</ref>.</s><s>The host anti-Candida response is mediated primarily by neutrophils <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Fulurija et al., 1996)</ref>, making this a good model for investigating the effect of Cdk6 and NET deficiency on immunity.</s><s>Mice were intravenously injected with live C. albicans and monitored over the course of the infection.</s><s>Cdk6 À/À animals lost weight more rapidly than WT animals (Figure <ref type="figure">6A</ref>) and also succumbed to the disease more rapidly than WT animals (Figure <ref type="figure">6B</ref>).</s><s>Nox2-deficient animals, which are similarly impaired in NET production, also showed reduced survival in response to C. albicans challenge (Figure <ref type="figure">6B</ref>).</s></p><p><s>We next infected mice with a sublethal dose of C. albicans and compared fungal loads in the kidneys 5 days post-infection.</s><s>We found a strikingly elevated C. albicans fungal load in knockout animals (Figure <ref type="figure">6C</ref>).</s><s>This effect was not due to differences in peripheral blood counts of neutrophils (Figure <ref type="figure">S6A</ref>) or other immune cells (Figure <ref type="figure">S5C</ref>).</s><s>Cdk6 was previously implicated in regulating cytokine production <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Handschick et al., 2014</ref>), but we found equivalent, or even elevated numbers of neutrophils infiltrating the kidneys of Cdk6 À/À animals on day 5 post-infection (Figure <ref type="figure">S6B</ref>), indicating that migratory capacity was unaffected.</s><s>The higher rates of neutrophil accumulation in knockout mice was likely a reflection of higher fungal burdens in these animals.</s><s>Furthermore, bone marrow-derived macrophages from WT and Cdk6 null mice produced pro-and anti-inflammatory mediators at similar rates (Figure <ref type="figure">S6D</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Consistent with previous descriptions of sublethal C. albicans infections <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Fisher et al., 2011)</ref>, histological analysis of infected kidneys demonstrated that, 5 days post-infection, the fungus produced hyphal filaments, which are associated with tissue destruction, and that these hyphae were collecting in excretory lesions in the papillae of the renal pelvis (Figure <ref type="figure">6D</ref>).</s><s>Immunofluorescence analysis revealed that hyphal masses were more abundant in knockout animals: 90% of Cdk6 À/À mice had detectable hyphae in the renal papillae, compared with 25% of WT mice.</s></p><p><s>Cdk6 is broadly expressed in hematopoietic and some non-hematopoietic mouse tissues <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Tigan et al., 2015)</ref>, so its contribution to proper immune defenses could derive from non-myeloid cell activity.</s><s>To investigate if Cdk6 is required in neutrophils, we restored expression of the kinase in knockout animals by breeding Cdk6 À/À mice with animals expressing Cre recombinase (Cre) under the control of a lysozyme M promoter (LysM-Cre).</s><s>This driver leads to expression of Cre in cells of the myeloid lineage, including neutrophils, monocytes, and macrophages.</s><s>Expression of Cre in neutrophils led to excision of the floxed STOP cassette and restored Cdk6 to similar levels as in WT mice (Figure <ref type="figure">S6C</ref>).</s><s>Importantly, genetic rescue of Cdk6 in myeloid cells of knockout mice restored the ability of these mice to mount proper immune responses against C. albicans (Figure <ref type="figure">6C</ref>), demonstrating a role for Cdk6 in antimicrobial defense.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>Neutrophils are terminally differentiated cells that have stopped proliferating.</s><s>Indeed, an analysis of cell-cycle proteins demonstrated a downregulation of cyclins and CDKs as neutrophils differentiate from hematopoietic precursors into mature cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Klausen et al., 2004</ref>).</s><s>Here we show that, despite this downregulation, neutrophils can re-activate some aspects of cell-cycle signaling, most notably CDK4/6, upon mitogenic stimulation.</s><s>We show that NETosis is accompanied by upregulation of Ki-67, phosphorylation of pRb, lamin A/C, and histone H3S10, as well as duplication of centrosomes and nuclear envelope breakdown.</s><s>Neutrophil activation does not result in DNA synthesis, condensation of chromosomes or cytokinesis, indicating that cell-cycle re-entry is not occurring.</s></p><p><s>In dividing cells, the cell cycle is tightly controlled and rapidly aborted in response to abnormalities, stress, or disruption of the sequential order of events.</s><s>Activation of these checkpoints often results in cell death <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Malumbres and Barbacid, 2009)</ref>.</s><s>It is interesting to speculate that NETotic cell death also results from triggering of one of these checkpoints.</s><s>For instance, attempted DNA replication without concomitant production of histones arrests the cell cycle in G 2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Gunesdogan et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>Furthermore, NET formation also requires production of ROS <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Fuchs et al., 2007)</ref>, which can damage DNA and activate the DNA damage checkpoint in both dividing cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Malumbres and Barbacid, 2009)</ref> and in neutrophils <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Harbort et al., 2015)</ref>.</s><s>At this point, it is unclear if CDK4/6 promote NETs via cell-cycle signaling or completely unrelated pathways; therefore the involvement of checkpoints also remains speculative.</s></p><p><s>ROS can also be mitogenic by activating growth factor receptors <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(Verbon et al., 2012)</ref>, but, in NETosis, NOX2-derived ROS do not appear to be upstream of cell-cycle signaling, as phosphorylation of pRb and lamin A/C proceeds unchanged in neutrophils from CGD patients.</s><s>CDK4/6 thus function in a parallel pathway to ROS production; these kinases are necessary but not sufficient for NET formation.</s></p><p><s>NET formation was inhibited by transduction of a peptide mimic derived from the CDK binding domain of p21, providing an indication that a CDK is involved in the process.</s><s>p21 is an endogenous cell-cycle inhibitor that blocks CDK activity, just like the peptide mimic employed here.</s><s>Cells from p21 null mice have higher proliferative capacities <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Balomenos et al., 2000)</ref> and neutrophils from these mice also exhibited elevated rates of NET formation.</s><s>p21 knockout mice have been reported to have stronger inflammatory reactions <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Martin et al., 2016)</ref> and, interestingly, p21 knockout mice also spontaneously develop SLE <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Balomenos et al., 2000)</ref>, a chronic autoimmune disease that has been associated with excessive NET release <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(Kaplan and Radic, 2012)</ref> and accumulation of antibodies against DNA and histones.</s></p><p><s>Mitogenic signaling in quiescent cells can lead to cell-cycle restart by activating CDK4/6 <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Tigan et al., 2015)</ref>.</s><s>Consistent with this idea, we show that CDK4/6 are activated upon mitogenic stimulation of neutrophils, and that these kinases regulate NET formation.</s><s>Our observation that CDK4/6 are the only cell-cycle CDKs expressed in human neutrophils potentially explains the unusual mix of cell-cycle markers induced during NET formation, since these kinases are active in both phosphorylating pRb in G 1 phase, and inducing centrosome separation in M phase <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Hussain et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>It remains unclear, however, if CDK4/6 control NETs via cell-cycle substrates or via targets that are unrelated to cell-cycle control.</s><s>pRb phosphorylation and centrosome separation could thus simply be markers of CDK4/6 activation, rather than being integral to the mechanism of NET release.</s></p><p><s>CDK6 is predominantly expressed in blood cells where it plays a role in T cell development and lymphomagenesis <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Hu et al., 2009</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Hu et al., , 2011))</ref>.</s><s>It regulates cell-cycle re-entry in certain subsets of hematopoietic precursors <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Laurenti et al., 2015;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b52">Scheicher et al., 2015)</ref>, but, despite this, levels of peripheral blood leukocytes, including neutrophils, are normal in Cdk6 knockout mice (Figure <ref type="figure">S5</ref>), probably due to compensation from Cdk4.</s><s>Alternative roles for Cdk6 as a transcriptional regulator have also been uncovered <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Handschick et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>It is unlikely that Cdk6 regulates NETs via transcriptional regulation, since NET formation is independent of de novo gene expression <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Sollberger et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>Furthermore, the fact that ROS and cytokine production, as well as surface marker expression, are unperturbed in Cdk6 À/À neutrophils, argues against a defect in differentiation or a general deficiency in inflammatory signaling.</s></p><p><s>We identify a role for Cdk6 in innate immune defense.</s><s>Mice lacking this kinase are highly susceptible to infection with the fungal pathogen C. albicans.</s><s>In acute systemic candidiasis, the immune response is predominantly mediated by neutrophils and not by T cell responses, since mice lacking T cells do not show any increase in susceptibility to disease <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Cutler, 1976)</ref>.</s><s>CDK6 was shown to regulate cytokine production in HeLa cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Handschick et al., 2014)</ref>, but we failed to detect a defect in neutrophil recruitment to infected organs.</s><s>Macrophages, the major producers of cytokines during infections, produced normal levels of these inflammatory mediators despite lacking CDK6.</s><s>Elevated kidney fungal loads are thus likely a reflection of a defect in neutrophil function, specifically one in NET formation, although the use of the LysM-Cre driver in the rescue experiment means we cannot rule out other impairments in myeloid cells.</s><s>Cdk6 was shown to regulate macrophage adhesion in response to lipopolysaccharide LPS, and knockout mice are protected against LPS-induced sepsis <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Hennessy et al., 2011)</ref>.</s><s>This finding is in line with a role for Cdk6 in NET formation, since NETs are also implicated in the pathology of sepsis <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Camicia et al., 2014)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>NETs are important for immune defense, but are also dysregulated in many autoimmune diseases.</s><s>Intriguingly, a genetic polymorphism in CDK6 has been associated with rheumatoid arthritis <ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(Raychaudhuri et al., 2008)</ref>.</s><s>CDK6 expression levels are also elevated in various types of cancer, and inhibition of this kinase appears to be a promising new antitumor therapy <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(Tigan et al., 2015)</ref>.</s><s>It is of note that malignancies such as chronic myelogenous leukemia are associated with high levels of NETinduced thrombosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Demers et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>The contribution of (C) C. albicans CFU expressed per gram of kidney tissue in WT, Cdk6 À/À , and conditional rescue Cdk6 À/À ; LysM-Cre + mice, 5 days post-infection with 1 3 10 5 CFU.</s><s>Lines indicate median.</s><s>**p &lt; 0.01; *p &lt; 0.05 Mann-Whitney U test.</s><s>ns, not significant.</s><s>(D) C. albicans (red) and neutrophils (Ly6G, green) in papillae of renal pelvis (visualized by DNA stain/blue) of WT and Cdk6 À/À mice, day 5 post-infection.</s><s>Representative image of nine analyzed kidneys per genotype.</s><s>Scale bar, 200 mm.</s><s>See also Figure <ref type="figure">S6</ref>.</s></p><p><s>CDK6 to cancer may thus be 2-fold: cell-cycle dysregulation contributing to tumorigenesis as well as increased NET formation by myeloid cell precursors leading to thrombosis, the second most common cause of death in cancer patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b50">(Rickles et al., 1992)</ref>.</s><s>Use of CDK4/6 inhibitors in cancer therapy may consequently lower rates of thrombosis, but also dampen immune responses in patients.</s></p><p><s>Interestingly, other instances exist where cell-cycle signaling in postmitotic cells has been linked to disease <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(Herrup and Yang, 2007)</ref>.</s><s>In the brain, neurons can inappropriately re-activate the cell cycle, which leads to cell death just as it does in neutrophils.</s><s>Cell death resulting from neuron cell-cycle re-entry has been linked to several neurodegenerative diseases, including Alzheimer's disease and amyotrophic lateral sclerosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Busser et al., 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Herrup and Yang, 2007)</ref>.</s><s>Dysregulation of cell-cycle proteins in postmitotic neurons and neutrophils can thus be viewed as a unifying disease principle in neurodegenerative and inflammatory disorders.</s></p><p><s>In summary, NET formation, an antimicrobial form of cell death, is controlled by the activation of the cell-cycle kinases CDK4/6.</s><s>During infection, lymphocytes activate the cell cycle to rapidly increase their numbers and thus fulfill their memory or cytotoxic functions.</s><s>We show that, in neutrophils, similar pathways are used for regulating the NETotic cell death program, with essential consequences for immunopathology and defense against pathogens.</s><s>These findings open up avenues for therapeutic interventions in NET-related diseases.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>STAR+METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>STAR+METHODS KEY RESOURCES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONTACT FOR REAGENT AND RESOURCE SHARING</head><p><s>Further information and requests for reagents should be directed to and will be fulfilled by the Lead Contact, Arturo Zychlinsky (zychlinsky@mpiib-berlin.mpg.de).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EXPERIMENTAL MODEL AND SUBJECT DETAILS Human Samples</head><p><s>Our study was conducted in accordance with the Helsinki Declaration.</s><s>Blood donations from healthy donors (male and female, ages 23-53) and CGD patient (male, age 23) were collected after obtaining informed consent.</s><s>Information on sample size can be found in the figure legends.</s><s>Histopathological samples were collected anonymously from diagnostic biopsies and autopsies, therefore sex and age reporting is not possible.</s><s>Both blood and pathology sample collection was approved by the ethical committee of Charite Úniversity Hospital, Berlin, Germany.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mice</head><p><s>Mouse breeding and experiments were approved by the Berlin state authority Landesamt f€ ur Gesundheit und Soziales.</s><s>Animals were bred locally at the Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology.</s><s>They were housed in approved specific pathogen free (SPF) conditions, maintained on a 12-hour light/dark cycle and fed ad libitum.</s><s>Cdk6 À/À mice (B6.129S4-Cdk6 tm1 /J) were generated by a knock-in approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Hu et al., 2009)</ref> and obtained from the Hinds laboratory.</s><s>They were bred homozygous.</s><s>p21 À/À mice, generated in the Leder lab (B6.129S6(Cg)-Cdkn1a tm1Led /J) were obtained from Jackson laboratory and were bred homozygous.</s><s>For conditional rescue of Cdk6 in myeloid cells, cdk6 À/À mice were crossed with LysM-Cre mice (B6.129P2-Lyz2 tm1(cre)Ifo /J), obtained from Jackson laboratory.</s><s>Experiments were carried out with male and female sex-and age-matched 8-12 week old mice that were confirmed to be infection free and had not been exposed to any previous procedures.</s><s>For estimation of group size we used the software nQuery.</s><s>Experimenters were not blinded to animal genotype.</s><s>For group sizes and statistical tests please see figure legends.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mouse Infections</head><p><s>C. albicans strain SC5314 was grown as an overnight culture in YPD medium at 30 C with shaking.</s><s>For lung infections, 10 6 cfu in PBS were delivered via the oral-tracheal route into 8 week old female wild-type C57B6 mice (n=6).</s><s>Mice were sacrificed and lungs were removed 18 hours later and fixed in 2% PFA.</s></p><p><s>For disseminated candidiasis, two different doses were used: for survival experiments, animals were injected intravenously (i.v.) with 5x10 5 cfu and monitored daily.</s><s>For kidney fungal load, renal histology and immune cell infiltration assays, 8 week old female mice were injected i.v. with 1x10 5 cfu.</s><s>After 5 days, animals were sacrificed and kidneys were removed.</s><s>One kidney was homogenized in a Precellys Evolution bead homogenizer (Bertin technologies) for plating and cfu determination and the other was processed for FACS analysis.</s><s>For group sizes and statistical tests please see figure legends.</s></p><p><s>Cell Line PLB-985 cells (female; RRID:CVCL_2162) were kindly donated by Dr. Mary Dinauer.</s><s>They were cultured according to standard protocols in RPMI medium with 10% FCS, glutamine and antibiotics.</s><s>Cells were used exclusively for controls or as a reference.</s><s>They were not checked for contamination with mycoplasma or with other cell lines.</s><s>Synchronization in G2 phase was achieved by incubating cells in presence of 10 mM RO3306 for 14 hours, followed by washing and reseeding in normal medium.</s><s>Quantitative Real-Time PCR RNA was isolated with RNeasy mini kit (Qiagen).</s><s>cDNA was made using High-capacity RNA-to-cDNA kit (Applied Biosystems) according to manufacturer's protocol.</s><s>qPCR was performed on StepOnePlus Real-Time PCR System with 2x Fast SYBR Green master mix (Applied Biosystems).</s><s>The housekeeping gene b2-microglobulin (F 5'-CTCCGTGGCCTTAGCTGTG-3' and R 5'-TTTGGAGTACGCTGGATAGCCT-3') was used as an internal control for relative standard curves.</s><s>All other cDNAs were amplified with Quantitect primer (Qiagen).</s><s>Data were analyzed using StepOne software.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Peptide Inhibition Experiments</head><p><s>Tat conjugated peptides were synthesized by Peptide 2.0 Inc (Chantilly, VA, USA).</s><s>p21inh, corresponding to amino acids 46-65 of the p21 protein: Ac-YGRKKRRQRRRRERWNFDFVTETPLEGDFAW-NH2; p21ctrl: Ac-YGRKKRRQRRRLWARDENDEVFRWFT PEFGT-NH2.</s><s>Neutrophils were incubated with 20 mM of peptides for 1 hour in Hank's Balanced Salt Solution (HBSS) without magnesium or calcium ions, with orbital rotation.</s><s>Subsequently, the cells were diluted 1:20 in culture medium, plated and stimulated with PMA.</s></p><p><s>EdU Incorporation Assay DNA synthesis was monitored using the Click-iT EdU Alexa Fluor 488 Imaging Kit (Thermo Fisher) as per manufacturer's instructions.</s><s>Neutrophils, T cells or HEK cells were incubated with EdU for 20 min before stimulation (in the case of neutrophils and T cells).</s><s>Control human T cells were purified from peripheral blood mononuclear cell (PBMC) fractions.</s><s>After separation on Histopaque 1119 (Sigma-Aldrich), PBMCs were stimulated with PHA, incubated for 5 days and then restimulated with 20 ng/ml PMA and 200 ng/ml ionomycin to induce proliferation in the presence of EdU.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mouse NETs</head><p><s>Mouse peritoneal neutrophils were elicited with casein (Sigma) and purified on a Percoll gradient as previously published <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Swamydas et al., 2015)</ref>.</s><s>Mouse bone marrow neutrophils were purified as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Sollberger et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>Cells were stimulated in RPMI supplemented with 1% DNase À/À mouse serum and 100 ng/ml G-CSF (Peprotech) with either PMA (100 nM) or heat killed C. albicans hyphae <ref type="bibr" target="#b53">(Sollberger et al., 2016)</ref> for the indicated times.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Histology</head><p><s>Human biopsy and autopsy tissue was fixed in formalin and embedded in paraffin.</s><s>Four micrometer thick paraffin sections were stained using routine Periodic acid-Schiff (PAS) staining or with antibodies against Ki-67 (MiB1, Dako) by using the iView-Ventana diaminobenzidine (DAB) Detection Kit (Ventana) with biotinylated secondary antibodies and DAB visualization of the peroxidase reaction product with a Benchmark XT immunostainer (Ventana).</s></p><p><s>Mouse lungs and kidneys were fixed in 2% PFA, embedded in paraffin and cut to 5 mm sections.</s></p><p><s>Immunofluorescence experiments were carried out with anti-Ki67 (Abcam SP6), anti-pericentrin (Abcam), anti-Calgranulin A (S100A8) (produced in-house) and anti-C.</s><s>albicans (Acris BP1006) primary antibodies, followed by Alexa secondary antibodies (Invitrogen).</s></p><p><s>Microscopy was performed with a Leica SP8 confocal microscope.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mouse Peripheral Blood Counts</head><p><s>Cell populations in whole blood were identified and quantified by flow cytometry with the following antibodies: anti-CD115 (AF598, eBioscience), anti-Gr-1 (RB6-8C5, Biolegend), anti-CD3 (17A2, BD Bioscience), anti-CD4 (RM4-5, BD Bioscience), CD8a (53-6.7,</s><s>BD Bioscience), anti-B220 (RA3-6B2, Biolegend).</s><s>Antibodies were added directly to 100 mL of heparinized whole blood at a 1:200 dilution and incubated at room temperature for 30 minutes.</s><s>Stained cells were fixed and erythrocytes were lysed simultaneously with 1-step Fix/Lyse solution (Affymetrix eBioscience).</s><s>AccuCheck Counting beads (Invitrogen) were added to obtain total cell counts.</s><s>Samples were acquired on a BD LSRFortessa using DIVA software and analyzed by Flowjo (Treestar) software.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ROS Assay</head><p><s>Neutrophils were seeded in 96-well plates at a concentration of 1x10 5 cells per well in 200 ml medium supplemented with 50 mM luminol and 1.2 units/ml horseradish peroxidase, both from Sigma.</s><s>After 30 minute incubation at 37 C, cells were stimulated with 100 nM PMA and luminescence was measured over time in a VICTOR Light luminescence counter (Perkin Elmer) and expressed as Relative Light Units (RLU).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phagocytosis Assay</head><p><s>Green fluorescent protein (GFP)-expressing C. albicans strain sc5314 (kind gift of Brendan Cormack) was opsonized with 10% human serum for 20 minutes and incubated with purified human neutrophils.</s><s>For inhibitor experiments, neutrophils were pretreated with compounds for 30 minutes.</s><s>Phagocytocis was allowed to proceed for 30 minutes at 37 C with rotation in RPMI supplemented with 0.1% human serum albumin, after which cells were fixed with 2% PFA.</s><s>Neutrophils were labelled with an anti-CD15 antibody coupled with allophycocyanin (APC).</s><s>Percentage phagocytosis was determined by FACS analysis of GFP and APC positive cells.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>A</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Mitogens Induce NETs (A) Human peripheral blood neutrophils isolated from a healthy donor or CGD patient (n = 2) with a genetic deficiency in NOX2, stimulated with PMA (50 nM) or ConA (50 mg/mL) for 5 hr.</s><s>Both stimuli lead to colocalization of chromatin (red), DNA (blue), and the granule protein neutrophil elastase (green).</s><s>Representative image from three independent experiments.</s><s>Nonstim, nonstimulated.</s><s>Top row, merge; bottom row, DNA.</s><s>Scale bars, 5 mm.</s><s>(B) Quantification of NET induction with mitogens and C. albicans, and inhibition with the NOX2 inhibitor diphenyliodonium (DPI, 5 mM).</s><s>Representative result of three independent repeats, means ± SD. (C) Electron micrograph comparing nuclear envelope breakdown in mitosis and NETosis.</s><s>Left: PLB-985 cells were synchronized in G2 and then released into mitosis.In G2 the nuclear envelope is intact but disintegrates in the prophase of mitosis, concurrently with appearance of condensed chromosomes (darker staining territories in the nucleus).</s><s>In anaphase, chromosomes have separated and, eventually the nuclear envelope begins to reform.</s><s>Right: nonstimulated neutrophils have a lobulated nucleus, but this lobulation is lost as they prepare to release NETs.</s><s>Approximately 2 hr after PMA stimulation, the nuclear envelope starts to disintegrate, allowing nuclear material to mix with the contents of the granules and the cytoplasm before being released into the extracellular space.</s><s>The bottom row shows magnified details from corresponding top panels.</s><s>Arrows indicate vesiculation of the nuclear envelope.</s><s>Neutrophil images are representative from at least five different embeddings.</s><s>Scale bars, 5 mm (upper panels; overview) and 1 mm (lower panels; detailed views).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,69.89,503.47,161.04,68.89" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. NET Formation Is Associated with Induction of Cell-Cycle Markers</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>(A) Nonstimulated (nonstim, top panel) and PMA-treated human neutrophils stained for Ki-67 (red) and elastase (green).</s><s>Representative image from four different experiments.</s><s>Scale bars, 5 mm.</s><s>(B) Quantification of nuclear Ki-67 staining during PMA time course stimulation.</s><s>The percentage of Ki67-positive cells (gray) is plotted along with the percentage of SYTOX-positive cells (black).</s><s>The graph shows means ± SEM from combined data of four healthy donors.</s><s>(C) Western blot of G1/S and M phase markers in lysates prepared from human neutrophils simulated with NET inducers (PMA, ConA, and C. albicans) and a control stimulus that does not induce NETs (fMLP).</s><s>''P-'' indicates phosphorylation.</s><s>Representative blot from three or more repeats with different donors.</s><s>Molecular weights are indicated in kDa.</s><s>(D) Immunofluorescence analysis of EdU incorporation in control HEK cells (left) and human neutrophils making NETs (right).</s><s>Neutrophils were incubated with nucleotide analog EdU for 1 hr before PMA stimulation and were then fixed at indicated times.</s><s>HEK cells (nonstimulated) were incubated with EdU or vehicle control for 1 hr before fixing.</s><s>(E) Immunofluorescence detection of microtubules with an antibody against aand b-tubulin (red), in a time course experiment of human neutrophils stimulated with PMA.</s><s>(F) Nonstimulated and PMA-treated (1 hr) human neutrophils stained for g-tubulin (red) and DNA (blue).</s><s>(E and F) Representative images from three different independent experiments, with cells from different donors.</s><s>Scale bars 5 mm.</s><s>(G) Quantification of separated centrosomes from (F).</s><s>Graph shows means ± SEM from combined data of four donors.</s><s>See also Figure S1.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. Neutrophils Activate Cell-Cycle Signaling In Vivo</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,65.20,101.59,479.48,484.67" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>A and B) Immunostaining of mouse lung infected with C. albicans (A) or human brain fungal abscess (B) showing neutrophils labeled with calgranulin (red) expressing Ki-67 (green) in the nucleus.</s><s>Representative image from six mice or four different human specimens.</s><s>(C) Neutrophils (red/calgranulin) in human brain fungal abscess, showing duplicated and separated centrosomes (green).</s><s>(A-C) Blue, DNA.</s><s>Scale bars, 10 mm.</s><s>See also Figure S2.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. p21 Regulates NETs (A) Human neutrophils were incubated with a peptide corresponding to the CDK inhibitory domain of the p21 protein (p21inh), or a scrambled control peptide (p21ctrl), at a concentration of 20 mM before activation of NETs with PMA.</s><s>The graph shows means ± SEM of NET formation after 4 hr.</s><s>n = 3 donors.</s><s>**p &lt; 0.01, unpaired Student's t test.</s><s>(B) Representative immunofluorescence images of PMA-stimulated cells pre-incubated with p21 peptide or scrambled control, from three independent repeats.</s><s>DNA is shown in blue and chromatin in red.</s><s>Scale bars, 10 mm.</s><s>(C) NET formation in WT and p21 À/À mouse peritoneal neutrophils after 5 hr of PMA stimulation.</s><s>Bars show means ± SEM, n = 4 mice.</s><s>***p &lt; 0.001, unpaired Student's t test.</s><s>(D) Oxidative burst in WT and p21 À/À mouse peritoneal neutrophils in response to PMA.</s><s>Bars show means of maximum luminescence intensity, ± SEM. n = 4; ns, non-significant, unpaired Student's t test.</s><s>See also Figure S3.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 .Figure 6 .</head><label>56</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. Cdk4/6 Control NET Formation For a Figure360 author presentation of Figure 5, see https://doi.org/10.1016/j.devcel.2017.10.013#mmc3.</s><s>(A) Expression of CDKs in human neutrophils (neutro) and control T cells by western blot analysis.</s><s>Molecular weights indicated in kDa.</s><s>(B) Left: image showing subcellular localization of CDK6 in naive and PMA-stimulated human neutrophils.</s><s>DNA is shown in blue and CDK6 in green.</s><s>Scale bars, 5 mm.</s><s>Right: Quantification of enrichment of CDK6 in neutrophil nuclei, n = 3 donors, bars show means and SEM.</s><s>**p &lt; 0.01, unpaired Student's t test.</s><s>(C) Expression of cyclin D in human neutrophils (neutro) and control PLB-985 cells (PLB) by western blot.</s><s>(A-C) Representative blots or image from three independent experiments with different donors.</s><s>(D and E) NET inhibition with the Cdk4/6 inhibitor abemaciclib (LY2835219) (D) and palbociclib (PD-0332991) after 4 hr of PMA or ConA stimulation (E).</s><s>Combined data from four donors.</s><s>Graph shows means and SEM.</s><s>(F) Oxidative burst in human neutrophils treated with Cdk4/6 inhibitor or vehicle.</s><s>Representative data from three independent repeats.</s><s>Bars = mean and SD.</s><s>(G) Phagocytosis of C. albicans by human neutrophils pretreated with vehicle (DMSO, black), abemaciclib (red), and cytochalasin D (blue), n = 3 donors.</s><s>(H) NET formation in WT and Cdk6 À/À mouse peritoneal neutrophils after 5 hr of stimulation with PMA or heat-killed C. albicans hyphae.</s><s>n = 4 per group.</s><s>****p &lt; 0.0001, ***p &lt; 0.001.</s><s>(I) Oxidative burst measured by luminol assay in WT or Cdk6 À/À mouse peritoneal neutrophils stimulated with 100 nM PMA.</s><s>n = 4 mice per group.</s><s>ns, not significant.</s><s>(J) Mip1a production in WT and Cdk6 À/À mouse neutrophils (n = 3 per group), in response to LPS (200 ng/mL).</s><s>(F-J) Graph shows means ± SEM, unpaired Student's t test.</s><s>See also Figures S4 and S5.</s><s>Developmental Cell 43, 449-462, November 20, 2017 457</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,97.19,103.75,433.54,554.05" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>REAGENT or RESOURCE</cell><cell>SOURCE</cell><cell>IDENTIFIER</cell></row><row><cell>Antibodies</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ki67</cell><cell>Abcam</cell><cell>ab16667, RRID: AB_302459</cell></row><row><cell>a/b Tubulin</cell><cell>Cell Signaling</cell><cell>Cat. No. 2148, RRID: AB_2288042</cell></row><row><cell>pericentrin</cell><cell>Abcam</cell><cell>ab4448, RRID: AB_304461</cell></row><row><cell>Lamin A/C phospho-ser392 (immunofluorescence)</cell><cell>Biorbyt</cell><cell>orb99257</cell></row><row><cell>Cdk6 (for human detections)</cell><cell>Santa Cruz</cell><cell>Cat. No. 177 (C-21) RRID: AB_631225</cell></row><row><cell>Cdk6 (for mouse detections)</cell><cell>Abcam</cell><cell>ab54576, RRID: AB_940952</cell></row><row><cell>Elastase</cell><cell>LsBio</cell><cell>B24-244</cell></row><row><cell>g tubulin</cell><cell>Thermo</cell><cell>MA1-19421, RRID: AB_1075282</cell></row><row><cell>anti-chromatin (reacts with a complex of Histone 2A,</cell><cell>Monestier lab</cell><cell>Losman et al., 1992</cell></row><row><cell>Histone 2B and DNA)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Cdk4 (for human detections)</cell><cell>Abcam</cell><cell>EPR4513, RRID: AB_10861376</cell></row><row><cell>Cdk4 (for mouse detections)</cell><cell>Genetex</cell><cell>GTX102993, RRID: AB_1949951</cell></row><row><cell>CCND1</cell><cell>Santa Cruz</cell><cell>sc-753, RRID: AB_2070433</cell></row><row><cell>CCND2</cell><cell>Santa Cruz</cell><cell>sc-593, RRID: AB_2070794</cell></row><row><cell>CCND3</cell><cell>Cell Signaling</cell><cell>2936, RRID: AB_10698739</cell></row><row><cell>CCNE1</cell><cell>Cell Signaling</cell><cell>HE12, RRID: AB_2071200</cell></row><row><cell>CCNE2</cell><cell>Abnova</cell><cell>10197, RRID: AB_1671803</cell></row><row><cell>CCNB1</cell><cell>Cell Signaling</cell><cell>4138, RRID: AB_2072132</cell></row><row><cell>CCNA2</cell><cell>Cell Signaling</cell><cell>BF683, RRID: AB_2071958</cell></row><row><cell>CDK2</cell><cell>Cell Signaling</cell><cell>78B2, RRID: AB_10695594</cell></row><row><cell>CDK7</cell><cell>Thermo</cell><cell>PA5-34791, RRID: AB_2552143</cell></row><row><cell>phospho-Lamin A/C S22</cell><cell>Cell Signaling</cell><cell>2026, RRID: AB_2136155</cell></row><row><cell>Lamin A/C</cell><cell>Cell Signaling</cell><cell>2032, RRID: AB_2136278</cell></row><row><cell>phospho histone H3 S10</cell><cell>Cell Signaling</cell><cell>9701, RRID: AB_331535</cell></row><row><cell>phospho pRb S780</cell><cell>Cell Signaling</cell><cell>9307, RRID: AB_330015</cell></row><row><cell>GAPDH</cell><cell>Cell Signaling</cell><cell>2118, RRID: AB_561053</cell></row><row><cell>Bacterial and Virus Strains</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Candida albicans</cell><cell>Urban lab, Umea University</cell><cell>SC5314</cell></row><row><cell>Biological Samples</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Human blood</cell><cell>This study</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Chemicals, Peptides, and Recombinant Proteins</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Abemaciclib</cell><cell>Selleck</cell><cell>LY2835219</cell></row><row><cell>Ribociclib</cell><cell>Selleck</cell><cell>PD-0332991</cell></row><row><cell>SYTO Green</cell><cell>Thermo Fisher</cell><cell>S7575</cell></row><row><cell>SYTOX Orange</cell><cell>Thermo Fisher</cell><cell>S11368</cell></row><row><cell>P21inh peptide</cell><cell>Peptide 2.0 Inc</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Ac-YGRKKRRQRRRRERWNFDFVTETPLEGDFAW-NH2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>P21 ctrl peptide</cell><cell>Peptide 2.0 inc</cell><cell>N/A</cell></row><row><cell>Ac-YGRKKRRQRRRLWARDENDEVFRWFTPEFGT-NH2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Deposited Data</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Microarray data</cell><cell>GEO repository</cell><cell>GSE103755</cell></row><row><cell>Experimental Models: Cell Lines</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PLB985</cell><cell>Mary Dinauer, University of Washington</cell><cell>CVCL_2162</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(Continued on next page)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Developmental Cell 43, 449-462.e1-e5, November 20, 2017 e1</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">DevelopmentalCell 43, 449-462.e1-e5, November 20, 2017 e3</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">e4 Developmental Cell 43, 449-462.e1-e5, November 20, 2017</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">DevelopmentalCell 43, 449-462.e1-e5, November 20, 2017 e5</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>We thank the blood donors; Alf Herzig and Baerbel Raupach for helpful discussions; and Christian Goosman for transmission electron microscopy.</s><s>B.A. was supported by an EMBO Long-Term Fellowship; B.E.C. is supported by Sonderforschungsbereich grant SFB-TR84.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Detailed methods are provided in the online version of this paper and include the following:</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHOD DETAILS</head><p><s>Purification of Human Peripheral Blood Neutrophils Venous blood was collected into EDTA tubes (S-Monovette, Sarstedt), layered on Histopaque 1119 (Sigma-Aldrich) and centrifuged for 20 min at 800 3 g.</s><s>The plasma and upper layers consisting mainly of lymphocytes and monocytes were discarded (or collected for T cell purification).</s><s>The neutrophil-rich layer was collected, leaving the red blood cells on the bottom of the tube.</s><s>Neutrophils were washed in PBS, and further fractionated on a discontinuous Percoll (Pharmacia) gradient consisting of layers with densities of 1105 g/ml (85%), 1100 g/ml (80%), 1093 g/ml (75%), 1087 g/ml (70%), and 1081 g/ml (65%).</s><s>After centrifugation for 20 min at 800 3 g, the interface between the 80% and 85% Percoll layers was collected and washed with PBS.</s><s>Neutrophil purity was determined to be &gt; 95% by FACS.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>NET Induction and Quantification</head><p><s>Human NETs were induced in culture medium consisting of RPMI supplemented with HEPES (10 mM) and 0.05% human serum albumin (HSA, Grifols), with 50 nM PMA (Sigma), 50 mg/ml ConA (Sigma), 50 mg/ml PHA (Sigma) or live C. albicans (previously opsonized in human serum) at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 5. Cells were stimulated with mitogens for 4 hours and with C. albicans for 2 hours.</s></p><p><s>NETs were enumerated using a SYTO/SYTOX staining technique.</s><s>The cell impermeable SYTOX orange dye (1 mM, Thermofisher) was used to detect NETs.</s><s>SYTO green, a cell-permeable DNA dye (250 nM, Thermofisher), was used to determine the total number of cells.</s><s>Images were taken on a Leica DM IRBE inverted microscope.</s><s>Percentage of NET release was calculated by dividing the number of SYTOX positive cells by the number of SYTO positive cells.</s><s>For studies with chemical inhibitors, cells were plated directly into culture medium containing the inhibitors.</s><s>Preincubation with Abemaciclib (LY2835219, Selleck) and Palbociclib (Selleck) was for 30 min at the indicated concentrations.</s><s>Stock solutions of inhibitors were made by dissolving in DMSO and stored for one week at room temperature after which they were discarded.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Immunofluorescence</head><p><s>Neutrophils were fixed on uncoated glass coverslips with 2% paraformaldehyde (PFA), permeabilized for 5 minutes with 0.5% Triton X-100, and then blocked at room temperature for 30 minutes in 1% bovine serum albumin, 5% normal donkey serum, and 3% cold-water fish gelatin (Sigma-Aldrich).</s><s>To promote attachment of unstimulated cells, neutrophils were first plated for 5 minutes in RPMI without human serum albumin, after which culture medium was added (RPMI with 0.05% HSA).</s><s>Primary antibodies used were: anti-Ki67 (Abcam SP6), anti-a/b Tubulin (Cell Signaling Technology [CST]), anti-pericentrin (Abcam), anti-Lamin A/C phospho-ser392 (Biorbyt), anti-Cdk6 (Santa Cruz, C-21), anti-elastase (EMD), anti-g tubulin (Thermo) and anti-chromatin (reacts with a complex of Histone 2A, Histone 2B and DNA, <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Losman et al., 1992)</ref>).</s><s>Samples were stained with primary antibodies for 1h at 37 C in blocking buffer, followed by secondary antibodies conjugated to Alexa Fluor 488 or 568 (Invitrogen) together with Hoechst 33342.</s><s>Coverslips were mounted in Mowiol and images were taken with a Leica SP8 confocal microscope.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Transmission Electron Microscopy</head><p><s>Cells were fixed with 2.5% glutaraldehyde, postfixed with 1% osmiumtetroxide, contrasted with uranylacetate and tannic acid, dehydrated and embedded in Polybed (Polysciences).</s><s>Specimens were then cut at 60 nm and contrasted with lead citrate.</s><s>Analysis was carried out on a Leo 906E transmission electron microscope (Oberkochen).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Western Blotting</head><p><s>Protein immunoblotting was performed as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Harbort et al., 2015)</ref>, with lysates prepared directly in hot SDS loading dye.</s><s>Primary antibodies used were as follows: anti-CDK6 (Santa Cruz, c-21 [for detecting human protein]), anti-Cdk6 (Abcam ab54576, [for detecting mouse protein]), anti-CDK4 (Abcam EPR4513 [for detecting human protein]), anti-Cdk4 (Genetex GTX102993 [for detecting mouse protein]), anti-CCND1, CCND2, CCND3 (Santa Cruz), anti-CCNE1 (CST HE12), anti-CCNE2 (Abnova 10197), anti-CCNA2 (CST BF683), anti-CCNB1 (CST 4138), anti-CDK1 (Abcam, clone A17), anti-CDK2 (CST 78B2), anti-CDK7 (Thermo Fisher PA5-34791), anti-phospho-Lamin A/C (S22 [CST]), anti-Lamin A/C (CST), anti-phospho histone H3 (S10 [CST]), anti-Histone H3 (CST), anti-phospho pRb (S780 [CST D59B7]), anti-pRb (CST) anti-Ki67 (Abcam SP6) and anti-GAPDH (CST).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Microarray Analysis</head><p><s>RNA from 8 healthy donors was isolated using RNeasy mini kit (Qiagen) and labeled with the Fluorescent Linear Amplification Kit (Agilent Technologies) according to manufacturer's instructions before hybridization to whole-genome 4344k human expression arrays (Agilent).</s><s>Data analysis was performed using the limma R package.</s><s>Expression values were background-corrected followed by quantile normalization between samples.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Degranulation Assay</head><p><s>Human neutrophils were stimulated with opsonized zymosan (10 mg/ml) or medium for 2 hours to stimulate degranulation of elastase.</s><s>Zymosan (Sigma) was opsonized with 10% pooled human serum from 6 donors for 30 minutes at 37 C. Elastase release in supernatants was quantified using the human elastase ELISA kit (Hycult).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Purification of Kidney Immune Infiltrate</head><p><s>Neutrophils in infected kidneys were analyzed as outlined in <ref type="bibr" target="#b56">(Swamydas et al., 2015)</ref>.</s><s>Briefly, kidneys were finely sliced with a scalpel and digested for 30 min in the presence of 0.2125 mg/ml Liberase TL (Roche) and 0.1 mg/ml DNase I (Roche).</s><s>After digestion, kidneys were strained through a 70 mm sieve, red cells were lysed with ACK lysis buffer (Lonza) and the pellet was resuspended in 40% Percoll.</s><s>This was loaded over 70% Percoll and centrifuged at 872x g for 30 min.</s><s>Cells were collected from the interface and analyzed by FACS.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>QUANTIFICATION AND STATISTICAL ANALYSIS</head><p><s>GraphPad Prism was used to generate graphs and perform all statistical tests.</s><s>For NET assays, immunofluorescence quantifications, ROS production, phagocytosis and cytokine secretion, graphs show means +/-standard error of the mean and unpaired t test was used for statistical comparisons.</s><s>Mann-Whitney U test was used for comparing cfu enumeration and neutrophil counts.</s><s>Survival data were analyzed by the Kaplan-Meier method with Mantel-Cox log-rank testing.</s><s>Details of statistical analyses for quantifications are in corresponding figure legends, including significance levels, exact n values and what n represents for each experiment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DATA AND SOFTWARE AVAILABILITY</head><p><s>The values for microarray expression analysis have been deposited in GEO repository as GEO: GSE103755.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil function: from mechanisms to disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Amulic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Cazalet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Hayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Metzler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zychlinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="459" to="489" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The cell cycle inhibitor p21 controls T-cell proliferation and sex-linked lupus development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Balomenos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Martin-Caballero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Garcia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Prieto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Flores</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Serrano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Martinez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="176" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lack of p21 expression links cell cycle control and appendage regeneration in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Bedelbaeva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Snyder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gourevitch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Clark</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leferovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cheverud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lieberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Heber-Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5845" to="5850" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophils sense microbe size and selectively release neutrophil extracellular traps in response to large pathogens</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Branzk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lubojemska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Hardison</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Gutierrez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Papayannopoulos</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1017" to="1025" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil extracellular traps kill bacteria</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Brinkmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Reichard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Goosmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Fauler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Uhlemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Weinrauch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zychlinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">303</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1532" to="1535" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ectopic cell cycle proteins predict the sites of neuronal cell death in Alzheimer&apos;s disease brain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Busser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Geldmacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Herrup</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2801" to="2807" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil extracellular traps in sepsis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Camicia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Pozner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">De</forename><surname>Larranaga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Shock</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="286" to="294" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acute systemic candidiasis in normal and congenitally thymic-deficient (nude) mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cutler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Reticuloendothel. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="124" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cancers predispose neutrophils to release extracellular DNA traps that contribute to cancer-associated thrombosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Demers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Krause</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Schatzberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Martinod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Voorhees</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Scadden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13076" to="13081" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Candida urinary tract infection: pathogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Fisher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kavanagh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Sobel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kauffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Newman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Infect. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="S437" to="S451" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Novel cell death program leads to neutrophil extracellular traps</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Abed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Goosmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hurwitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Schulze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Wahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Weinrauch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Brinkmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zychlinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">176</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="241" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil depletion increases susceptibility to systemic and vaginal candidiasis in mice, and reveals differences between brain and kidney in mechanisms of host resistance</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fulurija</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Ashman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Papadimitriou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Microbiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3487" to="3496" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A mimic of p21WAF1/CIP1 ameliorates murine lupus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Goulvestre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chereau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Nicco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mouthon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Weill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Batteux</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">175</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6959" to="6967" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Histone supply regulates S phase timing and cell cycle progression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Gunesdogan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jackle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Herzig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e02443</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Activation of the Raf-MEK-ERK pathway is required for neutrophil extracellular trap formation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hakkim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Martinez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hess</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Prinz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zychlinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Waldmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Chem. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="77" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Handschick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Beuerlein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Jurida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bartkuhn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Muller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Soelch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Weber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Dittrich-Breiholz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Scharfe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cyclin-dependent kinase 6 is a chromatin-bound cofactor for NF-kappaBdependent gene expression</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="193" to="208" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil oxidative burst activates ATM to regulate cytokine production and apoptosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Harbort</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Soeiro-Pereira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Von</forename><surname>Bernuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kaindl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Costa-Carvalho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Condino-Neto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Reichenbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Roesler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zychlinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amulic</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2842" to="2851" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutations of phosphorylation sites in lamin A that prevent nuclear lamina disassembly in mitosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Heald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Mckeon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="579" to="589" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toll-like receptor-4 (TLR4) down-regulates microRNA-107, increasing macrophage adhesion via cyclin-dependent kinase 6</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hennessy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Sheedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Santamaria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barbacid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A J</forename><surname>Neill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Biol. Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">286</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="25531" to="25539" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cell cycle regulation in the postmitotic neuron: oxymoron or new biology?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Herrup</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Yang</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="368" to="378" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A requirement for cyclin-dependent kinase 6 in thymocyte development and tumorigenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Deshpande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Enos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hinds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">69</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="810" to="818" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Deshpande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Schlichting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hinds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G.-F</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Van Etten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gounari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hinds</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">CDK6 kinase activity is required for thymocyte development</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6120" to="6131" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CDK6 associates with the centrosome during mitosis and is mutated in a large Pakistani family with primary microcephaly</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Hussain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Baig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Neumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Peche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Szczepanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Nurnberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tariq</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jameel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Khan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fatima</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum. Mol. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5199" to="5214" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil extracellular traps: doubleedged swords of innate immunity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kaplan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Radic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">189</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2689" to="2695" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diverse stimuli engage different neutrophil extracellular trap pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Kenny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Herzig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kruger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Muth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mondal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Brinkmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Von Bernuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zychlinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.7554/eLife.24437</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.24437" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Elife</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Klausen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bjerregaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Borregaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Cowland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">End-stage differentiation of neutrophil granulocytes in vivo is accompanied by up-regulation of p27kip1 and down-regulation of CDK2, CDK4, and CDK6</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Leukoc. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="569" to="578" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genetic defects in severe congenital neutropenia: emerging insights into life and death of human neutrophil granulocytes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Klein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="399" to="413" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CDK6 levels regulate quiescence exit in human hematopoietic stem cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Laurenti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Frelin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ferrari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Dunant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zandi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Neumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Plumb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Doulatov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Stem Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="302" to="313" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cyclin-dependent kinases 7 and 9 specifically regulate neutrophil transcription and their inhibition drives apoptosis to promote resolution of inflammation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Leitch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Lucas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Marwick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Duffin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Haslett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Rossi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Death Differ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1950" to="1961" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PAD4 is essential for antibacterial innate immunity mediated by neutrophil extracellular traps</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Lindberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kennett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Xiong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wang</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Exp. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">207</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1853" to="1862" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cdks, cyclins and CKIs: roles beyond cell cycle regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kaldis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Development</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">140</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3079" to="3093" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Monoclonal autoantibodies to subnucleosomes from a MRL/Mp(-)+/+ mouse. Oligoclonality of the antibody response and recognition of a determinant composed of histones H2A, H2B, and DNA</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Losman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Fasy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Novick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Monestier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1561" to="1569" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cell cycle, CDKs and cancer: a changing paradigm</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Malumbres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barbacid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Cancer</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mammalian cells cycle without the D-type cyclin-dependent kinases Cdk4 and Cdk6</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Malumbres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sotillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Santamaria</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Galan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Cerezo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ortega</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Dubus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Barbacid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="493" to="504" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mantovani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cassatella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Costantini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jaillon</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophils in the activation and regulation of innate and adaptive immunity</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="519" to="531" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Breaking the ties that bind: new advances in centrosome biology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mardin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Schiebel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">197</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="18" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ohayon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alkan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mocek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pederzoli-Ribeil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Candalh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Thevenot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Millet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tamassia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cassatella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil-expressed p21/waf1 favors inflammation resolution in Pseudomonas aeruginosa infection</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am. J. Respir. Cell Mol. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="740" to="750" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thrombosis: tangled up in NETs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Martinod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2768" to="2776" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A myeloperoxidase-containing complex regulates neutrophil elastase release and actin dynamics during NETosis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Metzler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Goosmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lubojemska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zychlinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Papayannopoulos</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Rep</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="883" to="896" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Identification of G1 kinase activity for cdk6, a novel cyclin D partner</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Meyerson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Harlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Cell. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2077" to="2086" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Papayannopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Metzler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hakkim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zychlinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil elastase and myeloperoxidase regulate the formation of neutrophil extracellular traps</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Cell Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">191</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="677" to="691" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Wysocki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Amoozgar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Maiorino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Fein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Jorns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Schott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kinugasa-Katayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Won</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cancer cells induce metastasis-supporting neutrophil extracellular DNA traps</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Sci. Transl. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="361" to="138" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Requirements for NADPH oxidase and myeloperoxidase in neutrophil extracellular trap formation differ depending on the stimulus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Parker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dragunow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Hampton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kettle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Winterbourn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Leukoc. Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">92</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="841" to="849" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Common variants at CD40 and other loci confer risk of rheumatoid arthritis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Raychaudhuri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Remmers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Hackett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Guiducci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Burtt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Gianniny</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Korman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Padyukov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kurreeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1216" to="1223" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hemostatic alterations in cancer patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Rickles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Levine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Metastasis Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="248" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Growth inhibition by CDK-cyclin and PCNA binding domains of p21 occurs by distinct mechanisms and is regulated by ubiquitin-proteasome pathway</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Rousseau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Cannella</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Boulaire</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Fitzgerald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fotedar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fotedar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncogene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4313" to="4325" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CDK6 as a key regulator of hematopoietic and leukemic stem cell activation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Scheicher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hoelbl-Kovacic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bellutti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tigan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Prchal-Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Heller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Schneckenleithner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Salazar-Roa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zochbauer-Muller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zuber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="90" to="101" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil extracellular trap formation is independent of de novo gene expression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Sollberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Amulic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zychlinsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e0157454</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mice with disseminated candidiasis die of progressive sepsis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Spellberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ibrahim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Edwards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Filler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Infect. Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">192</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="336" to="343" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Developmental Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">461</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017-11-20">November 20. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Isolation of mouse neutrophils</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Swamydas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Luo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Dorf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lionakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr. Protoc. Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>3.20.1-3.20.15</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CDK6 -a review of the past and a glimpse into the future: from cell-cycle control to transcriptional regulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Tigan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bellutti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kollmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tebb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Sexl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Oncogene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3083" to="3091" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The influence of reactive oxygen species on cell cycle progression in mammalian cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Verbon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Post</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Boonstra</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gene</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">511</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Warnatsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ioannou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Papayannopoulos</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neutrophil extracellular traps license macrophages for cytokine production in atherosclerosis</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inflammation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">349</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="316" to="320" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Science</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diabetes primes neutrophils to undergo NETosis, which impairs wound healing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Demers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Martinod</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gallant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Goldfine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Kahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="815" to="819" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
