<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Supplementary Table 1. Association of asthma DMP enrolment in the past 12 months (yes vs. no) with non-medication asthma care PM among adults with current asthma and structured review for asthma in the past 12 months. GEDA 2010. Odds ratios for having received an intervention (yes vs. no)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Supplementary Table 1. Association of asthma DMP enrolment in the past 12 months (yes vs. no) with non-medication asthma care PM among adults with current asthma and structured review for asthma in the past 12 months. GEDA 2010. Odds ratios for having received an intervention (yes vs. no)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5814AB4955B3AA07AC8B21F7775A51B6</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:43+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>For each variable, weighted proportions and unweighted n refer to survey participants who provided the information.</s><s>Unweighted n may vary due to missing values.</s><s>Odds ratio (OR) and 95% confidence interval (95%CI) obtained from multivariable logistic regression analyses; crude OR 0 ; 1 OR adjusted for age groups and gender; 2 OR adjusted for age groups and gender plus body mass index status, educational attainment status, and smoking status.</s></p><p><s>3 OR additionally adjusted for comorbidities, 4 OR additionally adjusted for urban-rural residence and having a personal family physician.</s></p><p><s>For all measure but inhalation technique monitoring and smoking cessation advice for current smokers, rates refer to population with current asthma; * process measure on inhalation technique monitoring refers to population with current asthma and prescription inhaler; and ** process measure on smoking cessation advice refers to population with current asthma and self-reported current smoking.</s></p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
