<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Human Genome Editing in the Clinic: New Challenges in Regulatory Benefit-Risk Assessment</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Mohamed</forename><surname>Abou-El-Enein</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Berlin-Brandenburg Center for Regenerative Therapies (BCRT)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite ´-Universit€ atsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Toni</forename><surname>Cathomen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute for Transfusion Medicine and Gene Therapy</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Medical Center</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Freiburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Freiburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Faculty of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Freiburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Freiburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zolta</forename><surname>´n Ivics</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Medical Biotechnology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Paul-Ehrlich-Institut</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Langen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Carl</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>June</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Center for Cellular Therapies</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Pennsylvania Perelman School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
									<region>PA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Matthias</forename><surname>Renner</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Division of Medical Biotechnology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Paul-Ehrlich-Institut</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Langen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Christian</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">National Institute for Biological Standards and Control (NIBSC), Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">South Mimms</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hertfordshire</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Gerhard</forename><surname>Bauer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="institution">University of California</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Davis</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="institution">Institute for Regenerative Cures (IRC)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Sacramento</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Human Genome Editing in the Clinic: New Challenges in Regulatory Benefit-Risk Assessment</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3FF4D7EE431E289460DE3E0F903A30E4</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.stem.2017.09.007</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:43+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>As genome editing rapidly progresses toward the realization of its clinical promise, assessing the suitability of current tools and processes used for its benefit-risk assessment is critical.</s><s>Although current regulations may initially provide an adequate regulatory framework, improvements are recommended to overcome several existing technology-based safety and efficacy issues.</s></p><p><s>Gene therapy to correct inborn defects has now been in clinical use for more than two decades, and several gene therapy products have received European marketing authorization <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Abou-El-Enein et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>Many successful gene therapy applications have focused on the transfer of therapeutic genes using both integrating and non-integrating viral vector systems.</s><s>The transferred genes usually complement or replace the function of the dysfunctional genes, thereby correcting the phenotype of the targeted cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Naldini, 2015)</ref>.</s><s>Other forms of gene therapy are based on targeted genome editing, such as by the use of designer nucleases.</s><s>In this context, a faulty gene is repaired in situ to correct loss-of-function mutations underlying inherited disorders, or alternatively, functional genes are mutated to confer resistance to a pathogen.</s><s>A major drawback of genome editing has been the low efficiency in human cells, but progress in the last 5 years significantly improved gene-editing efficiencies and enabled a swift translation of this technology to the clinic <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Cornu et al., 2017)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Clinical genome editing has been based on the development of reliable and more efficient designer nucleases for applications in humans, such as zinc-finger nucleases (ZFNs), transcription activator-like effector nucleases (TALENs), and CRISPR-Cas nucleases <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Carroll, 2014)</ref>.</s><s>These custom-made nucleases can be targeted to a specific region in the genome where they introduce a double-stranded DNA break, which triggers cellular DNA repair mechanisms <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Carroll, 2014)</ref>.</s><s>Due to the reasonably high efficiencies in several cells and tissues, genome editing has the potential to act as a long-lasting genetic therapy.</s></p><p><s>Valuable experience obtained from ex vivo gene transfer into lymphocytes and hematopoietic stem cells (HSCs) has guided initial applications of ex vivo genome editing.</s><s>In particular, ZFNs have shown promising success in gene editing of human cells over the past decade.</s><s>The first in-human clinical trial featuring ZFN technology was for the treatment of HIV infection, in which the gene coding for the CCR5 co-receptor was disrupted in T cells of HIV-infected individuals <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Tebas et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>More recently, TALENs have been clinically applied for the generation of universal chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) T cells, achieving remission in infants with relapsed refractory CD19+ B cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Qasim et al., 2017)</ref>.</s><s>However, the CRISPR-Cas system has recently taken the lead in gene-editing approaches.</s><s>Similar to ZFNs and TALENs, CRISPR-Cas has been used to edit a variety of primary hu-man cells, including HSCs and pluripotent stem cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Cornu et al., 2017)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The first in-human trial using CRISPR-Cas technology recently began at Sichuan University in China (NCT02793856).</s><s>The goal of this study is to test the safety and feasibility of disrupting the PDCD1 gene (encoding PD-1) in tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes obtained from patients with advanced lung cancer.</s><s>The first trial in the United States to use CRISPR-Cas was recently approved by the NIH Recombinant DNA Advisory Committee (NIH RAC) (1604-1524).</s><s>The trial aims to target melanoma through multiplex genome editing with three different targets to generate gene-disrupted allogeneic CAR T cells as universal effector cells against the cancer <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Ren et al., 2017)</ref>.</s><s>This protocol was subjected to full public NIH RAC review because it met the criteria of using ''a new vector, genetic material, or delivery methodology that represents a first-in-human experience, thus presenting an unknown risk.''</s><s>The main concerns raised by the scientific review committee of the NIH RAC were that gene-edited T cells could possibly harbor translocations resulting from the simultaneous editing of three different loci by the CRISPR-Cas9 system, and therefore samples from manufactured products require sensitive assays to detect any potential translocations.</s></p><p><s>Creating genetic changes that can correct disease phenotypes in vivo is the ultimate goal of many genome-editing therapeutic applications.</s><s>In the United States, the first FDA-approved Investigational New Drug (IND) for in vivo genome editing targets hemophilia B using ZFN-mediated targeted integration into the albumin gene locus as a liver-specific genomic ''safe-harbor site'' to express Factor IX (NCT02695160).</s><s>Follow-up studies have been proposed for patients with mucopolysaccharidosis I and II to use targeted integration of sequences encoding iduronidase or iduronate-2sulfatase, respectively, into the albumin locus of hepatocytes (NCT02702115 and NCT03041324).</s><s>Currently, no clinical data have been presented for any in vivo genome-editing protocols.</s></p><p><s>Since few ex vivo and in vivo geneediting strategies of somatic cells are currently in the clinic (reviewed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Cornu et al., 2017)</ref>, it seems appropriate to provide academic and industry investigators with an appropriate regulatory framework for upcoming approaches.</s><s>The United States Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and European Medicines Agency (EMA) guidelines provide standards for manufacturing, non-clinical assessment, and clinical evaluation, as well as product approval requirements for cellular and gene therapy products.</s><s>Ex vivo gene-editing strategies are comparable to ex vivo gene transfer applications, in which similar rules may apply for product quality, safety, and efficacy testing, as well as the evaluation of the benefit-risk balance.</s><s>However, in vivo gene editing differs substantially from conventional in vivo gene therapy; therefore, new rules for quality, safety, and efficacy testing may need to be developed.</s><s>Here, we explore several technology-based safety and efficacy issues that may inform the regulatory benefit-risk assessment of genome-editing approaches entering the clinic (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reagent Delivery under Good Manufacturing Practice Conditions</head><p><s>For the manufacturing of gene-edited cell populations in clinical settings under Good Manufacturing Practice (GMP) conditions, programmable nucleases need to be efficiently delivered to target cells <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Cornu et al., 2017)</ref>.</s><s>For ex vivo transfer of genome-editing tools, designer nucleases are generally transferred in the form of mRNA (ZFN, TALEN, and Cas9) or as a ribonucleoprotein complex (CRISPR-Cas).</s><s>Delivery in the form of RNA or protein has several advantages: fast kinetics of action, fast nuclease turnover, ease of fine-tuning nuclease concentration and activity, and no risk of integrating exogenous DNA into the host genome.</s><s>If gene correction or gene addition by HDR is the goal, an additional DNA component carrying the genetic information to be copied into the edited locus needs to be included.</s><s>Commonly, the HDR template is provided in the form of non-integrating viral vectors, such as integrase-deficient lentiviral vectors (IDLVs) or vectors based on adeno-associated virus (AAV).</s><s>For clinical in vivo genome editing, AAV vectors have been employed almost exclusively to deliver both the designer nuclease and the HDR template.</s><s>For all of the delivery systems described above (reviewed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Yin et al., 2017)</ref> For in vivo genome-editing approaches, biodistribution assessments will be much more challenging.</s><s>In addition to their impact on gene editing in different tissues and cell types, the presence and potential persistence of the genome-editing tools (nucleic acids and proteins) need to be evaluated.</s><s>Usually, a diverse panel of tissues from all major organ systems is collected for biodistribution studies, and dose levels, dosing schedule, and route of administration of the gene-editing agents need to be taken into consideration.</s><s>Half-lives may vary from tissue to tissue, and also clearance of the agents will likely be mediated by different mechanisms, dependent on the gene-editing tools and their delivery system.</s><s>During this phase of assessment, identifying and quantifying any potential toxicities, and establishing a dose response by defining the best effective clinical dose with the least toxic effects, are also warranted.</s><s>The currently available regulatory guidance does not specifically address preclinical assessments of genome editing.</s><s>Nevertheless, some EMA guidance can provide a basis for the assessment of ex vivo genome-edited products (European <ref type="bibr">Medicines Agency, 2008a</ref><ref type="bibr">, 2012)</ref>, while other EMA and FDA guidance can provide the basic principles of non-clinical testing for in vivo genome-edited products (European Medicines Agency, 2008b; Food and Drug Administration, 2013).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Identifying Predicted and Unpredicted Effects</head><p><s>In a clinical setting, potential toxicities from ex vivo gene-edited cellular products, such as immunogenicity, will likely be similar to those encountered with ex vivo genetically manipulated cellular products using integrating vectors.</s><s>The toxicities will likely be caused by the cellular product itself, as well as the gene-editing processes.</s><s>We can learn about handling the risk of insertional oncogenesis from previous clinical experience with ex vivo transduction of HSCs or differentiated lymphocytes with retro-or lentiviral vectors <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Naldini, 2015)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>A major concern with using gene editing for therapeutic purposes is off-target activity, which is unintended cleavage of the designer nuclease at loci closely related to the actual target site.</s><s>Off-target activity can induce chromosomal translocations and/or indel mutations that produce loss-of-function or gain-of-function mutations, such as downregulating tumor suppressor genes or activating protooncogenes <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Corrigan-Curay et al., 2015)</ref>.</s><s>Moreover, multiplex genome editing, such as with CRISPR-Cas, has an even higher potential to induce chromosomal translocations due to the creation of two (or more) intended double-strand breaks on multiple chromosomes.</s><s>It will be important to reliably identify intrachromosomal and interchromosomal translocations with high sensitivity, ideally at the singlecell level.</s></p><p><s>Currently, several sensitive assays based on high-throughput sequencing are used to measure off-target effects, including bioinformatics tools to predict off-target sites followed by targeted amplicon sequencing, genome-wide double-strand break capture assays followed by tag-specific amplicon sequencing, and genome-wide translocation sequencing (reviewed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Tsai and Joung, 2016)</ref>.</s><s>While some of these methods are highly sensitive and may identify off-target activity in the actual human target cells with high accuracy, there is still no means of predicting the biological long-term consequences of these off-target effects.</s><s>Reliable biological control tests are needed that can demonstrate efficacy, specificity, and safety in the targeted tissue.</s></p><p><s>The issue of off-target toxicity depends on the genomic makeup of each individual and can only be addressed experimen-tally for each manufactured cellular product batch for ex vivo gene-editing cases, or clinically for each patient for in vivo gene-editing cases.</s><s>Undeniably, off-target effects are a major safety factor in in vivo genome-editing applications, and persistent nuclease expression may even enhance these effects.</s><s>Continuous nuclease activity may trigger unpredictable phenotypic changes in cells, which will be difficult to model in vitro or in animal models.</s><s>For in vivo gene-editing approaches, it may therefore be necessary to specifically target tissues in need of correction while restricting nuclease expression to a certain time window in order to minimize off-target effects and to direct maximal therapeutic efficacy to the desired tissues.</s><s>Besides evaluating potential genotoxic effects related to the actual process of gene editing, all other toxic effects associated with the delivery and expression of the gene-editing components and the expression of the actual therapeutic or corrected gene also need to be addressed in appropriate preclinical studies prior to clinical evaluation.</s></p><p><s>Finally, it is critical to evaluate product potency through relevant parameters for biological activity.</s><s>Potency assays, which are indicators of clinical efficacy, will need to be specific for the desired genome-editing effect.</s><s>However, these assays also need to consider the possibility of a selective survival advantage being conferred to the gene-edited cells, which could be deleterious or beneficial, depending on the clinical application.</s><s>The potency of the ex vivo-edited cellular product is not only determined by the expression level of the corrected gene and the resulting function of the expressed gene product, but also by its phenotypic composition, cell viability, growth, and, potentially, differentiation capability.</s><s>Testing for absence of the gene-modifying protein or nucleic acids is also an important safety aspect to prevent ongoing genome modification, and this test should be incorporated into the panel of release tests for a clinical-grade product.</s><s>In the United States, the FDA Guidance for Industry on Potency Tests for Cellular and Gene Therapy Products (Food and Drug Administration, 2011) acknowledges that there may be complex mechanisms of action and difficulties in assessing the in vivo fate of the product.</s><s>These same problems spill over into the development of potency</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cell Stem Cell</head><p><s>Forum assays for gene-edited products.</s><s>Eventually, during clinical trials, particular attention needs to be paid to any functional implications and long-term toxicities.</s><s>For detecting such toxicities, adequate follow-up measures should be in place.</s><s>After the 1999 gene therapy incident in the United States <ref type="bibr">(Washington Post, 1999)</ref> and the X-linked SCID gene therapy incidences in France and the United Kingdom <ref type="bibr">(New York Times, 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">BBC News, 2007)</ref>, the FDA implemented a lifelong follow-up after HSC gene therapy, which was later reduced to 15 years.</s><s>It is understandable that a lifelong follow-up of clinical trial subjects is almost impossible, particularly if a normal lifespan is achieved after therapy, and even a 15year follow-up is plagued with enormous logistical hurdles.</s><s>According to guidelines in the EU, the proposed follow-up for gene therapies is at least 5 years (European Medicines Agency, 2009), while a 15-year follow-up was recommended in the European public assessment reports (EPARs) for Strimvelis, the first ex vivo stem cell gene therapy approved in Europe <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Abou-El-Enein et al., 2016)</ref>.</s><s>Perhaps regulatory agencies could suggest a reasonable range of follow-up times tailored to specific genome-editing clinical applications.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>Genome-editing technologies allow unprecedented possibilities for modifying, adding, or deleting genetic sequences in human cells for the prevention, treatment, or cure of a large number of diseases, either inherited or acquired <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Cornu et al., 2017)</ref>.</s><s>Many of the regulatory principles established at the Asilomar Conference on Recombinant DNA in 1975 for ''classical gene therapy'' will apply to genome editing, particularly if ex vivo gene editing is performed.</s><s>Nevertheless, there are several challenges in the therapeutic development process that influence the benefit-risk profile of these therapies, which are not always feasible to overcome (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref>).</s><s>Particular caution is required to minimize possible off-target mutations before wider utilization of CRISPR technology in clinical testing.</s><s>As the science around genome editing rapidly evolves, regulators should adjust and advance the current tools and processes used for risk assessments based on a dialog with basic, translational, and clinical scientists to enhance clinical success of these novel therapeutic approaches.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>A Regulatory Perspective on Feasibility to Surmount Genome-Editing Safety and Efficacy Challenges</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">, well-known</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">manufacturing and testing standards</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">already exist and are readily adaptable</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">for acceptable clinical gene transfer</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">system creation (European Medicines</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Agency, 2012; Food and Drug Administra-</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">tion, 1998). Nevertheless, raw materials</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">used during manufacture of genome-edi-</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">ted products may not be available as</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">GMP grade. Being aware of this dilemma,</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">a new European Pharmacopoeia general</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">chapter for ''Raw materials of biological</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">origin for the production of cell-based</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">and gene therapy medicinal products''</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">became effective at the beginning of</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">2017 (European Pharmacopoeia, 2017),</cell></row><row><cell>wherein</cell><cell>appropriate</cell><cell>guidance</cell><cell>is</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>The authors thank Luigi Naldini for his valuable comments and suggestions on an earlier draft of</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>the manuscript.</s><s>The views expressed in this article are the personal views of the authors and may not be understood or quoted as being made on behalf of or reflecting the position of the</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Abou-El-Enein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Elsanhoury</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Reinke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell Stem Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="297" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Carroll</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu. Rev. Biochem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">83</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="439" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Cornu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mussolino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Cathomen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="415" to="423" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Corrigan-Curay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>O'reilly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kohn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cannon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Bao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Bushman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Carroll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Cathomen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Joung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Roth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mol. Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="796" to="806" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Naldini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">526</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="360" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Qasim</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Samarasinghe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Adams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Amrolia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Stafford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rivat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Somana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Sci. Transl</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Med</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/scitranslmed.aaj2013</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.aaj2013" />
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>June</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin. Cancer Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2255" to="2266" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Tebas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Stein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Frank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Spratt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Surosky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Giedlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Nichol</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N. Engl. J. Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">370</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="901" to="910" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Tsai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Joung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="300" to="312" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kauffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anderson</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat. Rev. Drug Discov</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="387" to="399" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
