<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Initial experience in the application of the PowerQuant TM system and the Investigator 1 ESSplex SE QS kit for aDNA analysis</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-09-25">25 September 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Pflugbeil</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Legal Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leipzig</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Johannisallee 28</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-04103</postCode>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Applied Sciences -Forensic Science Investigation Lab (FoSIL)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Technikumplatz 17</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-09648</postCode>
									<settlement>Mittweida</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Groß</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Applied Sciences -Forensic Science Investigation Lab (FoSIL)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Technikumplatz 17</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-09648</postCode>
									<settlement>Mittweida</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rothe</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute of Legal Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Forensic Genetics</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Augustenburger Platz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Charité Berlin, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Heinke</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Applied Sciences -Forensic Science Investigation Lab (FoSIL)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Technikumplatz 17</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-09648</postCode>
									<settlement>Mittweida</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Bruchhaus</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Legal Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leipzig</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Johannisallee 28</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-04103</postCode>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Edelmann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Legal Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leipzig</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Johannisallee 28</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-04103</postCode>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Labudde</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Applied Sciences -Forensic Science Investigation Lab (FoSIL)</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Technikumplatz 17</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-09648</postCode>
									<settlement>Mittweida</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dreßler</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Legal Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leipzig</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Johannisallee 28</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-04103</postCode>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Thiele</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Legal Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leipzig</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Johannisallee 28</addrLine>
									<postCode>D-04103</postCode>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Molecular Genetics</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Institute of Legal Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Leipzig</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Johannisallee 28</addrLine>
									<postCode>04103</postCode>
									<settlement>Leipzig</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Initial experience in the application of the PowerQuant TM system and the Investigator 1 ESSplex SE QS kit for aDNA analysis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-09-25">25 September 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">38A213A46C8B094AD6ACA02C4D5FB098</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.fsigss.2015.09.167</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 5 September 2015 Accepted 21 September 2015</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:43+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>aDNA Degradation PCR inhibition Down-stream analyses</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Degradation-related poor quality of ancient DNA from long-time stored biological material (e.g.</s><s>historical skeletal remains) often leads to a loss of information in molecular genetic characterisation.</s><s>A new generation of DNA quantification and STR technologies consider mentioned issue by an optimised primer design combined with active master mix components.</s><s>In this respect, the efficiency of the new PowerQuant TM (Promega) quantification kit and the Investigator 1 ESSplex SE QS STR kit (QIAGEN) was tested and analysed.</s><s>Both analyses tools were evaluated by their applicability to monitor the presence of possible PCR inhibitors and DNA degradation that influences downstream STR analyses and further result interpretation.</s><s>Characteristic features that reflect mentioned phenomena of both systems where correlated with respect to a combined use in aDNA analyses.</s></p><p><s>Here, especially the Investigator 1 ESSplex SE QS kit, which features an intelligent system design comprising both DNA typing and quality control, has shown to be valuable.</s><s>Some given result interpretation thresholds were adapted with regard to aDNA applicability in forensic case work and anthropological interest.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p><s>The major problem, when ancient DNA (aDNA) is analysed in a forensic or anthropological interest, is the present constitution of the molecule, which can influence the success of down-stream analyses steps in different ways.</s><s>Poor quality of long-time stored samples, e.g.</s><s>historical skeletal remains, can be explained on the one hand by time depended DNA degradation processes, that are caused by different environmental and physical factors <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2]</ref>.</s><s>Moreover, the presence and co-extraction of PCR inhibitors e.g.</s><s>humic acid or organic solvents can influence the step of DNA quantification in form of reduced product yields or complete failure in quantification <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s>Both points lead to a loss of information in aDNA typing and furthermore to a decrease of the evidential power of biostatistics.</s><s>Taking into account the mentioned issues there is a big need of multi-faceted approaches and suitable tools for casework and anthropological samples, which make it possible to handle the state of the molecule in an efficient way.</s></p><p><s>For quantification of those challenging samples, Promega offers a novel multicopy target system, called PowerQuant TM .</s><s>Beside the quantification of Y-chromosomal and autosomal DNA, it is possible to fix the degradation level by the calculation of a degradation index.</s><s>This index is described by the ratio of quantified concentrations for the autosomal and degradation target [C Auto /C D ].</s><s>Furthermore, possible inhibition can be addressed by an internal positive control (IPC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>Corresponding effects are indicated by a defined shift from given C t value for that IPC target.</s></p><p><s>For down-stream STR applications, the Investigator 1 ESSplex SE QS kit was used in this study.</s><s>The Primer Mix contains two innovative internal amplification controls (Quality Sensor QS1 and QS2) to provide helpful information about the presence of PCR inhibitors and the success of PCR <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s>Both artificial integrated Quality Sensors are amplified simultaneously with the polymorphic STR markers.</s><s>By calculating the ratio of the peak areas of both quality sensors [QS2/QS1] statements about the presence of potential inhibitors can be made.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Material studied, methods and techniques</head><p><s>We analysed three different sample sets.</s><s>Two of these included DNA extracts of historical skeletal material (bones and teeth) of the migration period (n = 80) and the early middle age (n = 23).</s><s>The third set included specific prepared DNA extracts (n = 12) that were charged with different amounts of humic acid.</s><s>DNA of skeletal material was purified by a phenol chloroform/isoamyl alcohol method.</s><s>In the case of artificial prepared samples, DNA was extracted by the application of two silica based methods.</s><s>All extracts were quantified with the novel PowerQuant TM kit.</s><s>STR analysis was carried out by the Investigator 1 ESSplex SE QS kit.</s><s>The power of different kit features (degradation indices, IPC-shift, QS ratio) of both technologies were then evaluated with respect to display degradation and inhibition.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head><p><s>In general, the PowerQuant TM kit proved to be very sensitive for quantifying low template or degraded DNA.</s><s>Estimated DNA concentrations for historical sample sets ranged from 0.3 pg/ul to 350 pg/ul.</s><s>For degradation monitoring, observed degradation ratios (PowerQuant TM ) were correlated with the number of locus drop out in related STR profiles (Investigator 1 ESSplex SE Plus).</s><s>Inhibitory effects were explained by measured shifts in C t values of the IPC target.</s><s>We observed some peak imbalances in heterozygous loci and locus drop out events of samples with IPC-shift &gt;0.3.</s><s>Overall 50% of samples from set one and two showed locus drop out events in more than one STR system.</s><s>Estimated values for IPCshift also increased with increasing concentrations of humic acid and peak areas in related Investigator 1 ESSplex SE QS profiles decreases.</s><s>Strong inhibitory effects were reliable displayed by the Quality Sensors in STR profiles of prepared DNA extracts with 500 mg up to 5000 mg amount of humic acid.</s><s>Effects of either degradation or inhibition could be distinguished by the estimation of the ratio based on peak areas of both quality sensors [QS2/QS1].</s><s>DNA profiles with estimated [QS2/QS1] ratio &gt;0.8 reflected no inhibitory effects.</s><s>Considering a combined application of both systems, it was seen that IPC-shifts correlate with estimated [QS2/ QS1] ratios and corresponding profiles for inhibited samples (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p><s>It can be suggested that a higher threshold (&gt;10) for the degradation index is more suitable for validation of aDNA results than given threshold of the manufacturer (&gt;2), especially when complex STR kits with fragment length higher than 400 bp are used.</s><s>In some of the cases, it was possible to create full STR profiles with suitable peak heights with a degradation index up to 10.</s><s>When using miniSTR kits, the correlation between degradation index and profile quality is not recommended due to the length of the degradation target (435 bp).</s></p><p><s>It was found that the given threshold for IPC-shift (&gt;0.3) for the interpretation of possible inhibitory effects is appropriate.</s></p><p><s>The Investigator 1 ESSplex SE QS kit has shown to be valuable.</s><s>Inhibitory effects due to the influence of humic acid amounts up to 5000 mg were displayed reliable by the ratio of peak areas of both quality sensors.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head><p><s>In summary a reliable indication of PCR inhibition by the application of features "IPC-shift" (PowerQuant TM ) and "[QS2/ QS1]" (Investigator 1 ESSplex SE QS) could be observed.</s><s>The level of DNA degradation can be assessed by the [Auto/D] index, but does not reflect STR profile quality in any case.</s><s>Thus a higher degradation index should be considered in aDNA analyses.</s><s>In general it should be noted, that the significance of STR profile quality at aDNA quantification &lt;10 pg/ml should be carefully evaluated.</s></p><p><s>Here, especially the Investigator 1 ESSplex SE QS kit, which features an intelligent system design comprising both DNA typing and quality control, has shown to be valuable.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1.</s><s>QS ratio vs. IPC-shift.</s><s>The figure illustrates the coaction of two analysed system features: IPC-shift and QS ratio [QS2/QS1].</s><s>It can be seen, that in case of analysed inhibited samples (defined as sample set three), the presence of PCR inhibitors can be assessed by a combination of both features as a kind of inhibition control.</s><s>Dashed lines imply IPC-shift threshold (0.3) and QS ratio threshold (0.8).</s><s>Different coloring of symbols (green and orange) refers to an experimental set up in duplicate for samples, which were charged with humic acid.</s><s>Size of symbols correlates with amount of humic acid [mg].</s><s>(For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.)</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,60.04,464.77,216.00,194.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p><s>We thank all participants who contributed to the successful completion of the project.</s><s>In particular we want to thank the companies Promega and QIAGEN for the provision of test kits.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p><s>We wish to confirm that there are no known conflicts of interest associated with this publication and there has been no significant financial support for this work that could have influenced its outcome.</s><s>We confirm that the manuscript has been read and approved by all named authors.</s><s>We further confirm that the order of authors listed in the manuscript has been approved by all of us.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Forensic DNA testing of skeletal remains from massgraves: a pilot study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Boles</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Forensic Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="349" to="355" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Factors affecting the STR amplification success in poorly preserved bone samples</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Putkonen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Palo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Cano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Invest. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Forensic implications of PCR inhibition -a review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Alaeddini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Forensic Sci. Int. Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="297" to="305" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Promega</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.promega.de/resources/protocols/technical-manuals/101/powerquant-system-protocol" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PowerQuant TM System Technical Manual</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Qiagen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Se Qs</forename><surname>Investigator 1 Essplex</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Kit</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.qiagen.com/us/resources/download.aspx?id=b0eb75b0-9b62-4bb3-8672-91eaa506f2ee&amp;lang=en" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
