<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Incidence, prevalence and 1-year all-cause mortality of heart failure in Germany: a study based on electronic healthcare data of more than six million persons</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MPH</roleName><forename type="first">Christoph</forename><forename type="middle">;</forename><surname>Ohlmeier</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Leibniz Institute for Prevention Research and Epidemiology -BIPS</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bremen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD, MSc</roleName><forename type="first">Rafael</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Mikolajczyk</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Johann</forename><forename type="middle">;</forename><surname>Frick</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Franziska</forename><forename type="middle">;</forename><surname>Prütz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Wilhelm</forename><forename type="middle">;</forename><surname>Haverkamp</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><roleName>Edeltraut</roleName><surname>Garbe</surname></persName>
							<email>garbe@bips.uni-bremen.de</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Edeltraut</forename><surname>Garbe</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Leibniz Institute for Prevention Research and Epidemiology -BIPS</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bremen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">University of Bremen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bremen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Augustenburger</forename><surname>Platz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Leibniz Institute for Prevention Research and Epidemiology -BIPS</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bremen</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">D -13353</forename><surname>Berlin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Helmholtz Centre for Infection Research</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Braunschweig and Hannover Medical School</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hannover</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Leibniz Institute for Prevention Research and Epidemiology -BIPS Department of Clinical Epidemiology Unit Epidemiology in Patient Populations Achterstraße 30</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>D -28359</postCode>
									<settlement>Bremen</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Helmholtz Centre for Infection Research Head of Research Group &quot;Epidemiological and Statistical Methods&quot; Inhoffenstraße 7</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>D-38124</postCode>
									<settlement>Braunschweig</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Deputy Head of Medical Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Division of Cardiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="department">Leibniz Institute for Prevention Research and Epidemiology -BIPS Head of Department of Clinical Epidemiology Achterstraße</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>30 1 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 1 2 3</addrLine>
									<postCode>D -28359</postCode>
									<settlement>Bremen</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Incidence, prevalence and 1-year all-cause mortality of heart failure in Germany: a study based on electronic healthcare data of more than six million persons</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">4D63B840965188FE22A9F9B38986B82C</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1007/s00392-015-0841-4</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:43+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Atrial fibrillation</term>
					<term>health insurance data</term>
					<term>epidemiology</term>
					<term>antithrombotic medication</term>
					<term>Germany 5 10 11 12</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Data on the epidemiology of atrial fibrillation (AF) and its antithrombotic management in elderly populations are scarce.</s><s>The aims of this study were to estimate the incidence and prevalence of AF in the elderly in Germany and to describe antithrombotic management of AF cases.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head><p><s>Estimation of prevalence and incidence was based on data of three German statutory health insurances, which insured more than 800,000 people aged 65 years and older in the study period.</s><s>The one year period prevalence of AF was estimated for each of the years 2004-2007.</s></p><p><s>The incidence rate of AF in 2007 was assessed in patients with a preceding continuous threeyear insurance period without diagnoses of AF.</s><s>Antithrombotic management of AF was described among incident AF cases in 2008 and predictors for lack of prescriptions of oral anticoagulants were identified.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>Age-standardised period prevalence of AF among those 65 years or older was 7. 7% in 2004,   9.4% in 2005, 9.8% in 2006 and 10.3% in 2007.</s><s>The age-standardised incidence of AF was 27.4/1,000 person-years in 2007.</s><s>Prevalence and incidence increased with age and were higher in men than in women.</s><s>In 2008, 58.2% of new AF cases received antithrombotic drugs.</s></p><p><s>Treatment was less common among women and older people.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>Incidence and prevalence of AF are relatively high in the elderly in Germany.</s><s>A considerable fraction of new AF cases did not receive antithrombotic drugs in routine care.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Condensed abstract</head><p><s>Using a large health care database, we estimated incidence and prevalence of atrial fibrillation <ref type="bibr">(27.4</ref>/100,000 person-years and 10.3%, respectively) in Germany among the ≥65 years old.</s></p><p><s>Around 60% of patients with new atrial fibrillation diagnoses received antithrombotic drugs; this treatment was less common among women and at older age.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>What's new?</head><p><s> Information on the prevalence of atrial fibrillation in the elderly in Europe is scarce.</s></p><p><s>Our study showed that the condition is common in the ≥65 years old in routine care in Germany (~10%).</s></p><p><s> Based on consideration of also secondary hospital discharge diagnoses of atrial fibrillation, our study revealed higher incidence and prevalence estimates as previously reported, especially in the older age groups.</s></p><p><s> Previous studies showed high proportions of patients with incident atrial fibrillation receiving antithrombotic treatment, but were restricted mostly to patients from specialised centres  In contrast, our study showed that a considerably higher fraction of patients with new atrial fibrillation diagnoses did not receive antithrombotic treatment in routine care, which applied to both patients with rhythm and rate control.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Atrial fibrillation (AF) is the most common cardiac rhythm disorder and affects mainly older people <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2)</ref>.</s><s>The most serious complication of AF is stroke.</s><s>AF is associated with an up to 5fold elevated risk for developing stroke, which is increasing with age <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</s><s>In people aged 80-89 years, approximately 25% of all strokes are due to AF <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</s><s>Strokes associated with AF are more likely to be severe and have a higher initial mortality than non-AF strokes <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4)</ref>.</s><s>In the context of demographic changes, the number of people suffering from AF will increase in the future.</s><s>Modelling studies suggest a 2 to 3-fold increase in the number of AF cases by the year 2050 <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Antithrombotic management of AF was reported in several studies, but the results differed substantially.</s><s>Some of these studies did not reflect routine care <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8)</ref>, failed to include elderly AF patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref> or were limited by low numbers of AF cases <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10)</ref>.</s><s>Moreover, the proportion of AF patients receiving antithrombotic drugs was possibly overestimated, since field studies based on voluntary participation of the treating physicians may have overrepresented those who already provide adequate antithrombotic treatment to their AF patients <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>For adequate planning of health care resources, knowledge about the epidemiology of AF and possible deficiencies in the care of AF patients is essential.</s><s>However, reliable data on the epidemiology of AF in Europe and antithrombotic management of elderly AF patients in routine health care are scarce.</s><s>Therefore, the aim of this study was to estimate incidence and prevalence of AF in the elderly in Germany and to assess antithrombotic management in these patients.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data source</head><p><s>Source of data was the German Pharmacoepidemiological Research Database (GePaRD).</s><s>This study was based on data from three statutory health insurances (SHI) including more than 8 million insurants during the study period.</s><s>The database was described elsewhere <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13)</ref>.</s><s>In brief, GePaRD contains demographic variables, information on hospital admissions, outpatient physician visits and data on outpatient prescriptions.</s><s>The hospital data comprises information on admission diagnoses, main and secondary hospital discharge diagnoses, therapeutic and diagnostic procedures with their respective dates, admission and discharge dates and the reason for hospital discharge.</s><s>Outpatient claims include information on outpatient treatments, procedures and diagnoses.</s><s>Outpatient diagnoses, which are only related Revision (ICD-10 GM) <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>.</s><s>Data on outpatient prescriptions of reimbursed drugs contains the date of prescription and dispensation, information on the prescribing physician, the pharmaceutical reference number and the amount of substance prescribed.</s><s>Using the pharmaceutical reference number, prescriptions can be linked to the pharmaceutical reference database containing information on the anatomical-therapeutical-chemical (ATC) code, the defined daily dose (DDD), packaging size, strength, formulation, generic and trade name.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study design</head><p><s>Estimation of the period prevalence of AF for each of the years 2004-2007 was based on cross-sectional analysis.</s><s>To assess the incidence of AF in 2007, a retrospective cohort study was conducted.</s><s>For 2008 data from only one company was available and this data was used to assess antithrombotic management of AF.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study population</head><p><s>Included in the study population were people insured in one of the participating SHIs, if they had valid information on sex, year of birth and place of residence and were aged &gt;65 years.</s></p><p><s>For each of the different study populations, further inclusion criteria were applied.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Period prevalence of AF</head><p><s>For each of the study years, separate study populations were defined.</s><s>Insurants had to be continuously insured during the study year or continuously insured until death in the respective year to be eligible for the study population.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Incidence of AF</head><p><s>For inclusion in the study population, insurants had to have an active insurance period in 2007, preceded by a continuous three-year insurance period without outpatient or hospital diagnoses indicating the presence of AF.</s><s>Patients remained in the cohort until the end of the study period (31.12.2007), end of insurance period, death or first AF diagnosis, whichever came first.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management of incident AF</head><p><s>The study population which was used to assess the management of incident AF included insurants who had been insured in the first three quarters of 2008, preceded by a continuous four-year insurance period without outpatient or hospital diagnoses indicating the presence of AF.</s><s>Finally, insurants were included in the study population, if they had been diagnosed with AF in one of the first three quarters in 2008, so that data on prescriptions and procedures in the quarter of the AF diagnosis and the subsequent quarter could be used to describe the management of AF.</s><s>Patients remained in the cohort until the end of the subsequent quarter, end of insurance period or death, whichever came first.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definitions</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ascertainment of cases</head><p><s>Cases of AF were ascertained by using one of the following ICD-10 GM codes: I48.10 (paroxysmal atrial fibrillation), I48.11 (chronic atrial fibrillation), I48.19 (atrial fibrillation not further specified).</s><s>To be identified as cases, insurants had to have at least one confirmed outpatient diagnosis, one main hospital discharge diagnosis or one secondary hospital discharge diagnosis with the above codes.</s><s>Since an outpatient diagnosis can only be related to a calendar quarter, the date of the outpatient diagnosis of AF was defined as the middle of the quarter.</s><s>In two sensitivity analyses we studied different combinations of the criteria for AF cases: (i) two confirmed outpatient diagnoses in different quarters or one hospital discharge diagnosis (main or secondary); or (ii) one confirmed outpatient diagnosis or one main hospital discharge diagnosis without consideration of secondary hospital discharge diagnoses.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Drug therapy</head><p><s>The proportion of incident AF patients receiving at least one antithrombotic drug and the proportion of incident AF patients receiving more than one antithrombotic drug was described</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Comorbidities</head><p><s>A range of comorbidities including risk factors and secondary diseases of AF was selected to describe the study population.</s><s>These comorbidities were assessed using ICD-10 GM codes related to confirmed outpatient diagnoses, main hospital discharge diagnoses or secondary hospital discharge diagnoses during the respective study year (relevant codes are displayed in table 1 of the supplementary material).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical analysis</head><p><s>Period prevalence of AF was calculated by dividing the cumulative number of AF cases in a given year by the mid-year population of the respective year.</s><s>Corresponding confidence intervals (CIs) were calculated using the Wilson-Score method <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>.</s><s>CIs for age-standardised estimates were calculated according to the method based on the gamma distribution <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Incidence rates of AF were calculated by dividing the number of incident AF cases by the accumulated person-time in the corresponding time period.</s><s>CIs for incidence rates were calculated using the substitution method <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(18)</ref>.</s><s>Prevalence and incidence estimates were standardised using direct standardisation for the population distribution of &gt;65 year-aged Germans in the respective year obtained from the German Federal Statistical Office.</s><s>In two sensitivity analyses, the incidence and prevalence estimations were repeated applying both case definitions described above.</s><s>Using a logistic regression model, we determined predictors of lack of therapy with oral anticoagulants in incident AF patients.</s><s>Independent variables contained in the full model included sex, age (5-year age categories), cardiac treatment strategy (rate control, rhythm control, neither), physician speciality of the AF diagnosing doctor (General Practitioner (GP), internist, other physician in private practice, physician in hospital), the CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score (dichotomised into &gt;2 and &lt;2) and selected comorbidities ascertained during a four-year period preceding the incident AF diagnosis (as shown in Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</s><s>Relevant factors were selected by backward elimination using the Wald test (p&lt;0.05) to determine the final model.</s></p><p><s>All statistical analyses were conducted using SAS 9.2 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Prevalence of AF</head><p><s>AF cases were older and the proportion of men among AF cases was higher than in the total study population (Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</s><s>Assessed comorbidities were more frequent in AF cases than in the study population.</s></p><p><s>In 2007, the standardised prevalence of AF was 10.3% and was higher in men (11.4%) than in women (8.7%) (Table <ref type="table">2</ref>).</s><s>The prevalence was 5.1% in the age-group 65-69 years and increased to 19.7% in the age-group 85-89 years (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">1</ref>).</s><s>In patients aged &gt;90 years, the prevalence was slightly lower than in the preceding age group.</s><s>Throughout the four study years, the prevalence of AF increased steadily.</s><s>The increase in the prevalence of AF was seen in both sexes and all age-groups.</s><s>The first sensitivity analysis in which two confirmed outpatient diagnoses were required for case ascertainment revealed slightly lower prevalence estimates.</s><s>Here, the prevalence of AF in 2007 was 4.5% in patients aged 65-69 years and increased with advancing age to 18.1% in the age-group 85-89 years.</s><s>Similar differences between the two estimation approaches were seen in both sexes (data not shown).</s><s>The second sensitivity analysis which did not consider secondary hospital discharge diagnoses for case ascertainment resulted in lower prevalence estimates than the first sensitivity analysis, particularly in the oldest age groups.</s><s>In this analysis, the AF prevalence was 4.6% in patients aged 65-69 years and 15.3% in those aged 85-89 years.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Incidence of AF</head><p><s>The overall standardised incidence of AF in 2007 was 27.4/1,000 py and was higher in men than in women (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">3</ref>).</s><s>The incidence of AF increased with advancing age from 13.2/1,000 10 py in patients aged 65-69 years to 67.7/1,000 py in the age-group &gt;90 years and was higher in men than in women across all age-groups.</s><s>The incidence estimates from the first sensitivity analysis which required two confirmed outpatient diagnoses for case ascertainment were somewhat lower in both sexes.</s><s>Here, the incidence rate of AF in 2007 was 7.7/1,000 py in the age-group 65-69 and increased to 51.7/1,000 py in patients aged &gt;90 years (data not shown).</s></p><p><s>The second sensitivity analysis which did not include secondary hospital discharge diagnoses in the case ascertainment revealed considerably lower incidence rates of AF compared to the main analysis.</s><s>In this estimation approach, the incidence of AF was 10.1/1,000 py in the age group 65-69 years and 31.3/1,000</s><s>py in patients aged &gt;90 years.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Antithrombotic drug management</head><p><s>Of the 10,177 incident AF cases identified in 2008, 59.3% were newly diagnosed in hospital.</s></p><p><s>Of the 40.7% who were newly diagnosed in the outpatient sector, 52.5% received the first AF diagnosis by an internist and 39.1% were diagnosed by a GP.</s><s>Of the newly diagnosed AF cases, 58.2% received antithrombotic drugs in the quarter of the AF diagnosis or in the subsequent quarter (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">2</ref>).</s><s>Antithrombotic drugs were more often prescribed to men (61.8%) than to women (51.6%).</s><s>The proportion of incident AF cases receiving antithrombotic drug therapy declined with advancing age.</s><s>In the age-group 65-69 years, 60.2% were supplied with antithrombotic medications, however, in the age-group &gt;90 years only 32.2% received an antithrombotic drug.</s></p><p><s>In 59.1% of the incident AF cases, treatment was classified as rate control, whereas in 19.3% of the cases -as rhythm control.</s><s>The remaining 21.6% received no medications classified as rhythm or rate control in the quarter of the AF diagnosis or in the following quarter.</s><s>AF patients treated with rhythm control received more often antithrombotic agents (75.2%) than patients treated with rate control (61.3%) (Table <ref type="table">4</ref>).</s><s>In particular, vitamin K antagonists and low-molecular-weight heparin were more rarely prescribed in patients with rate control than in those with rhythm control.</s><s>Patients, whose rhythm disorder remained untreated, were considerably less often treated with antithrombotics (34.7%).</s><s>Heparinoids and direct thrombin inhibitors were not prescribed in our study population of AF patients.</s><s>With regard to the dichotomised CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score, only slight differences in the proportion of patients without oral anticoagulation treatment were observed between patients with a CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score of 0-1 compared to those with a CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score of &gt;2 (69.2% versus 61.7%).</s><s>The multivariate analysis showed that increasing age, female sex, rate control or no therapy strategy (neither rhythm control nor rate control) compared to rhythm control myocardial infarction, valvular heart disease, diabetes mellitus, chronic renal failure and a CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score of 0-1 were associated with a significantly increased risk of not receiving oral anticoagulants after incident AF diagnosis, whereby especially subjects aged 90 years or older were less likely to receive oral anticoagulants (Table <ref type="table">5</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>Using data from a large German health insurance database we assessed prevalence, incidence and antithrombotic drug treatment of AF in Germany.</s><s>The incidence and prevalence increased with advancing age and were higher among men than women.</s><s>More than 40% of incident AF cases received no antithrombotic drug treatment in 2008.</s></p><p><s>The prevalence of AF estimated in our study is somewhat higher than the estimates derived from the considerably older, population-based Rotterdam Study which was conducted between 1990 and 1999 <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>.</s><s>In this study, the prevalence of AF was 4.0% in the age-group 65-69 years (5.1% in our study) and similarly showed a marked increase with age.</s><s>In subjects aged 80-84 years, the prevalence of AF was 13.5% in the Rotterdam Study compared to <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">16</ref>.5% in our study.</s><s>In contrast, we found a lower AF prevalence in our study than the recently published population-based Gutenberg Health Study (GHS) in Rhineland Palatinate (9).</s><s>This is not surprising since in the GHS active screening for AF with a 12-lead electrocardiogram was conducted in addition to obtaining the medical history of the patient in an anamnestic interview.</s><s>In the GHS, the prevalence of AF was provided in 10-year age bands up to the age of 74 years and was 10.6% in men and 4.9% in women aged 65-74 years, whereas it was 7.7% and 4.2% in this age group in our study, respectively.</s></p><p><s>Our prevalence estimates of AF are somewhat higher than those of another recently published German study which was also based on claims data <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref>.</s><s>This study by <ref type="bibr">Wilke et al. (20)</ref> estimated the prevalence of AF at 4.8% in patients aged 65-69 years and at 15.1% in the age group 85-89 years (5.1% and 19.7% in our study, respectively) using a different algorithm for case ascertainment.</s><s>This algorithm required one main hospital discharge diagnosis or two outpatient diagnoses in two different quarters and was used in analogy to the algorithms applied in the German morbidity-based risk structure equalisation scheme <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref>, where two outpatient diagnoses are required in order to improve security of the diagnosis.</s><s>Since AF is an intermittent disease, which is characterised by short and rare episodes particularly at the beginning of the disease, a first AF diagnosis has not necessarily to be followed by a second AF diagnosis in the same year <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref>.</s><s>Therefore we applied an algorithm based on a single diagnosis only.</s><s>Requiring a second outpatient diagnosis of AF in another quarter in our first sensitivity analysis resulted in a similar prevalence for those aged 65-69 years as in the study by <ref type="bibr">Wilke et al. (20)</ref>, but still yielded a higher prevalence in the older age groups in our study.</s></p><p><s>As our second sensitivity analysis which did not consider secondary hospital discharge diagnoses for case ascertainment revealed prevalences similar to those of Wilke et al., the difference between our and the Wilke study at higher age is likely due to the fact that the algorithm for case ascertainment by Wilke et al. did not consider secondary hospital discharge diagnoses of AF.</s><s>From the hospital diagnoses, Wilke et al.</s><s>only included patients with a main hospital discharge diagnosis, which in the German coding system states the disease giving rise to the hospitalisation.</s><s>Since up to 30% of AF patients have asymptomatic AF <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23)</ref>, it might not be infrequent that AF is detected first during the routine examinations in the context of a hospital stay which was due to another disease.</s></p><p><s>The incidence rates of AF from our study are most comparable with the results of the Cardiovascular Health Study <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref>.</s><s>In this study, 18.0% of the incident AF cases were solely identified based on diagnoses reported by the patients which may have led to over-or underestimation of incidence, since patients could have forgotten about the arrhythmia or could have confused AF with another arrhythmia <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(24)</ref>.</s><s>The Rotterdam study <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref>, the US ARIC-Study <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref> and another US study reported by Miyasaka et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref> reported lower incidence rates of AF in comparison to our study.</s><s>In the ARIC study, only inpatient diagnoses were used to identify AF cases which presumably led to a considerable underestimation of the incidence rate, since AF does not necessarily require inpatient treatment.</s><s>Only 67% of AF patients in our study were identified by inpatient diagnoses so that 33% of the patients would have been missed had the outpatient diagnoses not been considered.</s><s>In comparison to the study by <ref type="bibr">Wilke et al. (20)</ref>, the incidence estimates in our study were also higher with the difference being most pronounced in the oldest age groups.</s><s>These differences likely result from the different case finding algorithms used in both studies, as already discussed above.</s><s>In particular, the non-consideration of secondary hospital discharge diagnoses may have led to the lower incidence estimates in the study by Wilke et al. since our second sensitivity analysis, in which only confirmed outpatient diagnoses and main hospital discharge diagnoses were considered revealed comparable estimates to the results provided by Wilke et al.</s></p><p><s>Comparing our incidence and prevalence estimates with those from other studies, it has to be taken into account that most other studies were conducted in the late 1980's or 1990's (1, 19, 24, 25) and this has several implications.</s><s>Improved survival of patients with cardiac diseases has led to an increase in elderly patients who are at high risk of AF.</s><s>Furthermore, a growing awareness of AF among physicians may have resulted in a smaller proportion of undetected AF cases.</s><s>Therefore the higher estimates in our study were to be expected compared to those from these earlier studies.</s><s>Our similar prevalence estimates to those of the considerably older Rotterdam study <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref> may be explained by the active screening approach for AF in the Rotterdam study which would be expected to outweigh the lower prevalence during the time period of its study conduct (26).</s></p><p><s>Our estimates regarding the proportion of incident AF cases receiving antithrombotic therapy in general as well as defined antithrombotic agents compare well with the results of the recently published GHS study <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>, but are considerably lower than the estimates reported by the Euro Heart Survey <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref> or those of the Registry of the German Competence Network on Atrial Fibrillation (AFNET) <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(8)</ref>.</s><s>All AF patients participating in the Euro Heart Survey and 67% of AF patients participating in the AFNET were treated in specialized university hospitals or cardiologist centres <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8)</ref> who have been shown to provide adequate antithrombotic treatment more frequently <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(27)</ref>.</s><s>In our study, a more balanced distribution regarding the sector of the diagnosis and the physician speciality of the AF diagnosing doctor was seen.</s><s>Both in the Euro Heart Survey and the AFNET, the participating centres are presumably not representative for anticoagulant management of AF patients in routine care, but are likely to include a selected sample of physicians who due to their scientific interest in the study question are more likely to provide adequate antithrombotic therapy in accordance with current guidelines.</s><s>It is an advantage of our study that it includes all physicians who care for AF patients thereby avoiding a selected sample of physicians.</s><s>A further explanation for the lower proportion of AF patients with antithrombotic therapy in our study may be that acetylsalicylic acid (ASA) in the therapy of AF is not reimbursed by the SHIs in Germany, so that the data source of our study did not contain such claims.</s><s>Wilke et al. ( <ref type="formula">28</ref>) also evaluated the antithrombotic management of patients with AF and also showed an underuse of treatment with antithrombotic drugs, but since this study focussed on the antithrombotic therapy of prevalent AF cases and used other methods to evaluate the antithrombotic treatment, we did not compare our results to this study.</s><s>At the time of the analysis, health insurance data were only available to us until the end of 2008.</s><s>It was therefore not possible to study which impact the newer oral anticoagulants might have on the antithrombotic management of AF patients.</s><s>Further, health insurance data have only been available to us since 2004.</s><s>Calculation of the CHA 2 DS 2 -VASc score was limited by this fact, since prior diagnoses of stroke or ischaemic attack were not available to us before this time.</s><s>In some cases, patients could have had diagnoses of AF prior to 2004 and would thus be misclassified as incident cases in 2007, although they were prevalent cases.</s><s>However, such misclassification is probably of low magnitude, since it is unlikely that an AF patient will not see his physician for three years and will not obtain the AF diagnosis in his records.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations</head><p><s>A validation of the AF diagnosis in our data by chart review could not be carried out for reasons of protection of personal data.</s><s>However, we assume a valid coding of AF diagnoses in SHI data, since our results regarding the prevalence of AF were similar to the German GHSstudy or showed expected differences <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Due to lack of specific codes it could not be clearly distinguished between rhythm and rate controlling catheter ablations.</s><s>Therefore catheter ablations could not be taken into account when defining rhythm and rate control, which could have led to an underestimation of both treatment strategies.</s><s>However, this potential underestimation is suspected to be rather small, since catheter ablations are rarely performed in incident AF cases.</s></p><p><s>Since many contraindications for the use of antithrombotic agents in patients with AF cannot adequately be operationalized in claims data, we did not exclude patients with contraindications when evaluating the antithrombotic treatment in incident AF patients, which could have led to an overestimation of undertreatment.</s><s>However, since these contraindications are rare disorders, not accounting for them will likely not change the results of undertreatment with antithrombotics to a relevant extent.</s></p><p><s>The categorization of the physician speciality in claims data is rather unspecific, as for example cardiologists cannot be distinguished from gastroenterologists, since both are coded as internists in our data.</s><s>This presumably led to the fact that the physician speciality had no influence on receiving oral anticoagulants in the multivariate logistic regression model, although this is a known association in other studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(27)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Strengths</head><p><s>The major strength of this study is the large study sample, which allowed a precise estimation of incidence, prevalence and antithrombotic treatment even in the highest age-categories.</s><s>Since this study is based on administrative data, recall bias or selection bias (e.g.</s><s>due to voluntary participation of patients or physicians) could be avoided.</s><s>We further did not restrict our analyses on the antithrombotic treatment of incident AF to selected physician specialities, so that our results are more likely to reflect routine care.</s><s>In addition, it could be shown that the age-and sex-distribution as well as drug use of patients included in GePaRD is similar to that of Germany, leading to a high external validity of the results <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">29)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In conclusion, our study showed that the incidence and prevalence of AF in elderly people in Germany is rather high.</s><s>Compared with incidence and prevalence estimates of older studies, an increase of the incidence and prevalence can be assumed.</s><s>Our analysis revealed a considerable fraction of AF patients who were not treated with antithrombotic drugs, whereby especially old-aged people and women had a high risk of not receiving antithrombotic treatment.</s></p><p><s>In the context of an aging society and therefore increasing numbers of multi-morbid AF cases at a high risk of stroke, providing adequate antithrombotic therapy is an important task for the physicians and interventions are necessary to improve the current situation.</s></p><note type="other">Figure legends</note></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>, can be distinguished into confirmed diagnoses, suspected diagnoses, diagnoses ruled out and status post diagnoses.</s><s>Both, outpatient and inpatient diagnoses, are coded according to the German Modification of the International Classification of Diseases 10 th</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>At the time of the study, data from two smaller SHIs were available for the years 2004-2007; one large SHI provided data for 2004-2008.</s><s>Use of the data for research purposes needs to be approved by the SHIs contributing the data and by local or federal government authorities responsible according to data protection legislation.</s><s>In accordance with § 75 of Volume 10 of the Social Insurance Code, informed consent of involved insurants was not required.</s><s>Since the study was based on pseudonymised routine data delivered by the SHIs, a vote of the ethics committee was not required.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>by treatment strategies of rhythm versus rate control.</s><s>Both treatment strategies were defined by applying a modified definition originally proposed by Nieuwlaat et al.<ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>.</s><s>A patient was assigned to rhythm control, if a class IA, IC or III antiarrhythmic drug (Vaughan Williams Classification (15)) had been prescribed or an electrical cardioversion had been conducted.</s><s>Patients not included in the rhythm control group were classified into the rate control group, if they received prescriptions of digitalis, class II or class IV antiarrhythmic drugs.</s><s>Cordichin (a combination drug of verapamil and quinidine) was classified as rhythm controlling agent.Antithrombotic therapy was defined as at least one prescription of a vitamin K antagonist, antiplatelet drug, low molecular weight heparin, unfractionated heparin, heparinoid, direct thrombin inhibitor or other antithrombotic drug in the quarter of the AF diagnosis or the subsequent quarter.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1: Age-and sex-stratified prevalence of atrial fibrillation in 2007.</s><s>Error bars represent 95% confidence intervals.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2: Age-and sex-stratified proportions of incident cases with atrial fibrillation receiving antithrombotic therapy.</s><s>Error bars represent 95% confidence intervals.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="1,15.00,16.20,565.28,141.22" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Sex-stratified crude and standardised incidence rate of atrial fibrillation per 1,000 person-years in 2007 Stand.=Standardised</s><s>(Standardisation was based on the population distribution of Germany of the respective year)</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Men</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="26">. Dewilde S, Carey IM, Emmas C, Richards N, Cook DG. Trends in the prevalence of diagnosed atrial fibrillation, its treatment with anticoagulation and predictors of such treatment in UK primary care. Heart 2006;92(8):1064-1070.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>The authors are grateful to all statutory health insurances that provided data for this study, namely the Allgemeine Ortskrankenkasse (AOK) Bremen/Bremerhaven, the Techniker Krankenkasse (TK), and the hkk.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of interest</head><p><s>Christoph Ohlmeier: None declared Rafael Mikolajczyk: Rafael Mikolajczyk received research funding from Sanofi Pasteur MSD (SPMSD) and Bayer-Pharma Wilhelm Haverkamp: Wilhelm Haverkamp has received honoraria and research funding from several pharmaceutical companies.</s><s>However, the present work is unrelated to any grant and relationship.</s></p><p><s>Edeltraut Garbe: Edeltraut Garbe is running a department that occasionally performs studies for pharmaceutical industries with the full freedom to publish.</s><s>The companies include Mundipharma, Bayer, Stada, Sanofi-Aventis, Sanofi-Pasteur, Novartis, Celgene, and GSK.</s><s>She has been consultant to Bayer-Schering, Nycomed, Teva, GSK, Schwabe and Novartis in the past.</s><s>The present work is unrelated to the above grants and relationships.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Text tables</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prevalence of diagnosed atrial fibrillation in adults: national implications for rhythm management and stroke prevention: the AnTicoagulation and Risk Factors in Atrial Fibrillation (ATRIA) Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Go</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hylek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Phillips</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Henault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Selby</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JAMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">285</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2370" to="2375" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atrial fibrillation as an independent risk factor for stroke: the Framingham Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Abbott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Kannel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="983" to="988" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atrial fibrillation as a predictive factor for severe stroke and early death in 15,831 patients with acute ischaemic stroke</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kimura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Minematsu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yamaguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="679" to="683" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stroke severity in atrial fibrillation. The Framingham Study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kelly-Hayes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Beiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Kase</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Benjamin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stroke</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1760" to="1764" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Secular trends in incidence of atrial fibrillation in Olmsted County</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Miyasaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Barnes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gersh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Cha</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Bailey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Abhayaratna</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">114</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="125" />
			<date type="published" when="1980">1980 to 2000. 2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>and implications on the projections for future prevalence</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increasing prevalence of atrial fibrillation and flutter in the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Naccarelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Varker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Schulman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1534" to="1539" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atrial fibrillation management: a prospective survey in ESC member countries: the Euro Heart Survey on Atrial Fibrillation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Nieuwlaat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Capucci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Camm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Olsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Andresen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Davies</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2422" to="2434" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Registry of the German Competence NETwork on Atrial Fibrillation: patient characteristics and initial management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nabauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gerth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Limbourg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Schneider</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Oeff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kirchhof</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Europace</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="423" to="434" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Atrial fibrillation: its prevalence and risk factor profile in the German general population</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Schnabel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wilde</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wild</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Munzel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Blankenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dtsch Arztebl Int</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">109</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="293" to="299" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anticoagulation treatment for the reduction of stroke in atrial fibrillation: a cohort study to examine the gap between guidelines and routine medical practice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mcbride</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bruggenjurgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Roll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Willich</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Thromb Thrombolysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="72" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Management of atrial fibrillation by primary care physicians in Germany: baseline results of the ATRIUM registry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Meinertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Kirch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Rosin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Pittrow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Willich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kirchhof</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Res Cardiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="897" to="905" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Establishment of a pharmacoepidemiological database in Germany: methodological potential, scientific value and practical limitations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Pigeot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ahrens</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="223" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Linkage of mother-baby pairs in the German Pharmacoepidemiological Research Database</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Garbe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Suling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kloss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lindemann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Schmid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="258" to="264" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">DIMDI German Institute of Medical Documentation and Information. International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems, 10th Revision: Version</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.dimdi.de/static/de/klassi/icd-10-gm/index.htm15" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A classification of antiarrhythmic actions reassessed after a decade of new drugs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vaughan</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Pharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="147" />
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Proportions and their differences</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Newcombe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Altman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Statistics with Confidence</title>
				<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Altman</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Machin</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Bryant</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gardner</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Second ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Confidence intervals for directly standardized rates: a method based on the gamma distribution</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Fay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Feuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Stat Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="791" to="801" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Confidence limits made easy: interval estimation using a substitution method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Daly</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">147</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="783" to="790" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prevalence, incidence and lifetime risk of atrial fibrillation: the Rotterdam study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heeringa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Van Der Kuip</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hofman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kors</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Van Herpen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Stricker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="949" to="953" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incidence and prevalence of atrial fibrillation: an analysis based on 8.3 million patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wilke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Groth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pfannkuche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Verheyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Linder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Europace</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Göpffarth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gress</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Jacobs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wasem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Jahrbuch Risikostrukturausgleich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Von der Selektion zur Manipulation? Heidelberg: medhochzwei</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009. 2010. 2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Guidelines for the management of atrial fibrillation: the Task Force for the Management of Atrial Fibrillation of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Camm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kirchhof</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Lip</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Schotten</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Savelieva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ernst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2369" to="2429" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical relevance of silent atrial fibrillation: prevalence, prognosis, quality of life, and management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Savelieva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Camm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Interv Card Electrophysiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="382" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incidence of and risk factors for atrial fibrillation in older adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Psaty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Manolio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Kuller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kronmal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Cushman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Fried</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Circulation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">96</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2455" to="2461" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incidence of atrial fibrillation in whites and African-Americans: the Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alonso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Soliman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ambrose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chamberlain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Prineas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am Heart J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">158</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="111" to="117" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of the type of centre on management of AF patients: surprising evidence for differences in antithrombotic therapy decisions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kirchhof</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nabauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gerth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Limbourg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lewalter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Goette</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thromb Haemost</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1010" to="1023" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Oral anticoagulation use by patients with atrial fibrillation in Germany. Adherence to guidelines, causes of anticoagulation under-use and its clinical outcomes, based on claims-data of 183,448 patients</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Wilke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Groth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Pfannkuche</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Verheyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Linder</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Thromb Haemost</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">107</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1053" to="1065" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representativity of dispensations of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) in the German Pharmacoepidemiological Research Database</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Schink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Garbe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">S1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">S294</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
