<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Favorable outcome in cerebral abscesses caused by Citrobacter koseri in a newborn infant</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sarah</forename><surname>Algubaisi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neonatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite´University Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Christoph</forename><surname>Bu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neonatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite´University Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ulrich-Wilhelm</forename><surname>Thomale</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatric Neurosurgery</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite´University Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Birgit</forename><surname>Spors</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatric Radiology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charite´University Medical Center</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Favorable outcome in cerebral abscesses caused by Citrobacter koseri in a newborn infant</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">E5CADC8BC0C524C648B39C21991D31D7</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.idcr.2014.11.004</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 23 June 2014 Received in revised form 24 November 2014 Accepted 24 November 2014</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:43+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>Newborn infant Citrobacter koseri Brain abscess Fosfmycin Meropenem</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>The treatment of brain abscesses in newborn infants is controversial.</s><s>We report on a 6-week-old infant with multiple brain abscesses caused by Citrobacter koseri that resolved after treatment with combined surgical drainage and intravenous therapy with meropenem and fosfomycin.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Citrobacter koseri is a particular cause of meningitis and abscess especially during the neonatal period associated with high mortality and morbidity.</s><s>Neonatal Citrobacter disease is mostly considered sporadic, however vertical transmission during delivery and other healthcare linked spread may occur.</s><s>Since abscesses may grow very large in neonates before manifesting clinical signs, neuroimaging studies are pivotal for diagnosis and prediction of adverse complication as early as possible <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Case report</head><p><s>Our patient was a male baby born after 37 weeks gestation with a birth weight of 2140 g.</s><s>Delivery was by Cesarean section because of preeclampsia, Apgar score was 9 and 10 at 1 and 5 min.</s><s>The infant was admitted to the neonatal unit because of hypoglycemia.</s><s>Initial blood workup showed elevated interleukin-6 of 425 ng/l (normal value: &lt;50 ng/l) and empiric antimicrobial therapy with ampicillin and gentamicin was started.</s><s>Upon the negative result of blood culture, the antimicrobial therapy was discounted after 5 days.</s><s>Because of a good response to treatment, there was no lumbar puncture performed.</s><s>The slow oral intake und hypoglycemia was accepted for low birth weight and he was discharged at 11 days of age.</s></p><p><s>At 4 weeks of age, the infant presented to our emergency room with irritability and fever (38.5 8C).</s><s>He had leukocytosis (20.54/nl) and elevated C-reactive protein (CRP) of 17.8 mg/l (normal value: &lt;5 mg/l).</s><s>A urinalysis was negative and blood culture was negative.</s><s>Lumbar puncture was not considered at that time.</s><s>No antimicrobials were started and he was discharged well after 2 days.</s></p><p><s>Two weeks later, the infant presented with irritability, subfebrile a temperature of 38.0 8C and poor oral intake for 1 day.</s><s>Initial physical examination was normal and there was no focal neurological deficit.</s><s>No antimicrobials had been given prior to admission.</s><s>Because of the child's presentation, a full sepsis workup was done.</s><s>The infant had a C-reactive protein of 13.20 mg/l.</s><s>The blood and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) cultures were negative for bacterial growth, and there was no pleocytosis.</s><s>A head ultrasound examination revealed 2 fluid filled cavities in the frontal region (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>).</s><s>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the head was suggestive of brain abscesses (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Empiric therapy was initiated with ampicillin, gentamicin and cefotaxime.</s><s>The infant underwent burr-hole drainage of the right frontal abscess cavity at day 3 of admission and approximately 6 ml of yellow-colored sero-sanguineous fluid was drained.</s><s>The culture of the abscess fluid grew C. koseri.</s><s>After review of literature addressing C. koseri infections, ampicillin, gentamicin and cefotaxime were discontinued and intravenous meropenem (120 mg/kg/d) at day 12 of admission was started.</s><s>After the bacteria isolated were found to be sensitive to this drug, intravenous fosfomycin was added at a dose of 120 mg/kg/d at day 18 of admission.</s></p><p><s>Repeated ultrasound of the head revealed resolution of the abscesses at day 24 of admission.</s><s>After a total of 6 weeks antimicrobial therapy was discontinued and the infant was discharged.</s><s>MRI at the time of discharge showed a cystic defect in the right frontal lobe and a complete resolution of the abscess in the left frontal lobe (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">3</ref>).</s></p><p><s>At 9-month follow up, the patient was found in a good clinical condition, with only mild delay in gross motor skills, but with normal vision and hearing.</s><s>By elective orchidopexy at age of 2 years, the patient was seen with a mild speech delay, but other aspects of development were appropriate for age.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>A bacterial brain abscess is usually a well-circumscribed collection of purulent fluid within the brain parenchyma.</s><s>Certain gram-negative bacteria have a predilection for causing brain abscess, including Acinetobacter, C. Enterobacter, Salmonalle, Serratia, Proteus and Pseudomonas <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>During the first 2 months of life, C. koseri shows a strong predilection for meningitis and brain abscesses.</s><s>The mortality rate for meningitis due to Citrobacter is around 30%, and of infants who survive, more than 80% have some degree of neurological deficit <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Organisms of the genus Citrobacter are gram-negative bacilli of the family Enterobacteriaceae, tribe Citrobactereae <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>The pathogenesis of Citrobacter meningitis and brain abscess in humans is still not clear.</s><s>During experimental central nervous system (CNS) infection in neonatal rats, C. koseri resides primarily intracellularly within macrophages and neutrophils.</s><s>Accumulation of necrotic tissue and infiltrating phagocytes results in expansion of the brain abscess <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s>Some instances of intraparenchymal abscesses do not follow the classic pattern of common cerebral abscesses and lack a fibrous capsule <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In our case, the source of infection could not be determined as the infant became symptomatic at age of 4 weeks, so vertical transmission from the mother during delivery is unlikely.</s><s>She was   asymptomatic throughout her pregnancy and there was no sign of vaginal or intestinal infection or chorioamnionitis.</s><s>In general, Citrobacter infections occur in a sporadic fashion <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>Almost onethird of the sporadic cases are of late onset, typically occurring around 4-5 weeks, compared with early onset cases, which tend to occur between 5 and 12 days of age.</s><s>No cases of brain abscess have been reported in vertically transmitted Citrobacter meningitis <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s>Approximately one-third of the affected patients are less than 36 weeks gestational age at birth, suggesting that preterm infants have an increased risk of acquiring Citrobacter infection <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The clinical manifestations of C. koseri meningitis include poor feeding, vomiting, lethargy, apneic spells, seizures, irritability and bulging fontanelle.</s><s>Some infants who have brain abscess initially may exhibit no apparent neurologic symptoms other than increased irritability as has been described in our case.</s><s>Neurologic deficits are less obvious in extremely preterm infants <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</s><s>Infants with such signs and symptoms should have a complete evaluation, including blood culture, urine culture, and lumbar puncture for CSF chemistries, cytology, gram staining and culture.</s><s>Once the diagnosis of C. koseri meningitis is established, all infants should undergo serial neuroimaging evaluation.</s><s>Ultrasonography can be used for initial screening <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> but MRI is the diagnostic method of choice.</s></p><p><s>Repeat imaging examination may be helpful at the conclusion of therapy <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>It is not clear whether serial neuroimaging at first admission at the age of 4 weeks in our case could have been beneficial to pick up brain abscesses earlier.</s></p><p><s>The optimal management of Citrobacter CNS abscesses is antimicrobial therapy alone or a combination of antimicrobial therapy and surgical aspiration/drainage <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>.</s><s>The unique characteristics of C. koseri, including localization in neutrophils and rapid CSF penetration, allow bacterial survival and replication despite treatment with commonly used antimicrobial agents for meningitis.</s><s>According to in vitro antimicrobial sensitivity aminoglycosides, ciprofloxacin, meropenem, and imipenem/cilastatin are active against more than 90% of Citrobacter isolates <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s><s>Aminoglycosides, however, do not achieve adequate concentrations in the brain and C. koseri is usually ampicillin-resistant <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</s><s>In our case, initially we started with the third-generation cephalosporin cefotaxime, but after reviewing the literature we switched the therapy to meropenem.</s><s>However, the evidence to date seems rather sparse to recommend carbapenems in favor of thirdgeneration cephalosporins without evaluation or proof of real antimicrobial resistance in individual cases <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The ability of carbapenems to penetrate CSF and macrophages makes those drug a logical option to treat Citrobacter infection.</s><s>Meropenem appears to have a better safety profile and thus would be the preferred choice in neonates <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Lee et al. had reported a case of Lemierre syndrome complication multiple brain abscesses caused by extended-spectrum beta-lactamase-producing Klebsiella pneumonia which responded very well to fosfomycin and meropenem <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s><s>In the presented case, we added fosfomycin because its well-known bactericidal activity against gram negative pathogens including C. koseri and especially multidrug-resistant organisms <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>.</s><s>Surgical drainage is probably desirable but is not mandatory in every case.</s><s>Abscesses are often multiple or inaccessible, making a surgical approach impractical.</s><s>The neurosurgical approach may be associated with a better prognosis <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>In our patient, a complete regression of cerebral abscesses was reached after the aspiration of abscess and the introduction of meropenem and fosfomycin antimicrobial scheme.</s></p><p><s>Duration of seizures for more than 72 h, presence of coma, use of inotropes, and leukopenia have been reported to be the most important predictors of adverse outcome <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s>Gram negative ancillary meningitis was associated with worse prognosis comparing with those caused by gram-positive organisms <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</s><s>Favorable outcomes have been reported <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> as also seen in our case.</s><s>We suggest that meropenem in combination with fosfomycin as well as surgical drainage have probably attributed to a good outcome of our patient.</s><s>Long-term neurodevelopment follow up and neuroimaging studies are indicated.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 3. Cranial MRI showing no residuals from the cerebral abscesses.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,122.57,544.97,360.00,181.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1.</s><s>Cranial ultrasound imaging showing 2 fluid filled cavities in the frontal region.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,47.06,54.31,241.20,211.44" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 2. Cranial MRI showing 2 cerebral abscesses.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,343.56,54.19,186.72,208.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of Citrobacter in clinical disease of children: review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Doran</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="384" to="394" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Index of suspicion in the nursery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Stallworth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Murry</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neoreviews</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="e436" to="438" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Citrobacter koseri brain abscess in the neonatal rat: survival and replication within human and rat macrophages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Townsend</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pollak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Gonzalez-Gomez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Shimada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Badger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Infect Immun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5871" to="5880" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Citrobacter koseri meningitis: a neurosurgical condition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Martı ´nez-Lage</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Martı ´nez-Lage Azorı ´n</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Almagro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bastida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Reyes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Tellez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Paediatr Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="360" to="363" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transmission of Citrobacter koseri from mother to infant documented by ribotyping and pulsed-field gel electrophoresis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Papasian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kinney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Coffman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hollis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pfaller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="63" to="67" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Long term outcome of Citrobacter koseri meningitis treated with imipenem/meropenem and surgical drainage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Straussberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Harel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Amir</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Infection</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="280" to="282" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Treatment of Citrobacter koseri infection with ciprofloxacin and cefotaxime in a preterm infant</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Mcpherson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ransom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Pharmacother</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1134" to="1138" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Lemierre syndrome complicating multiple brain abscesses caused by extended-spectrum b-lactamase-producing Klebsiella pneumoniae cured by fosfomycin and meropenem combination therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Shieh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Teng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Ou</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Microbiol Immunol Infect</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="74" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fosfomycin for the treatment of multidrug-resistant, including extended-spectrum beta-lactamase producing Enterobacteriaceae infections: a systemic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Falagas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kastoris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kapaskelis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Karageorgopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="50" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Predicting the outcome of neonatal bacterial meningitis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Klinger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Chin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Beyene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Perlman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="477" to="482" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Australasian Study Group for Neonatal Infections. Early onset neonatal meningitis in Australia and New Zealand</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>May</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Daley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Donath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Isaacs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="F324" to="327" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992-2002. 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
