<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Synaptic drive in spinal motoneurons during scratch network activity</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Robertas</forename><surname>Guzulaitis</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neuroscience</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Copenhagen</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jorn</forename><surname>Hounsgaard</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Neuroscience</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Copenhagen</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Dept. of Neuroscience</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Univ. of Copenhagen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Panum Inst. Blegdamsvej 3B</addrLine>
									<postCode>DK-2200</postCode>
									<settlement>Copenhagen</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Synaptic drive in spinal motoneurons during scratch network activity</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">72D1F6112DF020259EACDD189FF2FE01</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1152/jn.00094.2018.-</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted 7 February 2018; accepted in final form 6 July 2018</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:13+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Synaptic activity in motoneurons may provide unique insight in the relation between functional network activity and behavior.</s><s>During scratch network activity in an ex vivo preparation from red-eared turtles (Trachemys scripta elegans), excitatory and inhibitory synaptic current can be separated and quantified in voltage-clamp recordings.</s><s>With this technique, we confirm the reciprocal synaptic excitation and inhibition in hip flexor motoneurons during ipsilateral scratching and show that out-of-phase inhibition and excitation also characterize hip extensor motoneurons during ipsi-and contralateral scratching.</s><s>In contrast, inhibition precedes and partly overlaps excitation in hip flexor-like motoneurons and delays depolarization of membrane potential.</s><s>We conclude that out-of-phase excitation and inhibition during rhythmic network activity is a common feature in spinal motoneurons.</s></p><p><s>NEW &amp; NOTEWORTHY During network activity, the firing pattern of individual neurons is shaped by their intrinsic conductances and synaptic input.</s><s>Quantification of synaptic input is, therefore, essential to understand how the properties of individual neurons contribute to function and help to reveal the structure of the network.</s><s>Here, we show how a combination of recording techniques can be used to quantify and compare the pattern of synaptic activity in different groups of motoneurons during rhythmic network activity.</s><s>central pattern generator (CPG); motoneuron; reciprocal excitation/ inhibition; spinal</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p><s>Locomotion in animals is secured by precisely timed sequential activation of many muscle groups.</s><s>A fundamental motif in this complex orchestra is alternation between flexors and extensors.</s><s>Mutual inhibition between flexors and extensors (half-centers) was proposed to explain the robust coordination between antagonists <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Brown 1914;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Jankowska et al. 1965</ref>).</s><s>The implication is that both flexors and extensors are driven by out-of-phase excitation and inhibition during rhythmic behaviors <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Goulding et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Grillner and Jessell 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kiehn 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Stein 2010)</ref>.</s><s>This pattern of synaptic activity in motoneurons has only been recorded directly in aquatic animals <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Dale 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Gabriel et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Russell and Wallén 1983)</ref> where locomotion is dependent on alternating activity between left-right and not flexors-extensors.</s><s>Neurons embedded in active networks in other brain areas can be driven by in-phase synaptic excitation and inhibition <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Priebe and Ferster 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Shu et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Wilent and Contreras 2005)</ref> resulting in a substantial conductance increase <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Borg-Graham et al. 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Destexhe et al. 2003)</ref>.</s><s>In line, the high-conductance states in spinal motoneurons during rhythmic network activity in the turtle <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Alaburda et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Guzulaitis et al. 2016</ref>) were suggested to be due to balanced excitation and inhibition <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Berg et al. 2007</ref>).</s><s>However, recent experiments in hip flexor (HF) motoneurons show that synaptic excitation is predominantly balanced by intrinsic outward rectification activated during depolarization rather than by synaptic inhibition <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Guzulaitis and Hounsgaard 2017)</ref>.</s><s>In fact, the experiments demonstrated explicitly that synaptic inhibition and excitation peaked out-of-phase in HF motoneurons during rhythmic motor behavior <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Guzulaitis and Hounsgaard 2017)</ref>.</s><s>It is not known whether this type of activation also applies for other types of motoneurons and whether out-of-phase synaptic inhibition and excitation remain during different spinal network activities.</s><s>In addition, gain and pattern control by in-phase inhibition in motoneurons (Currie and Lee 1997; <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Heckman and Enoka 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Johnson and Heckman 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Kishore et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Vestergaard and Berg 2015)</ref> might be more prominent in other motor pools and behaviors.</s><s>Therefore, in the present study, whole cell recordings were obtained from motoneurons in an ex vivo preparation from the adult turtle.</s><s>With voltage-clamp (VC) recordings, it is shown that HF and hip extensor (HE) motoneurons received out-of-phase excitation and inhibition during sensory-induced fictive scratching.</s><s>In contrast, overlap between excitation and inhibition in HF-like motoneurons was found, i.e., inhibition precedes excitation and delays depolarization during fictive scratching.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ethical Approval</head><p><s>The surgical procedures complied with Danish legislation and were approved by the controlling body under the Ministry of Justice.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>An Ex Vivo Carapace-Spinal Cord Preparation</head><p><s>Red-eared turtles (Trachemys scripta elegans), 10-to 15-cm carapace length, were obtained from Nasco (Fort Atkinson, WI).</s><s>Surgical procedures were described before <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(Guzulaitis et al. 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Briefly, turtles (n ϭ 29) of either sex were placed on crushed ice 2 h before surgery to induce drowsiness and reduce stress and pain by hypother-mia.</s><s>In this way, the head and neck could be protracted using minimal force.</s><s>Brain functions were terminated immediately on decapitation by crushing the head.</s><s>The blood was substituted by perfusion through the heart with a Ringer solution containing, in mM, 100 NaCl, 5 KCl, 30 NaHCO 3 , 2 MgCl 2 , 3 CaCl 2 , and 10 glucose saturated with 95% O 2 -5% CO 2 to obtain pH 7.4.</s><s>Transverse cuts were made at D9 -10 and D3 spinal cord segments (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>).</s><s>The HF nerve innervating puboischiofemoralis internus, pars anteroventralis muscle was exposed and cut.</s></p><p><s>Scratching was initiated by mechanically stimulating turtle carapace (M8.5-M9.5)</s><s>with a fire-polished glass rod mounted to the membrane of a loudspeaker controlled with a function generator (loudspeaker in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1A</ref>).</s><s>Only responses with Ն3 bursts in HF nerve were used for analysis.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recordings</head><p><s>Whole cell recordings from motoneurons were performed with a MultiClamp 700B amplifier (Molecular Devices).</s><s>Patch pipettes were filled with solution containing, in mM, 122 K-gluconate, 2.5 MgCl 2 , 5.6 Mg-gluconate, 5 K-HEPES, 5 H-HEPES, 5 Na 2 ATP, 1 EGTA, 0.3 CaCl 2 , and 2.5 biocytin.</s><s>pH was adjusted to 7.4 with KOH.</s><s>The electrode resistance was 4 -6 M⍀.</s><s>VC experiments were performed on neurons with low access resistance (R a Ͻ 20 M⍀) and compensated by 60 -80%.</s><s>Recordings were sampled at 20 kHz with a 16-bit analog-to-digital converter (Digidata 1322A; Molecular Devices), displayed by means of AxoScope and Clampex software (Molecular Devices), and stored on a hard disk for later analysis.</s><s>The electroneurogram of the HF nerve was recorded with a differential amplifier, Iso-DAM8 (World Precision Instruments, Sarasota, FL), using a suction electrode.</s><s>The bandwidth was 100 Hz to 1 kHz.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Identification of Motoneurons</head><p><s>Motoneurons were identified by their location in the ventral horn, size (as indicated by membrane resistance), and height of action potentials.</s><s>Recordings were accepted if motoneurons had a stable membrane potential (V m ) more negative than Ϫ50 mV and were not firing at rest.</s><s>A subset (n ϭ 20) of neurons in the ex vivo preparation were filled with biocytin for histological processing (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1B</ref>).</s><s>Lumbar segments were removed en bloc from the ex vivo preparation, kept in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) with 4% paraformaldehyde for 24 -48 h at 4°C, and subsequently rinsed with and stored in PBS.</s><s>Fixed spinal segments were mounted in an agar mount and sectioned transversely into 100-m-thick slices using a microtome (Leica VT1000 S).</s><s>The slices were incubated in a blocking solution (PBS ϩ 0.1% Triton X-100 ϩ 5% donkey serum) for 4 h at 4°C and later for 24 -48 h at 4°C with a goat polyclonal antibody directed against choline acetyltransferase (1:250; Millipore).</s><s>The slices were washed three times with PBS ϩ 0.1% Triton X-100 and incubated for 12-24 h at 4°C with secondary antibodies Alexa Fluor 647 conjugated with donkey anti-goat antibodies (1:500; Jackson ImmunoResearch) and cyanine 3 (Cy3) conjugated to streptavidin (1:500; Jackson Immu-noResearch).</s><s>After three washes with PBS, the slices were mounted and coverslipped using ProLong Gold antifade reagent (Invitrogen) and cured overnight at 4°C before microscopy.</s></p><p><s>Micrographs of neurons were produced using a confocal microscope, Zeiss LSM 700, with diode lasers, on a Zeiss Axio Imager M2 using ϫ20/0.8-numerical</s><s>aperture Plan-Apochromat objective (Zeiss).</s><s>The fluorophores were excited/detected at the following: Cy3 at 555/560 -800 nm and Alexa Fluor 647 at 643/560 -800 nm.</s><s>Images were handled with ZEN 2011 software (Zeiss) in the LSM and 8-bit TIFF format.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Analysis</head><p><s>Motoneuron classification.</s><s>Motoneurons were categorized based on how their V m related to motor output during scratch network activity.</s><s>To find the relationship, the HF nerve activity was rectified and both V m and the rectified HF nerve activity were low-pass filtered (5-Hz Gaussian; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>The correlation (Pearson) was calculated between the filtered signals.</s><s>A set of data from HF motoneurons (n ϭ 20) was presented in a previous paper <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Guzulaitis and Hounsgaard 2017)</ref> with additional analysis applied in this study.</s></p><p><s>Relationship between synaptic activity and motor nerve output.</s><s>HF nerve activity was rectified, and both intracellular recordings (V m or synaptic current) and rectified HF nerve activity were low-pass filtered (5-Hz Gaussian; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</s><s>The correlation between synaptic input and motor output was evaluated when motoneurons were recorded at Ϫ65 mV (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2C</ref>) and at 0 mV (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2E</ref>).</s><s>For convenience, the inward current recorded at Ϫ65 mV was inverted.</s><s>The inward current recorded at Ϫ65 mV was considered to be excitatory synaptic input, and outward current recorded at 0 mV was considered to be inhibitory synaptic input.</s><s>The correlation (Pearson) between synaptic current and nerve activity was evaluated at 0 time lag (histograms in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2,  C and E</ref>) and other time lags (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2, D and F</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Normalization of intracellular recordings.</s><s>First, intracellular records were normalized in time.</s><s>To do so, V m , but not membrane current (I m ), was low-pass filtered (5-Hz Gaussian) and normalized with respect to HF nerve activity (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>).</s><s>To determine the onset and offset of HF bursts, the electroneurographic activity was rectified and low-pass filtered (5-Hz Gaussian).</s><s>The onset of HF activity was defined as 0 (or 1) and the offset as 0.5.</s><s>The intracellular signal (V m or I m ) during the active and the quiescence HF phases were divided into 100 equal segments each, and the mean of Ն3 successive scratch cycles was calculated.</s><s>The correlation (Pearson) between current recorded at Ϫ65 and 0 mV was calculated (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5F</ref>).</s><s>Next, intensities of both V m and synaptic current were normalized to peak levels.</s></p><p><s>Regularity of firing.</s><s>The firing of motoneurons was evaluated by calculating interspike interval (ISI) between two adjacent action potentials (APs).</s><s>Only recordings of motoneurons with Ͼ30 APs were used, and only ISIs within motor bursts were included in the analysis.</s><s>The ratio of adaptation/acceleration was calculated as a ratio between adapting (ISIϩ1 Ͼ ISI) and accelerating (ISIϩ1 Ͻ ISI) ISI pairs and referred to as the adaptation index.</s><s>The irregularity of spiking was evaluated using coefficient of variation, also known as CV 2 <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(Holt et al. 1996;</ref><ref type="bibr">Eq. 1)</ref>:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">CV 2 ϭ 2 Խ ISI Ϫ ISI ϩ1Խ ISI ϩ ISI ϩ1 . (<label>1</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_1">)</formula><p><s>CV 2 was calculated for each pair of APs and averaged across multiple scratch cycles.</s></p><p><s>V m and synaptic input in HF and HE motoneurons during scratching.</s><s>First, the amplitude of the V m modulation during scratching was examined in HF and HE motoneurons.</s><s>The amplitude was determined from normalized intracellular recordings by subtracting hyperpolarized V m during the trough of the scratch cycle from peak V m during depolarization (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6C</ref>).</s><s>Next, the resting conductance of HF and HE motoneurons was compared from the conductance estimated from the current-voltage relationship obtained from the voltage response to current pulses in a range of intensities injected into the cells at rest (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6D</ref>).</s><s>Finally, the peak inhibitory and excitatory synaptic current was determined from normalized and averaged VC recordings during scratch cycles and compared between motoneuron groups (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>, E and F).</s><s>In addition, the ratio of inhibition and excitation was evaluated from the peaks of synaptic current at Ϫ65 and 0 mV during successive scratch episodes (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6G</ref>).</s></p><p><s>V m and synaptic input in HF and HF-like motoneurons during scratching.</s><s>Peaks of V m and synaptic current were determined from the normalized and averaged scratch cycles (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref>).</s><s>Next, timing of the peaks was used to compare V m and synaptic input to HF and HF-like motoneurons.</s></p><p><s>HE motoneurons during ipsilateral and contralateral scratching.</s><s>V m and excitatory and inhibitory current in HE motoneurons were recorded during both ipsilateral (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9A</ref>) and contralateral scratching (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9B</ref>).</s><s>Peaks of V m during contralateral scratching were normalized to peaks of V m during ipsilateral scratching (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9D</ref>).</s><s>The same normalization was applied for excitatory (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9E</ref>) and inhibitory current (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9F</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Methods</head><p><s>Data were analyzed statistically using two-tailed Wilcoxon signedrank test for paired comparison and two-tailed Mann-Whitney test for independent samples (Origin software; OriginLab, Northampton, MA).</s><s>Data are presented as means (SD).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Motoneuron Classification</head><p><s>Mechanical stimulation in the hindlimb scratch receptive field of the turtle carapace induces scratchlike rhythmic activity in the HF nerve (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1, C-E</ref>).</s><s>The period of the scratch rhythm varied from 0.7 to 4.9 s with mean of 2.26 (0.75) s (n ϭ 450 scratch cycles).</s><s>The motoneurons recorded (n ϭ 50) were divided into one of three classes according to how well changes in V m correlated with HF motor nerve activity during scratching (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>Motoneurons with a high correlation coefficient between V m and HF nerve activity (r Ͼ 0.8) were catego-rized as HF motoneurons (n ϭ 20; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1C</ref>).</s><s>Motoneurons with a lower but positive correlation between V m and nerve activity (0 Ͻ r Ͻ 0.8) were categorized as HF-like motoneurons (n ϭ 17; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1D</ref>).</s><s>The remaining motoneurons with negative correlation between V m and nerve activity were categorized as HE motoneurons (n ϭ 13; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1E</ref>).</s><s>The population of motoneurons recorded in this study is summarized in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1F</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Excitation and Inhibition in Spinal Motoneurons during Scratching</head><p><s>After recording V m during scratching (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref>), excitatory and inhibitory synaptic current were recorded during subsequent scratch episodes.</s><s>First, the excitatory synaptic input was recorded as the inward current at Ϫ65 mV during a scratch episode (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2C</ref>).</s><s>Note that inward current recorded at Ϫ65 mV is inverted.</s><s>Next, the inhibitory synaptic input was recorded as the outward current at 0 mV during scratching (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2E</ref>).</s></p><p><s>The correlation between HF nerve activity and intracellular recording in HF motoneurons was evaluated (histograms in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2, A, C, and E</ref>).</s><s>Next, the correlation between V m and HF nerve activity at different time lags was determined (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref>), and the peak correlation was identified.</s><s>For HF motoneurons, the correlation peak [0.93 (0.04), n ϭ 20] occurred close to 0 time lag [0.01 (0.02), n ϭ 20; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B, right</ref>].</s><s>The correlation between excitatory current and nerve activity [0.84 (0.12), n ϭ 20] also peaked close to 0 time lag [Ϫ0.001 (0.02), n ϭ 20; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>, right].</s><s>Finally, the correlation between inhibitory current and nerve activity was evaluated, and a negative correlation peak [Ϫ0.76 (0.12), n ϭ 20] was found close to 0 time lag [Ϫ0.002 (0.1), n ϭ 20], whereas a positive peak [0.62 (0.12), n ϭ 20] was observed when inhibitory current was delayed or advanced by half of a cycle (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2F</ref>, right).</s><s>To summarize, HF motoneurons receive in-phase excitatory synaptic input, whereas inhibitory synaptic input occurs out of phase.</s></p><p><s>The same procedure was applied for HF-like motoneurons (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_4">3</ref>).</s><s>Even though the correlation between V m and nerve activity was quite low for HF-like motoneurons at 0 time lag The correlation between HF nerve activity and intracellular recordings of HE motoneurons was also evaluated (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>).</s><s>In HE motoneurons, V m and HF nerve activity were negatively correlated during scratching [Ϫ0.68 (0.17</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Relation among V m , APs, Excitation, and Inhibition in Spinal Motoneurons</head><p><s>To relate V m , APs, excitation, and inhibition with each other, intracellular records were normalized in time with respect to HF nerve activity (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5</ref>).</s><s>The majority of the recorded motoneurons (35 out of 50 motoneurons) fired APs during scratching as shown in Figs.</s><s><ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">1-4</ref>.</s><s>The cumulative histogram of APs fired by HF motoneurons during scratching (histogram in top of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5A</ref>) is closely related to V m (top traces of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5A</ref>).</s><s>A similar close relation between firing and V m was observed in HE motoneurons (top of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5B</ref>) and HF-like motoneurons (top of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5C</ref>).</s><s>Close relation between V m and firing in recorded motoneurons is further supported by the finding that timing of the peak of V m during scratching is well-correlated (r ϭ 0.96, P ϭ 6EϪ14; n ϭ 25) to the timing of maximal firing (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5D</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Out-of-phase excitation and inhibition was observed in most HF and HE motoneurons (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5, A and B</ref>), whereas some overlap between inhibition and excitation was found in HF-like motoneurons (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5C</ref>).</s><s>The correlation between excitation and inhibition was Ϫ0.59 (0.32; n ϭ 20) for HF motoneurons and Ϫ0.65 (0.17; n ϭ 13) for HE motoneurons (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5F</ref>).</s><s>The correlation between excitation and inhibition in HF-like motoneurons varied from positive to negative with a mean of 0.06 (0.5; n ϭ 17; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5F</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Previous studies showed that motoneurons fire irregularly during scratching <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Berg et al. 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Guzulaitis et al. 2016</ref>) and swimming <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(Guzulaitis et al. 2016)</ref>.</s><s>Motoneurons recorded in this study demonstrated similar irregular firing indicated by CV 2 [0.46 (0.13), n ϭ 25] as in a previous study <ref type="bibr">(Guzulaitis et</ref>  al. 2016).</s><s>In addition, the adaptation index [1.01</s><s>(0.16), n ϭ 25] indicates that there is no clear acceleration or adaptation in firing rates during scratching.</s><s>Irregular firing suggests that spike activity is mainly driven by excitatory synaptic input as supported by the fact that maximal firing in recorded motoneurons is closely correlated with a peak of excitatory input (r ϭ 0.97, P ϭ 2.4EϪ15; n ϭ 25; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5E</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V m and Patterns of Synaptic Input in HF and HE Motoneurons</head><p><s>Mean V m and mean synaptic current are in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6A</ref>, left, for HF motoneurons (n ϭ 20) and in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6B</ref>, left, for HE motoneurons (n ϭ 13).</s><s>V m modulation during scratching was of similar amplitude in the two groups of motoneurons [17.86 (7.29) mV, n ϭ 20 for HF motoneurons and 18.16 (5.74) mV, n ϭ 13 for HE motoneurons; P ϭ 0.9, Mann-Whitney test; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6C]</ref>.</s><s>Excitatory input, i.e., current recorded in VC mode at Ϫ65 mV, peaked at higher levels in HF motoneurons [2.42 (1.58) nA, n ϭ 20] than in HE motoneurons [1.08 (0.51) nA, n ϭ 13; P ϭ 0.002, Mann-Whitney test; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6E]</ref>.</s><s>This could at least in part be explained by the fact that membrane conductance at rest in HF motoneurons <ref type="bibr">[68.86 (30.58</ref>) nS, n ϭ 20] is higher than membrane conductance in HE motoneurons [37.42 (26.09), n ϭ 13; P ϭ 0.0016, Mann-Whitney test; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6D]</ref>, meaning that more current is needed to depolarize HF motoneurons to the same V m level.</s><s>Inhibitory input, i.e., current recorded in VC mode at 0 mV, peaked at lower levels in HF motoneurons [2.35 (1.47) nA, n ϭ 20] than in HE motoneurons [3.57</s><s>(2.02) nA, n ϭ 13; P ϭ 0.047, Mann-Whitney test; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6F</ref>].</s><s>This means that even though less inhibition is needed to hyperpolarize HE motoneurons with lower membrane conductance, they, nevertheless, receive much stronger inhibitory input during scratching.</s><s>Finally, the ratio between synaptic current peaks was calculated and compared between groups of motoneurons.</s><s>The ratio between inhibitory and excitatory current peaks was lower in HF motoneurons [1.04 (0.42), n ϭ 20] than in HE motoneurons [3.7 (2.28), n ϭ 13; P ϭ 6.6EϪ8, Mann-Whitney test; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6G</ref>].</s><s>To sum up, HE motoneurons receive much stronger inhibition than HF motoneurons during scratching.</s></p><p><s>Next, the relationships between excitatory and inhibitory input to V m were plotted in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6A</ref>, right, for HF motoneurons (n ϭ 20) and in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6B</ref>, right, for HE motoneurons (n ϭ 13).</s><s>Hysteresis was observed for excitatory input in both HF (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6A</ref>) and HE motoneurons (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6B</ref>), indicating that the same V m levels in motoneurons are obtained with more excitation during depolarization than during hyperpolarization.</s><s>Similar hysteresis was observed for inhibitory input in HF motoneurons (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6A</ref>), i.e., a fairly linear relation between V m and inhibitory current was observed during hyperpolarization fol-lowed by a decrease in inhibition, whereas V m stayed the same and only little inhibition remained during depolarization.</s><s>A different pattern of inhibition was observed in HE motoneurons (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6B</ref>) with more inhibition during depolarization than during hyperpolarization.</s><s>In addition, it is clear from the plot that V m hyperpolarizes early before inhibition peaks and the subsequent increase in inhibition does not affect V m much.</s><s>This confirms the seemingly excessive inhibitory input observed in HE motoneurons.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V m and Patterns of Synaptic Input in HF-Like Motoneurons</head><p><s>As seen in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5C</ref>, inhibition and excitation clearly overlap in HF-like motoneurons.</s><s>However, it is also obvious that inhibition does not peak at the same time as excitation but rather is time-shifted so that inhibition leads excitation.</s><s>To highlight the difference between HF and HF-like motoneurons, the signals were superimposed in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref>.</s><s>The excitatory input is very similar in these two classes of motoneurons (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7C</ref>)  <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7D</ref>].</s><s>Note, however, that the V m depolarization is delayed in HF-like motoneurons (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7, A  and B</ref>).</s><s>HF motoneurons depolarize maximally early during the scratch cycle [0.28</s><s>(0.06), n ϭ 20], whereas HF-like motoneurons depolarize gradually to reach maximal depolarization later during the scratch cycle [0.35</s><s>(0.07), n ϭ 17; P ϭ 0.004, Mann-Whitney test].</s><s>The gradual depolarization is most likely due to the pattern of inhibition (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7E</ref>).</s><s>Inhibition in HF-like motoneurons peaks just before the onset of depolarization [0.24 (0.21), n ϭ 17] and gradually subsides during the excitatory phase as V m depolarization develops.</s><s>In contrast inhibition in HF motoneurons peaks out of phase with V m depolarization and excitation [0.59 (0.17), n ϭ 20; P ϭ 9.8EϪ6, Mann-Whitney test; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7F]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The role of inhibition in HF-like motoneurons was explored in an additional experiment.</s><s>First, the pattern of firing and V m were recorded in current-clamp mode in HF and HF-like motoneurons (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">8, A and E</ref>).</s><s>The excitatory input was then recorded in VC mode at Ϫ65 mV in each motoneuron.</s><s>This current was inverted and, in the absence of network activity, injected back to the motoneurons from which it was recorded (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">8, B and F</ref>).</s><s>All motoneurons (n ϭ 17) showed rhythmic firing and/or depolarizations of V m in response to the injected excitatory current obtained during scratching (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">8, C and G</ref>).</s><s>Qualitatively similar firing and/or V m pattern during scratching and current injection were observed in HF motoneurons (n ϭ 10; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">8D</ref>).</s><s>In contrast, early firing and/or V m depolarization was seen when HF-like motoneurons (n ϭ 7) were stimulated by excitatory input (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">8H</ref>).</s><s>This supports the idea that inhibition in HF-like motoneurons delays depolarization of V m and firing during scratching.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Synaptic Activity in HE Motoneurons during Ipsi-and Contralateral Scratching</head><p><s>Our experiments confirm that periods of synaptic inhibition and excitation alternate in both HF and HE motoneurons during scratching.</s><s>Next, we investigated the sensitivity of this pattern to changes in network activity.</s><s>Even though scratching is a predominantly unilateral behavior, the contralateral hindlimb is also involved <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Field and Stein 1997)</ref>.</s><s>Both HE and HF motoneurons are activated during ipsilateral scratching, whereas mainly HE but not HF motoneurons are active during contralateral scratching <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Currie and Gonsalves 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Guzulaitis et al. 2014)</ref>.</s><s>Therefore, HE motoneuron was recorded during both ipsilateral (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9A</ref>) and contralateral (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9B</ref>) scratch episodes.</s><s>As expected, HE motoneuron was activated during both ipsilateral and contralateral scratching (top of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9, A-C</ref>).</s><s>The intensity of excitatory current was similar during ipsilateral and contralateral scratching (middle of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9, A-C</ref>), whereas inhibition was much weaker during contralateral scratching than during ipsilateral scratching (bottom of Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9, A-C</ref>).</s></p><p><s>This pattern was observed for all 11 HE motoneurons recorded during ipsilateral and contralateral scratching.</s><s>V m depolarized slightly less during contralateral scratching [0.84 (0.23), n ϭ 11; P ϭ 0.02, Wilcoxon signed-rank test] than during ipsilateral scratching (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9D</ref>).</s><s>In line, weaker excitatory input [0.71 (0.23), n ϭ 11; P ϭ 0.005, Wilcoxon signed-rank test] was observed during contralateral scratching (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9E</ref>).</s><s>However, the most noticeable difference was be- tween inhibitory input during different behaviors in that inhibition was much weaker [0.43 (0.28), n ϭ 11; P ϭ 0.002, Wilcoxon signed-rank test] during contralateral scratching than during ipsilateral scratching (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9F</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Despite differences in synaptic intensity during the two behaviors, the phase relations were unaffected.</s><s>Inhibition and excitation were out of phase during both ipsilateral [Ϫ0.66 (0.18), n ϭ 11] and contralateral scratching [Ϫ0.75 (0.08), n ϭ 11; P ϭ 0.15, Wilcoxon signed-rank test; Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">9G]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>Patterns of excitatory and inhibitory synaptic input were investigated in spinal motoneurons during scratch network activity in an ex vivo preparation from the adult turtle.</s><s>Outof-phase excitation and inhibition was demonstrated for both HF and HE motoneurons during ipsilateral scratching and for HE motoneurons during contralateral scratching.</s></p><p><s>Alternation between flexors and extensors during rhythmic motor behaviors is commonly attributed to reciprocal inhibition between antagonistic half-centers and predicts that excitation and inhibition alternate in flexor and extensor motoneurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Goulding et al. 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Grillner and Jessell 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kiehn 2016;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Stein 2010</ref>).</s><s>However, out-of-phase excitation and inhibition in motoneurons has only been explicitly demonstrated in aquatic vertebrates where axial movements are produced by alternating activity between left and right sides <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Dale 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Gabriel et al. 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b33">Russell and Wallén 1983)</ref>.</s><s>The mecha-nisms responsible for left-right alternation during axial rhythmic movements in aquatic vertebrates are not necessarily the same as the ones securing alternation between flexors and extensors in limbed vertebrates.</s><s>First, coordination between flexor-extensor and left-right develop at different embryonic stages <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Kudo et al. 2004</ref>).</s><s>Second, commissural interneurons are crucial for left-right coordination both in aquatic <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(Moult et al. 2013</ref>) and limbed animals <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Butt and Kiehn 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b36">Talpalar et al. 2013)</ref>, whereas flexor-extensor coordination is well-preserved in hemisegments <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Kudo and Yamada 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Zhong et al. 2012)</ref>.</s><s>The first direct demonstration of out-of-phase excitation and inhibition in limbed vertebrates was recently obtained from HF motoneurons during scratch network activity in the turtle <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Guzulaitis and Hounsgaard 2017)</ref>.</s><s>The present study extends and confirms out-of-phase excitation and inhibition to apply for HE motoneurons during ipsi-and contralateral network activity.</s><s>Thus, although the networks that secure alternation between ipsilateral flexors and extensors and left and right limbs are different, motoneurons are driven by out-of-phase excitation and inhibition in both cases.</s><s>Probably because of lack of direct experimental support, the classic reciprocal inhibition in spinal motor function was challenged when high-conductance states were observed in turtle spinal motoneurons during rhythmic network activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Alaburda et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Guzulaitis et al. 2016)</ref>.</s><s>It is known that high-conductance states in cortical neurons are the outcome of concurrent excitation and inhibition <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Destexhe et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Shu et al. 2003</ref>; Wilent and Contreras 2005), and, indeed, concurrent excitation and inhibition was proposed also to explain conductance increase in HF motoneurons during rhythmic network activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Berg et al. 2007</ref>).</s><s>However, a recent study showed that intrinsic conductance in spinal motoneurons contributes significantly to the conductance increase during network activity and that neglecting this intrinsic conductance leads to overestimation of in-phase inhibition <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Guzulaitis and Hounsgaard 2017)</ref>.</s><s>In fact, the study showed that the outward current that balances excitation in HF motoneurons during scratching is predominantly generated by intrinsic conductance rather than synaptic inhibition.</s><s>This selfcompensatory in-built mechanism may secure V m stabilization near threshold for action potential during intense synaptic excitation.</s><s>In addition, out-of-phase synaptic excitation and inhibition was explicitly demonstrated in HF motoneurons in the adult turtle during scratch network activity (Guzulaitis and Hounsgaard 2017) and confirmed for HE motoneurons in this study.</s><s>These findings support reciprocal rather than concurrent activation of spinal motoneurons during rhythmic behaviors.</s></p><p><s>Ia inhibitory interneurons are likely candidates for reciprocal inhibition and alternation between flexors and extensors in the spinal cord <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Hultborn 1976;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">Jankowska et al. 1965</ref>).</s><s>These neurons are derived from V1 and V2b inhibitory interneurons, and alternation between extensors and flexors is abolished after inactivation of V1 and V2b interneurons in mouse spinal cord <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Zhang et al. 2014</ref>).</s><s>In addition, Ia interneurons are highly active when their target motoneurons are inhibited <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Geertsen et al. 2011</ref>).</s><s>However, Ia interneurons do not fire only when their target motoneurons are inhibited.</s><s>They are active throughout the locomotion cycle with substantial activity during motoneuron depolarization <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Geertsen et al. 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Pratt and Jordan 1987)</ref>.</s><s>Together with the activation pattern of Renshaw inhibitory interneurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Pratt and Jordan 1987)</ref>, it is not surprising that inhibitory synaptic activity is present even during mo- toneuron depolarization and firing <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Alaburda et al. 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">Guzulaitis and Hounsgaard 2017;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Guzulaitis et al. 2016)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Asymmetry in synaptic input between HF and HE motoneurons was observed in this study with inhibition dominating in HE motoneurons.</s><s>In the neonatal mouse, inhibition also exceeds excitation in HE motoneurons during rhythmic network activity <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Endo and Kiehn 2008)</ref>.</s><s>The low level of inhibition in HE motoneurons during contralateral scratching in the turtle may suggest that this asymmetry is behavior dependent.</s><s>Despite the asymmetry observed, both HF and HE are activated in a robust push-pull manner in which inhibition alternates with excitation.</s><s>However, substantial overlap between excitation and inhibition was detected in HF-like motoneurons.</s><s>Inhibition in HF-like motoneurons led excitation and delayed depolarization of V m during rhythmic motor output.</s><s>This pattern of excitation and inhibition first reported for turtle motoneurons in vivo <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Robertson and Stein 1988</ref>) was proposed to determine the recruitment order of motoneurons to form motor patterns.</s><s>Indeed, blocking inhibition in the lumbar enlargement changes the pattern of motor nerve activity, suggesting that inhibition shapes motor output by delaying activity in motoneurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Currie and Lee 1997)</ref>.</s><s>Overlap between inhibition and excitation has also been seen in zebrafish spinal motoneurons <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Kishore et al. 2014</ref>) but with excitation leading inhibition.</s><s>In cortical neurons, excitation followed by inhibition may be a design to increase temporal precision of spike generation <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(Wehr and Zador 2003)</ref>.</s><s>During scratch network activity, HF and HF-like motoneurons receive common synaptic excitation, whereas differential synaptic inhibition may serve to fine-tune the activity of each group of motoneurons separately.</s><s>This may be a way of coordinating different motor pools in a taskspecific manner.</s><s>To summarize, the majority of spinal motoneurons are driven by out-of-phase excitation and inhibition, and, even in case of overlap between inhibition and excitation as in HF-like motoneurons, their peaks are time-shifted (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">7</ref>).</s></p><p><s>Activation of HE motoneurons was studied during two different behaviors.</s><s>Although the amplitude of V m modulation was very similar during ipsilateral and contralateral scratching, the underlying intensity of synaptic input was strikingly different.</s><s>Synaptic inhibition was much stronger in ipsilateral scratching than during contralateral scratching.</s><s>Since the level of excitation is very low in the hyperpolarizing phase of both scratch forms, the functional significance of the difference in the pattern of inhibition is obscure.</s><s>It is interesting to note that the difference is not reflected in the voltage trajectory.</s><s>In fact, inhibition peaks late in the hyperpolarizing phase when V m is already stabilized rather than during the shift from the depolarized to the hyperpolarized phase (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6B</ref>).</s><s>Since V m in HE motoneurons can be successfully hyperpolarized with moderate intensity of inhibition as seen during contralateral scratching, the function of a surplus inhibition during ipsilateral scratching is not clear.</s><s>It may possibly be a consequence of an in-built robust reciprocal inhibition between HF and HE modules.</s><s>This is supported by the intense inhibition in HE motoneurons during ipsilateral scratching when the HF module (and HF nerve) is active and the low level of inhibition during contralateral scratching when HF module is almost silent.</s><s>Furthermore, rhythmic activity in HF and HF-like motoneurons was obtained when these motoneurons were stimulated by excitatory current alone (see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">8</ref>).</s><s>Therefore, inhibitory input in motoneurons is not simply to hyperpolarize V m but probably provides coordination within a motor pool <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(Robertson and Stein 1988</ref>) and among different motor pools.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 1.</s><s>Experimental paradigm.</s><s>A: whole cell recordings from motoneurons in an ex vivo spinal cord-carapace preparation from the adult turtle.</s><s>Mechanical stimulation (stim) of the carapace (loudspeaker) was used to induce rhythmic scratch network activity.</s><s>Network activity was monitored by electroneurographic recording from the hip flexor (HF) motor nerve.</s><s>B: subset (n ϭ 20) of the presumed motoneurons recorded from (red) were filled with biocytin for histological verification.</s><s>These neurons, recorded in the lateral part of the ventral horn, turned out to be choline acetyltransferase (ChAT)-positive cells, i.e., motoneurons.</s><s>C: intracellular recording of a HF motoneuron, i.e., motoneuron with high correlation (r Ͼ 0.8) between membrane potential (V m ) and HF nerve activity during scratching.</s><s>D: intracellular recording of a HF-like motoneuron, i.e., motoneuron with low positive correlation (0 Ͼ r Ͼ 0.8) between V m and HF nerve activity during scratching.</s><s>E: intracellular recording of a hip extensor (HE) motoneuron, i.e., motoneuron with negative correlation (r Ͻ 0) between V m and HF nerve activity during scratching.</s><s>F: histogram of correlation coefficients between V m and HF nerve activity during scratching for all recorded motoneurons (n ϭ 50).</s><s>C-E from the top: V m of motoneurons and HF nerve activity.</s><s>Light color traces depict the raw signals, and dark color traces depict the low-pass-filtered signals.</s><s>Note that the neuron shown in B was classified as HF-like motoneuron.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,73.00,220.44,456.00,425.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 2. Membrane potential (V m ) and synaptic input in hip flexor (HF) spinal motoneurons.</s><s>A: whole cell recording from a HF motoneuron during scratching.</s><s>Both V m and electroneurogram of the HF nerve activity (gray traces) were low-pass filtered (black traces), and the correlation (Pearson) between the filtered signals was calculated.</s><s>Correlation coefficients for all HF motoneurons (n ϭ 20) are shown in the histogram to the right.</s><s>B: correlation coefficient between the low-pass-filtered signals was calculated at different time lags (left), and the positive peak was identified (black arrow).</s><s>Correlation peaks were high in all HF motoneurons and occurred close to 0 time lag (right; n ϭ 20).</s><s>C: the same HF motoneuron was recorded in voltage-clamp (VC) mode at Ϫ65 mV during scratching, and signals were low-pass filtered.</s><s>Inward current recorded at Ϫ65 mV was inverted and interpreted as excitatory synaptic input.</s><s>Correlation between excitatory synaptic current and HF nerve activity was calculated for all HF motoneurons (n ϭ 20).</s><s>D: correlation between excitatory synaptic current and HF nerve activity was calculated at different time lags (left), and a positive peak of the correlation function was identified (red arrow).</s><s>High positive correlation peaks between excitatory input and HF activity were detected in all HF motoneurons, and correlations peaked around 0 time lag (right).</s><s>E: finally, the same HF motoneuron was recorded in VC mode at 0 mV during scratching.</s><s>Outward current recorded at 0 mV was interpreted as inhibitory input.</s><s>Membrane current (I m ) and HF nerve activity were low-pass filtered, and the correlation between the filtered signals was calculated (histogram to the right).</s><s>F: correlation between inhibitory current and HF nerve activity was calculated at different time lags (left).</s><s>The most positive (light blue arrow) and the most negative peaks (dark blue arrow) of the correlation function were identified.</s><s>Negative peaks of the correlation between inhibition and HF nerve activity occur close to 0 time lag, whereas positive peaks of correlation occur close to half of the scratch cycle (either Ϫ0.5 or 0.5 of scratch cycle).</s><s>A, C, and E from the top: V m (A) or I m recorded at Ϫ65 mV (C) and 0 mV (E) and HF nerve activity.</s><s>Light color traces depict raw signals, and dark color traces depict low-pass-filtered signals.</s><s>Black arrows indicate the resting V m or holding I m level before scratching.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,43.50,71.76,516.00,347.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig.2D, right].</s><s>Finally, the correlation between inhibitory current and nerve activity was evaluated, and a negative correlation peak [Ϫ0.76 (0.12), n ϭ 20] was found close to 0 time lag [Ϫ0.002 (0.1), n ϭ 20], whereas a positive peak [0.62 (0.12), n ϭ 20] was observed when inhibitory current was delayed or advanced by half of a cycle (Fig.2F, right).</s><s>To summarize, HF motoneurons receive in-phase excitatory synaptic input, whereas inhibitory synaptic input occurs out of phase.The same procedure was applied for HF-like motoneurons (Fig.3).</s><s>Even though the correlation between V m and nerve activity was quite low for HF-like motoneurons at 0 time lag[0.6</s><s>(0.19), n ϭ 17; Fig. 3A], the correlation peaked at 0.83 (0.06; n ϭ 17) with a positive time lag [0.1 (0.07), n ϭ 17; Fig. 3B, right].</s><s>This indicates that V m is well-correlated with HF nerve activity but delayed with respect to the HF nerve activity.</s><s>The correlation between excitatory input and HF nerve activity peaked [0.86 (0.07), n ϭ 17] close to 0 time lag [0.02 (0.07), n ϭ 17; Fig. 3D, right], showing that excitation in HF-like motoneurons is locked to HF nerve activity.</s><s>Finally, the negative peak of correlation between inhibitory current and HF nerve activity [Ϫ0.63 (0.18), n ϭ 17] is delayed by a quarter of the scratch cycle [0.28</s><s>(0.13), n ϭ 17; Fig. 3F, right], and the positive peak [0.71 (0.14), n ϭ 17] is also shifted by a quarter of the scratch cycle [Ϫ0.22</s><s>(0.11), n ϭ 17].</s><s>To sum up, both excitatory and inhibitory input in HF-like motoneurons are highly related to motor output, and the interplay between them gives rise to a delayed depolarization of V m .The correlation between HF nerve activity and intracellular recordings of HE motoneurons was also evaluated (Fig.4).</s><s>In HE motoneurons, V m and HF nerve activity were negatively correlated during scratching [Ϫ0.68 (0.17), n ϭ 13; Fig. 4A] and peaked near 0 time lag [Ϫ0.06 (0.06), n ϭ 13; Fig. 4B, right].</s><s>Excitatory synaptic activity correlated negatively with nerve activity [Ϫ0.45 (0.23), n ϭ 13; Fig. 4C], peaking at Ϫ0.12 (0.06) time lag (n ϭ 13; Fig. 4D, right), whereas</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>), n ϭ 13; Fig. 4A] and peaked near 0 time lag [Ϫ0.06 (0.06), n ϭ 13; Fig. 4B, right].</s><s>Excitatory synaptic activity correlated negatively with nerve activity [Ϫ0.45 (0.23), n ϭ 13; Fig. 4C], peaking at Ϫ0.12 (0.06) time lag (n ϭ 13; Fig. 4D, right), whereas</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 3. Membrane potential (V m ) and synaptic input in hip flexor (HF)-like spinal motoneurons.</s><s>A: whole cell recording from a HF-like motoneuron during scratching.</s><s>Both V m and electroneurogram of the HF nerve activity (light green traces) were low-pass filtered (dark green traces), and the correlation (Pearson) between the filtered signals was calculated.</s><s>Correlation coefficients for all HF-like motoneurons (n ϭ 17) are shown in the histogram to the right.</s><s>B: correlation coefficient between the low-pass-filtered signals was calculated at different time lags, and positive peaks were considered (arrow).</s><s>C: the same HF-like motoneuron was recorded at Ϫ65 mV during a subsequent scratch episode, and signals were low-pass filtered.</s><s>Inward current recorded at Ϫ65 mV was inverted and interpreted as excitatory synaptic input.</s><s>Correlation between excitatory synaptic current and HF nerve activity was calculated for all HF-like motoneurons (n ϭ 17).</s><s>D: correlation between excitatory synaptic current and HF nerve activity was calculated at different time lags, and positive peaks of the correlation function were considered (arrow).</s><s>E: finally, the motoneuron was recorded at 0 mV during scratching, and outward current recorded at 0 mV was interpreted as inhibitory synaptic input.</s><s>Membrane current (I m ) and HF nerve activity were low-pass filtered, and correlation between the filtered signals was calculated for all HF-like motoneurons (n ϭ 17).</s><s>F: correlation between inhibitory current and the HF nerve activity was calculated at different time lags.</s><s>The most positive (light blue arrow) and the most negative peaks (dark blue arrow) were considered.</s><s>A, C, and E from the top: V m (A) or I m recorded at Ϫ65 mV (C) and 0 mV (E) and HF nerve activity.</s><s>Light color traces depict the raw signals, and dark color traces depict low-pass-filtered signals.</s><s>Black arrows indicate the resting V m or holding I m level before scratching.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,43.50,275.45,516.00,343.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 4. Membrane potential (V m ) and synaptic input in hip extensor (HE) spinal motoneurons.</s><s>A: whole cell recording from a HE motoneuron during scratching.</s><s>Both V m and electroneurogram of the hip flexor (HF) nerve activity (light yellow traces) were low-pass filtered (dark yellow traces), and the correlation (Pearson) between the filtered signals was calculated.</s><s>Correlation coefficients for all HE motoneurons (n ϭ 13) are shown in the histogram to the right.</s><s>B: correlation coefficient between the low-pass-filtered signals was calculated at different time lags, and negative peaks were considered (arrow).</s><s>C: the same HE motoneuron was recorded at Ϫ65 mV during a subsequent scratch episode, and the signals were low-pass filtered.</s><s>Inward current recorded at Ϫ65 mV was inverted and interpreted as excitatory synaptic input.</s><s>Correlation between excitatory synaptic current and HF nerve activity was calculated for all HE motoneurons (n ϭ 13).</s><s>D: correlation between excitatory synaptic current and HF nerve activity was calculated at different time lags, and the negative peaks of the correlation function were considered (arrow).</s><s>E: finally, the neuron was recorded at 0 mV during scratching, and outward current recorded at 0 mV was interpreted as inhibitory synaptic input.</s><s>Membrane current (I m ) and HF nerve activity were low-pass filtered, and the correlation between the filtered signals was calculated for all HE motoneurons (n ϭ 13).</s><s>F: correlation between the inhibitory current and HF nerve activity was calculated at different time lags.</s><s>The most positive (light blue arrow) and the most negative peaks (dark blue arrow) were considered.</s><s>A, C, and E from the top: V m (A) or I m recorded at Ϫ65 mV (C) and 0 mV (E) and HF nerve activity.</s><s>Light color traces depict raw signals, and dark color traces depict low-pass-filtered signals.</s><s>Black arrows indicate the resting V m or holding I m level before scratching.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,43.50,71.76,516.00,343.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 5. Correlation between inhibition and excitation in spinal motoneurons.</s><s>Cumulative histograms are of action potentials (APs) and membrane potential (V m ; top) and excitatory (red; middle) and inhibitory (blue; bottom) current normalized with respect to hip flexor (HF) nerve activity for HF motoneurons (A), hip extensor (HE) motoneurons (B), and HF-like motoneurons (C).</s><s>D: relation between peak V m and peak firing rate (F) during scratching.</s><s>E: relation between peak excitatory current and peak firing rate during scratching.</s><s>F: negative correlation between excitatory (exc) and inhibitory (inh) current was observed in a majority of motoneurons.</s><s>Positive correlation between excitatory and inhibitory current was found in some HF-like motoneurons.</s><s>A-C from the top: cumulative histogram of APs fired during scratching, V m , membrane current (I m ) recorded at Ϫ65 mV, I m recorded at 0 mV, and HF nerve activity as a reference for scratch cycle.</s><s>Arrows show the resting V m or holding I m level before scratching.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="7,91.04,71.94,420.00,427.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 6.</s><s>Synaptic patterns in hip flexor (HF) and hip extensor (HE) motoneurons.</s><s>A: mean normalized membrane potential (V m ; black circles) and excitatory (red circles) and inhibitory current (blue circles) for HF motoneurons (n ϭ 20).</s><s>Relation between excitatory current and V m is shown in the top right.</s><s>Relation between inhibitory current and V m is shown in the bottom right.</s><s>B: mean of the normalized V m (yellow circles) and excitatory (red circles) and inhibitory current (blue circles) for HE motoneurons (n ϭ 13).</s><s>Relation between excitatory current and V m is shown in the top right.</s><s>Relation between inhibitory current and V m is shown in the bottom right.</s><s>Filled circles represent the depolarization phase, and open circles represent the hyperpolarization phase during scratching.</s><s>I m , membrane current.</s><s>C: V m modulation in HF motoneurons during scratching [17.86 (7.29) mV, n ϭ 20] is similar to V m modulation in HE motoneurons during scratching [18.16 (5.74) mV, n ϭ 13; P ϭ 0.9, Mann-Whitney test].</s><s>D: membrane conductance (g) of HF motoneurons [68.86 (30.58) nS, n ϭ 19] is higher than membrane conductance of HE motoneurons [37.42 (26.09) nS, n ϭ 13; P ϭ 0.0016, Mann-Whitney test].</s><s>E: peak inward current recorded at Ϫ65 mV is higher in HF motoneurons [2.42 (1.58) nA, n ϭ 20] than in HE motoneurons [1.08 (0.51) nA, n ϭ 13; P ϭ 0.002, Mann-Whitney test].</s><s>F: peak outward current recorded at 0 mV is lower in HF motoneurons [2.35 (1.47) nA, n ϭ 20] than in HE motoneurons [3.57</s><s>(2.02) nA, n ϭ 13; P ϭ 0.047, Mann-Whitney test].</s><s>G: ratio between inhibitory (inh) and excitatory (exc) current peaks is lower in HF motoneurons [1.04 (0.42), n ϭ 20] than in HE motoneurons [3.7 (2.28), n ϭ 13; P ϭ 6.6EϪ8, Mann-Whitney test].</s><s>Level of significance is indicated as not significant (ns; P Ͼ 0.05), *P Ͻ 0.05, **P Ͻ 0.01, and ***P Ͻ 0.001.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,43.50,71.76,516.00,342.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 7. Synaptic patterns in hip flexor (HF) and HF-like motoneurons.</s><s>A: superimposed mean of the normalized membrane potential (V m ) for all HF motoneurons (black; n ϭ 20) and all HF-like motoneurons (green; n ϭ 17).</s><s>B: V m in HF motoneurons peaks earlier during the scratch cycle [0.28</s><s>(0.06), n ϭ 20] than V m of HF-like motoneurons [0.35 (0.07), n ϭ 17; P ϭ 0.004, Mann-Whitney test].</s><s>C: mean of the normalized excitatory synaptic current in HF motoneurons (dark red) and HF-like motoneurons (light red).</s><s>D: excitatory synaptic current in HF motoneurons peak at the same time [0.26 (0.05), n ϭ 20] as in HF-like motoneurons [0.3 (0.09), n ϭ 17; P ϭ 0.1, Mann-Whitney test].</s><s>E: mean of the normalized inhibitory synaptic current in HF motoneurons (dark blue) and HF-like motoneurons (light blue).</s><s>F: inhibitory synaptic current in HF motoneurons peaks out of phase with V m [0.59 (0.17), n ϭ 20], whereas inhibition in HF-like motoneurons peaks slightly earlier than excitation and V m [0.24 (0.21), n ϭ 17; P ϭ 9.8EϪ6, Mann-Whitney test].</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,222.76,71.69,336.00,312.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 8. Stimulation of hip flexor (HF) and HF-like motoneurons with excitatory current recorded during scratching.</s><s>A: membrane potential (V m ) of a HF motoneuron during scratching (black).</s><s>Excitatory current was recorded in voltage-clamp mode at Ϫ65 mV (light red) during a subsequent scratch episode.</s><s>This current was inverted (dark red) and injected back to recorded motoneuron in current-clamp mode in the absence of network activity.</s><s>B: expanded episodes from recordings obtained during scratching (black) and excitatory current stimulation (red) in A. C: normalized V m during scratching (gray) and excitatory current stimulation (light red) in all HF motoneurons (n ϭ 10).</s><s>D: mean normalized V m during scratching (black) and excitatory current stimulation (dark red) of all HF motoneurons (n ϭ 10).</s><s>E: V m of HF-like motoneuron during scratching (black) and excitatory current stimulation (dark red).</s><s>F: expanded episodes from recording obtained during scratching (black) and excitatory current stimulation (red) in E. G: normalized V m during scratching (gray) and excitatory current stimulation (light red) in all HF-like motoneurons (n ϭ 7).</s><s>H: mean normalized V m during scratching (black) and excitatory current stimulation (dark red) of all HF-like motoneurons (n ϭ 7).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,43.50,71.59,516.00,266.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 9 .</head><label>9</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Fig. 9. Excitation and inhibition in hip extensor (HE) motoneurons during ipsilateral and contralateral scratching.</s><s>A: membrane potential (V m ) from a HE motoneuron during ipsilateral scratching (black).</s><s>Excitatory current was recorded at Ϫ65 mV (red) and inhibitory current was recorded at 0 mV (blue) during subsequent ipsilateral scratch episodes.</s><s>Note that the excitatory current is inverted.</s><s>B: V m of the same HE motoneuron was recorded during contralateral scratching (gray).</s><s>Excitatory current recorded at Ϫ65 mV (red) and inhibitory current recorded at 0 mV (light blue) during subsequent contralateral scratch episodes.</s><s>C: normalized V m (top) and excitatory (middle) and inhibitory current (bottom) during both ipsilateral (left) and contralateral (right) scratching from the HE motoneuron shown in A and B. D: peak depolarization of V m in HE motoneurons is slightly lower during contralateral scratching [0.84 (0.22), n ϭ 11; P ϭ 0.02, Wilcoxon signed-rank test] than during ipsilateral scratching.</s><s>E: in line, the peak of excitatory input in HE motoneurons is lower during contralateral scratching [0.71 (0.23), n ϭ 11; P ϭ 0.005, Wilcoxon signed-rank test] than during ipsilateral scratching.</s><s>F: stronger inhibitory input is present during ipsilateral scratching than during contralateral scratching [0.43 (0.28), n ϭ 11; P ϭ 0.002, Wilcoxon signed-rank test].</s><s>G: no difference in correlation between excitation and inhibition in HE motoneurons during ipsilateral [Ϫ0.66 (0.18), n ϭ 11] and contralateral scratching [Ϫ0.75 (0.08), n ϭ 11; P ϭ 0.15, Wilcoxon signed-rank test], i.e., excitation is negatively correlated with inhibition.</s><s>Level of significance is indicated as not significant (ns; P Ͼ 0.05), *P Ͻ 0.05, and **P Ͻ 0.01.</s><s>cHF, contralateral hip flexor nerve; iHF, ipsilateral hip flexor nerve.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="11,43.50,71.78,516.00,352.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="22">-3077/18 Copyright © 2018 the American Physiological Society www.jn.org Downloaded from journals.physiology.org/journal/jn (176.172.000.127) on May 17, 2022.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">J Neurophysiol • doi:10.1152/jn.00094.2018 • www.jn.org Downloaded from journals.physiology.org/journal/jn (176.172.000.127) on May 17, 2022.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>Histology experiments were performed at the Core Facility for Integrative Microscopy, University of Copenhagen.</s></p><p><s>Present address of R. Guzulaitis: The Florey Inst. of Neuroscience and Mental Health, Univ. of Melbourne, Melbourne, VIC, Australia.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GRANTS</head><p><s>This study was supported by The Lundbeck Foundation and Danish Research Council.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCLOSURES</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Periodic high-conductance states in spinal neurons during scratch-like network activity in adult turtles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alaburda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Russo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Macaulay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hounsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0843-05.2005</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6316" to="6321" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005. 2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Balanced inhibition and excitation drive spike activity in spinal half-centers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Berg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alaburda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hounsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/science.1134960</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">315</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="390" to="393" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Intense synaptic activity enhances temporal resolution in spinal motoneurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Berg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ditlevsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hounsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0003218</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual input evokes transient and strong shunting inhibition in visual cortical neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Borg-Graham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Monier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Frégnac</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/30735</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">393</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="369" to="373" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the nature of the fundamental activity of the nervous centres; together with an analysis of the conditioning of rhythmic activity in progression, and a theory of the evolution of function in the nervous system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1113/jphysiol.1914.sp001646</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="46" />
			<date type="published" when="1914">1914</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Functional identification of interneurons responsible for left-right coordination of hindlimbs in mammals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Butt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Kiehn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0896-6273(03)00353-2</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="953" to="963" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Right-left interactions between rostral scratch networks generate rhythmicity in the preenlargement spinal cord of the turtle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Currie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Gonsalves</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1152/jn.1997.78.6.3479</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurophysiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3479" to="3483" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glycinergic inhibition contributes to the generation of rostral scratch motor patterns in the turtle spinal cord</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Currie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.17-09-03322.1997</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3322" to="3333" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reciprocal inhibitory interneurones in the Xenopus embryo spinal cord</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Dale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1113/jphysiol.1985.sp015695</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">363</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="70" />
			<date type="published" when="1985">1985</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The high-conductance state of neocortical neurons in vivo</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Destexhe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rudolph</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Paré</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nrn1198</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1019</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Nat Rev Neurosci</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Asymmetric operation of the locomotor central pattern generator in the neonatal mouse spinal cord</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Endo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Kiehn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1152/jn.90729.2008</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurophysiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3043" to="3054" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spinal cord coordination of hindlimb movements in the turtle: interlimb temporal relationships during bilateral scratching and swimming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Field</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Stein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1152/jn.1997.78.3.1404</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurophysiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1404" to="1413" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Serotonergic modulation of locomotion in zebrafish: endogenous release and synaptic mechanisms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Gabriel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mahmood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kyriakatos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Söll</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hauptmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Calabrese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">El</forename><surname>Manira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1978-09.2009</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10387" to="10395" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reciprocal Ia inhibition contributes to motoneuronal hyperpolarisation during the inactive phase of locomotion and scratching in the cat</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Geertsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Stecina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Meehan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Nielsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hultborn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1113/jphysiol.2010.199125</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">589</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="134" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inhibition downunder: an update from the spinal cord</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goulding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bourane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Garcia-Campmany</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dalet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.conb.2014.03.006</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Neurobiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="166" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Measured motion: searching for simplicity in spinal locomotor networks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Grillner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jessell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.conb.2009.10.011</idno>
		<idno>doi:10.1016/ j.conb.2009.10.011</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Neurobiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="572" to="586" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dense distributed processing in a hindlimb scratch motor network</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Guzulaitis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alaburda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hounsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1079-14.2014</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="10756" to="10764" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increased activity of pre-motor network does not change the excitability of motoneurons during protracted scratch initiation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Guzulaitis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alaburda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hounsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1113/jphysiol.2012.246025</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">591</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1851" to="1858" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synaptic excitation in spinal motoneurons alternates with synaptic inhibition and is balanced by outward rectification during rhythmic motor network activity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Guzulaitis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hounsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0800-17.2017</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">37</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9239" to="9248" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Irregular firing and high-conductance states in spinal motoneurons during scratching and swimming</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Guzulaitis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Hounsgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alaburda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0320-16.2016</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5799" to="5807" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motor unit</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Heckman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Enoka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/cphy.c100087</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Compr Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2629" to="2682" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of discharge variability in vitro and in vivo in cat visual cortex neurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Holt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Softky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Douglas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1152/jn.1996.75.5.1806</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurophysiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1806" to="1814" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transmission in the pathway of reciprocal Ia inhibition to motoneurones and its control during the tonic stretch reflex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hultborn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0079-6123(08)60736-0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog Brain Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="255" />
			<date type="published" when="1976">1976</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reciprocal innervation through interneuronal inhibition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Jankowska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Jukes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lundberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/206198a0</idno>
		<idno>doi:10.1038/ 206198a0</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">206</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="198" to="199" />
			<date type="published" when="1965">1965</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gain control mechanisms in spinal motoneurons</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Heckman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3389/fncir.2014.00081</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front Neural Circuits</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">81</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decoding the organization of spinal circuits that control locomotion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Kiehn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nrn.2016.9</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="224" to="238" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Systematic shifts in the balance of excitation and inhibition coordinate the activity of axial motor pools at different speeds of locomotion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kishore</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Bagnall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Mclean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0514-14.2014</idno>
		<idno>doi:10. 1523/JNEUROSCI.0514-14</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="14046" to="14054" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014. 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Developmental changes in rhythmic spinal neuronal activity in the rat fetus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kudo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Nishimaru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nakayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Prog Brain Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">143</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="49" to="55" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">N-methyl-D,L-aspartate-induced locomotor activity in a spinal cord-hindlimb muscles preparation of the newborn rat studied in vitro</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kudo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Yamada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/0304-3940(87)90072-3</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurosci Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">75</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="43" to="48" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fast silencing reveals a lost role for reciprocal inhibition in locomotion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Moult</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cottrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.neuron.2012.10.040</idno>
		<idno>doi:10. 1016/j.neuron.2012.10.040</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">77</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="140" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ia inhibitory interneurons and Renshaw cells as contributors to the spinal mechanisms of fictive locomotion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Pratt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Jordan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1152/jn.1987.57.1.56</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurophysiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="1987">1987</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Direction selectivity of excitation and inhibition in simple cells of the cat primary visual cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Priebe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ferster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.neuron.2004.12.024</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="145" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synaptic control of hindlimb motoneurones during three forms of the fictive scratch reflex in the turtle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Robertson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Stein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1113/jphysiol.1988.sp017281</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">404</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="128" />
			<date type="published" when="1988">1988</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the control of myotomal motoneurones during &quot;fictive swimming&quot; in the lamprey spinal cord in vitro</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Russell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wallén</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1748-1716.1983.tb07193.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Acta Physiol Scand</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="161" to="170" />
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Turning on and off recurrent balanced cortical activity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hasenstaub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Mccormick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nature01616</idno>
		<idno>doi:10.1038/ nature01616</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">423</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="288" to="293" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternation of agonists and antagonists during turtle hindlimb motor rhythms</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Stein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2010.05500.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann N Y Acad Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1198</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="118" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dual-mode operation of neuronal networks involved in left-right alternation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Talpalar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bouvier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Borgius</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Fortin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pierani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Kiehn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nature12286</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">500</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="88" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Divisive gain modulation of motoneurons by inhibition optimizes muscular control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vestergaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Berg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3899-14.2015</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3711" to="3723" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Balanced inhibition underlies tuning and sharpens spike timing in auditory cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Wehr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Zador</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nature02116</idno>
		<idno>doi:10.1038/ nature02116</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">426</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="442" to="446" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dynamics of excitation and inhibition underlying stimulus selectivity in rat somatosensory cortex</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Wilent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Contreras</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nn1545</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1364" to="1370" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">V1 and V2b interneurons secure the alternating flexor-extensor motor activity mice require for limbed locomotion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lanuza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Britz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Siembab</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Velasquez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Alvarez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Frank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Goulding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.neuron.2014.02.013</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">82</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="150" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neuronal activity in the isolated mouse spinal cord during spontaneous deletions in fictive locomotion: insights into locomotor central pattern generator organization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Zhong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Shevtsova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rybak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Harris-Warrick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1113/jphysiol.2012.240895</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Physiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">590</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4735" to="4759" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
