<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2022-05-17">17 May 2022</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Judy</forename><surname>Ozkan</surname></persName>
							<email>j.ozkan@btinternet.com</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Vera</forename><surname>Regitz-Zagrosek</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Sanne</forename><forename type="middle">A E</forename><surname>Peters</surname></persName>
							<email>sanne.peters@georgeinstitute.ox.ac.uk</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute for Gender medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Deutsches Zentrum für Herz-Kreislaufforschung</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Center Cardiovascular research</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité University medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">The George Institute for Global Health University of Oxford</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Le Gros Clark Building</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>South Parks Road Oxford</addrLine>
									<postCode>OX1 3QX</postCode>
									<country key="GB">United Kingdom</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2022-05-17">17 May 2022</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">ED3062158B89E54EE55E3D7C0EA571FA</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:13+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>There is a lot that women can do to help each other.</s><s>Becoming a generous mentor can be very potent, as can being a good boss or supervisor.</s><s>Standing up for female peers and making sure their roles in investigational work are included in publications and presentations at conferences can go some way in addressing some of the biases that exist against women.</s></p><p><s>She is frequently approached by female cardiology trainees about combining a demanding career with a family life.</s><s>Based on her own experience of being told to lower her expectations, her advice is uncompromising 'Don't start off thinking that you can't do it all simply because someone else said so.</s><s>You absolutely can if you want to.</s><s>Is it easy?</s><s>No, and sometimes other areas have to give, but that's your choice to make and all choices are good.</s><s>The key is to learn to simplify, to be focused, to be human, authentic, and ask for help when you need it -all lessons I am still learning!</s><s>Whatever you do, please don't start with a closed mind-set, or half the battle is lost'.</s></p><p><s>Sharing and airing experiences in print and online can help to raise awareness of gender inequalities, as can forming subgroups for women to connect in societies and committees.</s><s>Initiatives such as the Rosalind Franklin Fellowship in the Netherlands are a good way to promote women in science with real funding and guaranteed career opportunities.</s><s>Taking on high-profile roles and responsibilities</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>should inspire others to do the same.</s><s>Lam pays tribute to Executive Director of the Biomedical Research Council of Singapore Benjamin Seet, and Circulation editor-in-chief Joseph Hill, for bringing women into the fold.</s><s>With their leadership, Lam took on the role of Programme Lead of the Asian neTwork for Translational Research and Cardiovascular Trials (ATTRaCT) in Singapore, Associate Editor of Circulation, and host of its podcast series Circulation on the Run.</s></p><p><s>Although countries in Western Europe and the USA have woken up to gender inequalities in medicine and science, other parts of the world have not shown the same progress.</s><s>Lam has spoken about the burden of burden of cardiovascular disease moving eastwards as countries in Asia and the Indian subcontinent modernize and industrialize.</s><s>Being prepared to deal with large-scale epidemics of cardiovascular disease in the future will require a big effort on the part of these countries and more trained cardiologists-both male and female.</s><s>doi:10.1093/eurheartj/ehx221</s></p><p><s>Pregnancy and risk of cardiovascular disease: is the relationship due to childbearing or childrearing?</s></p><p><s>Pregnancy has long been considered as a risk factor for cardiovascular disease.</s><s>However, recent evidence showing similar relationships between the number of children and cardiovascular disease in men suggests that childrearing is more likely than childbearing to affect the risk of cardiovascular disease A major problem in the prevention of cardiovascular disease (CVD) is the difficulty in identifying individuals at high risk at an early enough stage for them to benefit from lifestyle modification or preventive medications.</s><s>This is especially the case for women, who, on average, develop CVD some 5-10 years later than men.</s><s>Pregnancy is a factor unique to women and it is now largely recognized that pregnancy complications, such as pre-eclampsia and diabetes are risk factors for the development of CVD or diabetes decades later. <ref type="bibr">1</ref> Furthermore, it has been suggested that the number of pregnancies or live births is associated with the risk of CVD later in life.</s><s>If causal, more intensive screening of women with multiple pregnancies could therefore support the timely identification of those at the highest risk.</s></p><p><s>To date, several studies have investigated the association between pregnancy and the risk of CVD in women. 2-5</s><s>Some studies found a Jshaped or U-shaped association between number of pregnancies and risk of CVD, with nulligravida or multigravida associated with an increased risk of coronary heart disease (CHD) and, to a lesser extent, of stroke.</s><s>Other studies, however, have not been able to replicate these findings, and findings were different in different regions of the world, which raises the discussion as to whether biological factors related to pregnancy and childbearing or socioeconomic and lifestyle factors associated with parenthood and childrearing explain the apparent associations.</s></p><p><s>A causal link between pregnancy and CVD risk is biologically plausible and supported by the profound effects of pregnancy on the maternal cardiometabolic system. <ref type="bibr">6,</ref><ref type="bibr">7</ref></s><s>Pregnancy is characterized by physiological changes that are similar to several components of the metabolic syndrome, including a relative degree of insulin resistance, accumulation of abdominal fat, hyperlipidaemia, an increase in coagulation factors, endothelial dysfunction, and increased systemic inflammation.</s><s>These metabolic changes are of benefit for the mother and infant as they support the growth of the foetus and prepare the mother's body for breastfeeding.</s><s>While the visible metabolic changes of pregnancy reverse after childbirth, epigenetic modifications induced by high-oestrogen levels could persist and repeated pregnancies may have permanent effects on the cardiovascular system that could lead to a higher risk of CVD later in life.</s></p><p><s>Alternatively, the relationship between the number of pregnancies and maternal risk of CVD in later life may be explained by socioeconomic or lifestyle factors associated with parenthood and childrearing.</s><s>Women with multiple pregnancies may have larger families and fewer financial resources or may be exposed to greater physical and mental pressures than women with fewer pregnancies (and smaller families).</s><s>Such exposures might result in poorer housing conditions, stress, reduced physical activity, and increased intake of cheaper and unhealthier foods, which, in turn, could increase their risk of CVD.</s><s>To the contrary, having children might induce a healthier lifestyle in their parents and adult children may also provide important social and material support to their parents as they age.</s></p><p><s>The relative contribution of the biological factors related to pregnancy and socioeconomic and lifestyle factors related to parenthood and childrearing is uncertain and it may be that much of the association between pregnancy and CVD is mediated by socioeconomic factors and body mass index (BMI).</s><s>Men do not get pregnant and it is difficult to imagine through what biological mechanism the number of offspring would be associated with the risk of CVD in men.</s></p><p><s>Examination of the relationship between the number of children and the risk of CVD in men is therefore a useful method to address the limitations of studies in women, especially when combined with simultaneous examination in women from the same study.</s></p><p><s>Few studies have assessed the relationship between the number of children and the risk of CVD, and diabetes, in both women and men.</s><s>We recently assessed this relationship in the China Kadoorie Biobank, a prospective cohort study of 500 000 men and women recruited from 10 diverse regions in China. <ref type="bibr">8,</ref><ref type="bibr">9</ref></s><s>There have been striking intergenerational changes in family size in China, due partly to the rapid socio-economic developments occurring in China and partly to introduction of the one-child per family policy in the late 1970s which set strict regulations regarding family size.</s></p><p><s>Compared with older generations, individuals born in more recent decades tend to have fewer children, and, particularly in urban areas, increased mean age at first birth.</s><s>Despite this, there are still large parts of the population with more than 1 child.</s><s>Our analyses demonstrated that the association between the number of children and the risk of diabetes, stroke, and CHD was largely identical between women and men (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>Compared to those with one child, the risk of these outcomes was higher in those without children and in those with multiple children.</s></p><p><s>Among those with children, each additional child was associated with a small (3-5%) but significant increase in the risk of CHD, stroke, and diabetes.</s><s>These findings suggest that not only biological factors related to pregnancy and childbearing but also social, cultural, or psychological factors related to parenthood and childbearing may be important contributors to the link between repeated pregnancy and CVD risk.</s><s>The increased risk of CVD in women and men without children could be the result of health behaviours or health conditions related to infertility that also might increase the risk of CVD.</s></p><p><s>Alternatively, these individuals may receive limited social or economic support otherwise, in many parts of the world, provided by adult children.</s><s>Individuals with a limited number of children may be best situated in terms of long-term benefits for CVD, because personal resources may be less likely to be depleted, and adequate support from their children may still be received.</s><s>Support in achieving and maintaining healthy lifestyle and dietary habits might help in reducing the risk of diabetes and CVD seen in those with larger families.</s></p><p><s>Thus, while pregnancy per se may not be causally linked to CVD, women with a history of pregnancy complications appear to be at increased risk of metabolic and vascular diseases in later life. 1 Gestational diabetes complicates an estimated 5-10% of all pregnancies and is associated with a seven-fold higher risk of diabetes in later life.</s><s>Women diagnosed with pre-eclampsia, which is estimated to affect 3-5% of pregnancies, are at increased a doubled risk of future cardiovascular events compared to unaffected women.</s></p><p><s>Hence, the onset of pregnancy-associated complications can temporarily unmask the vulnerability of the maternal cardiovascular system and provides a major opportunity for more intensive screening to prevent or delay the re-emergence of CVD in later life.</s><s>However, awareness of the implications that adverse pregnancy outcomes have for a woman's future cardiometabolic health is limited.</s><s>At present, care for women with a history of pregnancy complications tends to stop shortly after delivery, may recommence in a subsequent pregnancy, but does not continue during the life-course.</s><s>Integration of maternal and child health care services with those that identify and manage women at high risk of CVD could help to reduce the burden of CVD for the maximum number of women possible. <ref type="bibr">10</ref></s><s>ore systematic collection and analyses of reproductive history, pregnancy complications, and family size, together with data on hor-monal status, sexual function and hormone therapies, and long-term follow-up for the onset of CVD is required to strengthen the evidence needed to inform a life-course approach to the prevention of CVD in both men and women.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure1Adjusted hazard ratios (HRs) and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) for incident coronary heart disease associated with number of children.</s><s>Analyses are stratified by age at risk and study area, and adjusted for level of attained education, household income, smoking status, alcohol use, systolic blood pressure, history of hypertension, physical activity, body mass index, and history of diabetes.</s><s>The HRs are plotted on a floating absolute scale.</s><s>Each square (solid for women and blank for men) has an area inversely proportional to the standard error of the log risk.</s><s>Vertical lines indicate the corresponding 95% CIs.</s><s>Data were obtained from Ref. 9.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,64.18,75.80,207.95,199.11" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/eurheartj/article/38/19/1448/3823351 by guest on 17 May 2022</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>'It has always been thought that peripartum cardiomyopathy (PPCM) was much more common and severe in Africans and that it was a disease of poverty but our study clearly shows that it's not', said lead author Professor Karen Sliwa, director of the Hatter Institute for Cardiovascular Research in Africa, Cape Town, South Africa.</s><s>Cases were reported from many countries for the first time.</s><s>The study was conducted by the Heart Failure Association (HFA) of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) Study Group on PPCM under the EURObservational Research Programme (EORP).</s></p><p><s>PPCM occurs in women either at the end of pregnancy or up to 5 months after giving birth.</s><s>Patients were previously healthy and then present with shortness of breath and heart failure.</s><s>In about one-third of women with PPCM the cardiac muscle spontaneously recovers, but about 10% die from the disease and over half have a weakened myocardium for the remainder of their lives.</s><s>The baby is sometimes born smaller and premature and in rare cases dies.</s></p><p><s>Research has shown that women with PPCM produce an abnormal breastfeeding hormone that leads to apoptosis and damage to the cardiac myocytes.</s></p><p><s>There is very little known about PPCM and until recently it was assumed that it occurred predominantly in African women.</s><s>This registry study was conducted to find out whether PPCM occurs in other continents.</s><s>Specifically, the researchers set out to discover how the disease presents, is diagnosed, and treated in different countries.</s></p><p><s>The paper reports the baseline results of 411 patients from 43 countries representing all continents.</s><s>Data collected included demographic characteristics, co-morbidities, treatments, type of hospital, and specialization of the treating physician.</s></p><p><s>The researchers found cases of PPCM in all 43 countries studied.</s><s>All women with PPCM presented at the same age, and with the same symptoms and heart size, despite different ethnic backgrounds and huge disparities in socioeconomic factors and access to healthcare.</s><s>'The disease presented quite uniformly despite occurring globally in different ethnic groups and in very different healthcare systems', she continued.</s><s>'This tells us that PPCM is to some extent a biological disease and women may have a genetic predisposition, which is probably a cellular and cardiac signalling abnormality.</s><s>This is not a disease with marked differences between ethnic groups'.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
