<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Investigating Category-and Shape-Selective Neural Processing in Ventral and Dorsal Visual Stream Under Interocular Suppression</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014-10-01">1 October 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Karin</forename><surname>Ludwig</surname></persName>
							<email>karin.ludwig@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Visual Perception Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Charit</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Humboldt-Universit€ at zu Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Norbert</forename><surname>Kathmann</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Humboldt-Universit€ at zu Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Philipp</forename><surname>Sterzer</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Visual Perception Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Charit</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Guido</forename><surname>Hesselmann</surname></persName>
							<email>guido.hesselmann@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Visual Perception Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Charit</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<address>
									<settlement>Mitte, Charit e -Universit€ atsmedizin Berlin, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Visual Perception Laboratory</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Charit</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charit eplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Mitte, Charit e -Universit€ atsmedizin Berlin, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Visual Perception Laboratory</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">or Guido Hes-selmann</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Campus Charit</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charit eplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Mitte, Charit e -Universit€ ats-medizin Berlin, Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Investigating Category-and Shape-Selective Neural Processing in Ventral and Dorsal Visual Stream Under Interocular Suppression</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2014-10-01">1 October 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A55EBC181BBEFCA162801C135B191762</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1002/hbm.22618</idno>
					<note type="submission">Revised 18 August 2014; Accepted 19 August 2014.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:14+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>continuous flash suppression</term>
					<term>dual-stream model</term>
					<term>consciousness</term>
					<term>functional magnetic resonance imaging</term>
					<term>multivariate pattern analysis r r Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes (German National Academic Foundation</term>
					<term>to K.L.)</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Recent behavioral and neuroimaging studies using continuous flash suppression (CFS) have suggested that action-related processing in the dorsal visual stream might be independent of perceptual awareness, in line with the "vision-for-perception" versus "vision-for-action" distinction of the influential dual-stream theory.</s><s>It remains controversial if evidence suggesting exclusive dorsal stream processing of tool stimuli under CFS can be explained by their elongated shape alone or by actionrelevant category representations in dorsal visual cortex.</s><s>To approach this question, we investigated category-and shape-selective functional magnetic resonance imaging-blood-oxygen level-dependent responses in both visual streams using images of faces and tools.</s><s>Multivariate pattern analysis showed enhanced decoding of elongated relative to non-elongated tools, both in the ventral and dorsal visual stream.</s><s>The second aim of our study was to investigate whether the depth of interocular suppression might differentially affect processing in dorsal and ventral areas.</s><s>However, parametric modulation of suppression depth by varying the CFS mask contrast did not yield any evidence for differential modulation of category-selective activity.</s><s>Together, our data provide evidence for shape-selective processing under CFS in both dorsal and ventral stream areas and, therefore, do not support the notion that dorsal "vision-for-action" processing is exclusively preserved under interocular suppression.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p><s>A widely accepted and influential theory in cognitive neuroscience concerns the functional specialization of the primate visual system into a dorsal "vision-for-action" and a ventral "vision-for-perception" stream <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[Milner and Goodale, 1995]</ref>.</s><s>A core component of the dual-stream theory is the hypothesis that ventral stream processes are closely associated with conscious perception, whereas processing in the dorsal stream can occur without giving rise to awareness <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[Milner, 2012]</ref>.</s><s>To a large degree, the theory is based on neuropsychological data from patients with relatively circumscribed brain lesions in either visual stream, for example, patient DF who exhibits some intact visuomotor behaviors despite suffering from visual form agnosia due to ventral stream lesions <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[Goodale et al., 1991;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">James et al., 2003]</ref>.</s><s>Attempts to test the dual-stream theory in neurologically healthy observers have mainly focused on the differential effects of visual illusions on perception and action, but the results have remained controversial <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[Franz and Gegenfurtner, 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b42">Westwood and Goodale, 2011]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Recently, a series of behavioral and functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) studies using continuous flash suppression (CFS) in normal observers have provided new evidence suggesting that dorsal stream processing might in fact be independent of awareness.</s><s>CFS is a powerful method of interocular suppression which can eliminate monocularly presented stimuli from conscious perception for up to seconds by presenting dynamic masks to the other eye <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[Tsuchiya and Koch, 2005</ref>; for a variant see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Bahrami et al., 2007]</ref>.</s><s>Visual priming experiments showed that the presentation of tools which were rendered invisible by CFS facilitated the recognition of visible tool images, while this effect was absent for other stimulus categories <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[Almeida et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Almeida et al., 2008]</ref>.</s><s>Interestingly, when backward masking was used to suppress stimuli from awareness, priming was not restricted to tools but was also found within other categories.</s><s>In line with the dual-stream theory, it was proposed that dorsal stream areas may form action-relevant representations for manmade manipulable objects (tools), even in the absence of awareness during CFS, while there are no such representations in ventral visual areas.</s><s>More recent results, however, cast doubt on this scenario.</s><s>In similar priming experiments, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Sakuraba et al. [2012]</ref> observed tool priming whenever elongated stimuli including simple geometric lines were used as primes, but not when non-elongated stimuli were used, suggesting that priming effects under CFS can be fully explained by stimulus shape alone and not by action-relevance of stimuli.</s></p><p><s>In this study, therefore, we sought to investigate whether neural activity in the dorsal "vision-for-action" stream in response to images of tools is due to their close association with visually guided action or rather to their specific elongated shape.</s><s>As a first step to answer this question, we compared blood-oxygen-level dependent (BOLD) responses to visible and invisible tools that were clearly manipulable, but not elongated, to activation to tools with an elongated shape, using both univariate and multivariate measures.</s></p><p><s>The second aim of our study was to contribute to the understanding of the CFS method per se and its neural underpinnings, respectively.</s><s>Neuroimaging studies using CFS have already produced an extensive but heterogeneous body of data on the scope and limits of processing under interocular suppression [for recent reviews: <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Hesselmann, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">Sterzer et al., 2014]</ref>.</s><s>Specifically, discrepant results were reported with respect to activity in both visual streams.</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Fang and He [2005]</ref> found that, in comparison to the ventral stream, activity in the dorsal stream was much less reduced in amplitude relative to visible stimuli.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Hesselmann and Malach [2011]</ref>, however, observed a stream-invariant reduction of activity whenever stimuli were rendered invisible by CFS [also see <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">Fogelson et al., 2014]</ref>.</s><s>Here, we hypothesized that depth of interocular suppression would be a candidate factor susceptible to reconcile both previous findings.</s><s>Based on psychophysical and fMRI data suggesting that suppression strength varies with CFS mask contrast <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[Dubois et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b26">Ledgeway et al., 2013]</ref>, we expected to replicate Fang and He's findings with weak interocular suppression (low-contrast CFS masks), and Hesselmann and Malach's results with strong suppression (high-contrast CFS masks).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MATERIAL AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participants</head><p><s>All 26 participants had normal or corrected-to-normal vision, were na€ ıve to the purpose of the study, and were paid for participation.</s><s>Procedures conformed to local ethics guidelines and all observers gave informed written consent.</s><s>The data of five participants had to be excluded (one due to excessive movement in the scanner, two had a 2AFC performance of &gt;60% in the "invisible" condition, two because stimuli could not be rendered invisible despite low contrast).</s><s>All remaining 21 participants (17 female) were right-handed according to their own statement.</s><s>Their mean age was 23 years (range 18 to 32).</s><s>As tested with the hole-in-card test (a modified version of the original ABC test, <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Miles, 1930)</ref>, 15 of the participants were right eye dominant.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Apparatus and Setup</head><p><s>During the psychophysical pretest the observers were seated in a dark environment, the only light coming from the experimental monitor and a second monitor, and viewed the dichoptic images on a 19" CRT screen with a spatial resolution of 1280 3 960 pixels and a refresh rate of 60 Hz, via a mirror stereoscope that prevented all crosstalk between the eyes.</s><s>To stabilize head position, the participants placed their heads on a chinrest.</s><s>The viewing distance from the eyes to the screen (including distances within the mirror system) was 66 cm, resulting in each pixel subtending approximately 0.024 of visual angle.</s></p><p><s>In the scanner, the stimuli were presented via a Sanyo LCD projector at 60 Hz that projected from the head-end of the scanner onto an opal glass projection screen.</s><s>The participant viewed the stimuli via a mirror fixed onto the head coil while wearing prism glasses.</s><s>Together with these glasses, a cardboard divider that was installed between glass pane and mirror ensured dichoptic stimulation and prevented crosstalk <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[Schurger, 2009]</ref>.</s><s>The viewing distance from the eyes to the screen (including distances within the mirror system) was 68 cm, resulting in each pixel subtending approximately 0.022 of visual angle.</s></p><p><s>Visual stimuli were generated with MATLAB 7.9.0 (MathWorks, Natick, MA) and the Psychophysics Toolbox 3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[Brainard, 1997;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">Pelli, 1997]</ref> and displayed via IBMcompatible computers.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stimuli</head><p><s>The stimuli consisted of gray scale images of tools (elongated and non-elongated) and faces (Supporting Information Figure <ref type="figure">S1</ref>).</s><s>They were adjusted so that the stimulus area (as compared to background area) was the same for all tools (9%), irrespective of elongation, and all faces (17%).</s><s>They were low-pass filtered with a 2D-Gaussian filter with a standard deviation of 30 pixels.</s><s>The low-level image properties (luminance histograms and rotational average of the Fourier spectra) were matched across all exemplars (of all categories) using the SHINE toolbox <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[Willenbockel et al., 2010]</ref>.</s><s>All elongated tool stimuli had a width/length ratio smaller than 0.4, while all non-elongated tool stimuli had a width/length ratio larger than 0.4 (width orthogonal to the longest extension).</s><s>Note that highly similar ratios can be found for the tool stimuli used in the studies by <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Sakuraba et al. [2012]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Almeida et al. [2013]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Interocular Masking</head><p><s>We used an interocular suppression paradigm <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">[Tsuchiya and Koch, 2005]</ref> called CFS.</s><s>This technique uses highcontrast images flashed to one eye to suppress images presented to the other eye from awareness.</s><s>The images consisted of rectangles of five gray levels (ranging from black to white) and sizes ranging from 4 to 18% of the size of the CFS area, which measured 5.1 (pretest) or 4.8 (scanner), respectively.</s><s>The rectangles were positioned at random locations and at different random angles (0 and multiples of 7 ) on the mask image.</s><s>We used different angles of orientation for the CFS rectangles to ensure strong suppression for stimuli of various orientations, as suppression is strongest if mask and stimulus are alike in certain features <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[Yang and Blake, 2012]</ref>.</s><s>Hundreds of these images were produced and flashed in random order at 10 Hz to the dominant eye.</s><s>This rendered the stimulus presented to the non-dominant eye largely invisible.</s><s>The masks were presented on and off together with the stimulus presentation (see method section "Main experiment").</s><s>To promote stable binocular fusion during dichoptic presentation, a blackand-white square frame was presented around the stimuli.</s><s>Its outer and inner dimensions in the pretest were 6.1 and 5.1 of visual angle, respectively, and in the scanner 5.7 and 4.8 , respectively.</s><s>The stimulus images took up the same space.</s><s>In the main experiment, we varied the contrast of the CFS masks; the Michelson contrast was either 0.49, 0.70, or 0.95, in the pretest the contrast was 0.70.</s></p><p><s>While aiming at different suppression levels that would be reflected in the neuronal data, it was important that the stimuli suppressed by the different masks would be judged similarly concerning their visibility as the trials judged as visible were discarded from the analysis.</s><s>In a more sensitive control experiment (see method section "Control Experiment"), we further established the different suppression strengths of the CFS masks.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Procedure</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pretest</head><p><s>A few days before the main experiment, the participants completed a pretest in which the stimulus contrast for the main experiment was determined.</s><s>After a stimulus presentation that conformed to that of the main experiment (see method section "Main experiment"), the participant had to press a key according to whether the stimulus (tool or face) had been visible or not.</s><s>Based on this response, the stimulus contrast was decreased or increased following a logarithmic scale in the next trial (1-up-1-down staircase).</s><s>The stimuli were always masked with the medium CFS mask, and each participant completed two staircases of 20 trials for each of the stimulus categories (faces, non-elongated and elongated tools).</s><s>The stimulus contrast in the main experiment was set to the highest stimulus contrast that the participant always judged as invisible in the pretest.</s><s>The contrast of faces and tools was adjusted separately.</s><s>This individual adjustment of contrasts ensured maximal stimulus strength even under full suppression.</s><s>The resulting average Michelson contrasts were 0.124 for faces and 0.263 for tools (for individual contrasts see Supporting Information Figure <ref type="figure">S2</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Main experiment</head><p><s>In each trial, all 10 images of one stimulus category were shown in random order to the non-dominant eye while the CFS masks were shown to the dominant eye (at 10 Hz and only when a stimulus was shown).</s><s>Each image was shown for 200 ms followed by a 300 ms blank.</s><s>After this 5 s stimulation and a blank screen (1 s), the participants were presented with two questions that they had to answer via button press.</s><s>First, they were asked what they r Neural Visual Processing Under CFS r r 139 r thought had been presented (1: face, 2: tool) and had 2.5 s to answer during which the response options stayed on the screen.</s><s>On button press, the selected option slightly changed its color so that the participants knew that their answer had been recorded.</s><s>The second question concerned the subjective visibility of the stimulus.</s><s>The observers had to choose one of the following options during another 2.5 sinterval: 1 5 "No experience," 2 5 "Weak glimpse," 3 5 "Almost clear," and 4 5 "Absolutely clear."</s><s>This was a short version of the 4-point perceptual awareness scale (PAS) to which the participants were introduced during the instruction <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[Ramsoy and Overgaard, 2004]</ref>.</s><s>The next trial started after a blank screen of 1-5 s (drawn from a uniform distribution).</s><s>The paradigm is depicted in Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Each of the six runs contained 38 trials: in 16 of the trials faces were presented, in another 16 trials tools were presented (8 elongated, 8 non-elongated), in the remaining six trials there was no stimulus.</s><s>The stimuli were either suppressed (mask levels 0.95, 0.70, and 0.49, 10 trials each) or fully visible (mask level 0, 8 trials).</s><s>There were no trials with mask level 0 and no stimulus.</s><s>The total duration of the six fMRI runs was approximately 53 min.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Localizer experiment</head><p><s>In the localizer experiment, the stimuli were presented at maximum contrast (Michelson: 0.847) for 10 s, alternating between nine exemplars of one category: elongated and nonelongated tools, faces, and houses (not used for analysis).</s><s>Within one miniblock, each exemplar was shown for 800 ms and the exemplars were shown in randomized order with interstimulus intervals of 200 ms.</s><s>Between these miniblocks was always a pause of 6 s in which only the blank fusion frame was shown.</s><s>There were eight miniblocks per category, the order of which was also randomized.</s><s>To ensure participants' attention to the stimuli, one of the exemplars was repeated in two consecutive presentations to which the participants had to respond by pressing a button.</s><s>The total duration of the localizer experiment was just under 9 min.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>FMRI Acquisition</head><p><s>BOLD images were acquired by T2*-weighted gradientecho echo-planar imaging (field of view (FOV) 192 mm 3 192 mm, 33 slices, repetition time (TR) 2000 ms, echo time (TE) 30 ms, flip angle 78 , voxel size 3 3 3 3 3 mm, interslice gap 10%) on a 3T MRI scanner <ref type="bibr">(Tim Trio, Siemens, Erlangen)</ref>.</s><s>Two hundred and seventy three volumes were recorded for each of the six experimental runs, and 257 images for the localizer run.</s><s>Anatomical images were acquired using a T1-weighted MPRAGE sequence (FOV 256 mm 3 256 mm 3 192 mm, 160 slices, TR 1900 ms, TE 2.52 ms, flip angle 9 , voxel size 1 3 1 3 1 mm).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>FMRI Data Analysis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Preprocessing</head><p><s>The images were preprocessed using statistical parametric mapping (SPM8, http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm/</s><s>Continuous flash suppression (CFS) paradigm.</s><s>On each trial, participants viewed 10 exemplars of a given stimulus category (tools or faces).</s><s>Tools were either elongated or non-elongated.</s><s>Exemplars were presented to the non-dominant eye for 200 ms followed by a 300-ms blank.</s><s>Dynamic masks were presented to the dominant eye to render stimuli invisible.</s><s>After each trial, participants had to indicate whether tools or faces had been presented (2AFC) and report subjective stimulus visibility using the 4-point perceptual awareness scale (PAS).</s></p><p><s>software/spm8/) with the following steps: standard realignment, coregistration, normalization to MNI stereotactic space using unified segmentation <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[Ashburner and Friston, 2005]</ref>, and spatial smoothing with 8 and 10 mm full-width at half-maximum isotropic Gaussian kernels for single-subject and group analyses, respectively.</s><s>The images for the multivariate pattern analysis underwent the same steps except for normalization and smoothing.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exclusion criteria for participants and trials</head><p><s>Only participants with less than 60% performance in the 2AFC objective task (face versus tool) when rating the stimulus as completely invisible (PAS 5 1) in the invisible condition were included in the analysis.</s><s>For the remaining participants, we followed the following strategy.</s><s>If their objective task performance was below 55% even when including PAS ratings of 2 (weak glimpse: "something was seen, but content unclear"), trials with PAS ratings of 2 were included.</s><s>This strategy maximized the number of trials and was applied to 13 participants.</s><s>If performance exceeded 55%, only trials with a PAS rating of 1 were included in the analyses of the invisible condition (N 5 8).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>General linear model</head><p><s>Using a general linear model (GLM) approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[Friston et al., 1994]</ref> with a mixed event-related and block design, the 5 s intervals of stimulus presentation were modeled using a boxcar function convolved with the canonical hemodynamic responses function (HRF) implemented in SPM8.</s></p><p><s>In the main experiment, the first GLM for the analysis of elongated versus non-elongated tools included nine regressors: "visible elongated tools", "invisible elongated tools", "visible non-elongated tools", "invisible non-elongated tools", "visible faces", "invisible faces", "CFS masks only", "trials judged visible in "invisible" condition", and "response screens".</s><s>The second GLM for the analysis of faces versus tools included seven regressors: "visible tools", "invisible tools", "visible faces", "invisible faces", "CFS masks only", "trials judged visible in "invisible" condition", and "response screens".</s><s>The third GLM for the analysis of the effects of suppression strength included 13 regressors: "visible tools", "invisible tools" (33: mask contrast 0.49, 0.70, and 0.95), "visible faces", "invisible faces" (33: mask contrast 0.49, 0.70, and 0.95), "CFS masks only" (33: mask contrast 0.49, 0.70, and 0.95), "trials judged visible in "invisible" condition", and "response screens".</s><s>The localizer experiment was analyzed using four regressors: "elongated tools", "non-elongated tools", "faces", and "houses".</s></p><p><s>In both experiments, the design matrix included the first derivative of the canonical HRF and six rigid-body realignment parameters as nuisance covariates.</s><s>After high-pass filtering at 1/128 Hz, we estimated single-subject statistical parametric maps, then created contrast images, and entered these into one-sample t-tests at the group level.</s></p><p><s>The dorsal and ventral regions of interest (ROIs) were identified as follows: We mapped the group-level contrasts "tools &gt; faces" and "faces &gt; tools" from the localizer experiment, respectively, at P &lt; 0.001, uncorrected, and defined search spheres of 10 mm radius around local cluster peaks with the highest t-values in left and right parietal cortex <ref type="bibr">([227 276 34]</ref>  <ref type="table">and [27 279 37], t(20) 5 5</ref>.54; t(20) 5 6.92) and the right fusiform face area, FFA <ref type="bibr">([42 252 220]</ref>, t(20) 5 4.99).</s><s>We refer to the parietal ROIs as left and right V3A/V7, following previous work <ref type="bibr">[Hesselmann and Malach, 2011]</ref>.</s><s>Note that these regions were not the only clusters in this map (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>) but were selected based on a priori knowledge from previous studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[Fang and He, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hesselmann and Malach, 2011]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Individually for each participant, we then created three ROIs for the univariate analysis by selecting a 2 mm radius sphere around the peak voxel within the corresponding group-level search spheres for the same contrast at the single-subject level.</s><s>This procedure resulted in ROIs containing the peak voxel and directly neighboring voxels.</s><s>A larger ROI containing all active voxels (same contrast at single subject level) within the group-level search spheres was also created separately for each participant.</s><s>We adjusted the threshold so that the ROI contained on average 48 voxels.</s><s>However, as we found larger category selectivity in the peak voxel ROIs, we report the results from those ROIs.</s><s>The peak voxel ROI coordinates are provided in Supporting Information Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>.</s><s>Parameter estimates were calculated using the MarsBaR Toolbox 0.42 (http://marsbar.sourceforge.net/),</s><s>averaged across all ROI voxels.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Multivariate pattern analysis</head><p><s>The spherical ROIs defined at the group-level for the univariate analysis were also used for the MVPA.</s><s>For this purpose, they were retransformed into the native space of each participant.</s><s>The number of voxels included in each of these ROIs was variable between participants due to this retransformation, as shown in Supporting Information Table <ref type="table">S2</ref>.</s><s>All voxels within these ROIs were selected for MVPA, which was conducted using a standard linear support vector machine as implemented by LIBSVM <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[Chang and Lin, 2011]</ref> with a cost parameter of c 5 1 in the framework of "The Decoding Toolbox" <ref type="bibr">[G€ orgen et al., 2012]</ref>.</s><s>GLMs were recalculated on unnormalized and unsmoothed data.</s><s>The prediction accuracies (face versus tool) were calculated for each participant and ROI using a leave-one-run-out cross-validation approach.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dependent Variables and Data Analysis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Behavioral analysis</head><p><s>For the subjective visibility report, the frequency of each PAS rating was counted for each participant and then averaged, separately for each mask contrast.</s><s>The result is displayed in Figure <ref type="figure">3A</ref>.</s><s>The objective 2AFC performances were compared to chance performance (50%) using a twosided t-test.</s><s>As a nonsignificant t-test result is no evidence for the null hypothesis, we further conducted a Bayes analysis.</s><s>This analysis provides the likelihood of the data given the null hypothesis and the likelihood of the data given the alternative hypothesis as well as their quotientthe Bayes factor (BF)-as an output.</s><s>In contrast to null hypothesis testing, one needs to formulate the alternative hypothesis mathematically to be able to test it against the null hypothesis.</s><s>In our case, the alternative hypothesis is that the participants had some impression of the stimulus and were thus above chance.</s><s>Hence, we formulated the alternative hypothesis as a normal distribution with a mean of 63.51% (i.e., the average performance in the 2AFC task for trials in which the participants indicated degraded perception of the stimulus, PAS 5 2) and a standard deviation of 23.8%.</s><s>The BF was calculated using a freely available online Bayes calculator (www.lifesci.sussex.ac.</s><s>uk/home/Zoltan_Dienes/inference/bayes_factor.swf),</s><s>provided by <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Dienes [2011]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Univariate fMRI analysis</head><p><s>In all univariate analyses, the dependent variables were the ROI parameter estimates.</s><s>In all univariate analyses of the invisible condition, we subtracted mask activation from the joint activation of mask and stimulus.</s><s>To test for selective activation for faces and tools in the ventral and dorsal ROIs we used a two-way repeated measures (rm-) ANOVA with the factors category (face/tool) and ROI (ventral/dorsal).</s><s>To test for preferential processing of elongated stimuli in the dorsal ROIs, a two-way rm-ANOVA with the factors shape (elongated/non-elongated) and visibility (visible/invisible) was used.</s><s>For completeness, the same analysis was carried out for the ventral ROI.</s><s>To answer the question whether invisible tools were processed in the dorsal stream, a three-way rm-ANOVA with</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Multivariate fMRI analyses</head><p><s>To test whether invisible tools were processed in the dorsal stream, we also used a multivariate approach.</s><s>The dependent variables were the decoding accuracies and for statistical testing a permutation test was used, as t-tests on decoding accuracies have been shown to be inappropriate <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[Schreiber and Krekelberg, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">Stelzer et al., 2013]</ref>.</s><s>In a first step, the labels/classes were shuffled in all possible permutations, and then the decoding was carried out as for the original labels, which yielded 32 accuracies for each participant.</s><s>For the group statistic, the permutations were combined with a boot-strapping procedure: 100,000 times one of the 32 values was drawn for each participant and then averaged over participants.</s><s>These values then constituted the test distribution under the null hypothesis.</s><s>The number of boot-strapped values that were higher than the actual accuracy divided by the number of all values yielded the P-value (e.g., P 5 400/100,000 5 0.004).</s><s>An example of these test distributions for one of the tests is shown in Supporting Information Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S5</ref>.</s><s>To test for preferential processing of elongated stimuli, decoding accuracies were submitted to a two-way rm-ANOVA with the factors shape and visibility.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control Experiment</head><p><s>The control experiment was conducted to establish different levels of suppression strength for the different mask contrasts.</s><s>Thirty-one (23 female) participants took part in this control experiment.</s><s>All had normal or corrected-tonormal vision, were na€ ıve to the purpose of the study, and were paid for participation.</s><s>Procedures conformed to local ethics guidelines and all observers gave informed written consent.</s><s>All participants were right-handed according to their own statement.</s><s>Their mean age was 22 years (range 18-29).</s><s>As tested with the hole-in-card test (a modified version of the original ABC test; <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">Miles, 1930)</ref>, 23 of the participants were right eye dominant.</s><s>Sixteen of the participants also participated in the main experiment and pretest.</s></p><p><s>The settings of the control experiment were as described for the main experiment and pretest.</s><s>The experiment's procedure was adapted from <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Tsuchiya et al. [2006]</ref>.</s><s>After initiating the trial by button press, a horizontal sinusoidal grating (Michelson contrast 0.10) was presented to the participant's non-dominant eye while CFS masks were presented to the dominant eye.</s><s>CFS masks were the same as in the main experiment and pretest.</s><s>Subsequently, they confirmed by button press that they only saw the CFS masks, which initiated a contrast change of the upper or the lower half of the grating.</s><s>The contrast increased for 250 ms and then decreased for 250 ms, initially to full con-trast (Michelson: 0.95), following a Gaussian distribution with a standard deviation of 100 ms.</s><s>After the contrast change, a beep was presented and the participants had to indicate if the contrast change had occurred in the upper or the lower half of the presentation area (2AFC).</s><s>When the participants gave two correct responses in a row, the maximum of the contrast change was decreased by 20%, after an erroneous response it was increased by 20%.</s><s>This step was reduced to 610% after four reversals.</s><s>After 12 reversals, the staircase finished and the geometric mean of the last 10 reversals yielded the contrast detection threshold (71% as measured by a 2 down-1 up staircase procedure <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[Levitt, 1971]</ref>).</s><s>A difference to the main experiment and pretest were the specifics of the fusion frame which were also adapted from <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">Tsuchiya et al. [2006]</ref>.</s><s>It consisted of one row of black and white squares surrounding the presented stimuli and masks.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Behavioral Results</head><p><s>Figure <ref type="figure">3A</ref> shows that the different mask contrasts led to similar levels of subjective invisibility, with most trials being rated as eliciting no visual experience (PAS 5 1) or a weak glimpse (PAS 5 2), leading to our aspired result, namely that approximately the same number of trials for each mask contrast entered into our analyses.</s><s>In the condition without interocular masking, most stimuli were rated as almost clearly (PAS 5 3) or absolutely clearly visible (PAS 5 4).</s><s>Under the exclusion criteria described in the "Exclusion criteria for participants and trials" section, the participants had an average performance of 51.21% in the objective 2AFC task (Fig. <ref type="figure">3B</ref>).</s><s>This performance did not differ significantly from chance in the t-test (t(20)5 1.63, P 5 0.119).</s><s>The Bayes analysis yielded a BF of 0.10, that is, substantial evidence for the null hypothesis of chance performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[Dienes, 2011]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control Experiment</head><p><s>The control experiment revealed a significant influence of mask contrast on contrast detection thresholds (F(2,60) 5 3.48, P 5 0.037; Supporting Information Figure <ref type="figure">S3</ref>).</s><s>Post hoc t-tests showed that this was mainly due to a difference between the medium and the highest contrast levels (t(30) 5 22.63, P 5 0.013).</s><s>The differences between the lowest and the medium mask contrast, and between the lowest and the highest mask contrast were not significant (t(30) 5 1.24, P 5 0.223; t(30) 5 21.40, P 5 0.173).</s><s>Hence, interpretations about the effect of mask contrast on neural processing should focus on the difference between the conditions of medium and high contrast.</s><s>For completeness, however, all results are plotted and discussed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Univariate fMRI Results</head><p><s>We first verified the validity of the ventral and dorsal ROIs by testing for category-selective responses to visible stimuli in the main experiment, that is, when stimuli were not masked by CFS.</s><s>The results are shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">4</ref>. We found larger activations to faces in the FFA, and to tools in V3A/V7 (interaction category*ROI: F(1,20) 5 41.20, P &lt; 0.001).</s><s>Of the main effects of the rm-ANOVA, only the effect of category turned out to be significant (category: F(1,20) 5 9.95, P &lt; 0.005; ROI: F(1,20) 5 2.78, P 5 0.111).</s><s>The FFA also responded to tool stimuli, albeit significantly weaker than to face stimuli (t(20) 5 2.38, P 5 0.027).</s><s>This is in line with previous findings concerning the fusiform gyrus <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[Chao and Martin, 2000]</ref>.</s><s>In V3A/V7, the response to tools was significantly stronger than to faces (t(20) 5 6.07, P &lt; 0.001).</s><s>Visually, the same pattern emerged for stimuli that were visible because they broke through suppression (PAS ratings &gt; 1).</s><s>Here, the interaction did not reach significance (interaction category*ROI: F(1,20) 5 1.35, P 5 0.260; category: F(1,20) &lt; 1, P 5 0.943; ROI: F(1,20) 5 9.82, P &lt; 0.006).</s></p><p><s>Next, we addressed the question whether dorsal processing of tools depends merely on their (mostly elongated) shape attributes (i.e., whether elongated tools elicited higher activation than non-elongated tools) or whether it reflects genuine activation to tools due to their connection to visually guided action, irrespective of shape (i.e., whether activation to elongated and non-elongated tools was similar).</s><s>For this purpose, we compared the activation in the dorsal ROIs to elongated tools with activation to non-elongated but clearly manipulable tools, both in the visible and invisible condition.</s><s>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">5</ref> shows that there was no significant effect of shape (F(1,20) 5 2.85, P 5 0.107), supporting the notion of genuine tool selectivity in dorsal areas.</s><s>In the remaining analyses, therefore, elongated and non-elongated tools were analyzed together.</s><s>There was, however, a significant effect of visibility: when the tools were rendered invisible with CFS, activation levels decreased, again irrespective of shape (effect visibility: F(1,20) 5 9.28, P &lt; 0.007; interaction shape*visibility: F(1,20) 5 2.47, P 5 0.132).</s><s>In the ventral ROI, we found a significant interaction of shape and visibility, because in the visible condition non-elongated tools yielded higher activation than elongated tools, while activation levels were similar in the invisible condition (F(1,20) 5 4.60, P 5 0.044; t(20) 5 2.61, P 5 0.017).</s></p><p><s>The latter finding of reduced BOLD responses under invisibility was confirmed in a further analysis in which we looked at a possible dissociation between the ventral and dorsal stream concerning the processing of stimuli that did not enter awareness (Supporting Information Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">S4</ref>).</s><s>Both invisible tools and faces led to significantly reduced activation relative to visible stimuli in their respective ROI (effect visibility: F(1,20) 5 6.36, P 5 0.020), and this reduction turned out to be stream-invariant (interaction ROI*visibility: F(1,20) &lt; 1, P 5 0.415; see Supporting Information Table <ref type="table">S3</ref> for a full summary of the effects).</s><s>Faces, even when visible, did not show robust activation in dorsal ROIs, hence there was also no observable decrease due to invisibility.</s><s>This is reflected in a significant three-way interaction (category*ROI*visibility: F(1,20) 5 47.46, P &lt; 0.001).</s><s>A highly similar reduction from the visible to the invisible condition was obtained with larger ROIs (see method section "General linear model").</s></p><p><s>Finally, we tested the hypothesis that dorsal processing of invisible stimuli is spared when the contrast of the  mask is low, thus yielding a lower suppression level relative to CFS masks of higher contrast.</s><s>BOLD responses to invisible stimuli were analyzed with respect to stimulus category, ROI, and mask contrast.</s><s>Note that for this analysis only 18 of 21 participants who had at least two trials for each of the mask contrasts in each category were included.</s><s>The results are shown in Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref>.</s><s>As can be seen, there was no effect of mask contrast on BOLD responses to invisible stimuli (F(2,34) &lt; 1, P 5 0.977).</s><s>None of the other main and interaction effects were significant (all P &gt; 0.153).</s><s>Supporting Information Figure <ref type="figure">S6</ref> displays the processing of faces in the FFA and tools in V3A/V7 without the subtraction of the mask activation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Multivariate fMRI Results</head><p><s>As the univariate analysis showed no sign of residual processing of the invisible stimuli, neither in the ventral nor in the dorsal ROI, we used MVPA to probe whether there was category selectivity in the ROIs even under invisibility <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[Haynes and Rees, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b25">Kamitani and Tong, 2005]</ref>.</s><s>Figure <ref type="figure">7A</ref> shows the average prediction accuracies from decoding tools from faces.</s><s>Note that the values of left and right dorsal ROIs did not show significant differences and thus were averaged in Figure <ref type="figure">7</ref> for the sake of clarity.</s><s>Visible stimuli were significantly decodable from each other above chance in all ROIs: 77.38% (P &lt; 0.001) in the right FFA, 72.02% (P &lt; 0.001) in V3A/V7.</s><s>By contrast, in the invisible condition, the average prediction accuracies were not different from chance: 51.19% (P 5 0.315) in the right FFA, 51.79% (P 5 0.254) in V3A/V7.</s><s>Next, we tested for effects of interocular suppression strength (Fig. <ref type="figure">7B</ref>): If any decoding accuracy hinted at successful decoding of category, it was for the lowest mask contrast in the FFA (55.21%,</s><s>P 5 0.069; not corrected for multiple tests).</s><s>For the higher mask contrasts, the decoding accuracies were 49.36% (P 5 0.583) and 50.00% (P 5 0.472) in the FFA.</s><s>The decoding accuracies for V3A/V7 for the corresponding contrasts were 49.74% (P 5 0.528), 50.32% (P 5 0.475), and 47.28% (P 5 0.799).</s></p><p><s>Finally, we tested if there was a decoding benefit for elongated tools compared to non-elongated tools, the decoding being carried out versus faces in both cases (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">8</ref>).</s><s>For visible stimuli, both elongated and non-elongated tools can be successfully decoded from faces (all P &lt; 0.001).</s><s>In case of invisible stimuli, the MVPA showed enhanced decoding of elongated relative to non-elongated tools, in both the FFA (56.19%,</s><s>P 5 0.025), and right V3A/ V7 (56.27%,</s><s>P 5 0.025), but not in left V3A/V7 (52.66%,</s><s>P 5 0.193).</s><s>The decoding accuracies for non-elongated tools in the FFA and V3A/V7 were virtually at chance level (50%, all P &gt; 0.470; Supporting Information Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">S5</ref> plots the results of the permutation tests underlying the Activation to faces and tools in FFA and V3A/V7.</s><s>The activation to the masks alone was subtracted in the three invisible conditions.</s><s>The ANOVA described in the main text was calculated only over the invisible conditions to be able to detect possible effects of mask contrast.</s><s>The responses to invisible stimuli were low, irrespective of ROI or mask contrast and the differences between the three mask contrasts not significant.</s><s>Error bars denote 6 1 SEM.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 7.</head><p><s>(A) Decoding accuracies for faces versus tools in FFA and V3A/ V7.</s><s>Decoding accuracies for the visible condition (no masks) were significantly higher than chance as tested in a permutation test, while the stimulus category could not be decoded from the neural data in the invisible condition.</s><s>(B) Decoding accuracies for faces versus tools in FFA and V3A/V7 plotted separately for visible (mask level 0) and invisible trials (mask levels 0.49, 0.70, and 0.95; only invisible trials were included).</s><s>Note that the values of left and right dorsal ROI did not show significant differences and were averaged for the sake of clarity.</s><s>Dashed line: approximate chance level (exact chance level is determined by the permutation method and is different for each test).</s><s>Error bars denote 6 1 SEM.</s><s>Asterisks: ***:P &lt; 0.001, not corrected for multiple comparisons.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>P-values</head><p><s>).</s><s>An ANOVA with the factor shape confirmed a tendency toward enhanced decoding for elongated compared to non-elongated tools (F(1,20) 5 4.24, P 5 0.053; Supporting Information Table <ref type="table">S4A</ref> provides a full summary of the effects).</s><s>Pairwise comparisons revealed a tendency in right V3A/V7: t(20) 5 1.91, P 5 0.071 (FFA: t(20) 5 1.42, P 5 0.172; left V3A/V7: t(20) 5 0.64, P 5 0.532).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>In this study, we investigated category-and shapeselective fMRI-BOLD responses in both visual streams when stimuli were either visible or rendered invisible by CFS.</s><s>In line with behavioral priming experiments, we found that for the processing of invisible tool stimuli their shape plays a role.</s><s>Specifically, the multivariate analysis showed enhanced decoding of elongated relative to nonelongated tools.</s><s>To resolve conflicting earlier fMRI findings related to the differential link to awareness in dorsal and ventral stream <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[Fang and He, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hesselmann and Malach, 2011]</ref>, we also looked at category-selective BOLD activity in both visual streams, dependent on the depth of interocular suppression.</s><s>For all levels of suppression, we observed a stream-invariant reduction of responses compared to a visible condition.</s><s>Each of these points will be discussed in turn.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Invisible Processing of Elongated Versus Non-elongated Tool Stimuli</head><p><s>Our results show that visible tools elicit similar levels of activation in the dorsal visual stream, irrespective of their shape attributes.</s><s>This finding is in agreement with research establishing the dorsal stream as an important area for the preparation of visually guided actions <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[Binkofski et al., 1998;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Chao and Martin, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Culham and Valyear, 2006]</ref>, and it thus validates our dorsal ROIs.</s></p><p><s>One previous study reported largely preserved activity in the dorsal stream when images of tools were rendered invisible by CFS <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[Fang and He, 2005]</ref>.</s><s>Building on this result, it has been proposed that behavioral priming effects observed for invisible tool primes under CFS are due to processing in the dorsal stream specific for stimuli with a relation to visually guided action <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[Almeida et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Almeida et al., 2008]</ref>.</s><s>Speaking against this scenario, however, <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Sakuraba et al. [2012]</ref> found priming effects for all types of elongated prime stimuli (e.g., lines and elongated vegetables) but not for non-elongated primes.</s></p><p><s>Although we did not find a significant difference in the level of activation to invisible elongated and non-elongated tools in a standard univariate analysis, the MVPA revealed enhanced decoding of invisible elongated tools compared to invisible non-elongated tools (decoding for visible tools was similar for the two categories).</s><s>We conclude that the activation that survives interocular suppression might in fact not reflect category-specific processing but merely show that stimuli with certain shape attributes (e.g., elongated with a principal axis) are more likely to be processed under interocular suppression than others.</s><s>This residual shape-related activation could also explain why the presentation of elongated invisible tools primed the categorization of elongated tool stimuli <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[Almeida et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Almeida et al., 2008]</ref>.</s><s>Our findings support the notion of <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Sakuraba et al. [2012]</ref> that tool-priming effects observed under CFS can be attributed to preferential processing of stimuli with an elongated shape.</s><s>It is interesting to note that the tool stimuli used by <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Fang and He [2005]</ref> were exclusively elongated (personal communication).</s><s>In a next step, therefore, one could investigate whether representations in the dorsal stream for non-action-relevant elongated images (such as geometric lines) are similar to those of elongated tools.</s></p><p><s>Despite their different accounts of the nature of the priming effects, both <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Almeida et al. [2008</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Almeida et al. [ , 2010] ]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">Sakuraba et al. [2012]</ref> assume that priming with tools and elongated stimuli originates from dorsal visual processes only [also see <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">Hebart and Hesselmann, 2012]</ref>.</s><s>Our results do not seem to support this notion as we found above chance decoding of elongated tools also in our ventral ROI, suggesting instead that both ventral and dorsal processes mediate the priming effects.</s></p><p><s>Based on a new series of priming experiments, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Almeida et al. [2013]</ref> proposed that elongation, irrespective of the category of the elongated object, triggers grasp preparation and, therefore, represents a core feature of "manipulability".</s><s>According to <ref type="bibr">Almeida et al.,</ref> this actionrelevant cue can be extracted by the dorsal stream even under impoverished situations such as interocular suppression, whereas category cannot be processed.</s><s>In this framework, our result of enhanced decoding of elongated tools despite interocular suppression could be interpreted as preserved processing of "manipulability" and not mere residual processing of elongated shape.</s><s>But again, this scenario seems unlikely as we also observed enhanced decoding of elongated tools in the ventral visual stream.</s><s>Importantly, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Almeida et al. [2013]</ref> do not show whether their priming effects can be also found when non-elongated tools are used as targets, thus not excluding the possibility of shape priming.</s><s>It remains to be investigated whether the neural activity evoked by elongated stimuli reflects processing related to visually guided action or a mere preference in processing for elongated objects unrelated to action.</s></p><p><s>We found that successful decoding of category (face vs. elongated tool) was possible in right but not in left V3A/ V7, although tool processing has been described as leftlateralized <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[Chao and Martin, 2000;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Johnson-Frey et al., 2005]</ref>.</s><s>Neither <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Fang and He [2005]</ref> nor <ref type="bibr">Hesselmann and Malach [2011]</ref>, however, reported a left-lateralization of tool-related BOLD responses in their experiments.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stream-Invariant Reduction of BOLD Responses Under CFS</head><p><s>In two previous fMRI studies, the link between BOLD responses in ventral and dorsal stream areas and visual awareness has been studied with similar experimental designs but conflicting outcomes <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[Fang and He, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hesselmann and Malach, 2011]</ref>.</s><s>Both studies used CFS to suppress visual stimuli from awareness.</s><s>While <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Fang and He [2005]</ref> showed preserved activity to invisible tool stimuli in dorsal areas, <ref type="bibr">Hesselmann and Malach [2011]</ref> showed a reduction of activity across all ROI.</s><s>We hypothesized that-under the assumption of different suppression levels in the two studies-we should be able to replicate Fang and He's findings with weak suppression (i.e., lowcontrast CFS masks) and Hesselmann and Malach's findings with strong suppression (i.e., high-contrast CFS masks).</s><s>Contrary to our expectation, we found a streaminvariant reduction of BOLD responses to tool and face stimuli even for low suppression levels and were thus unable to replicate the findings of <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Fang and He [2005]</ref>.</s><s>Importantly, we established the effectiveness of our modulation of suppression levels based on CFS mask contrasts in a control experiment.</s><s>It should be noted, however, that measured suppression levels were significantly different only between medium and high mask contrasts.</s></p><p><s>Why have we not found a differential link of dorsal and ventral areas to visual awareness, even with varying suppression levels in the invisible condition?</s><s>There are a number of possibilities how this came about.</s><s>Possibly, the suppression in the invisible condition was still too strong in our study to find any neural activation to the suppressed stimuli.</s><s>What speaks against this scenario is that we were able to decode the category of invisible stimuli in one multivariate analysis (elongated tool vs. face).</s><s>Although this might be purely based on different lowlevel stimulus properties (oval faces vs. elongated tools), it shows that at least some stimulus information reached higher visual areas despite suppression.</s><s>Arguably, the suppression could still have been too strong to find univariate responses to invisible stimuli.</s><s>Furthermore, as in previous studies <ref type="bibr">[Hesselmann et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hesselmann and Malach, 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Ludwig et al., 2013]</ref>, we tried to keep the suppression as low as possible but as high as necessary by individually adjusting the contrast of the stimuli.</s><s>Individual contrast adjustment is one of three options; the other options would be to choose a very low contrast for all subjects, risking not to find any effect, or to choose a higher contrast and exclude all subjects with above chance performance due to visibility of the stimulus.</s><s>In our case, adjustment of contrasts ensured that contrasts were sufficient to produce category-selective BOLD responses whenever stimuli broke through suppression.</s></p><p><s>In this study, we used smaller ROIs than in the previous studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[Fang and He, 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Hesselmann and Malach, 2011]</ref>.</s><s>The lack of response to invisible stimuli, however, cannot be attributed to this fact as a highly similar reduction from the visible to the invisible condition was also found with larger ROIs.</s></p><p><s>One of the central questions we addressed in this study is the difference in the depth of suppression possibly underlying different results in different CFS studies.</s><s>Here, we managed the challenging task of manipulating the depth of interocular suppression while keeping the object stimuli equally invisible in all experimental conditions of the fMRI experiment.</s><s>To achieve approximately the same number of trials for each condition (i.e., to avoid differential exclusions due to visibility), we had to make sure that the stimuli were largely invisible for all mask contrasts.</s><s>In this range of mask contrasts yielding successful suppression, we further modulated suppression strength by means of the mask contrast.</s><s>In the control experiment, we could show that these different contrasts indeed led to different contrast detection thresholds, albeit not in the parametrical fashion that we had anticipated.</s><s>On a purely speculative note, we hypothesize that the mask of the lowest contrast might have been successful in suppressing the stimulus due to the higher similarity of stimulus and mask (in the contrast domain) as similarity of mask and stimulus (in terms of their spatial properties) has been shown to lead to high suppression <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">[Yang and Blake, 2012]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>To our knowledge, the BOLD responses reported by Fang and He represent the strongest nonconscious visual signal that has been observed under interocular suppression.</s><s>For that reason alone, further investigation of these responses in dorsal visual stream seems worthwhile.</s><s>Future studies should explore the effect of experimental parameters which have not been addressed by our study.</s><s>For example, the impact of a primary detection task at fixation, which was present in Fang and He's experiment but absent in our experiment.</s><s>Another relevant parameter might be the effective duration of intermittent CFS stimulation, which was 20 s in the case of Fang and He, and 5 s in our study.</s><s>However, a potential challenge will be that longer stimulation generally results in more stimuli that escape suppression by CFS and thus become visible <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[Stein et al., 2011]</ref>.</s><s>Finally, the spatial frequency of CFS masks might have had a major influence in producing the different results (Fang and He: "random noise"; Hesselmann and Malach: "Mondrians") as <ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Yang and Blake [2012]</ref> have shown that suppression strength depends on the respective spatial frequency of mask and stimulus.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSION</head><p><s>To conclude, our data do not support the notion that opposed to ventral processes, dorsal stream activity is exclusively preserved under interocular suppression.</s><s>We found a reduction in both visual streams for invisible as compared to visible stimuli.</s><s>In the only condition in which we found successful stimulus decoding despite invisibility, both visual streams showed the same pattern of results.</s><s>Whether this successful decoding under CFS is based on category information or on shape attributes remains a topic for future research.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,89.07,86.97,434.11,197.07" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .Figure 3 .</head><label>23</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Tool-and face-selective areas defined by the localizer experiment.</s><s>(A) Activation for faces &gt; tools in the localizer run, P &lt; 0.001 uncorrected.</s><s>(B) Activation for tools &gt; faces in the localizer run, P &lt; 0.001 uncorrected.</s><s>The lines show the position of the spherical ROIs (after rendering them in the same way as the depicted activations).</s><s>[Color figure can be viewed in the online issue, which is available at wileyonlinelibrary.com.]</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,113.39,86.97,385.56,120.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4.Category-selective BOLD responses in FFA and V3A/V7 to visible face and tool stimuli in the main experiment.</s><s>On the left, parameter estimates are shown for all visible trials (trials with a mask contrast of 0, i.e., no masks).</s><s>On the right, parameter estimates are shown for trials in which the stimuli were subjectively visible (PAS rating &gt; 1) despite masking by CFS.</s><s>The activation to the masks alone was subtracted in this condition.</s><s>Error bars denote 6 1 standard error of the mean (SEM).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,68.20,86.97,223.89,180.62" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. BOLD responses to elongated and non-elongated tools in V3A/ V7, separately for the visible and invisible condition.</s><s>In case of the invisible condition, the activation to the masks alone was subtracted.</s><s>Error bars denote 6 1 SEM.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,326.21,478.94,211.65,169.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6.Activation to faces and tools in FFA and V3A/V7.</s><s>The activation to the masks alone was subtracted in the three invisible conditions.</s><s>The ANOVA described in the main text was calculated only over the invisible conditions to be able to detect possible effects of mask contrast.</s><s>The responses to invisible stimuli were low, irrespective of ROI or mask contrast and the differences between the three mask contrasts not significant.</s><s>Error bars denote 6 1 SEM.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,68.20,86.97,223.89,184.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 8. Decoding accuracies faces versus elongated tools (left) and nonelongated tools (right) in FFA and left and right V3A/V7 for the visible and the invisible condition.</s><s>Decoding was carried out separately for elongated tools versus faces and for non-elongated tools versus faces.</s><s>Dashed line: approximate chance level (exact chance level is determined by the permutation method and is different for each test).</s><s>The MVPA showed enhanced decoding of elongated relative to non-elongated tools, in both the FFA and right V3A/V7 but not in left V3A/V7.</s><s>Error bars denote 6 1 SEM.</s><s>Asterisks: *: P &lt; 0.05; ***: P &lt; 0.001, not corrected for multiple comparisons.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="10,71.21,86.97,217.77,206.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">r Ludwig et al. r r 138 r</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">r Ludwig et al. r r 140 r</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">r Neural Visual Processing Under CFS r r 141 r</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">r Ludwig et al. r r 142 r</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">r Neural Visual Processing Under CFS r r 143 r</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">r Ludwig et al. r r 144 r</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">r Neural Visual Processing Under CFS r r 145 r</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">r Ludwig et al. r r 146 r</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">r Neural Visual Processing Under CFS r r 147 r</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">r Ludwig et al. r r 148 r</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">r Neural Visual Processing Under CFS r r 149 r</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENT</head><p><s>The authors would like to thank Martin Hebart and Kai G€ orgen for their invaluable MVPA support.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unconscious processing dissociates along categorical lines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Almeida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Mahon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Nakayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Caramazza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15214" to="15218" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The role of the dorsal visual processing stream in tool identification</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Almeida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Mahon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Caramazza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="772" to="778" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Grasping with the eyes: The role of elongation in visual recognition of manipulable objects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Almeida</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Mahon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Zapater-Raberov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dziuba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Cabaco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Marques</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Caramazza</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cogn Affect Behav Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="319" to="335" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unified segmentation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ashburner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Friston</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="839" to="851" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Attentional load modulates responses of human primary visual cortex to invisible stimuli</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bahrami</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Lavie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rees</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="509" to="513" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human anterior intraparietal area subserves prehension</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Binkofski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Dohle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Posse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Stephan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hefter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Seitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H-J</forename><surname>Freund</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1253" to="1259" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Brainard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The Psychophysics Toolbox</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="433" to="436" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LIBSVM: A library for support vector machines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Trans Intell Syst Technol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="27" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Representation of manipulable manmade objects in the dorsal stream</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Chao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="478" to="484" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human parietal cortex in action</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Culham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Valyear</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Neurobiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="212" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bayesian versus orthodox statistics: Which side are you on?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Dienes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Perspect Psychol Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="274" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">fMRI activation to visible and invisible faces and houses using continuous flash suppression with a confidence rating task</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Dubois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tsuchiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Adolphs</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Poster presented at SfN</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Washington, DC</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cortical responses to invisible objects in the human dorsal and ventral pathways</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1380" to="1385" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Unconscious neural processing differs with method used to render stimuli invisible</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Fogelson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kohler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Granger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Tse</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Grasping visual illusions: Consistent data and no dissociation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Franz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Gegenfurtner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cogn Neuropsychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="920" to="950" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical parametric maps in functional imaging: A general linear approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Friston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Homes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Worsley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Poline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Frith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Frackowiak</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum Brain Mapp</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="189" to="210" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A neurological dissociation between perceiving objects and grasping them</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Goodale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Milner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Jakobson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Carey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">349</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="156" />
			<date type="published" when="1991">1991</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>G€ Orgen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Hebart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J-D</forename><surname>Haynes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Decoding Toolbox (TDT): A new fMRI analysis package for SPM and MATLAB. Poster presented at HBM</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Beijing, China</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decoding mental states from brain activity in humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Haynes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rees</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Rev Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="523" to="534" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What visual information is processed in the human dorsal stream?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Hebart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hesselmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="8107" to="8109" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dissecting Visual Awareness with fMRI</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hesselmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroscientist</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="495" to="508" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The link between fMRI-BOLD activation and perceptual awareness is &quot;stream-invariant&quot; in the human visual system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hesselmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Malach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cereb Cortex</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2829" to="2837" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Differential BOLD activity associated with subjective and objective reports during &quot;blindsight&quot; in normal observers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hesselmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hebart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Malach</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">31</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12936" to="12944" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ventral occipital lesions impair object recognition but not object-directed grasping: An fMRI study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>James</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Culham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Humphrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Milner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Goodale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brain</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">126</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2463" to="2475" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Pt 11</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A distributed left hemisphere network active during planning of everyday tool use skills</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Johnson-Frey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Newman-Norlund</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Grafton</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cereb Cortex</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="681" to="695" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decoding the visual and subjective contents of the human brain</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kamitani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Tong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="679" to="685" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">What determines the depth of interocular suppression during continuous flash suppression?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ledgeway</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Mcgraw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Vis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">541</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transformed up-down methods in psychoacoustics</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hcch</forename><surname>Levitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of the Acoustical society of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="467" to="477" />
			<date type="published" when="1971">1971</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Learning to detect but not to grasp suppressed visual stimuli</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ludwig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sterzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kathmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Franz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hesselmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuropsychologia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2930" to="2938" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ocular dominance in human adults</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Miles</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Gen Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="412" to="429" />
			<date type="published" when="1930">1930</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Is visual processing in the dorsal stream accessible to consciousness?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Milner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Biol Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">279</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2289" to="2298" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Milner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Goodale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The visual brain in action</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Oxford</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The VideoToolbox software for visual psychophysics: Transforming numbers into movies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Pelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Spatial Vision</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="442" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Introspection and subliminal perception</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Ramsoy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Overgaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phenomenol Cogn Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does the human dorsal stream really process a category for tools?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sakuraba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Sakai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Yamanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yokosawa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hirayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3949" to="3953" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The statistical analysis of multivoxel patterns in functional imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schreiber Krekelberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e69328</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A very inexpensive MRI-compatible method for dichoptic visual stimulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Schurger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Neurosci Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">177</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="199" to="202" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Breaking continuous flash suppression: A new measure of unconscious processing during interocular suppression?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Stein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Hebart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sterzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front Hum Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">167</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical inference and multiple testing correction in classification-based multi-voxel pattern analysis (MVPA): Random permutations and cluster size control</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stelzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Turner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroimage</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">65</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="82" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural processing of visual information under interocular suppression: A critical review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sterzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Stein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ludwig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rothkirch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hesselmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Continuous flash suppression reduces negative afterimages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tsuchiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nat Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1096" to="1101" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Depth of interocular suppression associated with continuous flash suppression, flash suppression, and binocular rivalry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tsuchiya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gilroy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Blake</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Vis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1068" to="1078" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Converging evidence for diverging pathways: Neuropsychology and psychophysics tell the same story</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Westwood</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Goodale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Vis Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="804" to="811" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Controlling low-level image properties: The SHINE toolbox</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Willenbockel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sadr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fiset</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Horne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gosselin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behav Res Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">42</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="671" to="684" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deconstructing continuous flash suppression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Blake</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Vis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
