<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">M Faraji Zonooz et al</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-04-27">27 April 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Joerg</forename><surname>Wenzel</surname></persName>
							<email>joerg.wenzel@ukb.uni-bonn.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Dermatology and Allergy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital of Bonn</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bonn</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nadine</forename><surname>Van Holt</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Dermatology and Allergy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital of Bonn</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bonn</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Judith</forename><surname>Maier</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Dermatology and Allergy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital of Bonn</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bonn</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Maria</forename><surname>Vonnahme</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Hematology, Oncology and Rheumatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Medical Clinic 3</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University Hospital of Bonn</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bonn</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Bieber</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Dermatology and Allergy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University Hospital of Bonn</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bonn</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Dominik</forename><surname>Wolf</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Hematology, Oncology and Rheumatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Medical Clinic 3</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University Hospital of Bonn</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Bonn</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wolf</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ruxolitinib</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">M Faraji Zonooz et al</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-04-27">27 April 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">7D2A55E784322FD1C6F66CE352A6BFAB</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">.org/10.1111/bjh.13644</idno>
					<note type="submission">Accepted manuscript published online 9 March 2016; corrected proof</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>HS, hidradenitis suppurativa</term>
					<term>PASH syndrome, pyoderma gangrenosum, acne, and suppurative hidradenitis syndrome</term>
					<term>PG, pyoderma gangrenosum</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>significant repigmentation in vitiligo was reported with tofacitinib citrate treatment (Craiglow et al., 2015).</s><s>A case of reversal of alopecia areata has been observed with baricitinib treatment (Jabbari et al., 2015).</s></p><p><s>In summary, we demonstrate a substantial benefit from ruxolitinib therapy in a case of chilblain LE.</s><s>Our observation supports the idea that JAK/STAT inhibition provides a promising therapeutic approach for the treatment of cutaneous autoimmune diseases, particularly LE.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</head><p><s>DW reports research support and honorary payments from Novartis.</s><s>JW, NvH, JM, MV, and TB state no conflicts of interest.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Punwani N, Scherle P, Flores R, Shi J, Liang J, <ref type="bibr">Yeleswaram S, et</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TO THE EDITOR</head><p><s>The familial form of hidradenitis suppurativa (HS), also known as acne inversa (AI), is an autosomal dominant autoinflammatory genodermatosis caused by mutations in the genes encoding g-secretase subunits <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Ingram and Piguet, 2013)</ref>.</s><s>Recently, HS has been described as a triad with acne and pyoderma gangrenosum (PG), so-called PASH (pyoderma gangrenosum, acne, and suppurative hidradenitis) syndrome, and increased number of CCTG microsatellite repeats in the promoter region of PSTPIP1 was suggested to be associated with the phenotype <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Braun-Falco et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>In this study, we characterized an extended multigenerational Iranian family, including 24 affected and 32 unaffected individuals, presenting with manifestations of HS, acne, and PG in an autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1a</ref>).</s><s>This study was approved by the Institutional Review Board of Kariminejad-Najmabadi Pathology and Genetics Center, Tehran.</s><s>Clinical evaluation of the affected individuals revealed HS and acne with different degrees of severity and extent in the spectrum of symptoms (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> and Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S1 online)</ref>.</s><s>The clinical features were documented in the Hospital of Kerman University of Sciences in nine patients, as detailed in Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S1</ref>; among them, three patients had a history of PG.</s></p><p><s>DNA was isolated from 13 affected and 10 unaffected members of the extended family from peripheral blood leukocytes after a written, informed consent.</s><s>Mutation analysis was first performed by PCR amplification of the promoter region as well as all 15 exons and flanking intronic sequences of PSTPIP1 as the candidate gene previously shown to harbor mutations with PG and acne with pyogenic sterile arthritis <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Wise et al., 2002)</ref>.</s><s>One additional primer pair was designed to investigate the possibility of increased number of CCTG microsatellite repeats in the promoter region of PSTPIP1.</s><s>No pathogenic variants were detected in the coding region of this gene.</s><s>Sequencing of the promoter region showed (CCTG) 5 repeat as normal allele size, and thus, no increase in repeats of the CCTG microsatellite motif within 545 nucleotides of the 5 0 side of the ATG start codon was noted (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">S1 online</ref>).</s></p><p><s>In the next step, whole genome single nucleotide polymorphism genotyping was applied using an Illumina Humancoreexome-12v1-1 array (Illumina, San Diego, CA).</s><s>Linkage analysis resulted in the identification of genomic intervals with LOD scores &gt;2 on chromosomes 1, 11, and 20 (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2a</ref> and Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S2</ref> online).</s><s>Analysis of key individuals in the pedigree with flanking single nucleotide polymorphisms revealed a conserved haplotype in chromosome 1q23.2 in affected individuals but not in the controls (Supplementary Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">S2 online</ref>).</s><s>Whole exome sequencing was performed on the proband's DNA, and a total of 20 rare sequence variants were detected in the genomic intervals on chromosomes 1, 11, and 20 (Supplementary Table <ref type="table">S3</ref> online).</s><s>These variants were prioritized according to gene function and expression, mutation type, bioinformatics predictions, and frequency in our in-house ethnicspecific control panel.</s></p><p><s>Candidate prioritization resulted in selection of eight candidate genes (SELENBP1, HRNR, DAP3, GPATCH4, NCSTN, DDR2, AHNAK, and TTC24) consistent with the autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance.</s><s>Cosegregation studies further narrowed the possible candidates to two rare heterozygous variants, one in NCSTN and one in TTC24; all affected individuals were heterozygous, whereas the healthy individuals showed wild-type genotype.</s></p><p><s>The variant in NCSTN, c.1635C&gt;G (p.Tyr545*) (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2b</ref>), leads to a premature termination codon, whereas the c.888G&gt;A variant in TTC24 affects a splice site at 5 0 border of exon 8 and was considered a putative splicing variant.</s><s>To examine the latter possibility, the effect of c.888G&gt;A in TTC24 was evaluated at the mRNA level.</s><s>PCR amplification using flanking primers revealed no difference between sizes of the amplicons spanning exons 7e9 in the affected and healthy individuals.</s><s>Therefore, the c.888G&gt;A variant in TTC24 does not have a major effect on RNA splicing that excluded this variant from further study.</s><s>Based on these findings, the c.1635C&gt;G (p.Tyr545*) nonsense variant in the NCSTN gene was considered as the cause of the phenotype in this large family (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2b</ref>).</s></p><p><s>During the course of our study, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Duchatelet et al. (2015)</ref> reported a truncating variant in NCSTN as the gene responsible for HS, acne, and PG.</s><s>In their study, PSTPIP1, PSEN1, PSENEN, and NCSTN, genes previously reported to be mutated in patients with HS <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Miskinyte et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">Pink et al., 2013)</ref>, were investigated by Sanger sequencing, and a heterozygous frameshift deletion, c.344_351del (p.Thr115Asn*20), in the NCSTN gene was suggested as the causative mutation in one patient with so-called PASH syndrome.</s><s>In their study, the proband was an adopted child, and no family studies were performed.</s><s>Our study now extends these findings to a large multiplex pedigree with 24 affected individuals with HS, acne, and PG.</s><s>It should be noted that PG was present only in three of the nine patients attesting to the phenotypic heterogeneity in this family.</s><s>Consequently, PASH syndrome is not a genetically distinct entity, but rather belongs to the spectrum of gsecretase-related disorders, potentially caused by mutations in different genes.</s></p><p><s>NCSTN encodes nicastrin, one of the three subunits of g-secretase, a transmembrane endoprotease complex that catalyzes the cleavage of many transmembrane proteins, such as amyloid precursor, and E-and N-cadherin, as well as Notch receptors <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Lu et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>g-Secretase maintains skin appendages through Notch signaling involving both autonomous and nonautonomous signaling <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(Pan et al., 2004)</ref>.</s><s>Recently, nonsense and truncating mutations in genes encoding gsecretase subunits (NCSTN, PSENEN, and PSEN1) have been reported in cases of HS or familial AI <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Wang et al., 2010)</ref>, and here extended to a large family also with PG.</s><s>How the mutations in the g-secretase genes elicit the autoinflammatory phenotypes is not clear, but it has been recently demonstrated that tumor necrosis factor-a and IL-10 levels were elevated in patients with HS with NCSTN mutations, possibly contributing to the chronic, recurrent in these skin conditions <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Wang, 2015)</ref>.</s><s>Thus, PG may be part of the autoinflammatory spectrum, together with HS and acne.</s><s>Genetic studies have identified 21 distinct mutations in NCSTN, most of them associated with HS/acne inversa <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Li et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Liu et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">Nomura et al., 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Pink et al., 2011;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">Wang et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Zhang et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>To the best of our knowledge, the pathogenic variant identified in this study, c.1635C&gt;G (p.Tyr545*) in NCSTN, is previously unreported, providing strong evidence for the critical functional role of NCSTN in the phenotype of our patients.</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">et al., 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Pigatto et al., 1992)</ref>.</s><s>Strong evidence has shown that the T helper-2 (Th2) cytokine, IL-13, is the dominant disease-causing factor in the pathogenesis of AD in mice <ref type="bibr">(Nieuwenhuizen et al., 2009;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sivaprasad et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Tazawa et al., 2004</ref>).</s><s>Hence, it is possible that patients with AD would benefit from</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure1.</s><s>The pedigree and clinical features in the family with hidradenitis suppurativa (HS), acne, and pyoderma gangrenosum (PG).</s><s>(a) The pedigree is consistent with autosomal dominant inheritance (upper panel).</s><s>Skin lesions in affected family members include keloid scars in the armpit (b), in the buttocks (c), on the back (d), scarring as a result of fistules (e), HS (acne inversa) with abscesses and fistules in the neck (f), hyperpigmentation and scars symmetrically on the legs (g), hyperpigmentation and scars on the back (h), and scarring as a result of PG (i).</s><s>The patients consented to publication of these images.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,44.67,54.31,504.71,413.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Whole genome linkage analysis and mutation detection in NCSTN.</s><s>(a) Whole genome parametric linkage analysis (Merlin software, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI).</s><s>The top row shows the chromosome number and the vertical rows represent the LOD scores associated with each chromosome.</s><s>The highest LOD scores (&gt;2) are located on chromosomes 1, 11, and 20 with a prominent genomic interval on chromosome 1.</s><s>(b) Chromatogram of the heterozygous truncating sequence variant c.1635C&gt;G (p.Tyr545*), detected in NCSTN in an affected individual (top), compared with the wild-type sequence in an unaffected family member (bottom).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,43.77,54.31,332.38,436.59" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>IL-13 Signals Independent of IL-4 Receptor-Alpha Chain to Drive Ovalbumin-Induced Dermatitis Journal of Investigative Dermatology (2016) 136, 1286e1290; doi:10.1016/j.jid.2015.11.033</s><s>TO THE EDITOR Atopic dermatitis (AD) is an allergic skin condition that can result from intrinsic genetic factors or repetitive occupational damage.</s><s>Disruption of the skin barrier leads to sensitization to allergens followed by local inflammation (Leung</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Journal of Investigative Dermatology (2016), Volume 136</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">www.jidonline.org 1285</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</head><p><s>The authors state no conflict of interest.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>We thank the families for their participation in this study.</s><s>Carol Kelly assisted in manuscript preparation.</s></p><p><s>Mehrshid Faraji Zonooz 1,9 , Farahnaz Sabbagh-Kermani 2,9 , Zohreh Fattahi 1,3 , Mahsa Fadaee 1,3 , Mohammad Reza Akbari 4,5 , Rezvan Amiri 6 , Hassan Vahidnezhad 7,8 , Jouni Uitto 8 , Hossein Najmabadi 1,3 and Ariana Kariminejad</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pyoderma gangrenosum, acne, and suppurative hidradenitis (PASH)-a new autoinflammatory syndrome distinct from PAPA syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Braun-Falco</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Kovnerystyy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lohse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Ruzicka</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Am Acad Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="409" to="e415" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">First nicastrin mutation in PASH (pyoderma gangrenosum, acne and suppurative hidradenitis) syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Duchatelet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Miskinyte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Join-Lambert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Ungeheuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Frances</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nassif</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">173</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="610" to="e612" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phenotypic heterogeneity in hidradenitis suppurativa (acne inversa): classification is an essential step toward personalized therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Ingram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Piguet</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Invest Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1453" to="e1456" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two novel mutations of the nicastrin gene in Chinese patients with acne inversa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">X</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">165</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="415" to="e418" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Confirmation by exome sequencing of the pathogenic role of NCSTN mutations in acne inversa (hidradenitis suppurativa)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lv</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Invest Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1570" to="e1572" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-dimensional structure of human gammasecretase</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Bai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">512</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="166" to="e70" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Nicastrin mutations in French families with hidradenitis suppurativa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Miskinyte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nassif</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Merabtene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Ungeheuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Join-Lambert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Jais</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Invest Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">132</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1728" to="e1730" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A novel splice site mutation in NCSTN underlies a Japanese family with hidradenitis suppurativa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Nomura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nomura</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sakai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sasaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ohguchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Mizuno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">168</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="206" to="e209" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Gamma-secretase functions through Notch signaling to maintain skin appendages but is not required for their patterning or initial morphogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Tian</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Gridley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Dev Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="731" to="e743" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">PSENEN and NCSTN mutations in familial hidradenitis suppurativa (Acne Inversa)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Pink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Simpson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Brice</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Desai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mortimer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Invest Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">131</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1568" to="1e70" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">g-Secretase mutations in hidradenitis suppurativa: new insights into disease pathogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Pink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Simpson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Desai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Trembath</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Barker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Invest Dermatol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">133</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="601" to="e607" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">g-Secretase mutation and consequently immune reaction involved in pathogenesis of acne inversa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Invest Dermatol Symp Proc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">25</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">g-Secretase gene mutations in familial acne inversa</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Wen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Su</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">330</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1065</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mutations in CD2BP1 disrupt binding to PTP PEST and are responsible for PAPA syndrome, an autoinflammatory disorder</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wise</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Gillum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Seidman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lindor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Veile</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bashiardes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Hum Mol Genet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="961" to="e969" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two novel mutations of the NCSTN gene in Chinese familial acne inverse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mei</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1571" to="e1574" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
