<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">HealtHcare reSource utiliSation among cHronic SPontaneouS/ idioPatHic urticaria PatientS-FindingS From tHe FirSt international Burden oF illneSS Study (aSSure-cSu)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Chapman-Rothe N</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>East Hanover</addrLine>
									<region>NJ</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Novartis Pharmaceuticals Canada Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Dorval</settlement>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Lynderm Research Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>4 1St</addrLine>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Michael&apos;s Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">University of Toronto</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Toronto</settlement>
									<region>ON</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Knulst</forename><surname>Ac</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Novartis Pharmaceuticals Canada Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Dorval</settlement>
									<region>QC</region>
									<country key="CA">Canada</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">Novartis Pharma GmbH</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Nuernberg, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Charite -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff6">
								<orgName type="department">Novartis Pharma B.V</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Netherlands</addrLine>
									<settlement>Arnhem</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff7">
								<orgName type="institution">University Medical Center Utrecht</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Netherlands</addrLine>
									<settlement>Utrecht</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Elberink</forename><surname>Jn</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff8">
								<orgName type="institution">Unviersity Medical Center Groningen</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Netherlands</addrLine>
									<settlement>Groningen</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Halliday</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>10</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="institution">Novartis Pharmaceuticals UK Limited</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Surrey</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexopoulos</forename><surname>St</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff9">
								<orgName type="institution">Novartis Pharmaceuticals UK Limited</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Surrey</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nakonechna</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>11</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff10">
								<orgName type="institution">Hull and East Yorkshire NHS Hospital Trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hull</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Grattan</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>12</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff11">
								<orgName type="institution">Norfolk and Norwich University Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Norwich</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Abouzakouk</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>11</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff10">
								<orgName type="institution">Hull and East Yorkshire NHS Hospital Trust</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hull</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff12">
								<orgName type="institution">RTI Health Solutions</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Research Triangle Park</addrLine>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Sweeney</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff12">
								<orgName type="institution">RTI Health Solutions</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Research Triangle Park</addrLine>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>McBride</roleName><forename type="first">Wolin</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>14</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Charite -Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin, Germany</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff12">
								<orgName type="institution">RTI Health Solutions</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Research Triangle Park</addrLine>
									<region>NC</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff13">
								<orgName type="institution">RTI Health Solutions</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ann Arbor</settlement>
									<region>MI</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff14">
								<orgName type="institution">RTI Health Solutions</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Manchester</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff15">
								<orgName type="institution">Novartis Pharma AG</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Basel</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">HealtHcare reSource utiliSation among cHronic SPontaneouS/ idioPatHic urticaria PatientS-FindingS From tHe FirSt international Burden oF illneSS Study (aSSure-cSu)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5FF35FB298AF74D4A007C1FD9D86B7EC</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Probabilistic sensitivity analysis indicated robustness in the Conclusionsof dominance/highly cost-effective approach for SEC vs. UST.</s><s>ConClusions: Applying stricter criteria for response (i.e., PASI≥ 75 instead of PASI≥ 50) for treatment dis/ continuation for highly efficacious PSO therapy (SEC) Resultsin overall greater QALYs and cost savings for the health-care system.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>objeCtives: There are limited data on healthcare resource utilisation associated with inadequately controlled chronic spontaneous (idiopathic) urticaria (CSU/ CIU) patients.</s><s>ASSURE-CSU is an observational, multinational study conducted to identify and quantify burden of illness in these patients.</s><s>Data on resource utilisation for Canada, Germany, UK and the Netherlands are summarised.</s><s>Methods: This study included a 1-year retrospective medical record abstraction and a crosssectional patient-reported outcomes survey.</s><s>Adult CSU/CIU patients with disease persisting for ≥ 12 months despite treatment were assessed.</s><s>Data on resource utilisation were extracted from patient medical records, and reported descriptively.</s><s>Results: Medical records were abstracted for 99 patients each in Canada and the Netherlands, 100 in Germany and 83 in the UK.</s><s>In Canada, 83% patients had one or more visits to a health care professional (HCP) with a total mean (SD) of 3.1 (2.57) annual visits.</s><s>In the prior 12 months, visits to allergists and dermatologists were reported by 72% and 11% patients.</s><s>In Germany, 52% patients visited HCPs <ref type="bibr">[annual visits: 3.3 (3.81)</ref>].</s><s>Hospitalisations and emergency room (ER) visits were reported by 18% and 15% patients.</s><s>Allergists and dermatologists were visited by 33% and 31% patients.</s><s>In UK, 86% patients visited HCPs <ref type="bibr">[annual visits: 3.7 (2.68)</ref>].</s><s>Dermatologists were seen by 54% patients, allergists by 30% and hospital nurses by 10%.</s><s>HCPs were visited by 87% patients in the Netherlands <ref type="bibr">[annual visits: 4.1 (3.87)</ref>].</s><s>Visits to dermatologists, allergists and other consultants were reported by 51%, 42% and 13% patients.</s><s>ER visits and hospitalisations were less frequent in Canada, the UK and the Netherlands compared with Germany.</s><s>ConClusions: This is the first study to quantify resource utilisation associated with inadequately controlled CSU/CIU.</s><s>The types of medical resources differ among the countries depending on the local healthcare specificities.</s><s>Resource utilisation pattern was primarily outpatient but varied across countries.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SenSory SyStemS diSorderS -Patient-reported outcomes &amp; Patient Preference Studies</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PSS53 economic Burden oF cHronic SPontaneouS urticaria and PSoriaSiS: PatientS PerSPective From euroPe</head><p><s>Vietri J 1 , Tian H 2 , Gabriel S 2 , Balp M 3 , Khalil S 3 , Zuberbier T 4 1 Kantar Health, Horsham, PA, USA, 2 Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation, East Hanover, NJ, USA, 3 Novartis Pharma AG, Basel, Switzerland, 4 Allergie-Centrum-Charité, Berlin, Germany objeCtives: Chronic urticaria (CU) (or chronic hives) can be inducible or spontaneous (also known as idiopathic urticaria) (CSU/CIU).</s><s>Data supporting the impact of CSU/CIU on patients and comparison with other dermatological diseases are scarce.</s><s>This study evaluated economic burden associated with CU relative to psoriasis (PsO) overall and different severity levels of PsO among the adults in 5 European (France, Germany, Italy, Spain and UK) countries.</s><s>Methods: Data from patients diagnosed with chronic hives (proxy for CSU) and PsO were collected in the National Health and Wellness Survey (NHWS).</s><s>Outcome measures included the Work Productivity and Activity Impairment (WPAI) questionnaire and self-reported healthcare use in prior 6 months.</s><s>Generalized linear models with different link functions were used to compare patients with CU vs. overall PsO (includes all severity levels) and CU vs. moderate-severe-PsO, controlling for patient characteristics.</s><s>Results: Study included 769 CU patients and 7,857 PsO patients (26.9% moderate-severe).</s><s>CU patients reported non-significant higher rate ratio (RR) of absenteeism (RR= 1.31), presenteeism (1.15) and overall work impairment (1.15) than overall PsO, however, activity impairment was significantly higher among CU patients (1.21; p&lt; 0.05).</s><s>The rates of work and activity impairment were similar between CU and moderate-severe-PsO patients (RR: absenteeism; 0.99, presenteeism; 0.97, overall work impairment; 0.97 and activity impairment; 1.08) (all p= NS).</s><s>Rate of healthcare visits were higher among CU than overall PsO (RR: HCP visits; 1.16, ER visits; 2.13, Hospitalizations; 1.94, all p&lt; 0.001) and also than moderate-severe-PsO patients (RR: HCP visits;1.07,</s><s>ER visits;1.77,</s><s>Hospitalizations;1.47,</s><s>all p&lt; 0.001).</s><s>ConClusions: Patients with CU and PsO report a similar negative impact on work ability.</s><s>Compared to overall PsO patients with CU have a significantly higher impact on daily activities and non-significant higher impairment on work components.</s><s>The impact on work and activities is similar among CU and moderate-severe PsO.</s><s>CU patients report significantly higher use of medical resources than Pso.</s></p><p><s>objeCtives: To estimate the incremental cost-utility ratio (ICUR) for ingenol mebutate vs diclofenac 3% for actinic keratosis (AK) patient's treatment on the face and scalp, and trunk and extremities, in Spain.</s><s>Methods: A hypothetical cohort of 73 aged AK patients was simulated for a 5-year time horizon with a Markov model.</s><s>Duration of treatments was 3 days (face-scalp) and 2 days (trunk-extremities) for ingenol mebutate and 90 days (face-scalp and trunk-extremities) for diclofenac.</s><s>Total clearances rates (42.24% and 34.07%</s><s>for ingenol mebutate and 24.64% and 25.07% for diclofenac on face-scalp and on trunk-extremities, respectively) obtained from indirect mixed comparisons and adjusted according compliance were used as effectiveness measure.</s><s>Annual recurrence rate (20%) derived from literature.</s><s>The perspective of the Spanish National Health System (NHS) was choosen.</s><s>Total cost estimation (€ ,2015) included: pharmaceutical cost (retail price VAT included with mandatory deduction), and dermatology visits cost (for adverse events and disease management).A 3% annual discount rate was applied for costs and outcomes.</s><s>Utilities values (0.986 for AK and 1.00 for clearance) were used to derive quality-adjusted-life years (QALY).</s><s>Several sensitivity analyses were performed to test model robustness.</s><s>Results: Ingenol mebutate showed higher effectiveness, with 0.192 incremental clearances and 0.011 incremental QALYs (face-scalp), and 0.129 incremental clearances and 0.007 incremental QALYs (trunk-extremities) compared to diclofenac.</s><s>Total costs accounted were € 551.50 and € 622.27 (46% drug cost) for ingenol mebutate, compared to € 849.11 and € 844.93 (54% drug cost) for diclofenac (for face-scalp and trunk-extremities, respectively).</s><s>Ingenol mebutate versus diclofenac 3% was dominant on face-scalp and trunk-extremities AK treatment.</s><s>Further, ingenol mebutate remained a dominant option in 96% (face-scalp) and 91% (trunk-extremities) of the 1,000 MonteCarlo simulations of probabilistic sensitivity analysis.</s><s>ConClusions: Ingenol mebutate was a dominant strategy for Spanish NHS, compared to diclofenac 3%, for treatment of patients with AK both, face-scalp and trunk-extremities.</s><s>Ceutical, Milano, Italy, 2 RTI Health Solutions, NC, NC, USA, 3 Novartis Farma SpA,   Origgio, Italy, 4 Aix-Marseille University, Marseille, France objeCtives: Secukinumab (SEC300), an IL-17A antibody, was recently approved as highly effective therapy for moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis (PSO).</s><s>We examined the cost-effectiveness of SEC300 compared against other systemic biologic drugs: adalimumab (ADA), etanercept (ETA), infliximab (INF), ustekinumab (UST) 45 and 90 mg, and standard of care (SOC -cyclosporine and methotrexate) for plaque psoriasis, in the Italian National Health System (NHS) setting.</s><s>Methods: A previous cost-effectiveness model was adapted to the Italian healthcare setting.</s><s>The model was designed to consider the clinical benefits, resource use and costs related to SEC300.</s><s>A decision tree reflecting response to treatment (PASI change &lt; 50, 50-75, 75-90, 90-99, 100) fed into a long-term Markov model with health states related to treatment continuation, dropout, and death.</s><s>Clinical data (PASI change scores, percentage of adverse events, discontinuation rate) and utility scores were derived from clinical trials as well as from published evidence on Italian patients.</s><s>The perspective of the model is the Italian NHS, therefore only direct medical costs (drug prices, inpatient and outpatient hospital tariffs, etc.) were taken in account.</s><s>Both costs and benefits were discounted at 3% according to Italian National Guidelines for Health Economics Evaluations.</s><s>Incremental cost-effectiveness ratios (ICERs) were calculated.</s><s>Results: At 10 years, SEC300 is a dominant (less costly and more effective) option compared with UST45 and UST90.</s><s>It is a cost-effective option -with a threshold &lt; € 50,000/QALY gained as per National Health Economics Evaluation Guidelines -vs.</s><s>ADA, <ref type="bibr">IFN,</ref><ref type="bibr">ETA,</ref><ref type="bibr">and SOC with an ICERs of € 37,</ref><ref type="bibr">252,</ref><ref type="bibr">€ 48,</ref><ref type="bibr">949,</ref><ref type="bibr">€ 21,</ref><ref type="bibr">943 and € 41,</ref><ref type="bibr">896,</ref><ref type="bibr">respectively</ref>.</s><s>The sensitivity analysis demonstrated the robustness of model results.</s><s>ConClusions: The model shows that SEC300 is a cost-effective option when compared to other biologic agents and SOC currently funded by NHS in Italy for the treatment of moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PSS50 a coSt-eFFectiveneSS analySiS oF SecukinumaB 300 mg vS current tHeraPieS For tHe treatment oF moderate to Severe Plaque PSoriaSiS in italy</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">D'Ausilio A 1 , Aiello A 1 , Daniel F 1 , Graham C 2 , Roccia A 3 , Toumi M 4 1 Creativ</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PSS51 coSt-eFFectiveneSS analySiS oF SecukinumaB comPared to uStekinumaB in tHe treatment oF moderate to Severe Plaque PSoriaSiS in tHe czecH rePuBlic</head><p><s>Klimes J 1 , Mollon P 2 , Graham C 3 , Rajnoch J 1 , Dostal F 1 , Skalicky D 1 , Jordan P 1 , Depta J 2 1 Novartis, s.r.o., Prague, Czech Republic, 2 Novartis Pharma AG, Basel, Switzerland, 3 RTI Health Solutions, NC, NC, USA objeCtives: Secukinumab (SEC), an IL-17A antibody, is a new highly effective therapy for moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis (PSO).</s><s>Ustekinumab (UST) is reimbursed in the Czech Republic under the condition of ≥ PASI50 response at week 16.</s><s>We estimated the cost effectiveness of SEC vs. UST based on different PASI response (dis/continuation) criteria; PASI≥ 75 for SEC and PASI≥ 50 for UST.</s><s>Methods: A decision tree reflecting response to treatment <ref type="bibr">(PASI change &lt; 50,</ref><ref type="bibr">(75)</ref><ref type="bibr">(76)</ref><ref type="bibr">(77)</ref><ref type="bibr">(78)</ref><ref type="bibr">(79)</ref><ref type="bibr">(80)</ref><ref type="bibr">(81)</ref><ref type="bibr">(82)</ref><ref type="bibr">(83)</ref><ref type="bibr">(84)</ref><ref type="bibr">(85)</ref><ref type="bibr">(86)</ref><ref type="bibr">(87)</ref><ref type="bibr">(88)</ref><ref type="bibr">(89)</ref><ref type="bibr">(90)</ref><ref type="bibr">(90)</ref><ref type="bibr">(91)</ref><ref type="bibr">(92)</ref><ref type="bibr">(93)</ref><ref type="bibr">(94)</ref><ref type="bibr">(95)</ref><ref type="bibr">(96)</ref><ref type="bibr">(97)</ref><ref type="bibr">(98)</ref><ref type="bibr">(99)</ref><ref type="bibr">100)</ref> fed into a long-term Markov model with health states related to treatment continuation, dropout, and death.</s><s>Responders at week 16 (defined as PASI≥ 75 for SEC, PASI≥ 50 for UST) continued on biologic treatment.</s><s>Non-responders and drop-outs were switched to standard-of-care (MTX, CyA, emollients).</s><s>A health-care system perspective with 3% discount rate was adopted.</s><s>Dosing schedule for maintenance treatment for SEC and UST as 12.0 and 4.35 doses per year was calculated.</s><s>Baseline patient characteristics and efficacy data were derived from the CLEAR study, a head-to-head 52-week superiority trial (SEC 300 mg vs. UST 45/90 mg).</s><s>Long-term treatment resistance and dropout were modelled by assuming a 20% annual discontinuation rate.</s><s>Utility weights for each health state were calculated from EQ-5D measures from the SEC clinical program.</s><s>Results: With a 10-year time horizon, SEC treatment gains 0.05 QALYs and 0.80 years in PASI≥ 90 with € 144 in cost savings vs. UST, reflecting dominance of SEC vs. UST.</s><s>Absolute (discounted) QALYs, years in ≥ PASI90 and costs (discounted)</s></p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
