<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kröncke</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology and Neuroradiology</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Klinikum Augsburg</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Gynecology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<address>
									<postCode>86156</postCode>
									<settlement>Augsburg</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Med</forename><forename type="middle">Thomas</forename><surname>Pd</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Kröncke</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Prof. Dr. med</roleName><forename type="middle">Matthias</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">MBA Department of Diagnostic and Interventional Radiology</orgName>
								<address>
									<country>Neuroradiology Klinikum Augsburg Stenglinstraße</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Gynecology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin Campus Virchow-Klinikum Augustenburger Platz</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>13353</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">0016-5751</idno>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">DF01DDE8059ED0B10BB69EE42B1E116A</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1055/s-0035-1546000</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Treating myoma using MR-guided focused ultrasound surgery (MRgFUS; synonym: MR HIFU = high-intensity focused ultrasound) is a thermoablative procedure in which focused ultrasound, under constant MR tomographic monitoring, heats the treated tissue in individual small volume increments (sonications) until the planned fibroid volume has been completely denatured.</s><s>Upon completion of thermoablation, the control (contrast-enhanced MRI) indicates an absence of contrast enhancement in the treated tissue (i.e.</s><s>NPV = non-perfused volume).</s><s>The MRgFUS procedure is organ-preserving, noninvasive and can be performed on an outpatient basis.</s><s>This treatment method is provided by only a few specialized facilities.</s><s>The aim of MRgFUS therapy is the reduction or elimination of myoma-based symptoms among affected women.</s><s>Ultrasonic treatment can achieve shrinking of a fibroid.</s><s>Complete remission of the fibroid should not be expected and is not the goal of treatment.</s><s>There is a consensus between the disciplines of gynecology and radiology that determination of required treatment of uterine fibroids should be based on an examination and advice by a gynecologist.</s><s>Comprehensive advice regarding treatment options for symptomatic uterine fibroids encompasses not only medication-based and surgical options, but also non-surgical therapy options including uterine artery embolization (UAE) and MRgFUS.</s><s>The decision for or against an alternative therapy should be made taking into account the patientʼs desire for, and knowledge of, therapeutic alternatives, their chances of success and limita-tions, as well as typical side effects and possible complications (informed decision).</s><s>In Germany, Austria and Switzerland, the option of MRgFUS treatment offers the possibility of a therapeutic procedure for patients with myomarelated symptoms which provides further individualization of therapy in cases of uterine fibroids.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Aim of the Consensus Meeting</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>The intention of this second consensus meeting was the evaluation and integration of the MRgFUS procedure into the therapeutic spectrum of myoma treatment.</s><s>The 14 participants in the meeting of radiological-gynecological experts, after taking into account current literature and their own experience, and after extensive discussion, came to a consensus between the two disciplines.</s><s>The panel of experts was aware that this was an assessment of the possibilities and limits of a radiological therapy held in conjunction with specialists in gynecology who do not perform the procedure themselves, but who possess expertise and experience in the diagnosis as well as medication-based and surgical treatment of disorders of female reproductive organs.</s><s>The group of experts composed of 6 radiologists and 8 gynecologists met on January 17, 2015 in Berlin for the second radiological-gynecological consensus meeting regarding MRgFUS therapy included gynecologists from Switzerland and Austria.</s><s>After extensiveand somewhat controversialdiscussion, the group came to a consensus regarding the following recommendations.</s><s>The consensus statement is supported by the gynecologists * To be distinguished from non-MR-guided methods for the application of focused ultrasound.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Structural Prerequisites for the Performance of MRgFUS Therapy</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>MRgFUS should be performed only at clinics possessing the requisite expertise and experience with MRgFUS therapy.</s><s>This also includes non-surgical and surgical management of side effects and complications.</s><s>In addition, there should be options to initiate post-interventional pain management.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Examinations Required Prior to MRgFUS Therapy</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>The choice of therapy should be based on an examination performed by a gynecologist including vaginal and/or abdominal ultrasound (as a function of the size of the uterine fibroid).</s><s>A necessary prerequisite is the performance of a planning MRI using contrast medium (CM), in prone position if possible.</s><s>The contrastenhanced image is also used to assess whether, and to what degree, the fibroid is perfused.</s><s>Prior to each MRgFUS the indications for hysteroscopy and fractionated curettage must be critically reviewed with respect to bleeding pattern, endometrium thickness and structure.</s><s>Unremarkable cytological smear findings of the uterine cervix must have been obtained within the previous 12 months.</s><s>Likewise, prior to MRgFUS, within the context of the informed consent discussion, the patient should be informed regarding the absence of a pre-interventional histological confirmation of the presumed uterine fibroids, as is the case with all other organ-conserving myoma therapies (see also the statement of the DGGG [German Society of Gynecology and Obstetrics] "Implementation of the Medical Devices Act -Gynecological Morcellators" dated 08/29/2014).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Indications for MRgFUS Therapy</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>A symptomatic uterine fibroid is an indication for MRgFUS treatment.</s><s>The uterine fibroid must be in a position location that allows safe access to the myoma for the MRgFUS.</s><s>The presence of more than five myomas hinders the treatment.</s><s>In cases of myomas with a diameter greater than 10 cm, MRgFUS therapy should be critically reviewed due to the large volume of the myoma and resulting extended treatment time.</s><s>MRgFUS represents an alternative to surgical and medicationbased procedures as well as UAE.</s><s>The basis for the choice of therapy should be the aim of the treatment as well as the patientʼs desire.</s><s>Given technical feasibility, MRgFUS represents a good option for patients desiring a minimally-invasive procedure.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Success Criteria for MRgFUS Therapy</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>The goal of therapy using focused ultrasound should be the largest possible non-perfused volume (NPV).</s><s>The improvement or disappearance of myoma-related symptoms should be the result of successful MRgFUS treatment.</s><s>Although a reduction in volume is desired, it is considered a secondary therapeutic goal.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Contraindications for MRgFUS Therapy</head><p><s>! " Suspicion of malignancy (absolute) " Pregnancy (absolute) " Acute inflammatory process (absolute) " Pedunculated subserosal fibroids (absolute) " No sufficiently accessible acoustic window for treatment (e.g.</s><s>intestine in the planned path of the ultrasound beam) (absolute) " Uterine fibroids with more than 5 myomas (relative, case-bycase decision) " Uterine myomas with diameter greater than 10 cm (relative, case-by-case decision) " Large scars in acoustic window (relative) " Myoma in posterior wall or near os sacrum (relative) " General contraindications with respect to MR contrast media (relative) " Relative and absolute MRI contraindications Data regarding interactions between MRgFUS and ulipristal acetate is insufficient and requires additional studies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MRgFUS Therapy for Patients</head><p><s>Wishing to Become Pregnant !</s><s>Previous case reports indicate that pregnancy is possible after MRgFUS and can be successfully accomplished, but there are still insufficient data for a recommendation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Side Effects/Complications of MRgFUS Therapy</head><p><s>! Related side effects and complications during and after MRgFUS treatment are rare: " Pain " Skin burns " Inflammation of subcutaneous adipose tissue and musculature of the abdominal wall " Paresthesia of the leg due to nerve irritation or damage " Deep leg vein thrombosis (very rare) " Bowel perforation (extremely rare).</s><s>After therapy, tissue components may be discharged vaginally.</s><s>Increased and/or irregular bleeding may occur up to approx.</s><s>three months after treatment.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Post-treatment Examination after MRgFUS Therapy</head><p><s>! Post-treatment examination by a specialist is recommended approx.</s><s>6 months after MRgFUS.</s><s>Imaging procedures are useful (i.e.</s><s>sonography in conjunction with Doppler sonography, MRI).</s><s>Further clarification is required if the therapy is unsuccessful (no improvement of symptoms and/or size progression of the myoma), or there are abnormalities in the imaging (increase in size of myoma(s) or uterus).</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Magnetic Resonance Guided Focused Ultrasound* for Fibroid Treatment -Results of the Second Radiological Gynecological Expert Meeting Magnetresonanzgeführter fokussierter Ultraschall zur Myombehandlung -Ergebnisse des 2. radiologisch-gynäkologischen Expertentreffens and radiologists listed at the end of this work.</s><s>It reflects the current state of knowledge.</s></p></div></figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Kröncke T and David M. Magnetic Resonance Guided … Geburtsh Frauenheilk 2015; 75: 436-438</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outlook</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>Based upon available data and experience, a revision of recommendations for MRgFUS therapy of myomas is planned in about two years.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
