<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear Multiscale Regularisation in MR Elastography: Towards Fine Feature Mapping</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-06-04">June 4, 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Eric</forename><surname>Barnhill</surname></persName>
							<email>e.barnhill@sms.ed.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Clinical Research Imaging Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Medicine and Veterinary Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Edinburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>EH16 4TJ</postCode>
									<settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lyam</forename><surname>Hollis</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">College of Medicine and Veterinary Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">BHF Centre for Cardiovascular Science</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Edinburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>EH16 4TJ</postCode>
									<settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
									<region>YK</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ingolf</forename><surname>Sack</surname></persName>
							<email>ingolf.sack@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jürgen</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
							<email>juergen.braun@charite.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Charitéplatz 1</addrLine>
									<postCode>10117</postCode>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hoskins</surname></persName>
							<email>peter.hoskins@ed.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">College of Medicine and Veterinary Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">BHF Centre for Cardiovascular Science</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Edinburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>EH16 4TJ</postCode>
									<settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
									<region>YK</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Pankaj</forename><surname>Pankaj</surname></persName>
							<email>pankaj@ed.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">School of Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Edinburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>King&apos;s Buildings, Mayfield Road</addrLine>
									<postCode>EH9 3JL</postCode>
									<settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Colin</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
							<email>brown@mentholatum.co.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Research and Development</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The Mentholatum Company</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>G74 5PE</postCode>
									<settlement>East Kilbride</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Edwin</forename><forename type="middle">J R</forename><surname>Van Beek</surname></persName>
							<email>edwin-vanbeek@ed.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Clinical Research Imaging Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Medicine and Veterinary Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Edinburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>EH16 4TJ</postCode>
									<settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Neil</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
							<email>neil.roberts@ed.ac.uk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Clinical Research Imaging Centre</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">College of Medicine and Veterinary Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Edinburgh</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>EH16 4TJ</postCode>
									<settlement>Edinburgh</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Nonlinear Multiscale Regularisation in MR Elastography: Towards Fine Feature Mapping</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-06-04">June 4, 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">AB698370569927E781D25B5441530573</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.media.2016.05.012</idno>
					<note type="submission">Preprint submitted to Elsevier</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:27+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>elastography</term>
					<term>magnetic resonance elastography</term>
					<term>wave inversion</term>
					<term>complex dualtree wavelet</term>
					<term>denoising</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Fine-featured elastograms may provide additional information of radiological interest in the context of in vivo elastography.</s><s>Here a new image processing pipeline called ESP (Elastography Software Pipeline) is developed to create Magnetic Resonance Elastography (MRE) maps of viscoelastic parameters (complex modulus magnitude |G * | and loss angle φ) that preserve fine-scale information through nonlinear, multi-scale extensions of typical MRE postprocessing techniques.</s><s>Methods: A new MRE image processing pipeline was developed that incorporates wavelet-domain denoising, image-driven noise estimation, and feature detection.</s><s>ESP was first validated using simulated data, including viscoelastic Finite Element Method (FEM) simulations, at multiple noise levels.</s><s>ESP images were compared with MDEV pipeline images, both in the FEM models and in three ten-subject cohorts of brain, thigh, and liver acquisitions.</s><s>ESP and MDEV mean values were compared to 2D LFE mean values for the same cohorts as a benchmark.</s><s>Finally the proportion of spectral</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T A C C E P T E D M</head><p><s>A N U S C R I P T energy at fine frequencies was quantified using the Reduced Energy Ratio (RER) for both ESP and MDEV.</s><s>Results: Blind estimates of added noise (σ) were within 5.3% ± 2.6% of prescribed, and the same technique estimated σ in the in vivo cohorts at 1.7 ± 0.8%.</s><s>A 5 × 5 × 5 truncated Gabor filter bank effectively detects local spatial frequencies at wavelengths λ ≤ 10px.</s><s>For FEM inversions, mean |G * | of hard target, soft target, and background remained within 8% of prescribed up to σ = 20%, and mean φ results were within 10%, excepting hard target φ, which required redrawing around a ring artefact to achieve similar accuracy.</s><s>Inspection of FEM |G * | images showed some spatial distortion around hard target boundaries and inspection of φ images showed ring artefacts around the same target.</s><s>For the in vivo cohorts, ESP results showed mean correlation of R = 0.83 with MDEV and liver stiffness estimates within 7% of 2D-LFE results.</s><s>Finally, ESP showed statistically significant increase in fine feature spectral energy as measured with RER for both |G * | (p &lt; 1 × 10 −9 ) and φ (p &lt; 1 × 10 −3 ).</s><s>Conclusion: Information at finer frequencies can be recovered in ESP elastograms in typical experimental conditions, however scatter-and</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p><s>In the present study a new post-processing pipeline for the Magnetic Resonance Elastography (MRE) inversion problem, known as the Elastography Software Pipeline (ESP), was developed to enable fine-featured dual-parameter elasticity map reconstruction.</s><s>Soft tissue viscoelastic parameters are valuable diagnostic tools, and more finely featured viscoelastic property mapping would deliver additional information about the tissue under study that may be of Magnetic Resonance Elastography (MRE) <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">(Muthupillai et al., 1995)</ref> uses phase-contrast MRI imaging to measure tissue viscoelastic properties in vivo.</s></p><p><s>In a typical MRE experiment, steady-state wave propagation is induced in tissue using an external driver, and wave inversion is used to measure viscoelastic properties.</s><s>The most commonly reported result is a measure of tissue stiffness or elasticity, and some studies also report a second parameter of viscous dispersion.</s><s>Here the magnitude of the complex shear modulus |G * | is reported as a stiffness estimate, and phase angle of the complex modulus φ is reported as a viscosity estimate.</s><s>While phase angle technically measures the relationship between storage and loss moduli of the tissue, φ is commonly used as a viscosity measure since a value of 0 reflects a material with no viscosity, and a value of π 2 reflects a purely viscous material <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(Malkin and Isayev, 2006)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Increasing MRE resolution to map fine features in two parameters may enable new applications for non-invasive tissue analysis based on viscoelastic property measurements.</s><s>For example, the diffuse mechanical parameter alterations found in certain brain diseases <ref type="bibr" target="#b39">(Sack et al., 2013)</ref> can be mapped to regions of white or gray matter; or alterations in limb behaviour can be mapped to changes in specific intra-muscle structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Barnhill et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>However, rheological methods determine viscoelastic properties through wave inversion which is highly ill-posed and sensitive to noise <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Aster et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>MRE is well described by a mixed dense-sparse noise model, as it contains dense high and low frequency noise common to image processing <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Bertero and Boccacci, 2010)</ref>, as well as frequency-dependent sparse noise arising from the complexities of shear wave propagation in complex-boundaried materials.</s><s>As the first type of noise is stochastic while the second is structured and reproducible, such a pipeline must combine varied techniques to address these noise sources without sacrifice of bandwidth.</s></p><p><s>In the MRE literature a wide variety of filtering approaches are taken to reduce noise, including bandpass or other frequency-domain filtering <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(Klatt et al., 2007;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b28">Manduca et al., 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">Green et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">Honarvar et al., 2012</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">and Maniatty, 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">McGarry, 2013)</ref>, and derivative-fitting approaches such as binomial filtering <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Sinkus et al., 2000)</ref> or Savitsky-Golay filtering <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Manduca et al., 2001)</ref>.</s><s>All these filtering approaches require a priori windowing, which restricts results to features within a specified bandwidth.</s><s>Recovery of the finest features, however, requires preservation of the full bandwidth range.</s><s>This can be attained by multi-scale, non-linear denoising techniques including wavelet shrinkage <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Donoho and Johnstone, 1995;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Selesnick et al., 2005)</ref> and sparse approximation <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Aharon et al., 2006;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Chen and Selesnick, 2014)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The Elastography Software Pipeline (ESP) was developed to apply such techniques to preserve fine feature information in elastograms, with the aim of fine feature mechanical property recovery.</s><s>ESP accomplishes this with three steps:</s></p><p><s>• Denoising is performed in wavelet bases using shrinkage and sparsity promotion;</s></p><p><s>• Noise is estimated using adaptive, image-driven measurements;</s></p><p><s>• Multi-scale feature detection is incorporated into Helmholtz inversion using a bank of truncated Gabor filters.</s></p><p><s>The new features in the pipeline were tested with analytic and Finite Element Method (FEM) data at varying noise levels and the pipeline was then applied to ten-subject cohorts of brain, liver, and thigh muscle.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Pipeline</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.1.">Overview</head><p><s>ESP first phase unwraps the data using a 4D Laplacian-based algorithm described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Barnhill et al. (2014)</ref>.</s><s>ESP then applies two denoising methods not previously applied to MRE: a divergence-free-wavelet Hodge decomposition with</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T Phase Wrap</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Low-frequency dense noise</head><p><s>High-frequency dense noise</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Structured noise from wave motion</head><p><s>Laplacian-Based Unwrap [1]   Divergence-Free Wavelet (DFW) Decomposition [2]   Complex Dual-Tree Wavelet (CDTW) Denoise [3]   MDEV inversion [4]   N/A SureShrink [5]   Overlapping Group Sparsity (OGS) [6]   Magnitude of complex Gabor filter bank response N/A Median Absolute Deviation [7]   Principal Component Analysis (PCA) patchbased noise estimate [8]   N/A  SureShrink thresholding <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Ong et al., 2014)</ref>, and a complex dual-tree wavelet denoising <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Selesnick et al., 2005)</ref> with Overlapping Group Sparsity (OGS) thresholding <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Chen and Selesnick, 2014)</ref>.</s><s>For handling sparse noise, ESP then applies an overdetermination-based method from the MRE literature known as the MDEV equations <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">(Papazoglou et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>However, ESP applies a newly designed filter bank to extend the MDEV equations so that local directional spatial frequency information is used to weight the inversion at each voxel.</s><s>ESP's methodological components are summarised in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">1</ref> and described in more detail below.</s><s>Noise standard deviation is described below as % of maximum signal.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.2.">Removal of low frequency dense noise (e.g. bulk waves)</head><p><s>MRE possesses several slowly-varying noise sources, including phase field biases, rigid body motion, and bulk wave motion: as soft tissue is not fully incompressible, shear vibration of tissue also produces bulk waves which are an order of magnitude longer than shear waves.</s><s>Bulk waves have been shown</s></p><p><s>to impact shear wave measurements and therefore cannot be neglected <ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(Sinkus et al., 2000)</ref>.</s><s>Techniques used to handle bulk waves in other studies include</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_1">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><p><s>high-pass filtering <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Klatt et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b32">McGarry, 2013)</ref> or the inversion of x and y gradients <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(Hirsch et al., 2014)</ref>.</s><s>As bulk waves are divergent, one common technique is application of a Helmholtz-Hodge decomposition (HHD) to the MRE acquisition with retention of only the rotational component <ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(Sinkus et al., 2005a;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Honarvar et al., 2013)</ref>.</s><s>However, from a signal processing standpoint, the implementation of an HHD to heterogeneous data is not straightforward as sharp edges such as anatomical boundaries will have high divergence and errors will propagate through the image <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Ong et al., 2014)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>In ESP a 3D divergence-free wavelet <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">(Ong et al., 2014)</ref> is applied to eliminate dense low-frequency noise.</s><s>The technique makes use of the contrast between the large, sparse divergence coefficients of edges and the small, dense divergence coefficients of low frequency noise sources such as bulk waves and rigid body motion, thresholding the non-divergence free coefficients to suppress small values and retain large ones.</s><s>Image noise is estimated with median absolute deviation (MAD) and thresholds are determined with SureShrink <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Donoho and Johnstone, 1995)</ref>.</s><s>For validation, analysis and comparison with similar denoising algorithms, we refer the reader to <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">Ong et al. (2014)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>2.1.3.</s><s>Removal of high frequency dense noise (e.g.</s><s>sensor noise)</s></p><p><s>Correct high-frequency denoising is critical to avoid parameter overestimation from oversmoothing, parameter underestimation from insufficient noise removal, and feature loss in both cases.</s><s>The features to be denoised span all scales of the image and extend in arbitrary directions within the 3D volumetric space.</s><s>In ESP, images are denoised using a 3D complex dual-tree wavelet (CDTW) transform <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Selesnick et al., 2005)</ref>.</s><s>The CDTW is reported to be "an optimal representation" <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">(Selesnick et al., 2005)</ref>  separately along the Z axis and in the XY plane, as the noise profile along the Z axis can be quite different due to interslice phase discontinuities <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(Murphy et al., 2012)</ref>.</s><s>Image noise σ is estimated with a Principal Component Analysis (PCA) patch-based single image blind noise estimation technique <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(Liu et al., 2013)</ref> and this result is used to set the OGS sparsity enforcement term.</s><s>A calibration test was used to determine a relationship between detected noise level σ and sparsity enforcement term λ expected to de-noise the image below a value of σ = 0.05%, and this is described below in Experiments.</s><s>However, otherwise our procedure is identical to <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Chen and Selesnick (2014)</ref> in all respects and that paper can be consulted for algorithm comparison and sensitivity analysis.</s></p><p><s>λ is not a hard or soft threshold, but is used to separate high and low magnitude coefficients after the sparsification of the overlapping groups.</s><s>Given the findings of basis optimality reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b40">Selesnick et al. (2005)</ref> and the OGS analysis found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Chen and Selesnick (2014)</ref>, the technique can be expected to provide adaptive denoising for a range of noise levels in the image.</s><s>The propagation of acoustic waves through complex-boundaried soft tissue produces several sources of noise such as standing wave nodes, wave scattering and mode conversion.</s><s>(While these noise sources result from violation of the assumptions of the Helmholtz inversion, rather than sensor noise, they still fit the standard signal processing definition of noise as unwanted signal.)</s><s>These noise sources are irregularly placed and sparse in the input.</s><s>Further, as their location is frequency-dependent, they will be highly sparse in an acquisition overdetermined at multiple frequencies.</s><s>The MDEV equations, first described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b37">Papazoglou et al. (2012)</ref>, extend the Algebraic Helmholtz Inversion (AHI)</s></p><p><s>or Direct Inversion (DI) approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">(Papazoglou et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b30">Manduca et al., 2001)</ref>.</s><s>AHI uses simplifying assumptions of isotropy and local homogeneity to As tissue shear modulus values show frequency-dependence following a power law <ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(Szabo, 1995)</ref>, the combining of the |G * | results at various frequencies is a source of error.</s><s>MDEV accepts this error for the benefits of over-determining the tissue displacement matrix prior to inversion, which allows for the resolution of wave-related noise without sacrifice of bandwidth.</s><s>Such error is not present in the φ calculation which is, per the springpot model, expected to remain constant at all frequencies <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(Sinkus et al., 2005b)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>2.1.5.</s><s>Multi-Scale Feature Detection / Gabor-Weighted Inversion AHI and MDEV require estimation of the Laplacian and, as in the denoising techniques above, the estimator will favour particular frequencies if the estimation window is kept fixed.</s><s>Here the scale of the inversion is made responsive</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_2">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><p><s>to the features in the image through incorporation of Gabor filter bank results into the MDEV equations.</s></p><p><s>Complex Gabor filters are effective multi-scale feature detectors <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Gonzalez and Woods, 2002)</ref>: similarity between image wavelength λ and Gabor filter tuning φ results in a high magnitude response when the two images are convolved, while λ more distant from φ results in a lower magnitude response.</s><s>A Gabor filter combines a particular spatial frequency with directional smoothing appropriate to that frequency, and this provides the needed components for a Gabor Weighted Inversion (GWI).</s><s>In the GWI, the image is convolved with each filter in the bank; the magnitude response is used as a voxel-wise weighting; and the directionally smoothed image, along with its Laplacian, are incorporated into the inversion equations, weighted by magnitude response at each voxel.</s></p><p><s>The weighting ensures that the inversion is not simply the average of differently smoothed images: each voxel will have high response to the filters that detect spatial frequencies at that location, and low response to the other filters.</s></p><p><s>If this response is used as a weight, each voxel will effectively be inverted at its appropriate scale and not at other scales.</s></p><p><s>This result can be accomplished by extending the MDEV equations to incorporate the directionally smoothed images, the directionally smoothed Laplacians, and the voxel-wise weighting for each.</s><s>For example, inversion of an acquisition of four frequencies with 3D displacements would previously have combined 4 × 3 = 12 results using the MDEV equations.</s><s>However if the Gabor bank contains 64 filters the inversion now combines 12 × 64 results using the MDEV equations.</s><s>The MDEV |G * | equation (4a in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Braun et al. (2013)</ref>) thus expands to</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_3">|G * | = ρ 3 m=1 N n=1 π 2 Φ=− π 2 π 2 θ=− π 2 d 2 ν=1 ω 2 n |û * mnφθν (ω n )|w mnφθν 3 m=1 N n=1 π 2 Φ=− π 2 π 2 θ=− π 2 d 2 ν=1 |∇ 2 û * mnφθν (ω n )|w mnφθν (1)</formula><p><s>with Φ pitch, θ yaw, and ν the bandwidth of the directional smoothing, û the directionally smoothed complex wavefield, ∇ 2 û the Laplacian of this field,</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_4">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><p><s>and w the corresponding voxel wise Gabor magnitude weighting.</s><s>Similarly the equation for φ (4b in the same paper) expands to:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_5">φ=acos − m n Φ θ ν [ ( ûm) (∇ 2 ûmnφθν )+ (u mnφθν ) (∇ 2 ûmnφθν ) ] w mnφθν m n Φ θ ν | û * mnφθν (ωn)||∇ 2 û * mnφθν (ωn)|w mnφθν (2)</formula><p><s>The drawback to this approach is that estimation of large wavelengths λ typically requires a Gabor filter with wide support.</s><s>The GWI strikes a balance between these concerns by truncating the Gabor filters.</s><s>This trade-off reduces the ability of the filter to differentiate large λ, but increases the spatial resolution of the inversion.</s><s>As the interest of the paper is in the development of fine-featured elastograms, a truncated filter bank was designed to aid detection and inversion of the desired finer features, without underweighting coarse features.</s><s>The appropriate truncation level, and filter bank size, for the goals of the pipeline is determined in an experiment described in Section 2.3 below.</s></p><p><s>In the filter bank, smoothing along the filter's major axis is set at the "optimal" σ = 2 3 θ, with σ the Gaussian kernel and θ the cosine function bandwidth <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Clausi and Jernigan, 2000)</ref>.</s><s>Minor axis support was set at σ = 0.65px, effectively setting a support of one pixel along both minor axes to maximise fineness of feature detection along the major axis <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Gonzalez and Woods, 2002)</ref>.</s><s>As the minor axes were symmetric, roll was left stationary; as the magnitude of the response was retained, phase offset was left at zero.</s><s>Pa for the background and two inclusions respectively and expected φ of 0.127, 0.250, and 0.057 radians respectively.</s><s>These stiffness values were first verified with caliper measurements at all frequencies using the caliperbased wave measurement technique in e.g.</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Bensamoun et al. (2007)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Barnhill et al. (2013)</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Acquisitions</head><p><s>In Vivo cohorts Three cohorts of healthy volunteers were analysed with ESP.</s></p><p><s>All acquisitions were axial:</s></p><p><s>1.</s><s>A cohort of ten healthy volunteer abdomens, full field MRE acquisitions, vibrated at seven frequencies (30:5:60 Hz), using a single-shot SE-EPI sequence with FoV of 320×260mm 2 , ten slices, and isotropic 2.5mm 3 voxels on a 1.5T scanner (Magnetom Sonata; Siemens Erlangen, Germany) with piezoelectric actuator and acquisition details as described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">Guo et al. (2014)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>2. A cohort of ten healthy volunteer brains, full field MRE acquisitions, vibrated at seven frequencies (30:5:60 Hz), using a single-shot SE-EPI sequence with FoV of 176 × 192mm 2 , 15 slices, and isotropic 1.9mm 3 voxels on a 3T scanner (Trio, Siemens, Erlangen, Germany) with a head cradle actuator and acquisition details as described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">Guo et al. (2013)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>3. A cohort of ten healthy volunteer thigh muscles, full field MRE acquisitions, vibrated at four frequencies (25:12.5:62.5 Hz) SE-EPI sequence on a 3T scanner (Verio, Siemens, Erlangen, Germany) with FoV of 336 × 336mm 2 , 5 slices, and isotropic 3mm 3 voxels using a ring actuator as described in <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Barnhill et al. (2013)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>All acquisitions were approved by the relevant ethics boards.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M</head><p><s>A N U S C R I P T</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Experiments</head><p><s>Noise detection and testing To evaluate noise detection and denoising techniques, three experiments were performed.</s><s>Using the FEM simulation set described above, image noise σ was progressively added from 0 to 10% using the MATLAB (Mathworks, Natick, MA) randn function.</s><s>Then:</s></p><p><s>• In order to establish the accuracy of the PCA noise detection in the context of MRE, the PCA-based noise detection technique was applied to estimate the σ of the simulated MRE data.</s></p><p><s>• PCA noise detection was then applied to the three acquisition cohorts described above, to estimate in vivo σ.</s></p><p><s>• Finally, images were denoised using different levels of the OGS sparsity enforcement parameter λ to evaluate the lowest λ that reduces noise to ≤ 0.05%, for the σ levels detected in the cohorts.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Truncated Gabor filter frequency detection test</head><p><s>To investigate the frequency detection capacity of truncated Gabor filters, 1D spatial frequency data with λ ranging from 1 to 32px were convolved with 1D complex Gabor filters with tunings φ from 1 to 32 px, truncated to several different sizes.</s><s>The responses were used to choose a truncated support size for the bank.</s><s>A cut-off frequency also had to be chosen for the bank so that cumulatively for the bank, there was equal total response to all frequencies, to avoid specific frequencies being over-weighted in the inversion.</s><s>Comparison of in vivo cohorts The FEM results were followed with qualitative and quantitative comparisons of both inversion pipelines with in vivo acquisitions.</s><s>The qualitative approach is presentation and inspection of images: an exemplar image is presented and discussed in terms of features of interest.</s><s>Then two quantitative comparisons are made.</s><s>The first is calculation of means and standard deviations, discussed more in the next section.</s><s>Second is a quantitative evaluation of the proportion of image spectral energy at finer frequencies, the Reduced Energy Ratio (RER) <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Lee et al., 2009)</ref>, commonly used as a metric of image sharpness in computational photography.</s><s>RER quantifies image sharpness by measuring the ratio of selected (i.e.</s><s>reduced) higher frequency bands to the DC value of a discrete cosine transform (DCT) within 8 × 8 overlapping blocks.</s><s>Here we extend the procedure of <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Lee et al., 2009)</ref> to three dimensions due to the volumetric nature of the image, but retaining the suggested frequency bands in that paper, using frequencies above the DC but within radius 5 as the critical band.</s><s>We refer the reader to <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Lee et al., 2009)</ref> for further discussion of the method including robustness and sensitivity analysis.</s><s>Finally as the method operates on 8 × 8 × 8 blocks, the</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Comparative inversion of FEM simulations with added noise</head><formula xml:id="formula_6">A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</formula><p><s>values at boundaries were unreliable.</s><s>Consequently RER was calculated by manually masking the images 8 voxels away from external (skull for brain, air for thigh muscle, other organs for liver) and internal (ventricles for brain, bone for thigh muscle) boundaries.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cohort comparison of mean values of ESP, MDEV and LFE methods</head><p><s>We also compare mean values of ESP and MDEV results with mean values of results using the LFE method <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">(Manduca et al., 2001;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b24">Knutsson et al., 1994)</ref> as made available in the MRE-WAVE (Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA) software package.</s><s>LFE is widely used and is a useful benchmark for range and stability of ESP results.</s><s>However, LFE operates on singlefrequency data, and requires manually verified masking as well as several manual settings.</s><s>Consequently a full comparison of pipeline results is outside the scope of this paper and we only use summary statistics of the results as a benchmark.</s><s>For LFE, 3D (i.e.</s><s>full-field) displacements were unwrapped with a minimum-discontinuity algorithm, filtered with a 4th order Butterworth bandpass filter with default cutoffs (2.5 and 40 waves/FOV), and inverted with 2D LFE.</s><s>As LFE is single frequency, the 50Hz acquisition was used in all cases.</s><s>As LFE produces no φ image, only ESP and MDEV were compared for φ results.</s><s>Finally, it should be noted that LFE stiffness more closely approximates |G * | when G" is low, but diverges as G" increases.</s><s>The manual masks generated with MRE-WAVE were used to mask the elastograms in all three pipelines, and mean value and standard deviation for each subject in each pipeline was measured.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Blind Noise Estimation</head><p><s>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">2</ref> shows results for the three de-noising experiments.</s><s>In panel (a), estimated σ differs by 5.3% ± 2.6% from actual added σ.</s><s>In panel (b), the same method is then used to measure the noise of the in vivo cohorts.</s><s>In vivo image noise is estimated at 1.7 ± 0.8%, suggesting that resolution similar to the</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p><s>FEM 2% test case will be present in in vivo acquisitions.</s><s>Finally, the FEM simulation images have noise added, then are de-noised with varying levels of the OGS sparsity enforcement parameter λ.</s><s>As shown in panel (c), at values of ≈ 2%, that is to say, the estimated noise levels of the cohort, the image is effectively de-noised, that is to say, noise levels are reduced to &lt; 0.05%, when λ = 0.3σ.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">GWI Frequency Detection</head><p><s>Figure <ref type="figure">3</ref> shows the set of 1D vectors at stepped wavelengths λ of 1 to 32 px, as well as the magnitude of the Gabor response to each wavelength from a bank of Gabor filters with tunings θ of 1 to 32 px.</s><s>The Gabor response graph for 'full' shows the response of fully-supported filters, here set to a support of 3 standard deviations.</s><s>The maximum response values are on the diagonal of the graph.</s><s>This shows the expected result, that is, data at wavelength λ produced the highest response in filters where tuning θ = λ.</s></p><p><s>As the bank is progressively truncated in panels (c-f), the bank still differentiates finer λ, but the response of the bank to coarser λ becomes more uniform.</s></p><p><s>The result is a trade-off between support size (with a larger support combining a larger region of values, limiting image resolution) and sufficient scaling for coarse wavelengths.</s><s>For the FEM and in vivo cohorts, a 5 × 5 × 5 truncation, enabling appropriately scaled inversion of features λ ≤ 10px, was chosen.</s></p><p><s>As the 5 × 5 × 5 truncated bank produces a uniform weighting for λ ≥ 10px when θ ≥ 10px, coarser λ will be overweighted unless a cut-off θ was chosen for the bank that produced equal total Gabor magnitude response for each λ.</s><s>This was done by looking at the cumulative filter bank response as larger θ filters are added to the bank, and the results are shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">4</ref>.</s><s>The cut-off θ that produced the most similar total magnitude response, for the whole inversion, at all λ, was 12px as seen in panel (b).</s><s>Since the kernels in the bank needed to be of odd dimensions, the final bank consisted of 5 × 5 × 5 truncated Gabor filters with support sizes <ref type="bibr">[3,</ref><ref type="bibr">5,</ref><ref type="bibr">7,</ref><ref type="bibr">9,</ref><ref type="bibr">11]</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p><s>To visualise the filter's impact an illustration of the response of small and large truncated θ filters on a slice of brain MRE data is shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">5</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Simulation Noise Test</head><p><s>With the filter bank chosen, the FEM test data were processed with the ESP pipeline at the varying noise levels listed in Methods and compared to the MDEV pipeline.</s><s>Figure <ref type="figure">6</ref> shows displacement and inversion images for the chosen noise levels for both MDEV and ESP. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">7</ref> plots mean and standard deviation for hard target, soft target, and background material.</s></p><p><s>For MDEV |G * |, noise-free estimates for hard target, soft target and background were 81%, 110% and 99% of prescribed respectively.</s><s>The values decreased with increasing noise, such that in the 20% noise case, values were 33%, 72% and 60% of noise-free estimates respectively.</s><s>For ESP |G * |, noise-free estimates for hard target, soft target and background were 98%, 108% and 103% of noise-free estimates respectively.</s><s>The values remained similar through the 20% noise case, with noise values 94%, 105%, and 99% of noise-free estimates respectively.</s><s>Qualitatively, some artefacts can be seen.</s><s>MDEV inversion retains shape of targets accurately, but ESP shows some shape distortion as noise level increases.</s></p><p><s>For MDEV φ, noise-free estimates for hard target, soft target and background were 620%, 109% and 110% of prescribed respectively.</s><s>In the 20% noise case, values were 187%, 117% and 196% of noise-free estimates respectively.</s><s>For ESP φ, noise-free estimates for hard target, soft target and background were 491%, 102% and 107% of noise-free estimates respectively.</s><s>The values remained similar through the 20% noise case, with noise values 120%, 87%, and 101% of noise-free estimates respectively.</s><s>Qualitatively, bright rings are seen in the φ values around the hard target.</s><s>Noting that clinical liver MRE often uses manually drawn ROIs <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">(Mariappan et al., 2010)</ref>, a smaller region was drawn post-hoc in the hard target avoiding the artefactual rings.</s><s>In the post-hoc ROI, estimates of hard target φ dropped to 247% for MDEV and 105% for ESP.</s></p><p><s>For visualisation of the impact of the denoising methods, Figure <ref type="figure">8</ref> illustrates    <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">1 and Table 2</ref>.</s><s>All three methods are significantly (p &lt; 0.01) correlated in liver (R = 0.79, 0.88 and 0.77).</s><s>ESP and MDEV show a significant correlation (p &lt; 0.01) in all cohorts but no significant correlations to LFE in brain or muscle.</s><s>ESP showed consistently higher results than MDEV (16%, 55% and 32% for brain, liver, and thigh, respectively), while LFE did not show a consistent relationship to the values of the other two methods, being higher than both in brain, similar to ESP in liver, and lower than both in muscle.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary statistics for three-pipeline comparison</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.5.">Reduced Energy Ratio (RER) Analysis</head><p><s>Results for the RER comparison of the ESP and MDEV pipelines are shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">12</ref>.</s><s>Using a two-tailed t test, ESP significantly increases the RER for both the |G * | (p &lt; 1 × 10 −9 ) and φ (p &lt; 1 × 10 −3 ) maps.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Noise and artefact in ESP and MDEV: FEM Results</head><p><s>The FEM testing suggests that fine features can indeed be recovered with ESP, even at SNR levels much lower than that found in vivo, but with some limitations.</s><s>For |G * |, the FEM hard target showed some spatial distortion while the φ targets showed artefactual rings, particularly around the hard target.</s><s>Nonetheless, ESP recovered values within 8% of prescribed, at SNR levels substantially lower than that found in vivo, except in the case of hard target φ, and in this case, when the ROI was manually drawn rather than automatically chosen from the prescribed scheme, values also were within 5%.</s></p><p><s>In both cases of noticeable artefact -the hard target shape distortion in This is likely a benefit of the MDEV pipeline's band-pass approach, in which the fine spatial frequencies from the scattering are well suppressed by the Butterworth filter, leaving only spatial frequencies that correspond to propagation rather than scattering.</s><s>As ESP retains information along the entire available frequency spectrum, it may be susceptible to scattering from hard areas within a volume.</s><s>However, no such shape distortion is shown between the soft target and background material in ESP, suggesting that, as discussed for MDEV above, under the conditions and stiffness levels present in in vivo MRE, this is unlikely to be a concern.</s><s>This conclusion was supported further by qualitiative inspection of the in vivo images, which showed good spatial correspondence between elastogram features and features as seen on a T2 image.</s><s><ref type="bibr">et al., 1994)</ref>.</s><s>As MDEV uses only a compact-windowed Laplacian operator, this may explain its slightly lower values.</s></p><p><s>One weakness in this analysis is that LFE contains many manual settings, which were left to defaults when possible.</s><s>It is possible that tuning of the setting for each cohort, and indeed for each image, may have produced more correlated results in all three pipelines.</s><s>LFE did not show high correlation values with ESP or MDEV in brain or thigh.</s><s>This may relate to the default 2D approach of LFE, particularly in brain where waves are highly reverberant in all three dimensions.</s><s>Similar concerns may pertain to muscle although other 2D approaches to axial thigh images have produced similar values to this study <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Klatt et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Barnhill, 2013;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">Guo et al., 2015)</ref>.</s><s>Overall, such operatordependent choices are difficult to objectify and consequently we use the means from default LFE results for a benchmark comparison only.</s></p><p><s>The RER quantifies a statistically significant increase in fine frequency spectral energy found in ESP images as compared with MDEV.</s><s>The requirement of 8 × 8 × 8 blocks created variance at sharp boundaries so that some regions of anatomy were excluded.</s><s>However the finding of increased fine frequency activity in ESP was highly robust and the measurement was likely not confounded by this.</s><s>The statistical significance was lower in the φ map and this can be attributed to the increasing image noise resulting from φ scattering.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</head><p><s>Results from all three pipelines are available on request to interested researchers for further inspection, and a copy of the ESP pipeline as Matlab code can be obtained by contacting CRIC at the University of Edinburgh.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Sparsification and Phase Noise</head><p><s>Here our calibration of sparsity enforcement parameter λ resulted in reduction of estimated noise levels to ≤ 0.05%.</s><s>This is higher than the results for speech denoising reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">Chen and Selesnick (2014)</ref>, in which noisy signals are reduced to noise levels of σ = 3 × 10 −4 .</s><s>However, the above-mentioned improvement in RER suggests that this denoising takes place without loss of fine feature information, but rather improves its retention as compared to MDEV, and is therefore sufficient in the MRE context.</s></p><p><s>SNR is likely to change across the image in relation to wave amplitude, with SNR decreasing as the wave amplitude decreases from damping.</s><s>The independent sparsification of each overlapping group is expected to be responsive to this variance, however, the de-noising for each slice is still calibrated to a single SNR value, and future work will address this limitation.</s><s>As the FEM simulation used uniform noise parameters for each image, they did not address this issue directly, though it is noteworthy that ESP remained robust through a wide range of noise without changing any settings.</s><s>As each overlapping group is de-noised independently one likely avenue for future work is the use of an SNR map of the image to adaptively determine λ of each individual group.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1: Summary of noise removal steps in the ESP pipeline.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>of sparse noise / clutter (e.g.</s><s>low signal areas from standing wave nodes)</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>determine the complex shear modulus G * of a Fourier-transformed wave field U (x, y, z).</s><s>MDEV resolves sparse noise in AHI by overdetermination, pixel-wise averaging the complex modulus magnitude |G * | and loss angle φ across frequencies in a multi-frequency acquisition.</s><s>(Other approaches to MRE inversion that include multi-frequency based overdetermination can be found in<ref type="bibr" target="#b22">Klatt et al. (2007)</ref> and<ref type="bibr" target="#b21">Honarvar et al. (2013)</ref>).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>FEM simulations were used to verify accuracy of the ESP parameter recovery, including stiffness values of elastogram regions, and robustness to noise.Following testing, the pipeline was applied to three in vivo cohorts.Finite Element SimulationsFinite Element Method simulations (Thomas-Seale et al., 2011) within the ABAQUS software package (Simulia Corp., Providence, Rhode Island, USA) were used to verify the accuracy of ESP's parameter recovery in varied noise conditions.</s><s>The model was designed A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T with background material of 3200 Pa stiffness, one soft target at 1600 Pa, and one hard target at 7200 Pa.</s><s>The material was modelled as a Voigt solid, G * = µ + iωη, with η of 1 P a • s, and the solid was vibrated at four frequencies, 50, 60, 70, and 80 Hz, for an expected averaged loss modulus of 408 Pa.</s><s>This produced expected |G * | of 3226 Pa, 1651 Pa and 7211</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>The FEM simulated wave images were inverted at six different Gaussian noise levels: 0, 1, 2, 3, 5, 10 and 20 percent.</s><s>(Including 20% resulted in a noise level range of 46 to 16 dB which is comparable to a high-impact denoising paper such as<ref type="bibr" target="#b11">Dabov et al. (2009)</ref> in which a range of 35-17 dB was used.)</s><s>The volumes were manually segmented into soft target, hard target, and background using the original simulation settings.</s><s>The ROIs were measured A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T for mean and standard deviation in |G * | and φ at each noise level, and the images were inspected for retention of fineness of target boundaries.ESP results were compared with a previously published multi-frequency analysis pipeline.</s><s>Here it is useful to make a distinction between the MDEV equations, which are used and extended in ESP, and the MDEV method, an inversion pipeline that uses alternate phase unwrapping and denoising techniques.</s><s>In the present study ESP is compared with the MDEV method as described in<ref type="bibr" target="#b44">Streitberger et al. (2014)</ref>, which combines a gradient-based phase unwrap, 4th order Butterworth low-pass filter, and unweighted averaging of frequencies and components in the MDEV equations.</s><s>Both methods are used to invert the FEM simulations at the six noise levels.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 2 :Figure 3 :</head><label>23</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2: Testing of noise estimators and denoising parameters.</s><s>Panel (a) shows that the PCA-based noise estimation technique identifies added noise in an FEM MRE simulation to within 5.3% ± 2.6% of prescribed.</s><s>Panel (b) shows the same technique applied to the 30 cohorts in the study; estimated σ in the cohorts is 1.7 ± 0.8%.</s><s>Panel (c) compares different de-noising levels, in terms of OGS sparsity enforcement parameter λ, by estimating remaining noise after denoising with OGS.</s><s>Added noise is reduced to σ &lt; 0.05%, at the levels of noise detected in the cohorts, when λ is set at 0.3σ.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4: Cut-off for equal total frequency response for truncated Gabor bank.</s><s>(a) Cumulative magnitude response for each λ was measured for each possible cutoff θ.</s><s>(b) The filter bank with the most equal response across all λ (as measured by normalised SD) was chosen for the cut-off of the bank.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="21,268.89,488.72,148.34,111.26" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5: Illustration of Gabor feature detection in in vivo samples.</s><s>All filters, image volumes and convolutions are full 3D in the pipeline, and slices are shown only for demonstration.</s><s>(a) Central slice of real component of 3D filter, yaw π 4 , pitch 0, high and low spatial frequencies.</s><s>(b) Truncation of filters to 5px compact support.</s><s>(c) Magnitude of filter response in a slice of brain.</s><s>The high-frequency filter responds to fine features, with brighter values at interfaces, and the lowfrequency filter responds to coarse features, with brighter values at homogeneous tissue regions.Highest response is in the direction of the filter.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="23,163.08,434.89,100.30,119.41" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 7: Plot of summary statistics for the FEM noise test.</s><s>The MDEV pipeline shows sensitivity to noise while the ESP pipeline stays robust up to 20% noise.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="25,118.02,151.32,334.47,221.89" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure 8 :Figure 9 :</head><label>89</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 8: Illustration of ESP denoising results on central slice of an axial thigh muscle acqusition.</s><s>Images (a) is phase-unwrapped but not denoised.</s><s>To compare with other image processing pipelines, (b) shows denoising results for a 4th order Butterworth low-pass filter with cutoff of 10mm.</s><s>The remaining images show ESP methods.</s><s>(c) shows the impact of the divergence-free wavelet.</s><s>(d) shows the additional impact of the OGS denoising.</s><s>To study the denoising results a vertical plot line was drawn across heterogeneous tissue features in the image.</s><s>Comparison of the dark red and dark green lines shows the increase in detail from ESP's multiscale filtering (red) as opposed to lowpass filtering (green), even as both produce data sufficiently smoothed for wave inversion.</s><s>Below the plot, subtraction images from (a) are shown for each de-noising step.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="26,194.91,418.08,66.87,66.87" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 10 :Figure 11 :</head><label>1011</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 10: Example images of viscoelasticity parameter φ (in Radians) for the same three organs as Figure 9 above.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="28,314.80,286.34,76.90,75.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Figure 12 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 12: Reduced Energy Ratio (RER) comparison for ESP and MDEV pipelines.</s><s>ESP shows a statistically significant increase in spectral energy at finer frequencies for both |G * | and φ.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>4. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Details And Values In Three Inversion Pipelines: In Vivo Results For |G * | in vivo, ESP and MDEV showed good correlation.</s><s>While both methods use the same inversion equations, they use entirely different filtering A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T and phase unwrapping techniques, and the correlation between images suggests that both denoising methods deliver accurate assessment of the relative viscoelastic properties of anatomical structures.</s><s>In φ, results were mixed, with high R for brain, low R for liver and moderate R for thigh.</s><s>Inspection of the φ maps in Figure 10 suggests that as ESP picks up more details, it gains high scatter-related values, increasing and decorrelating the results from those of the MDEV pipeline.</s><s>The close correlation between ESP and LFE in liver was striking, and a further validation of the utility of MRE for liver stiffness measurement.</s><s>MDEV correlated to both but remained at lower values.</s><s>What ESP and LFE share, that MDEV does not, is the use of multiple scales in the inversion (Knutsson</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>ESP holds promise as a software tool for fine-featured MRE images.</s><s>The chief goal of ESP was the inversion of MRE data while preserving the complete bandwidth of the image.</s><s>This required denoising in wavelet bases using nonlinear thresholding techniques, combination of results at multiple frequencies, and the incorporation of Gabor-based feature detection to invert features at their appropriate scales.</s><s>The new pipeline produced a significant increase in Reduced Energy Ratio (RER) for both viscoelastic parameters, suggesting betterA C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P Tretention of the fine range of spatial frequencies, though FEM testing showed that some of the fine-frequency information may be scattering or inhomogeneity artefact.</s><s>Also FEM testing showed more accurate measurement than MDEV with coarse spatial frequencies, suggesting that the techniques incorporated into ESP improve spatial frequency estimation at both ends of the spectrum.The combination of FEM and RER results suggest that at the estimated noise levels of in vivo cohorts of brain, abdomen or thigh muscle, ESP can be expected to retain fine features and wider stiffness contrasts, while removing noise and clutter from known MRE noise sources, and this assertion is supported by qualitative inspection of in vivo results.</s><s>Further, ESP shows overall good correlation with the related MDEV pipeline, and in liver produces results similar in value to the 2D LFE inversion method.A C C E P T ED M A N U S C R I P T that of neurological disorders, cardio MRE and MRE of the liver.</s><s>He has over 90 refereed publications, several awards, 2 granted and 7 pending patents.</s><s>Peter R Hoskins Prof. Peter Hoskins studied Physics at Oxford University graduating in 1980.</s><s>He has been in Edinburgh for 30 years initially as a Hospital Physicist in the National Health Service where he became Consultant Physicist in 1998.</s><s>He moved to Edinburgh University in 2006 and is currently Professor of Medical Physics and Biomechanics.</s><s>He was awarded a PhD in 1990 for work on obstetric ultrasound and DSc in 2009 for work on arterial mechanics.</s><s>Research interests include development of ultrasound techniques for diagnosis of cardiovascular disease, patient specific modelling and elastography.</s><s>He has published 120 refereed journal papers and is principal author of 3 books.</s><s>Pankaj Pankaj Dr. Pankaj Pankaj is a Reader in computational biomechanics at the University of Edinburgh.</s><s>He obtained his PhD in numerical modelling from University of Wales Swansea.</s><s>At Edinburgh he leads the Orthopaedic Biomechanics research group and has research collaborations with universities in Europe, Asia, South America and Australia.</s><s>Research supervised by him has received a number of recent awards: Robertson Medal from the Carnegie Trust; IMechE award for the best medical engineering PhD; and Vicon award for the best medical engineering project.</s><s>Colin Brown Colin Brown has worked for 30 uninterrupted years in the pharmaceutical &amp; consumer healthcare industries.</s><s>As a chemist, he has held several positions in the pharmaceutical development, clinical trials supplies and research &amp; development of medicinal products across a range of therapeutic areas and pharmaceutical forms.</s><s>Having begun his career at Syntex Pharmaceuticals before moving to Quintiles, a Contract Research Organisation in Edinburgh, he is currently Director of Research &amp; Quality Development at Mentholatum's European headquarters in Scotland where A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T he is responsible for the R&amp;D, regulatory affairs, pharmacovigilance and quality of the company's activities in Europe, Middle East and Africa.</s><s>Edwin van Beek Prof van Beek is a graduate from Erasmus University Medical school, did his PhD and Radiology and Clinical Epidemiology training at Academic Medical Centre, University of Amsterdam, and subsequently spent 5 years at University of Sheffield, UK and nearly 6 years at University of Iowa, USA.</s><s>In 2009, he took up the SINAPSE Chair of Clinical Radiology and co-directorship of the Clinical Research Imaging Centre, University of Edinburgh.</s><s>He has published extensively in the field of cardiothoracic and molecular imaging, and was particularly involved in multidisciplinary research including medical physics and biomedical engineering applications in the field of diagnostic imaging.</s><s>Neil Roberts Between 1988 and 2008 Prof. Roberts led a research programme entitled "Magnetic Resonance Studies of the Neural Bases of Cognition: Theoretical and Clinical Interactions" at the University of Liverpool where he was Director of the Magnetic Resonance and Image Analysis Research Centre (MARIARC).</s><s>During this time Neil was a Principal Investigator on two Medical Research Council (MRC) Programme Grants concerning the study of the neural bases of memory and language, providing expertise in Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) and Image Analysis.</s><s>In 2009 Neil was appointed Chair of Medical Physics and Imaging Science at the University of Edinburgh and has established a new research programme in Magnetic Resonance Elastography.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Means and standard deviations for each cohort by inversion method.</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Mean / SD in Pascals</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>BRAIN</cell><cell>LIVER</cell><cell>MUSCLE</cell></row><row><cell>LFE</cell><cell>3047 ± 338</cell><cell>2609 ± 501</cell><cell>916 ± 353</cell></row><row><cell>MDEV</cell><cell>1919 ± 184</cell><cell>1570 ± 216</cell><cell>1725 ± 85</cell></row><row><cell>ESP</cell><cell>2532 ± 448</cell><cell>2440 ± 313</cell><cell>2003 ± 164</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Correlations between results for the 3 inversion methods of LFE, MDEV and ESP (*=p &lt; 0.05, **=p &lt; 0.01, ***=p &lt; 0.001).</s><s>Results are significantly correlated in the liver cohort for all three methods, while ESP and MDEV |G</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Stiffness</cell><cell></cell><cell>φ</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">MDEV &amp; ESP MDEV &amp; LFE ESP &amp; LFE</cell><cell>MDEV &amp; ESP</cell></row><row><cell>Brain</cell><cell>R=0.85**</cell><cell>R=0.55</cell><cell>R=0.38</cell><cell>R=0.92***</cell></row><row><cell>Liver</cell><cell>0.79**</cell><cell>0.88***</cell><cell>0.77**</cell><cell>0.32</cell></row><row><cell>Thigh</cell><cell>0.85**</cell><cell>0.12</cell><cell>0.18</cell><cell>0.64*</cell></row></table><note><p><s>* | are significantly correlated for all methods.</s></p></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p><s>The authors thank Frank Ong   Funding from the BBSRC and MRC is gratefully acknowledged.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">K-svd: An algorithm for designing overcomplete dictionaries for sparse representation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Aharon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Elad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bruckstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4311" to="4322" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Signal Processing</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Parameter estimation and inverse problems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Aster</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Borchers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Thurber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neural connectivity, music, and movement: A response to pat amos</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Barnhill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">29</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Statistical mapping of the effect of knee extension on thigh muscle viscoelastic properties using magnetic resonance elastography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Barnhill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hammer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Van Beek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physiological measurement</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1675</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Realtime 4d phase unwrapping applied to magnetic resonance elastography. Magnetic</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Barnhill</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Johnson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mada</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Resonance in Medicine</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Thigh muscle stiffness assessed with magnetic resonance elastography in hyperthyroid patients before and after medical treatment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Bensamoun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Ringleb</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ehman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-N</forename><surname>An</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Brennan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Magnetic Resonance Imaging</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="708" to="713" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to inverse problems in imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bertero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Boccacci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>Taylor &amp; Francis</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-resolution mechanical imaging of the human brain by three-dimensional multifrequency magnetic resonance elastography at 7t</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lützkendorf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Stadler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Papazoglou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hirsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bernarding</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NeuroImage</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Group-sparse signal denoising: non-convex regularization, convex optimization. Signal Processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P.-Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Selesnick</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="3464" to="3478" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Designing gabor filters for optimal texture separability</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Clausi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Jernigan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pattern Recognition</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1835" to="1849" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bm3d image denoising with shape-adaptive principal component analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Dabov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Foi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Katkovnik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Egiazarian</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">SPARS&apos;09-Signal Processing with Adaptive Sparse Structured Representations</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Adapting to unknown smoothness via wavelet shrinkage</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Donoho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Johnstone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the american statistical association</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">432</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1200" to="1224" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Digital image processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gonzalez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Woods</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<publisher>Prentice Hall Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">In vivo brain viscoelastic properties measured by magnetic resonance elastography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Bilston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sinkus</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">NMR in Biomedicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="755" to="764" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards an elastographic atlas of brain anatomy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hirsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Fehlner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Papazoglou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Scheel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS one</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e71807</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Three-parameter shear wave inversion in mr elastography of incompressible transverse isotropic media: Application to in vivo lower leg muscles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hirsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Scheel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Patient-activated three-dimensional multifrequency magnetic resonance elastography for high-resolution mechanical imaging of the liver and spleen</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hirsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Streitberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kamphues</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Asbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">RoFo: Fortschritte auf dem Gebiete der Rontgenstrahlen und der Nuklearmedizin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">186</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="260" to="266" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mr elastography of the liver and the spleen using a piezoelectric driver, single-shot wave-field acquisition, and multifrequency dual parameter reconstruction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hirsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Reiter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Papazoglou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Kroencke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">71</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="277" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>A C C E P T E D M A N U S C R I P T</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Sparsity regularization in dynamic elastography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Honarvar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sahebjavaher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Salcudean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rohling</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics in medicine and biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5909</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Curl-based finite element reconstruction of the shear modulus without assuming local homogeneity: Time harsdddmonic case</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Honarvar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sahebjavaher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sinkus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Rohling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Salcudean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Noninvasive assessment of the rheological behavior of human organs using multifrequency MR elastography: a study of brain and liver viscoelasticity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Klatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Hamhaber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Asbach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics in medicine and biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">7281</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Viscoelasticity-based MR elastography of skeletal muscle</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Klatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Papazoglou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics in Medicine and Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">21</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">6445</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Local multiscale frequency and bandwidth estimation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Knutsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-F</forename><surname>Westin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Granlund</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE International Conference</title>
				<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994. 1994</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="36" to="40" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Proceedings. ICIP-94</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reduced energy-ratio measure for robust autofocusing in digital camera</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-Y</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J.-T</forename><surname>Yoo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S.-W</forename><surname>Kim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Signal Processing Letters</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="133" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>IEEE</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Single-image noise level estimation for blind denoising. Image Processing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tanaka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Okutomi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5226" to="5237" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Rheology: concepts, methods, and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Malkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Isayev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>ChemTec Publishing</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatio-temporal directional filtering for improved inversion of mr elastography images</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Manduca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lake</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kruse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ehman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medical image analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="465" to="473" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>N U S C R I P T</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Magnetic resonance elastography: non-invasive mapping of tissue elasticity</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Manduca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Oliphant</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dresner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mahowald</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kruse</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Amromin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Felmlee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Greenleaf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ehman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Medical Image Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="237" to="254" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Magnetic Resonance Elastography: A Review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Mariappan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Glaser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ehman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical Anatomy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="497" to="511" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Improvement and evaluation of nonlinear inversion MR elastography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mcgarry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<pubPlace>Dartmouth College</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Phase correction for interslice discontinuities in multislice epi mr elastography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huston</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Glaser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Manduca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Felmlee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Ehman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 20th ISMRM Annual Meeting</title>
				<meeting>the 20th ISMRM Annual Meeting</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ISMRM</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Magnetic Resonance Elastography by Direct Visualization of Propagating Acoustic Strain Waves</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Muthupillai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Rossman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Greenleaf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Manduca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Ehman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">269</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5232</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1854" to="1857" />
			<date type="published" when="1995-09">Sep. 1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Robust 4d flow denoising using divergence-free wavelet transform</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Uecker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Tariq</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hsiao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Alley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Vasanawala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lustig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two-dimensional waveform analysis in mr elastography of skeletal muscles</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Papazoglou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Hamhaber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics in Medicine and Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1313</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Multifrequency inversion in magnetic resonance elastography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Papazoglou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Hirsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics in medicine and biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2329</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Shear modulus reconstruction in dynamic elastography: time harmonic case</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Maniatty</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics in medicine and biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">51</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">15</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Structure-sensitive elastography: on the viscoelastic powerlaw behavior of in vivo human tissue in health and disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Jöhrens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Würfel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soft Matter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5672" to="5680" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The dual-tree complex wavelet transform. Signal Processing Magazine</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Selesnick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Baraniuk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kingsbury</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="151" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">High-resolution tensor mr elastography for breast tumour detection</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sinkus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lorenzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Schrader</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lorenzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dargatz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Holz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics in medicine and biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1649</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imaging anisotropic and viscous properties of breast tissue by magnetic resonance-elastography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sinkus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tanter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Catheline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lorenzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kuhl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sondermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fink</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Magnetic resonance in medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="372" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005a</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Imaging anisotropic and viscous properties of breast tissue by magnetic resonance-elastography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Sinkus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Tanter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Catheline</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lorenzen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Kuhl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sondermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fink</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Magnetic Resonance in Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="372" to="387" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005b</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Highresolution mechanical imaging of glioblastoma by multifrequency magnetic resonance elastography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-J</forename><surname>Streitberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Reiss-Zimmermann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Freimann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Bayerl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Arlt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Wuerfel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Braun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K.-T</forename><surname>Hoffmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sack</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS one</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e110588</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Causal theories and data for acoustic attenuation obeying a frequency power law</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Szabo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of the Acoustical Society of America</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">14</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A simulation of the magnetic resonance elastography steady state wave response through idealised atherosclerotic plaques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">E J</forename><surname>Thomas-Seale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Klatt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pankaj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Roberts</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Sack</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Hoskins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IAENG International Journal of Computer Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="394" to="400" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
