<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Toward a new definition of mental health</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Silvana</forename><surname>Galderisi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of Naples SUN</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Naples</settlement>
									<country key="IT">Italy</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Heinz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charit e-University Medicine Berlin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Marianne</forename><surname>Kastrup</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Competence Center for Transcultural Psychiatry</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Psychiatric Center Ballerup</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Hellerup</settlement>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Julian</forename><surname>Beezhold</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Norwich Medical School</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Hellesdon Hospital</orgName>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="institution">University of East Anglia</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Norwich</settlement>
									<country key="GB">UK</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Norman</forename><surname>Sartorius</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="institution">Improvement of Mental Health Programmes</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Geneva</settlement>
									<country key="CH">Switzerland</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Toward a new definition of mental health</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BA17AB84CC9AE873F3D1D59FCB4EB855</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1002/wps.20231</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>According to the World Health Organization (WHO), mental health is "a state of well-being in which the individual realizes his or her own abilities, can cope with the normal stresses of life, can work productively and fruitfully, and is able to make a contribution to his or her community" <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>This definition, while representing a substantial progress with respect to moving away from the conceptualization of mental health as a state of absence of mental illness, raises several concerns and lends itself to potential misunderstandings when it identifies positive feelings and positive functioning as key factors for mental health.</s></p><p><s>In fact, regarding well-being as a key aspect of mental health is difficult to reconcile with the many challenging life situations in which well-being may even be unhealthy: most people would consider as mentally unhealthy an individual experiencing a state of well-being while killing several persons during a war action, and would regard as healthy a person feeling desperate after being fired from his/her job in a situation in which occupational opportunities are scarce.</s></p><p><s>People in good mental health are often sad, unwell, angry or unhappy, and this is part of a fully lived life for a human being.</s><s>In spite of this, mental health has been often conceptualized as a purely positive affect, marked by feelings of happiness and sense of mastery over the environment <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Concepts used in several papers on mental health include both key aspects of the WHO definition, i.e. positive emotions and positive functioning.</s><s><ref type="bibr">Keyes (5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6)</ref> identifies three components of mental health: emotional well-being, psychological well-being and social well-being.</s><s>Emotional wellbeing includes happiness, interest in life, and satisfaction; psychological well-being includes liking most parts of one's own personality, being good at managing the responsibilities of daily life, having good relationships with others, and being satisfied with one's own life; social well-being refers to positive functioning and involves having something to contribute to society (social contribution), feeling part of a community (social integration), believing that society is becoming a better place for all people (social actualization), and that the way society works makes sense to them (social coherence).</s></p><p><s>However, such a perspective of mental health, influenced by hedonic and eudaimonic traditions, which champion positive emotions and excellence in functioning, respectively <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>, risks excluding most adolescents, many of whom are somewhat shy, those who fight against perceived injustice and inequalities or are discouraged from doing so after years of useless efforts, as well as migrants and minorities experiencing rejection and discrimination.</s></p><p><s>The concept of positive functioning is also translated by several definitions and theories about mental health into the ability to work productively <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8)</ref>, and may lead to the wrong conclusion that an individual at an age or in a physical condition preventing her/him from working productively is not by definition in good mental health.</s><s>Working productively and fruitfully is often not possible for contextual reasons (e.g., for migrants or for discriminated people), which may prevent people from contributing to their community.</s><s>Jahoda ( <ref type="formula">9</ref>) subdivided mental health into three domains: self-realization, in that individuals are able to fully exploit their potential; sense of mastery over the environment; and sense of autonomy, i.e. ability to identify, confront, and solve problems.</s><s>Murphy <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(10)</ref> argued that these ideas were laden with cultural values considered important by North Americans.</s><s>However, even for a North American person, it is hard to imagine, for example, that a mentally healthy human being in the hands of terrorists, under the threat of beheading, can experience a sense of happiness and mastery over the environment.</s></p><p><s>The definition of mental health is clearly influenced by the culture that defines it.</s><s>However, as also advocated by Vaillant <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>, common sense should prevail and certain elements that have a universal importance for mental health might be identified.</s><s>For example, in spite of cultural differences in eating habits, the acknowledgement of the importance of vitamins and the four basic food groups is universal.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TOWARD A NEW DEFINITION OF MENTAL HEALTH</head><p><s>Aware of the fact that differences across countries in values, cultures and social background may hinder the achievement of a general consensus on the concept of mental health, we aimed at elaborating an inclusive definition, avoiding as much as possible restrictive and culture-bound statements.</s></p><p><s>The concept that mental health is not merely the absence of mental illness (1,8) was unanimously endorsed, while the equivalence between mental health and well-being/functioning was not, and a definition leaving room for a variety of emotional states and for "imperfect functioning" was drafted.</s></p><p><s>The proposed definition is reported herewith:</s></p><p><s>Mental health is a dynamic state of internal equilibrium which enables individuals to use their abilities in harmony with universal values of society.</s><s>Basic cognitive and social skills; ability to recognize, express and modulate one's own emotions, as well as empathize with others; flexibility and ability to cope with adverse life events and function in social roles; and harmonious relationship between body and mind represent important components of mental health which contribute, to varying degrees, to the state of internal equilibrium.</s></p><p><s>The addition of a note explaining what is meant in the definition by the expression "universal values" is deemed necessary, in the light of the misleading use of this expression in certain political and social circumstances.</s><s>The values we are referring to are: respect and care for oneself and other living beings; recognition of connectedness between people; respect for the environment; respect for one's own and others' freedom.</s></p><p><s>The concept of "dynamic state of internal equilibrium" is meant to reflect the fact that different life epochs require changes in the achieved equilibrium: adolescent crises, marriage, becoming a parent or retirement are good examples of life epochs requiring an active search for a new mental equilibrium.</s><s>This concept also incorporates and acknowledges the reality that mentally healthy people may experience appropriate human emotions -including for example fear, anger, sadness and grief -whilst at the same time possessing sufficient resilience to timeously restore the dynamic state of internal equilibrium.</s></p><p><s>All components proposed in the definition represent important but not mandatory aspects of mental health; as a matter of fact, they may contribute to a varying degree to the state of equilibrium, so that fully developed functions may offset an impairment in another aspect of mental functioning.</s><s>For instance, a very empathetic person, highly interested in mutual sharing, may compensate for a moderate degree of cognitive impairment, and still find a satisfactory equilibrium and pursue her/his life goals.</s></p><p><s>The main reasons underlying the choice of the components included in the definition are provided hereafter.</s></p><p><s>Basic cognitive and social skills are regarded as an important component of mental health in the light of their impact on all aspects of everyday life <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(15)</ref>.</s><s>Cognitive skills include the ability to pay attention, remember and organize information, solve problems, and make decisions; social skills involve the ability to use one's own repertoire of verbal/non-verbal abilities to communicate and interact with others.</s><s>All these abilities are interdependent and allow people to function in their environment.</s><s>Reference to the "basic" level of these abilities is meant to clarify that mild degrees of impairment are compatible with mental health, while moderate to severe degrees of impairment, especially if not balanced by other aspects, may require support by other members of the society and a number of social incentives, such as facilitated job opportunities, financial benefits or ad hoc training programs.</s></p><p><s>Emotional regulation, i.e. the ability to recognize, express and modulate one's own emotions, is also regarded as an important component of mental health <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(16)</ref>.</s><s>It has been proposed as a mediator of stress adjustment <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18)</ref>, and a link between inappropriate or ineffective emotional regulation and depression has been found in clinical and neuroimaging studies <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(19)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(20)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(21)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(22)</ref>.</s><s>A variety of modulated emotional response options, that can be flexibly employed, contribute to an individual's mental health, and alexithymia (i.e., an inability to identify and express one's own emotions) is a risk factor for mental and physical disorders <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(23,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b23">24)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Empathy, i.e., the ability to experience and understand what others feel without confusion between oneself and others, enables individuals to communicate and interact in effective ways and to predict actions, intentions, and feelings of others <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(25)</ref>.</s><s>The absence of empathy is not only a risk factor for violence and a feature of antisocial personality disorder, but also impairs social interactions at all levels.</s></p><p><s>Flexibility and ability to cope with adverse events are also deemed important to mental health maintenance.</s><s>Flexibility refers to the ability to revise a course of action in the face of unpredicted difficulties or obstacles, change one's own ideas in the light of new evidence, and adapt to changes that different life epochs or contingent situations may require.</s><s>Lack of flexibility may result in great distress for a person undergoing sudden and/or important life changes, and is an important aspect of several psychiatric disorders, such as obsessive personality or delusional disorder <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(26)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The basic ability to function in social roles and to participate in meaningful social interactions is an important aspect of mental health and particularly contributes to resilience against distress; however, social exclusion and stigmatization often impair social participation, so any definition of mental health alluding to this aspect has to avoid "blaming the victim" and to carefully analyze social patterns of stigmatization, discrimination and exclusion that impair participation <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(27)</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The inclusion of a harmonious relationship between body and mind is based on the concept that mind, brain, organism and environment are heavily interconnected, and the overall experience of being in the world cannot be separated from the way in which one's body feels in its environment <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">(28)</ref>.</s><s>Disturbances of this interaction may result in psychotic experiences, eating disorders, self-harm, body dysmorphic disorder or poor physical health.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSIONS</head><p><s>The definition of mental health drafted in this paper is aimed to overcome perspectives based on ideal norms or hedonic and eudaimonic theoretical traditions, in favor of an inclusive approach, as free as possible of restrictive and culture-bound statements, and as close as possible to human life experience, which is sometimes joyful, and at other times sad or disgusting or frightening; sometimes satisfactory, and at other times challenging or unsatisfactory.</s></p><p><s>The proposed definition is also compatible with the recovery movement perspective, in which recovery after an illness is seen as a process aimed to attain a fulfilled and valued life by building on the functions spared by the illness, in spite of the fact that other functions have been impaired <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(29)</ref>.</s></p></div>		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgement</head><p><s>This paper was drafted as part of the activities of the Committee on Ethical Issues of the European Psychiatric Association.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Promoting mental health: concepts, emerging evidence, practice (Summary Report). Geneva: World Health Organization</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>World Health Organization</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Two conceptions of happiness: contrasts of personal expressiveness (eudaimonia) and hedonic enjoyment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Waterman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pers Soc Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="678" to="691" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Subjective well-being: three decades of progress</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Diener</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Suh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lucas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psychol Bull</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">125</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="302" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating the psychometric properties of the Mental Health Continuum-Short Form (MHC-SF)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sma</forename><surname>Lamers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Westerhof</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bohlmeijer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="99" to="110" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Mental health in adolescence: is America&apos;s youth flourishing?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Keyes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Orthopsychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="395" to="402" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mental health as a complete state: how the salutogenic perspective completes the picture</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Clm</forename><surname>Keyes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Bauer GF, H€ ammig O</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="179" to="192" />
			<pubPlace>Dordrecht</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Bridging occupational, organizational and public health</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hedonia, eudaimonia, and well-being: an introduction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Deci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ryan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Happiness Stud</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mental health: a report of the Surgeon General. Rockville: U.S. Public Health Service</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Department of Health and Human Services</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Current concepts of positive mental health</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Jahoda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1958">1958</date>
			<publisher>Basic Books</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The meaning of symptom check-list scores in mental health surveys: a testing of multiple hypotheses</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Hbm</forename><surname>Murphy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Soc Sci Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="75" />
			<date type="published" when="1978">1978</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Positive mental health: is there a cross-cultural definition?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Vaillant</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="99" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Disability and mild cognitive impairment: a longitudinal population-based study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Artero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Touchon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ritchie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Geriatr Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1092" to="1097" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Borderline intellectual functioning is associated with poor social functioning, increased rates of psychiatric diagnosis and drug use -A cross sectional population based study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Gigi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Werbeloff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Goldberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur Neuropsychopharmacol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1793" to="1797" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cognitive functioning and the incidence of limitations in activities of daily living in an elderly community sample</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Moritz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Kasl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Berkman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Epidemiol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">141</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="49" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A correlation between cognitive performance and daily functioning in elderly people</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Warren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Grek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Conn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Geriatr Psychiatry Neurol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="100" />
			<date type="published" when="1989">1989</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Emotion regulation and mental health</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gross</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Muñoz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Psychol Sci Pract</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="151" to="164" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preventive resources and emotion regulation expectancies as mediators between attachment and college students&apos; stress outcomes</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mccarthy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lambert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Moller</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int J Stress Manag</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="22" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Community violence exposure and children&apos;s social adjustment in the school peer group: the mediating roles of emotion regulation and social cognition</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Schwartz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Proctor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Consult Clin Psychol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="670" to="683" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Toward a unified treatment for emotional disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Barlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Allen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Choate</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Behav Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="205" to="230" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acceptability and suppression of negative emotion in anxiety and mood disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Campbell-Sills</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Barlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Emotion</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="587" to="595" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Serotonin (5-HT) in the regulation of depression-related emotionality: insight from 5-HT transporter and tryptophan hydroxylase-2 knockout mouse models</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Araragi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lesch</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Drug Targ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="549" to="570" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dysregulation of endogenous opioid emotion regulation circuitry in major depression in women</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Koeppe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Young</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch Gen Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1199" to="1208" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alexithymia and health behaviors in healthy male volunteers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Helmers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mente</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Psychosom Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">47</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="635" to="645" />
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alexithymia and risk of death in middle-aged men</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kauhanen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kaplan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Psychosom Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="541" to="549" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A social neuroscience perspective on clinical empathy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Decety</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Norman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="237" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Dopaminergic control of cognitive flexibility in humans and animals</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Klanker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Feenstra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Denys</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front Neurosci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="23" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anthropological and evolutionary concepts of mental disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Heinz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Kluge</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Speculative Philosophy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="292" to="307" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Embodiment and psychopathology: a phenomenological perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Fuchs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Schlimme</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="570" to="575" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uses and abuses of recovery: implementing recovery-oriented practices in mental health systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Slade</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Amering</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Farkas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">World Psychiatry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/wps.20231</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
