<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Age-dependent Shift in Macrophage Polarization Causes Inflammation Mediated Degeneration of Enteric Nervous System</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-05-01">2018 May 01.</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Laren</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
							<email>lsbecker@stanford.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>California</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Linh</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>California</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jaspreet</forename><surname>Gill</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>California</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Subhash</forename><surname>Kulkarni</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johns Hopkins University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>Maryland</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Pankaj</forename><forename type="middle">Jay</forename><surname>Pasricha</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Johns Hopkins University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Baltimore</settlement>
									<region>Maryland</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD MSc</roleName><forename type="first">Aida</forename><surname>Habtezion</surname></persName>
							<email>aidah@stanford.edu.</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>California</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>300 Pasteur Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>94305</postCode>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University School of Medicine</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>300 Pasteur Drive</addrLine>
									<postCode>94305</postCode>
									<settlement>Stanford</settlement>
									<region>CA</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Age-dependent Shift in Macrophage Polarization Causes Inflammation Mediated Degeneration of Enteric Nervous System</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-05-01">2018 May 01.</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B7EF19032C8BC8F3C09D6B00F6DA3EAC</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1136/gutjnl-2016-312940</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:27+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Objective-The enteric nervous system (ENS) undergoes neuronal loss and degenerative changes with age.</s><s>The cause of this neurodegeneration is poorly understood.</s><s>Muscularis macrophages (MMs) residing in close proximity to enteric ganglia maintain neuromuscular function via direct crosstalk with enteric neurons and have been implicated in the pathogenesis of gastrointestinal motility disorders like gastroparesis and post-operative ileus.</s><s>The aim of this study was to assess whether aging causes alterations in macrophage phenotype that contributes to agerelated degeneration of the ENS.</s></p><p><s>Design-Longitudinal muscle and myenteric plexus (LMMP) from small intestine of young, mid-aged and old mice was dissected and prepared for whole mount immunostaining, flow cytometry, Luminex immunoassays, western blot analysis, enteric neural stem cell (ENSC) isolation, or conditioned media.</s><s>Bone marrow derived macrophages were prepared and polarized to classic (M1) or alternative (M2) activation states.</s><s>Markers for macrophage phenotype were measured using quantitative RT-PCR.</s></p><p><s>Results-Aging causes a shift in macrophage polarization from anti-inflammatory 'M2' to proinflammatory 'M1' that is associated with a rise in cytokines and immune cells in the ENS.</s><s>This phenotypic shift is associated with a neural response to inflammatory signals, increase in apoptosis and loss of enteric neurons and ENSCs, and delayed intestinal transit.</s><s>An age-dependent decrease in expression of the transcription factor FoxO3, a known longevity gene, contributes to the loss of anti-inflammatory behavior in macrophages of old mice and FoxO3 deficient mice demonstrate signs of premature aging of the ENS.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion-A</head><p><s>shift by macrophages towards a pro-inflammatory phenotype with aging causes inflammation-mediated degeneration of the ENS.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p><s>Aging causes physiologic changes in gastrointestinal function that contribute to many disorders including constipation and fecal incontinence which cause significant physical, emotional, and financial burdens[ <ref type="bibr">1 2</ref>].</s><s>Age-dependent loss and degeneration of the enteric nervous system (ENS), the intrinsic nervous system of the gastrointestinal tract, likely plays a role in these disorders <ref type="bibr">[1 3</ref>].</s><s>There is evidence that oxidative stress, alterations in neurotrophic factors, and calcium dysregulation may contribute, but the exact mechanism for these age-related changes remains poorly understood <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The muscular layer of the gut wall has been found to contain numerous tissue resident macrophages, termed muscularis macrophages (MMs), residing in close apposition to enteric ganglia <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</s><s>Through direct crosstalk with enteric neurons, MMs are important for gastrointestinal neuromuscular function and their depletion results in prolongation of colonic transit times <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</s><s>Macrophages have been classified as either M1 (classically activated) or M2 (alternatively activated) based on their role in inflammatory processes <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s><s>M1 macrophages produce pro-inflammatory mediators including cytokines and reactive oxygen and nitrogen species and function in host defense.</s><s>In contrast, M2 macrophages play a role in dampening inflammation and promoting wound healing <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>.</s><s>In the intestine, macrophage phenotype differs depending on their location, with macrophages in the lamina propria layer preferentially assuming a pro-inflammatory M1 phenotype while MMs displaying an antiinflammatory M2 phenotype <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s><s>However, macrophages demonstrate tremendous plasticity and are capable of reversibly switching between M1 and M2 phenotypes <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s><s>Perturbation of the normal balance of M1/M2 macrophages appears to be an important factor in disease pathogenesis including cancer, atherosclerosis, autoimmune disease, osteoporosis and neurodegeneration <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</s><s>Alterations in the phenotype of MMs have been implicated in gastrointestinal motility disorders including gastroparesis and post-operative ileus (POI) <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Loss of expression of mannose receptor C type 1 (CD206), an M2 marker, in MMs of Non-obese diabetic (NOD) mice has been found to correlate with development of gastric delay <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> suggesting that alterations in M1/M2 phenotype may contribute to gastrointestinal neuromuscular disorders.</s><s>Whether aging causes changes in macrophage phenotype that may contribute to the degeneration of the ENS and age-related gastrointestinal disorders is unknown.</s><s>Here we show that aging causes a shift in macrophage polarization from an antiinflammatory 'M2' state to a pro-inflammatory 'M1' state.</s><s>This shift is partly due to decreased expression of the transcription factor FoxO3, a gene linked to longevity, and accompanies inflammation-mediated loss of enteric neurons and enteric neural stem cells (ENSCs) and delayed intestinal transit.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials and Methods</head><p><s>Please see supplementary methods (available online only) for an expanded version of this section.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Animals</head><p><s>Male C57/BL6 mice of different age groups (3 months, 10-12 months, and 20-24 months) acquired from the National Institute of Aging Aged Rodent Colony, FoxO3 −/− mice in FVB/N background <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, and Wnt1-cre;tdTomato mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> were used in experiments.</s><s>All animal experiments were approved by Stanford University institutional animal care and use committees.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tissue and cell preparation</head><p><s>Mice were anesthetized, euthanized, and laparotomy was performed.</s><s>Small intestine was removed, lavaged, and longitudinal muscle with the adherent myenteric plexus (LMMP) was dissected as previously described <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</s><s>Tissue was either freshly frozen in dry ice, fixed in paraformaldehyde (PFA), enzymatically digested with collagenase, or placed in media for ex vivo organotypic cultures.</s><s>Tissue digestion was performed using protocol adapted from Joseph et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> by sequentially incubating tissue in Digestion Buffer (consisting of M199 media (Invitrogen, Carlsbad CA), 0.1% BSA, 1mM CaCl 2 , 20 mM HEPES, and 150 μM P188) containing 1.1 mg/ml collagenase (Sigma-Aldrich) for 30 minutes at 37°C, followed by 10 U/ml papain (Worthington Biochemicals, Lakewood NJ) in Hank's buffered salt solution (HBSS, Invitrogen) without calcium and magnesium, then quenched with ice-cold Digestion Buffer containing 50 U/ml DNAse I (Worthington).</s><s>Tissue was mechanically dissociated by gentle trituration and filtered through a 40 μm nylon mesh cell strainer.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Flow cytometry</head><p><s>Dissociated cells were incubated with Zombie Aqua Viability (Biolegend, San Diego, CA) followed by blocking with 5% rat serum and mouse anti-CD16/CD32 (eBioscience, San Diego, CA) in HBSS containing 2% BCS.</s><s>Samples were incubated for 30 minutes at 4°C with primary antibodies and isotype controls (supplemental table 1).</s><s>After washing, cells were passed through a 40 μm nylon mesh cell strainer and sorting was performed directly into Trizol (Qiagen, Valencia CA) using a BD FACS Aria (BD Bioscience, San Jose CA).</s><s>Gating strategy for sorting of macrophages is shown in supplemental figure 1. Analysis was performed using FlowJo Software (Tree Star Inc, Ashland OR).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RNA isolation and quantitative real-time PCR</head><p><s>RNA was extracted from cells with miRNeasy kit (Qiagen) and converted to cDNA using High-Capacity RNA-to-cDNA kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City CA).</s><s>For sorted MMs, cDNA preamplification performed with Taqman PreAmp Master Mix kit (Applied Biosystems).</s><s>Quantitative RT-PCR was performed on ABI StepOne Plus real time instrument using the Taqman expression assays listed in supplemental table 2. For analysis, each gene was normalized to the housekeeping gene GAPDH and fold change in gene expression between groups was calculated using the Pfaffl method.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistics</head><p><s>Data is expressed as mean +/− standard error of mean and was analyzed using Mann-Whitney, t-test, and one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA).</s><s>Significance was deemed when p value was less than 0.05.</s><s>Statistical analysis was performed with GraphPad Prism 5 (GraphPad Software Inc, La Jolla CA).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Muscularis macrophages demonstrate shift from anti-inflammatory to pro-inflammatory phenotype with aging</head><p><s>Consistent with a recent report by Gabanyi et al., which showed that macrophages in the muscularis preferentially express M2 markers compared to those in the lamina propria <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, we found the majority of MMs (in both young and old mice) to express the M2-marker CD206 by immunostaining (supplemental figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1A</ref>).</s><s>Within the muscle layers of the intestine, MMs were found to reside primarily in the myenteric plexus layer, surrounding enteric neurons (supplemental figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1B</ref>).</s><s>We performed flow cytometry on dissociated cells from LMMP of mice from 3 different age groups, young (3 month old), mid-aged (10-12 month old) and old (20-24 month old).</s><s>Macrophages, defined as CD45 + F4/80 + cells, were the predominant immune cell in the muscularis layer, comprising nearly 20% of total live cells and representing between 60-80% of all leukocytes or CD45 + cells (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1A</ref> and supplemental figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1C</ref>).</s><s>The numbers of MMs (as a percent of live cells) did not differ significantly with age (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1A</ref>).</s><s>Next we sorted MMs (see supplemental figure 1D for gating scheme) and performed mRNA expression analysis of a variety of anti-inflammatory 'M2' markers including CD206, Found In Inflammatory Zone 1 (FIZZ1), and transforming growth factor β (TGFβ), and pro-inflammatory 'M1' markers including inducible nitric oxide synthetase (iNOS), interleukin-6 (IL-6), and tumor necrosis factor α (TNFα).</s><s>MMs from mid-aged and old mice revealed reduced expression of M2 markers, CD206, FIZZ1 and TGFβ compared to young mice (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1B</ref>).</s><s>Additionally, MMs expressed higher proinflammatory M1 markers with age, although only IL-6 from old mice reached statistical significance (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1C</ref>).</s><s>Taken together, this suggests that aging is accompanied by a shift in macrophages from an anti-inflammatory to pro-inflammatory phenotype.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Increased inflammation in ENS microenvironment with age</head><p><s>To determine whether this age-dependent shift in macrophage phenotype affects the inflammatory milieu of the ENS microenvironment, we performed Luminex immunoassays on protein extract of LMMP from young and old mice.</s><s>Expression of pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines were increased overall in the ENS microenvironment from old mice with IL-6, IL-1β and IL-18 reaching statistical significance (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2A</ref>).</s><s>Elevation of IL-6 was confirmed in a second cohort of young and old mice using Western Blot analysis (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2B</ref>).</s><s>To evaluate whether alterations in immune cells accompanied these changes, we performed immunophenotyping of LMMP using flow cytometry.</s><s>A statistically significant increase in leukocytes (CD45 + cells) was found in the ENS microenvironment of mid-aged and old compared to young mice (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2C</ref>).</s><s>Although no difference was seen in the numbers of macrophages (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1A</ref>) and dendritic cells (CD45 + CD11c + F4/80 − ) as a percent of live cells, a statistically significant rise in lymphocytes (CD45 + CD3 + CD19 + ) was found in old compared to young mice (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2D</ref>).</s><s>A decline in macrophages and rise in lymphocytes as a percent of CD45 + cells was also observed in the old age group (supplemental figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1C</ref>).</s><s>In summary, we demonstrate that the age-associated shift in macrophages towards a M1 phenotype is associated with a rise in pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines and increased infiltration of lymphocytes in the ENS.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Age-associated neural response to inflammatory signals is associated with increased apoptosis, loss of enteric neurons and delayed intestinal transit</head><p><s>In order to evaluate whether this age-dependent inflammation causes changes to the ENS, we evaluated whether Signal Transducer and Activator of Transcription 3 (STAT3), a downstream mediator of IL-6, IL-18 and other cytokines, was preferentially activated in enteric neurons of old mice.</s><s>We found a 2-fold increase in percent of neurons expressing phosphorylated STAT3 (pSTAT3) in old compared to young mice, indicating increased STAT3 activity (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3A</ref>).</s><s>An increased ratio of pSTAT3/STAT3 was also observed in old mice by western blot analysis of LMMP protein extract (supplemental figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2A</ref>).</s><s>We found a statistically significant increase in number of enteric neurons expressing cleaved caspase-3 (Asp175) (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3B</ref> and supplemental table 3).</s><s>This perinuclear staining pattern of cleaved caspase-3 is similar to that observed in apoptotic neurons in the central nervous system <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref> and was observed in enteric neurons that were also TUNEL + (supplemental figure 2B).</s><s>A reduction in the density of neurons within myenteric ganglia (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3C</ref>) was observed in old compared to young mice, suggesting neuronal loss with aging.</s><s>This age-dependent reduction in neuronal density is similar to previous reports in human, rat and guinea pigs <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s>These neurodegenerative changes were associated with prolonged total intestinal transit time in old mice compared to young (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3D</ref>).</s><s>These findings suggest that age-dependent changes in macrophage phenotype are associated with neural response to inflammatory signals and loss of enteric neurons.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Increased pro-inflammatory cytokines cause reduction in enteric neural stem cells with aging</head><p><s>The ENS contains a resident population of multipotent stem cells termed enteric neural stem cells (ENSCs) capable of regeneration following injury[16 <ref type="bibr">19 20]</ref>.</s><s>In culture these stem cells, which can be identified by a variety of markers including p75, CD49b and nestin, can differentiate into neurons, glia and myofibroblasts <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>.</s><s>We have previously shown that, similar to in vitro cultures, an ex vivo organotypic culturing system can be used to assess proliferation and differentiation of ENSCs.</s><s>This ex vivo system, however, has the advantage of allowing their visualization within intact myenteric ganglia <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</s><s>We cultured LMMP sections from young and old mice with the thymidine analog EdU for 40 hours to assess proliferation.</s><s>We found a nearly 3-fold reduction in the number of EdU + cells per myenteric ganglia area in old compared to young mice (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4A</ref>), suggesting a decline in number of ENSCs with age.</s><s>These results are consistent with a prior report showing fewer cells expressing the ENSC marker p75 and decreased multipotent neurospheres isolated from guts of old mice compared to young <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</s><s>Next we evaluated whether factors in the aged-ENS microenvironment directly impact survival of ENSCs.</s><s>Using a Wnt1-cre;tdTomato mouse line in which neural crest-derived cells are fluorescently labeled <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">[22]</ref>, we enriched for ENSCs using CD49b <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> magnetic beads and cultured them in conditioned media prepared with LMMP from young (Young CM) or old mice (Old CM).</s><s>Old CM caused a 2-fold increase in TUNEL + ENSCs compared to Young CM (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4B and C</ref>).</s><s>Luminex immunoassays revealed that Old CM contained 2-fold greater levels of IL-6 compared to Young CM (supplemental figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">3</ref>).</s><s>Since IL-6 has been implicated in impaired survival of neural progenitor cells in the central nervous system <ref type="bibr">[23 24]</ref>, we explored whether this cytokine in particular was responsible for decreased survival of ENSCs.</s><s>The addition of IL-6 neutralizing antibody (and not IgG control) reversed the pro-apoptotic effect of Old CM (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4B and C</ref>).</s><s>Additionally, we found that recombinant murine IL-6 caused increased TUNEL-positivity when cultured with ENSCs but required over a 20-fold higher concentration (100 ng/ml) than found in Old CM (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4D</ref> and supplemental figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">3</ref>).</s><s>Given that cells which do not express IL-6 receptor can still signal through IL-6 via soluble IL-6 receptor, termed trans-signaling <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">[25]</ref>, we wanted to evaluate whether this may explain the discrepancy.</s><s>We found that adding soluble recombinant IL-6 receptor α (sIL-6Rα) caused increased TUNEL positivity at a lower concentration of IL-6 (50 ng/ml) (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4D</ref>) suggesting that IL-6 exerts its pro-apoptotic effect on ENSCs through trans-signaling.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Age-dependent loss of anti-inflammatory phenotype is in part intrinsic to macrophages</head><p><s>To assess whether the shift in phenotype is intrinsic to macrophages or related to extrinsic influences in aged-microenvironment, we generated congenic BM chimeras by transplanting BM from young or old mice into lethally irradiated young or old mice (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5A</ref>).</s><s>This technique has been shown to be an effective way to deplete host MMs and replace them with macrophages derived from BM graft <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s><s>Similar to old mice, sorted MMs from O→Y revealed reduction in expression of M2 markers CD206 (p&lt;0.05),</s><s>FIZZ1 and TGFβ (p=0.06)</s><s>compared to Y→Y mice (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5B</ref>), suggesting that cell intrinsic factors contribute to the age-dependent loss of suppressive phenotype.</s><s>While not statistically significant we also found a trend towards increased leukocytes in O→Y compared with Y→Y (supplemental figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4A</ref>).</s><s>MMs from chimeras transplanted with old BM (O→O and O→Y) showed a trend towards increased iNOS expression suggesting a more proinflammatory phenotype (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5C</ref>).</s><s>We also found a modest but statistically significant preservation of neuronal density in enteric ganglia from Y→O chimeras compared to O→O (supplemental figure 4B), supporting the possibility that young BM confers some protection against age-related neuronal loss.</s></p><p><s>To help confirm that aging causes intrinsic changes to macrophages, we prepared BMderived macrophages (BMDMs) from young and old mice.</s><s>BMDMs were treated with either interferon γ (IFNγ) or IL-4 and IL-13 to induce M1 or M2 polarization states respectively.</s><s>When treated with IL-4 and IL-13, cells of old mice showed decreased anti-inflammatory M2 markers CD206 and TGFβ compared to young (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5D</ref>) by RT-PCR.</s><s>There was no difference in expression of pro-inflammatory markers iNOS, IL-6 and TNFα in IFNγtreated BMDMs from young and old mice (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5E</ref>).</s><s>To assess whether this difference might be due to an age-related alteration in the ability to polarize, we performed flow cytometry on the BMDMs.</s><s>The majority of CD45 + cells (&gt;96%) from both young and old expressed the macrophage marker F4/80.</s><s>Furthermore, we found similar expression of CD206 in BMDMs treated with either IL-4/IL-13 (supplemental figure 5A) or IFNγ (supplemental figure 5B) from young and old suggesting the differences we observed in mRNA gene expression were not due to altered polarization.</s><s>To determine whether reduction in 'M2' markers corresponds to diminished anti-inflammatory properties, we performed a lymphocyte suppression assay.</s><s>CD4 + T cells isolated from spleen of a young mouse were labeled with CSFE, activated with anti-CD3 and anti-CD28, then co-cultured with IL-4/IL-13-treated BMDMs from young or old mice for 72 hours.</s><s>Co-culturing with BMDMs from young mice yielded dramatically fewer proliferated (CSFE-negative) lymphocytes (1.2% versus 18.4% of CD4 + cells) compared to old (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5F</ref>), indicating diminished suppressive behavior in macrophages from old mice.</s><s>Taken together, these findings suggest that intrinsic changes in macrophages contribute to their loss of antiinflammatory properties.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reduction in FoxO3 expression is associated with decreased anti-inflammatory phenotype in macrophages</head><p><s>FoxO3, a member of the family of Forkhead transcription factors, is one of a few genes in which genetic variants have been consistently linked to longevity in humans <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref>.</s><s>In addition to regulating metabolism, apoptosis, autophagy, and stem cell homeostasis, FoxO3 plays a role in modulating the immune response <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref>.</s><s>FOXO3 genetic variants have been associated with more aggressive disease courses for patients with Crohn's disease and rheumatoid arthritis, and FoxO3-deficient mice demonstrate an exaggerated inflammatory response to experimental colitis <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[27]</ref>.</s><s>Since FoxO3 appears to regulate the immune response through myeloid cells[27 28], we evaluated whether alterations in its expression may account for age-related changes to MMs.</s><s>We found a 20% reduction in FoxO3 expression in LMMP from old compared to young mice (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6A</ref>), which is similar to the reduction seen in skeletal muscle of old rats <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">[29]</ref>.</s><s>This age-dependent reduction was also seen in sorted MMs (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6B</ref>) and BMDMs by both qRT-PCR (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6C</ref>) and western blot analysis (supplemental figure 5C).</s><s>To determine whether this reduction in FoxO3 expression may account for changes in macrophage phenotype, we generated BMDMs from FoxO3 −/− and WT mice.</s><s>As seen in old mice, BMDMs from FoxO3 −/− mice treated with IL-4 and IL-13 demonstrated reduced expression of CD206 and TGFβ compared to WT (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6D</ref>).</s><s>IFNγtreated BMDMs from FoxO3 −/− mice demonstrated decreased expression of proinflammatory markers (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6E</ref>).</s><s>Despite this decline in M1 markers, we found that administration of LPS to similarly IFNγ-treated BMDMs caused increased elevation of proinflammatory markers relative to WT suggesting a more pro-inflammatory phenotype (supplemental figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5D</ref>).</s><s>These results suggest that an age-dependent reduction of FoxO3 accounts for the loss of suppressive phenotype of macrophages with aging.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>FoxO3 deficiency mirrors age-associated neural activation, apoptosis and enteric neuronal loss</head><p><s>Similar to C57/BL6 mice, we found an age-dependent increase in the numbers of enteric neurons immunoreactive for pSTAT3 in the FVB mouse strain (p&lt;.01 by two-way ANOVA).</s><s>FoxO3 deficiency caused a statistically significant increase in the percent of pSTAT3 + neurons compared to WT in the mid and old age groups (figure <ref type="figure">7A</ref>).</s><s>We also found a statistically significant increase in numbers of enteric neurons expressing the apoptosis marker Asp 175 in FoxO3 −/− mice compared to WT in all age groups (figure <ref type="figure">7B</ref> and supplemental table 3).</s><s>These findings corresponded to a decrease in neuronal density in FoxO3 −/− mice compared to WT in young and mid-aged groups but not old (figure <ref type="figure">7C</ref>).</s><s>On a separate cohort of male mice between 14-17 months of age, FoxO3 −/− mice demonstrated prolonged total intestinal transit times compared to age-matched controls (figure <ref type="figure">7D</ref>).</s><s>In summary, these findings suggest that FoxO3 deficiency mimics a premature aging phenotype in the ENS.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p><s>A growing body of evidence suggests that MMs play an important role in maintenance of gastrointestinal neuromuscular function and that perturbations in their phenotype may underlie motility disorders <ref type="bibr">[4 6 10-14]</ref>.</s><s>Here we show that MMs are the predominant immune cell within the muscularis layer of intestine, comprising between 60-80% of all leukocytes.</s><s>Although aging does not affect their abundance, it causes a shift in macrophage polarization from anti-inflammatory M2 to pro-inflammatory M1 (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">1</ref>).</s><s>This agedependent shift in macrophage phenotype parallels inflammatory changes in the ENS microenvironment including elevated pro-inflammatory cytokines and infiltration of immune cells particularly lymphocytes (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>), and functional delay in intestinal transit (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3D</ref>).</s><s>Our findings mirror those seen following acute injury using animal models for POI where macrophages have been shown to be responsible for driving inflammation and disrupting gastrointestinal neuromuscular function[ <ref type="bibr">13 14</ref>].</s><s>Notably, chronic low-grade inflammation, termed 'inflammaging', has been observed in other tissues and organs with aging <ref type="bibr" target="#b30">[30]</ref> and macrophages have been speculated to play a critical role <ref type="bibr" target="#b31">[31]</ref>.</s><s>In addition to macrophages, other cells may also contribute to the observed inflammation.</s><s>We noted an increase in the numbers of lymphocytes with age (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2D</ref>).</s><s>While this may be secondary to pro-inflammatory factors released by macrophages, intrinsic age-dependent alterations in lymphocyte populations, particularly regulatory and effector T cells, may contribute.</s><s>Additionally, non-immune cells particularly enteric glia and senescent cells may have a role in the inflammation.</s><s>Enteric glia have been implicated in production of IL-6 and MCP-1 following injury <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">[32]</ref>.</s><s>Senescent cells, which have been detected in myenteric ganglia of old mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">[33]</ref>, can secrete pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines termed senescenceassociated secretory phenotype <ref type="bibr" target="#b34">[34]</ref>.</s><s>Further experiments aimed at elucidating the contributions of various cell types on age-dependent inflammation are clearly needed.</s></p><p><s>Our analysis was restricted to the muscularis layer of the small intestine, but we believe our findings are generalizable to other regions of the gut including the colon and submucosal layer.</s><s>While local embryonic precursor cells of yolk sac origin maintain some macrophage populations, mucosal macrophages from intestine have been shown to derive from circulating monocytes from bone marrow <ref type="bibr" target="#b35">[35]</ref>.</s><s>Given that we observed a loss of suppressive behavior in BMDMs from old mice (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5E</ref>), it is likely that macrophages from other regions of the gut derived from circulating monocytes will have a similar phenotype.</s><s>Nonetheless, future experiments definitively showing that MMs from adult mice are derived from circulating monocytes are clearly warranted.</s></p><p><s>While the pathogenesis of gastrointestinal neuromuscular disorders including gastroparesis, functional dyspepsia and irritable bowel syndrome remains poorly understood, inflammation appears to play a role <ref type="bibr" target="#b36">[36]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b37">[37]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b38">[38]</ref>.</s><s>In animal models of colitis, inflammation has been shown to cause a loss of myenteric neurons <ref type="bibr">[39 40</ref>].</s><s>Our findings support a role for inflammation in the pathogenesis of age-related gastrointestinal disorders such as constipation.</s><s>We demonstrate that inflammation in the ENS microenvironment of old mice correlates with a neural response (increased STAT3 activity in myenteric neurons), neuronal loss, and delayed intestinal transit (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">3</ref>).</s><s>These findings suggest that immunotherapies may have a role in the treatment of age-related gastrointestinal disorders.</s><s>Future studies that replicate our findings in humans and manipulate the immune response to dampen age-dependent inflammation are likely to determine the potential of such therapies.</s></p><p><s>A decline in ENSCs has previously been noted in old mice <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref> and our finding of reduced EdU uptake in ganglia of old mice seems to support this (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4A</ref>).</s><s>We show that factors released from the aged ENS microenvironment, particularly IL-6, causes increased apoptosis of ENSCs (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4B-D</ref>).</s><s>While ENSCs remain quiescent in adult mice at steady state <ref type="bibr">[16 17 19]</ref>, they appear capable of neurogenesis after injury <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</s><s>Thus it suggests that elderly individuals may have more lasting damage to their ENS following acute insults such as gastroenteritis or toxin ingestion than young.</s></p><p><s>Our findings suggest that age-intrinsic differences in macrophages play a role in the observed shift in macrophage phenotype.</s><s>Despite an inherent limitation in our chimera experiment, the use of congenic mice which prevented us from determining efficiency of tissue engraftment, we observed a reduction in M2 markers in O→Y compared to Y→Y (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5B</ref>), suggesting both successful engraftment and intrinsic differences in macrophage phenotype.</s><s>Similar age-dependent reduction of M2 markers (FIZZ1, Arg1, and SOC1) has been observed in IL-4-treated macrophages derived from human peripheral blood monocytes and mouse adherent splenocytes <ref type="bibr">[41 42</ref>], arguing that this difference is common to humans and other populations of macrophages.</s><s>It is notable that despite the loss of antiinflammatory phenotype, MMs from O→Y did not demonstrate a significant rise in proinflammatory M1 markers compared to Y→Y (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5C</ref>).</s><s>Additionally, M1-polarized BMDMs from old mice did not demonstrate increased expression of pro-inflammatory markers compared to young either (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5F</ref>).</s><s>This suggests that while macrophages from old mice may have less suppressive properties, extrinsic factors in the aged microenvironment are likely responsible for their assuming a pro-inflammatory phenotype.</s><s>A recent study found a preference for M2 phenotype in mice deficient of IL-18 receptor <ref type="bibr" target="#b43">[43]</ref>, thus it is possible that the elevation of IL-18 we observed in the aged-microenvironment by Luminex (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2A</ref>) may be one such extrinsic factors that promotes a pro-inflammatory phenotype.</s></p><p><s>Our findings implicate a role for FoxO3 in the intrinsic differences observed in macrophages with age.</s><s>Although one explanation for the lower M1 and M2 markers seen in IFNγ and IL-4/IL-13-treated BMDMs from FoxO3 −/− mice (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6D and 6E</ref>) is a diminished ability to polarize, we do not believe this to be the case.</s><s>We found substantial differences in particular M1 and M2 markers (over 5-fold elevation of iNOS for IFNγ-treated FoxO3 −/− BMDMs and &gt;100,000-fold elevation of FIZZ1 for IL-4/IL-13-treated FoxO3 −/− BMDMs, data not shown) compared to untreated 'M0' BMDMs from both WT and FoxO3 −/− suggesting no lack in ability to polarize.</s><s>Therefore, our findings suggest that FoxO3 is necessary for maintaining suppressive and homeostatic properties of alternatively activated macrophages (figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6D</ref>).</s><s>A similar immune modulatory role for FoxO3 has been observed in human monocytes.</s><s>A similar immune modulatory role for FoxO3 has been observed in human monocytes.</s><s>A genetic variant of FOXO3 (rs12212067) that is associated with more aggressive Crohn's disease and rheumatoid arthritis was found to result in decreased expression of FoxO3 and increased production of pro-inflammatory cytokines in human monocytes following stimulation with LPS <ref type="bibr" target="#b27">[27]</ref>.</s><s>While this genetic variant has not been linked to longevity, others found in close proximity have been <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref>.</s><s>While the mechanism by which these FOXO3 genetic variants extend life is unclear, our results suggest that these polymorphisms may maintain higher expression of FoxO3 in macrophages with age thus dampening inflammation.</s></p><p><s>FoxO3 is expressed in a variety of tissues and cells and regulates diverse biologic processes including metabolism, autophagy, apoptosis and stem cell homeostasis <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">[26]</ref>.</s><s>Conditional deletion of FoxO3 in neural stem cells causes their premature depletion within the central nervous system with aging[ <ref type="bibr">15 44</ref>].</s><s>The importance of FoxO3 is highlighted by the resultant delay in intestinal transit (figure <ref type="figure">7D</ref>).</s><s>We believe this is due to the role of FoxO3 in immune modulation based on the increased STAT3 activity and neuronal loss observed in the ENS of FoxO3 −/− mice (figure <ref type="figure">7A-C</ref>); however, we cannot exclude the possibility that the effect of FoxO3 deficiency on non-immune cells like neurons and glia may be involved.</s><s>Thus, further studies including BM chimeras and cell-type-specific knockouts will be necessary to further elucidate the relative importance of FoxO3 deficiency in different cell types on the ENS.</s><s>It is unclear why we did not observe a difference in neuronal density in FoxO3 −/− and WT mice from the old age group but a possible explanation is selection bias given that only 26% of FoxO3 −/− mice survived to 20 months of age (data not shown).</s></p><p><s>Based on the findings of our study, we propose a model for age-dependent motility disorders (supplemental figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">6</ref>).</s><s>An age-related decline in FoxO3 expression in MMs causes loss of their suppressive properties and results in a low-grade chronic inflammatory state.</s><s>With time, this pro-inflammatory state results in tissue damage, a loss of regenerative capacity, and ultimately a decline in neuromuscular function.</s><s>Immunostaining of wholemount preparations of LMMP labeled with pan-neuronal marker HuC/D (red) and pSTAT3 (green) revealed increased numbers of Hu + neurons expressing pSTAT3 (arrows) in old compared with young mice (A).</s><s>This difference expressed as a percent of neurons (pSTAT3 + Hu + /total Hu + ) was statistically significant.</s><s>Increased STAT3 activity corresponded to an increase in number of Hu + neurons (red) co-expressing the apoptosis marker cleaved caspase-3 (Asp175, green, arrows) in old mice compared to young (B).</s><s>As a percent of neurons (Asp175 + Hu + /total Hu + ) this difference was statistically significant.</s><s>Old mice also demonstrated a statistically significant reduction in neuronal density (Hu + cells/ganglia area (100 μm    Western blot revealed a modest but statistically significant reduction of FoxO3 expression in protein extract of LMMP from old compared to young mice based on pixel intensity normalized to GAPDH (A).</s><s>A decline in FoxO3 expression was also found in sorted MMs (B) and IL-4/IL-13-treated BMDMs (C) from old mice.</s><s>To evaluate whether decreased FoxO3 expression might be responsible for alterations in macrophage phenotype, BMDMs were derived from FoxO3 −/− and WT mice and treated with either IFNγ (M 1 ) or IL-4 and IL-13 (M 2 ).</s><s>M 2 BMDMs from FoxO3 −/− mice demonstrated reduced expression of M2 markers particularly CD206 compared to WT (D).</s><s>Decreased expression of proinflammatory markers iNOS and TNFα was observed in M 1 BMDMs from FoxO3 −/− mice (E) although higher expression of M1 markers was seen following LPS stimulation (see supplemental figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">5D</ref>).</s><s>For (C-E) RNA expression was normalized to untreated (M 0 ) macrophages from WT mice.</s><s>*p&lt;.05, **p&lt;.01 by t-test.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIZZ1Found 3 Young</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>CM conditioned media prepared with LMMP from young miceOld CMconditioned media prepared with LMMP from old mice</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 1.</s><s>Muscularis macrophages demonstrate a shift from anti-inflammatory to proinflammatory state with agingOn flow cytometry, MMs (CD45 + F4/80 + cells) were found to be the predominant immune cell in the muscularis layer, comprising between 15-20% of all live cells, but their numbers did not differ significantly with age (A).</s><s>MMs sorted from old and mid-aged mice revealed a decline in expression of M2 markers CD206, FIZZ1 and TGFβ (B), and a rise in expression of M1 markers, particularly IL-6, which reached statistical significance in old (C) compared to young mice by qRT-PCR.</s><s>n≥10 for all groups, *p&lt;.05, ***p&lt;.001</s><s>by one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni's multiple comparisons test.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="15,143.04,62.00,385.92,124.32" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 2. Increased inflammation in ENS microenvironment with ageHeat map of cytokine and chemokine expression of LMMP lysate from young and old mice from Luminex analysis revealed higher pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines with age (A).</s><s>Elevation of IL-6 was seen on a second cohort of young and old mice by Western blot, which was statistically significant based on pixel intensity normalized to GAPDH (B).</s><s>Flow cytometry performed on enzymatically dissociated LMMP with gating of live, single cells revealed increased numbers of CD45 + leukocytes (as percent of live cells) in old mice compared to young (C).</s><s>There was also a statistically significant rise in lymphocytes (CD3 + CD19 + ) in old compared to young mice but no difference in dendritic cells (CD11c + F4/80 − ) as a percent of live cells (D).n≥5 for each group; *p&lt;.05, **p&lt;.01 by Mann Whitney for (A); **p&lt;.01 by t-test for (B); *p&lt;.05, **p&lt;.01 by one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni's multiple comparisons test for (C) and (D).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="16,143.04,62.00,385.92,202.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 3. Age-dependent changes to myenteric plexus are associated with delayed intestinal transit</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="17,119.28,62.00,433.44,354.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>2 )) compared to young (C).</s><s>Whole intestinal transit studies performed on a separate cohort of young and old mice revealed prolonged transit times in old mice (D).</s><s>**p&lt;.01,</s><s>***p&lt;.001</s><s>by t-test.</s><s>Scale bars, 50 μm.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Figure 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 4. Effect of aging and pro-inflammatory cytokines on enteric neural stem cellsUsing an ex vivo organotypic culturing system to measure proliferation, a nearly 3 fold reduction of EdU + cells (green) were found per ganglia area in old compared to young mice (A).</s><s>Using CD49b magnetic beads, ENSCs were isolated from a Wnt1-cre;tdTomato mouse (fluorescently labelled neural-crest cells) and cultured with conditioned media prepared with LMMP from young (Young CM) or old (Old CM) mice.</s><s>Old CM was also cultured with either IL-6 neutralizing antibody or an IgG control.</s><s>TUNEL assay revealed over 2-fold increase in numbers of TUNEL + cells (green) when ENSCs (red) were cultured with Old CM compared to Young CM indicating increased apoptosis due to factors in the aged ENS microenvironment.</s><s>This increase in TUNEL-positivity was reversed with the addition of IL-6 neutralizing antibody but not IgG control (B and C).</s><s>When cultured with recombinant IL-6 at increasing concentrations, ENSCs demonstrated a statistically significant increase in TUNEL + cells (D) at the highest concentration (100 ng/ml).</s><s>The addition of soluble IL-6 Rα (200 ng/ml) augmented the number of TUNEL + cells when added to IL-6 at a lower concentration (50 ng/ml).</s><s>*p&lt;.05 by t-test for (A); *p&lt;.05, **p&lt;.005 by one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni's multiple comparisons test for (C) and (D).</s><s>Scale bars, 50 μm.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="18,191.04,62.00,289.92,340.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 5. Macrophages from old mice have intrinsic differences that make them less antiinflammatoryCongeneic BM chimeras were generated by injecting BM harvested from young or old C57BL/6 mice into lethally irradiated young or old mice (A).</s><s>MMs sorted from O→Y expressed decreased M2 markers compared to Y→Y suggesting that the age-dependent loss of anti-inflammatory phenotype is intrinsic to the macrophage (B).</s><s>Although not statistically significant, mice transplanted with old BM (O→Y and O→O) had a trend towards increased expression of iNOS (C).</s><s>Bone marrow derived macrophages (BMDMs) prepared from old mice and treated with IL-4 and IL-13 to polarize to M2 activation state (M 2 ) exhibited reduced expression of M2 markers particularly CD206 and TGFβ (D).</s><s>IFNγ-treated BMDMs (M 1 ) from young and old mice did not demonstrate significant differences in expression of proinflammatory M1 markers (E).</s><s>When incubated with CD4 + T cells activated with anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 and labeled with CSFE, IL-4/IL-13-treated BMDMs from old mice demonstrated reduced suppression of lymphocyte proliferation (higher percent of CSFE-negative CD4 + cells) compared to those from young (F).</s><s>For (D) and (E) RNA expression was normalized to untreated (M 0 ) macrophages from young mice.</s><s>*p&lt;.05 by one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni's multiple comparisons test and t-test, **p&lt;.01 by ttest.</s><s>n≥5 for chimeric mouse groups.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="19,119.44,62.00,433.12,327.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>Figure 6.</s><s>Reduction of FoxO3 expression with aging contributes to decrease in antiinflammatory phenotype</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="20,119.52,62.00,432.97,218.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="21,155.04,62.00,361.92,267.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Gut. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2018 May 01.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p><s>Grant Support: Supported by NIH grants AG045098 (LB), DK103966 (LB) and AG049622 (AH).</s></p><p><s>We thank Jing Xue, Marisol Chang, Vishal Sharma, and Sidhartha Sinha for technical assistance.</s><s>We thank Anne Brunet for providing resources to conduct experiments.</s><s>We thank Vanda Lennon (Mayo Clinic, Rochester) for providing the HuC/D antibody.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supplementary Material</head><p><s>Refer to Web version on PubMed Central for supplementary material.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Abbreviations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BMDMs bone marrow derived macrophages</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary Box</head><p><s>What is already known about this subject?</s></p><p><s>• Direct cross-talk between muscularis macrophages and enteric neurons controls gastrointestinal neuromuscular function.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p><s>Muscularis macrophages have been implicated in disease pathogenesis of motility disorders including gastroparesis and post-operative ileus.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p><s>Aging is associated with neurodegenerative changes to the ENS and impairment of neuromuscular function but the mechanism remains unclear.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>What are the new findings?</head><p><s>• A shift in macrophage polarization from anti-inflammatory 'M2' to proinflammatory 'M1' states occurs in muscularis macrophages with aging and is associated with chronic low-grade inflammation in the ENS microenvironment and delayed transit.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p><s>Intrinsic changes in macrophages, particularly age-dependent decrease in expression of the transcription factor FoxO3, account for some of the alterations in macrophage phenotype with aging.</s></p><p><s>How might it impact on clinical practices in the foreseeable future?</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p><s>Our findings indicate that 'inflammaging', a chronic low-grade inflammatory state associated with aging, may contribute to age-dependent degeneration of the ENS and age-associated motility disorders.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p><s>This may lead to novel immunotherapies to treat common disorders like constipation and fecal incontinence.</s><s>compared to WT mice in the mid and old age groups (A).</s><s>Expressed as percent of neurons (pSTAT3 + Hu + /total Hu + ), this difference was statistically significant for the mid and old age groups.</s><s>An increased number of Hu + neurons (red) co-expressing cleaved caspase-3 (Asp175, green, arrow) was also found in FoxO3 −/− compared to WT mice and was statistically significant in all age groups (B).</s><s>A statistically significant decline in neuronal density (Hu + cells/ganglia area (100 μm 2 )) in was observed in FoxO3</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Neurogastroenterology and motility: the official journal of the European Gastrointestinal Motility Society</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Camilleri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Cowen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Koch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1365-2982.2007.01072.x</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="185" to="196" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Enteric neurodegeneration in ageing. published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 18257768</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Prevalence of gastrointestinal symptoms in the elderly: a population-based study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Talley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>O'keefe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Zinsmeister</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gastroenterology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="895" to="901" />
			<date type="published" when="1992">1992</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 1537525</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cellular changes in the enteric nervous system during ageing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Saffrey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ydbio.2013.03.015</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Developmental biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">382</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="344" to="355" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 23537898</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neuro-immune Interactions Drive Tissue Programming in Intestinal Macrophages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Gabanyi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Muller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Feighery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cell.2015.12.023</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">164</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="378" to="391" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 26777404</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Macrophages in the external muscle layers of mammalian intestines</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mikkelsen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Histology and histopathology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="719" to="736" />
			<date type="published" when="1995">1995</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 7579823</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crosstalk between muscularis macrophages and enteric neurons regulates gastrointestinal motility</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Muller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Koscso</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Rajani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cell.2014.04.050</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">158</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="300" to="313" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 25036630</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Alternative activation of macrophages</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gordon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nri978</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature reviews Immunology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Macrophage activation switching: an asset for the resolution of inflammation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Porcheray</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Viaud</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Rimaniol</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1365-2249.2005.02934.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical and experimental immunology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">142</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="481" to="489" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 16297160</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Macrophage biology in development, homeostasis and disease</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Wynn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Chawla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Pollard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nature12034</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">496</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7446</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="445" to="455" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 23619691</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Association of low numbers of CD206-positive cells with loss of ICC in the gastric body of patients with diabetic gastroparesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Bernard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gibbons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Mann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/nmo.12389</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurogastroenterology and motility: the official journal of the European Gastrointestinal Motility Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1275" to="1284" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 25041465</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">CD206-positive M2 macrophages that express heme oxygenase-1 protect against diabetic gastroparesis in mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Choi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Kashyap</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Dutta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1053/j.gastro.2010.02.014</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gastroenterology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">138</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2399" to="2409" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>409 e1. published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 20178793</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Diabetic Csf1op/op mice lacking macrophages are protected against the development of delayed gastric emptying. Cellular and molecular gastroenterology and hepatology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Cipriani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gibbons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Verhulst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jcmgh.2015.09.001</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="40" to="47" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 26771000</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A distinct vagal anti-inflammatory pathway modulates intestinal muscularis resident macrophages independent of the spleen</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Matteoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Gomez-Pinilla</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nemethova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/gutjnl-2013-304676</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gut</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">63</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="938" to="948" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 23929694</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inhibition of macrophage function prevents intestinal inflammation and postoperative ileus in rodents</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wehner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Behrendt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Lyutenski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1136/gut.2005.089615</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gut</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="176" to="185" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 16809419</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FoxO3 regulates neural stem cell homeostasis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Renault</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Rafalski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Morgan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.stem.2009.09.014</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell stem cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="527" to="539" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 19896443</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ex vivo neurogenesis within enteric ganglia occurs in a PTEN dependent manner</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Peterson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kulkarni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1371/journal.pone.0059452</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS one</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>):e59452. published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 23527198</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enteric glia are multipotent in culture but primarily form glia in the adult rodent gut</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Joseph</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>He</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Quintana</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1172/JCI58186</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of clinical investigation</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The human epilepsy mutation GABRG2(Q390X) causes chronic subunit accumulation and neurodegeneration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">Q</forename><surname>Kang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nn.4024</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="988" to="996" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 26005849</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Glial cells in the mouse enteric nervous system can undergo neurogenesis in response to injury</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Laranjeira</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Sandgren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Kessaris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1172/JCI58200</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of clinical investigation</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neurogenesis in the enteric nervous system</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Metzger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Arch Ital Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">148</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 20830970</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Increasing p16INK4a expression decreases forebrain progenitors and neurogenesis during ageing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Molofsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Slutsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Joseph</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">443</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="448" to="452" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Online First: Epub Date</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nature05091</idno>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 16957738</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Divergent fate and origin of neurosphere-like bodies from different layers of the gut</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Becker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kulkarni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tiwari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>DOI: 10.1152/ ajpgi.00511.2011</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American journal of physiology Gastrointestinal and liver physiology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">302</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="G958" to="G965" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 22361728</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inflammatory blockade restores adult hippocampal neurogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Monje</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Toda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Palmer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1126/science.1088417</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">302</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5651</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1760" to="1765" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 14615545</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Reduced hippocampal neurogenesis in adult transgenic mice with chronic astrocytic production of interleukin-6. The Journal of neuroscience: the official journal of the Society for</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Vallieres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Gage</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="486" to="492" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 11784794</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IL-6 trans-signaling promotes pancreatitis-associated lung injury and lethality</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Neuhofer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Song</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1172/JCI64931</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of clinical investigation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">123</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1019" to="1031" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 23426178</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FOXO3: A Major Gene for Human Longevity -A Mini-Review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Willcox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Donlon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1159/000375235</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gerontology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="515" to="525" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 25832544</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human SNP links differential outcomes in inflammatory and infectious disease to a FOXO3-regulated pathway</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Espeli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.cell.2013.08.034</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">155</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 24035192</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transcription factor Foxo3 controls the magnitude of T cell immune responses by modulating the function of dendritic cells</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Dejean</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Beisner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Ch'en</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Il</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/ni.1729</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature immunology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="504" to="513" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 19363483</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Effects of aging and caloric restriction on the gene expression of Foxo1, 3, and 4 (FKHR, FKHRL1, and AFX) in the rat skeletal muscles. Microscopy research and technique</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Furuyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yamashita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Kitayama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1002/jemt.10213</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="331" to="334" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 12424797</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Inflammaging and anti-inflammaging: a systemic perspective on aging and longevity emerged from studies in humans. Mechanisms of ageing and development</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Franceschi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Capri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Monti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.mad.2006.11.016</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">128</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="105" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 17116321</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Inflamm-aging. An evolutionary perspective on immunosenescence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Franceschi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bonafe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Valensin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">908</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="244" to="254" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PubMed: 10911963</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Postoperative Ileus Involves Interleukin-1 Receptor Signaling in Enteric Glia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Stoffels</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Hupa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Snoek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1053/j.gastro.2013.09.030</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gastroenterology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Postmitotic neurons develop a p21-dependent senescence-like phenotype driven by a DNA damage response</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Jurk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Miwa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1474-9726.2012.00870.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Aging cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="996" to="1004" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 22882466</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Four faces of cellular senescence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rodier</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Campisi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1083/jcb.201009094</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Journal of cell biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">192</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="547" to="556" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 21321098</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Constant replenishment from circulating monocytes maintains the macrophage pool in the intestine of adult mice</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Bain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bravo-Blas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/ni.2967</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature immunology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="929" to="937" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 25151491</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cellular changes in diabetic and idiopathic gastroparesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Grover</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Farrugia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Lurken</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>DOI: 10.1053/ j.gastro.2011.01.046</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Gastroenterology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">140</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1575" to="1585" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>e8. published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 21300066</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pathogenesis of IBS: role of inflammation, immunity and neuroimmune interactions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ohman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Simren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nrgastro.2010.4</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature reviews Gastroenterology &amp; hepatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="173" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 20101257</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Changes in gastrointestinal tract function and structure in functional dyspepsia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Vanheel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Farre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nrgastro.2012.255</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature reviews Gastroenterology &amp; hepatology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="149" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 23318268</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Activation of neuronal P2X7 receptor-pannexin-1 mediates death of enteric neurons during colitis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Gulbransen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bashashati</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hirota</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/nm.2679</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="600" to="604" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Indiscriminate loss of myenteric neurones in the TNBS-inflamed guinea-pig distal colon</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Linden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Couvrette</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ciolino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1111/j.1365-2982.2005.00703.x</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Neurogastroenterology and motility: the official journal of the European Gastrointestinal Motility Society</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="751" to="760" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 16185315</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Journal of interferon &amp; cytokine research: the official journal of the International Society for Interferon and Cytokine Research</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mahbub</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Deburghgraeve</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kovacs</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1089/jir.2011.0058</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="26" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Advanced age impairs macrophage polarization. published Online First: Epub Date</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comparison of chosen activation markers of human monocytes/macrophages isolated from the peripheral blood of young and elderly volunteers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Suchy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Labuzek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Buldak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.pharep.2014.04.008</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pharmacological reports: PR</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">66</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="759" to="765" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 25149978</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Divergent responses to thermogenic stimuli in BAT and subcutaneous adipose tissue from interleukin 18 and interleukin 18 receptor 1-deficient mice. Scientific reports</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Pazos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Lima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tovar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1038/srep17977</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">17977</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 26656097</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">FoxOs cooperatively regulate diverse pathways governing neural stem cell homeostasis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Paik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Narurkar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.stem.2009.09.013</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cell stem cell</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="540" to="553" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published Online First: Epub Date. PubMed: 19896444</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
