<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Comparative Evaluation of the Biodistribution Profiles of a Series of Nonpeptidic Neurotensin Receptor-1 Antagonists Reveals a Promising Candidate for Theranostic Applications</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jörg</forename><surname>Schulz</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Klinik für Radiologie und Nuklearmedizin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Otto-von-Guericke Universität Magdeburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Magdeburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Martin</forename><surname>Rohracker</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Klinik für Radiologie und Nuklearmedizin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Otto-von-Guericke Universität Magdeburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Magdeburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Marvin</forename><surname>Stiebler</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Klinik für Radiologie und Nuklearmedizin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Otto-von-Guericke Universität Magdeburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Magdeburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jürgen</forename><surname>Goldschmidt</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Leibniz-Institut für Neurobiologie</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Magdeburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Oliver</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Grosser</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Klinik für Radiologie und Nuklearmedizin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Otto-von-Guericke Universität Magdeburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Magdeburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Frank</forename><surname>Osterkamp</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">3B Pharmaceuticals GmbH</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Annette</forename><surname>Pethe</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Klinik für Radiologie und Nuklearmedizin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Otto-von-Guericke Universität Magdeburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Magdeburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ulrich</forename><surname>Reineke</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">3B Pharmaceuticals GmbH</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Christiane</forename><surname>Smerling</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">3B Pharmaceuticals GmbH</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Holger</forename><surname>Amthauer</surname></persName>
							<email>holger.amthauer@med.ovgu.de</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Klinik für Radiologie und Nuklearmedizin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Otto-von-Guericke Universität Magdeburg</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Magdeburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Nuclear Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charité-Universitätsmedizin</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Berlin</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Klinik</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Radiologie und Nuklearmedizin</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Otto-von-Guericke Universität</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Leipziger Strasse 44</addrLine>
									<postCode>39120</postCode>
									<settlement>Magdeburg</settlement>
									<country key="DE">Germany</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Comparative Evaluation of the Biodistribution Profiles of a Series of Nonpeptidic Neurotensin Receptor-1 Antagonists Reveals a Promising Candidate for Theranostic Applications</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">34DEF8B5BB5A7DE009F1D47333957C59</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.2967/jnumed.115.170530</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received Nov. 30, 2015; revision accepted Feb. 10, 2016.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:27+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>NTR1-radiotracer</term>
					<term>xenograft</term>
					<term>SPECT/CT</term>
					<term>biodistribution</term>
					<term>oncology</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Neurotensin receptor-1 (NTR1) is a promising target for diagnostic imaging and targeted radionuclide therapy.</s><s>The aim of this study was to evaluate the biodistribution profiles of a series of newly developed diarylpyrazole-based NTR1 antagonists regarding their suitability as diagnostic and potentially radiotherapeutic agents.</s><s>Methods: 3BP-227, 3BP-228, and 3BP-483 were labeled with 111 In and injected intravenously into NTR1-positive HT29 xenograftbearing nude mice.</s><s>At 3, 6, 12, and 24 h after administration, SPECT/ CT images were acquired or mice were sacrificed for ex vivo determination of tissue-associated radioactivity.</s><s>Results: High-contrast tumor visualization in SPECT/CT images was achieved using the 3 compounds of this study.</s><s>Ex vivo biodistribution studies confirmed a high and persistent tumor uptake, peaking at 6 h after injection for 111 In-3BP-227 (8.4 ± 3.1 percentage injected dose per gram [%ID/g]) and at 3 h after injection for 111 In-3BP-228 (10.2 ± 5.3 %ID/g) and 111 In-3BP-483 (1.9 ± 0.8 %ID/g).</s><s>Tumor-to-normal-tissue ratios obtained with 111 In-3BP-227 and 111 In-3BP-228 were consistently greater than 1.</s><s>Conclusion: On the basis of the superior biodistribution profile compared with previously reported radiolabeled NTR1 ligands, 111 In-3BP-227 is an ideal candidate for further development as a theranostic tracer.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Cer tain peptide receptors, such as the neurotensin receptors (NTRs), are commonly overexpressed in many primary human tumors and their metastases, making them ideal targets for molecular imaging and targeted cancer therapy <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2)</ref>.</s><s>The NTR subtype 1 (NTR1) has been associated with several oncogenic effects such as proliferation, survival, migration, invasion, and neoangiogenesis <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4)</ref> and has been demonstrated to be overexpressed, inter alia, in ductal pancreatic cancer, Ewing's sarcoma, and small cell lung cancer <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>.</s><s>Hence, NTR1 imaging might be a promising tool for tumor diagnosis and staging.</s></p><p><s>Previous attempts at specific delivery of diagnostic and therapeutic radionuclides to tumors using NTR1 as a target have focused on the development of radiolabeled derivatives of its natural ligand neurotensin with improved metabolic stability <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>.</s><s>Although some of the reported radiolabeled agonistic peptides achieved a distinct tumor uptake, in the cases of 177 Lu or 188 Re payloads even accompanied by a certain antitumoral effect, overall results were compromised by varying degrees of relatively low and unfavorable tumor-to-background ratios.</s><s>Because recent developments in somatostatin and gastrin-releasing peptide receptor targeting indicate a superior tumor uptake and retention of radiolabeled antagonists compared with agonists (6-8), Osterkamp et al. modified the known NTR1 antagonist SR142948A (9,10) by attaching short linker-chelator moieties, yielding the novel diarylpyrazole-based NTR1 antagonists 3BP-227, -228, and -483 (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>The incorporated DOTA chelator is capable of forming stable complexes with a wide range of diagnostic (e.g., 111 In or 68 Ga) and therapeutic (e.g., 177 Lu or 90 Y) radionuclides <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>.</s><s>In vitro evaluation of the compounds indicated a high NTR1 affinity and specificity as well as adequate metabolic stability in human and murine plasma, which warranted the further examination in in vivo studies.</s><s>The aim of this study was to evaluate and compare the potential for clinical translation of 3BP-227, 3BP-228, and 3BP-483 based on their imaging performance and biodistribution profiles in tumor-bearing mice.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MATERIALS AND METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Radiolabeling</head><p><s>Compounds were dissolved in buffer (0.4 M acetate, 0.325 M gentisic acid, pH 5), and aliquots (3BP-227, 4.4-39.0</s><s>mg; 3BP-228, 9.0 mg; 3BP-483, 4.6-9.2</s><s>mg) were incubated with 200-400 MBq of 111 InCl 3 in 0.05 M HCl (Covidien) at 95°C for 30 min.</s><s>After being cooled, the product was analyzed by instant thin-layer and high-performance liquid chromatography and formulated in 0.9% NaCl for intravenous administration.</s><s>Detailed analytic methods can be found in the supplemental data (supplemental materials are available at http://jnm.snmjournals.org).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tumor Model</head><p><s>Experiments were approved by the local animal welfare committee and performed according to national regulations.</s><s>Mice were kept in individually ventilated cages under standard conditions with food and water ad libitum.</s><s>NTR1-positive HT29 human colorectal carcinoma cells (European Collection of Authenticated Cell Cultures and Cell Lines Services) <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref> and NTR1-negative HEK293 human embryonic kidney cells (European Collection of Authenticated Cell Cultures) <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> were grown in McCoy 5A modified medium (Biochrom) and Dulbecco modified Eagle medium, respectively, each supplemented with 10% fetal calf serum, 2 mM L-glutamine, penicillin (10,000 U/mL), and streptomycin (10 mg/mL) at 37°C in 5% CO 2 .</s><s>Cells (2-3 • 10 6 suspended in McCoy 5A modified medium, 40 • 10 6 cells/mL) were inoculated subcutaneously in the right flank of 6-to 8-wk-old athymic nu/nu female mice (Nude-Foxn1 nu ; Harlan Laboratories).</s><s>Biodistribution and imaging studies were performed 2-4 wk after inoculation when the tumor was palpable.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SPECT/CT Imaging</head><p><s>Mice were injected via a lateral tail vein with 111 In-labeled 3BP-227 (21-47 MBq; n 5 6), 3BP-228 (33-44 MBq; n 5 4), or 3BP-483 (31-44 MBq; n 5 3) under isoflurane anesthesia (1%-2% isoflurane 2:1 O 2 : N 2 O volume ratio).</s><s>Whole-body imaging was performed 3, 6, 12, and 24 h after injection with a 4-head NanoSPECT/CT scanner (Mediso Ltd.).</s><s>SPECT scans were acquired using a multipinhole collimator set (SCIVIS), each collimator with 9 pinholes (1.4-mm pinhole diameters).</s><s>SPECT imaging was performed with 2 energy windows of 171 keV 6 5% and 245 keV 6 5% and an acquisition time of 60 min.</s><s>Images were reconstructed with isotropic voxel output sizes of 300-600 mm, depending on counting rates (HiSPECT; SCIVIS).</s><s>CT scans were acquired at a 192-mm isotropic detector resolution and reconstructed at isotropic voxel sizes of 200 mm (InVivoScope 1.43; Bioscan).</s><s>After the last acquisition, mice were sacrificed and included into the 24-h-after-injection cohort for the ex vivo biodistribution studies described below.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ex Vivo Biodistribution Studies</head><p><s>Mice were injected intravenously with 111 In-labeled 3BP-227 (0.2-12.2 MBq), 3BP-228 (5.5-7.6 MBq), or 3BP-483 (4.9-18.4</s><s>MBq) under isoflurane anesthesia and sacrificed 3, 6, 12, or 24 h later.</s><s>For each time point and tracer, 3-9 animals were examined.</s><s>As a control for receptor specificity, mice bearing NTR1-negative HEK293-tumors (n 5 3) were injected intravenously with 111 In-3BP-227 and sacrificed 12 h after administration.</s><s>Blood, urine, organs, and tumors were collected and weighed, and their activity content was assessed by wellcounter measurement.</s><s>Tissue counts and injected dose for individual mice were decay-corrected to the time of euthanasia.</s><s>Tissue uptake was expressed as the percentage injected dose per gram of tissue (%ID/g).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Analysis</head><p><s>OsiriX MD (open source version 1.3, 64-bit) was used for image analysis.</s><s>CT-guided delineation of volumes of interest for selected tissues was performed on the reconstructed SPECT dataset.</s><s>Tumor-to-kidney activity ratios were calculated by dividing counting rates of the corresponding volumes of interest.</s><s>The estimated ratios were correlated to tumor-to-kidney uptake ratios determined by ex vivo biodistribution using Spearman correlation.</s></p><p><s>Statistical analyses of differences in tissue uptake values and tumor-to-normal-tissue ratios were performed using ANOVA followed by the Tukey post hoc test for multiple comparisons and t test for comparing 2 groups.</s><s>Differences of P values less than 0.05 were considered statistically significant.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESULTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Radiolabeling</head><p><s>Radiochemical yields of 111 In labeling were 97% or greater for all compounds.</s><s>The specific activity of 111 In-3BP-227 was 4.4-6.7 MBq/nmol in initial experiments and increased to 26.0-66.8</s><s>MBq/nmol after further optimization.</s><s>The specific activities of 111 In-3BP-228 and 111 In-3BP-483 were 34.6-35.7 and 33.3-62.8</s><s>MBq/nmol, respectively.</s><s>Instant thin-layer and high-performance liquid chromatography profiles confirmed high radiochemical purity ($97%) as exemplified for 111 In-3BP-227 in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SPECT/CT Imaging</head><p><s>High tumor-to-background contrast allowed the clear visualization of HT29 tumors by all 3 111 In-labeled compounds using SPECT/CT imaging (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>).</s><s>Compared with 111 In-3BP-483, 111 In-3BP-228 and 111 In-3BP-227 displayed higher tumor accumulation at all time points examined. 111</s><s>In-3BP-483 also had the highest relative  kidney uptake, with tumor-to-kidney ratios decreasing from 0.9 at 3 h after injection to 0.5 at 24 h after injection.</s><s>In contrast, tumor-tokidney ratios increased from 2.0 and 3.3 at 3 h after injection to 2.7 and 6.6 at 24 h after injection for 111 In-3BP-227 and 111 In-3BP-228, respectively.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ex Vivo Biodistribution Studies</head><p><s>Ex vivo biodistribution data confirmed the high and specific tumor uptake of all 3 compounds (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">4</ref>; Supplemental Tables <ref type="table">1-3</ref>).</s><s>The uptake of 111 In-3BP-227 in HT29 tumors peaked at 6 h after injection with 8.4 6 3.1 %ID/g, whereas maximum uptake for 111 In-3BP-228 and -483 was observed at 3 h after injection with 10.2 6 5.2 and 1.9 6 0.8 %ID/g, respectively.</s><s>Tumor accumulation profiles of 111 In-3BP-227 and 111 In-3BP-228 were similar at 3, 6, and 12 h after injection, indicating high initial uptake followed by slow tumor activity washout.</s><s>However, 24 h after administration, the tumor uptake of 111 In-3BP-227 was significantly higher than that of 111 In-3BP-228 (2.3 6 1.3 vs. 0.8 6 0.2 %ID/g, P 5 0.020).</s><s>For both compounds, tumor-to-normal-tissue ratios were greater than 1 at all times after injection, and tumor-to-kidney ratios were generally higher for 111 In-3BP-228 than 111 In-3BP-227.</s><s>HT29 tumor uptake and tumor-to-background ratios of 111 In-3BP-483 were significantly lower than for the other 2 compounds.</s><s>A strong correlation of R 5 0.97 (P , 0.001) between tumor-to-kidney ratios determined by imaging and ex vivo counting demonstrated the comparability of these 2 methods. 111</s><s>In-3BP-227 uptake in NTR1-negative HEK293 xenografts was 11-fold lower than in HT29 tumors at 12 h after injection (P 5 0.001; Supplemental Table <ref type="table">1</ref>).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCUSSION</head><p><s>Several preclinical studies and a few clinical studies have previously addressed NTR1 as a target for nuclear oncology <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6)</ref>.</s><s>Most of these studies focused on modifications of the natural peptide ligand neurotensin, which is labile toward enzymatic cleavage in vivo.</s><s>However, attempts to stabilize analogs and improve properties for nuclear imaging and therapy have been of limited success <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref>.</s><s>Although yielding good tumor localization in PET, the only nonpeptidic NTR1 antagonist used as a tracer to date does not allow labeling with therapeutic radionuclides such as 177 Lu because of its lack of a chelator moiety <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>.</s><s>We now report the novel and highly tumor-specific NTR1 antagonists 3BP-227, 3BP-228, and 3BP-483 for diagnostic imaging and potentially therapeutic applications in NTR1-positive tumors.</s></p><p><s>Despite their structural similarity, the 3 compounds displayed a distinct behavior in vivo.</s><s>Uptake of 111 In-3BP-227 and 111 In-3BP-228 in the tumor exceeded that in all other tissues at all times after injection, a result that has not yet been achieved with NTR1 agonists.</s><s>The biodistribution profiles of 111 In-3BP-227 and 111 In-3BP-228 were similar, with higher tumor-to-kidney ratios for 111 In-3BP-228.</s><s>However, 111 In-3BP-227 tumor uptake was higher at 24 h after injection, indicating prolonged retention of 111 In-3BP-227 in the target tissue, and a potential advantage when considering the suitability for targeted radiotherapy.</s><s>Low uptake of 111 In-3BP-227 in NTR1-negative  HEK tumors suggests high target specificity and low unspecific binding. 111</s><s>In-3BP-483 exhibited the least favorable biodistribution profile, with tumor-to-kidney uptake ratios indicating a faster washout from tumor than from kidney tissue.</s></p><p><s>Interestingly, the differential tumor uptake of the 3 compounds, especially at the earlier time points (3-12 h after injection), parallels their potency in an in vitro functional calcium assay (half maximal inhibitory concentration for nat In-labeled compounds: 3BP-227, 5.35 nM; 3BP-228, 14.4 nM; 3BP-483, 75 nM <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>).</s><s>Binding of agonistic ligands to NTR1 causes phospholipase C activation, which leads to an increase in inositol phosphate levels and calcium mobilization, whereas receptor antagonists inhibit neurotensin-stimulated calcium flux <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>, with 3BP-227 and 3BP-228 being particularly potent competitive inhibitors in our series.</s><s>However, only the insights into the general biodistribution pattern with differential kidney accumulation and tumor-to-normal-tissue ratios obtained in this in vivo study allow conclusions about the potential suitability of each compound for radiotherapeutic applications.</s><s>In analogy to somatostatin and gastrin-releasing peptide receptor-based radionuclide imaging, the current investigation confirms the promising performance of receptor antagonists for diagnostic use and potential further therapeutic application.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONCLUSION</head><p><s>The high tumor accumulation and low uptake in normal tissues of 111 In-3BP-227 warrants its further preclinical and ultimately clinical evaluation as an NTR1-targeting imaging agent.</s><s>Moreover, the DOTA moiety of 3BP-227 allows the investigation of its therapeutic potential by labeling with 177 Lu or 90 Y without the need for additional structural modifications, which is currently under way in our laboratories.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIGURE 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 1.</s><s>Chemical structures of 3BP-227, 3BP-228, and 3BP-483.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,57.66,41.84,311.33,113.05" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FIGURE 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 2. Thin-layer (A) and high-performance (B) liquid radiochromatograms after 111 In labeling of 3BP-227, representative for each of the 3 compounds.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,308.75,355.75,227.85,305.35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>FIGURE 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 3. Representative images of 3 female nude mice bearing HT29 xenografts acquired by SPECT/CT at 3, 6, 12, and 24 h after injection (p.i.) of 22 MBq of 111 In-3BP-227 (A), 30 MBq of 111 In-3BP-228 (B), and 31 MBq of 111 In-3BP-483 (C).</s><s>Arrows show HT29.</s><s>SPECT data were scaled to 0%-90% (A and B) or 0%-120% (C) of maximum count values in HT29 tumors in the respective datasets.</s><s>B 5 urinary bladder; K 5 kidney.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,57.71,41.84,227.85,338.17" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>FIGURE 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 4. Uptake of 111 In-3BP-227, -228, or -483 in selected tissues 3, 6, 12, and 24 h after injection (p.i.) (mean %ID/g ± SD).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,308.75,407.17,227.85,263.45" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p><s>We thank Franziska Stoeber for her help with analyzing the data, Ines Heinemann for her expert technical assistance, and Aileen Hoehne for critical review of the manuscript.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DISCLOSURE</head><p><s>The costs of publication of this article were defrayed in part by the payment of page charges.</s><s>Therefore, and solely to indicate this fact, this article is hereby marked "advertisement" in accordance with 18 USC section 1734.</s><s>This work was supported by the KMU Innovativ program of the German Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF, grant 0315865) and the Foundation of German Business (SDW).</s><s>Frank Osterkamp, Ulrich Reineke and Christiane Smerling are cofounders, shareholders, and employees of 3B Pharmaceuticals GmbH and named inventors of the described compounds.</s><s>No other potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Peptide receptors as molecular targets for cancer diagnosis and therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Reubi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Endocr Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="389" to="427" />
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neurotensin receptors in pancreatic ductal carcinomas</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Körner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Waser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Strobel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Büchler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Reubi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">EJNMMI Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">17</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Neurotensin and its high affinity receptor 1 as a potential pharmacological target in cancer therapy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Martinez-Fong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Trédaniel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Forgez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">184</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The potential use of the neurotensin high affinity receptor 1 as a biomarker for cancer progression and as a component of personalized medicine in selective cancers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Dupouy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Mourra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Van Doan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gompel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Alifano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Forgez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochimie</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1369" to="1378" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Targeting neuropeptide receptors for cancer imaging and therapy: perspectives with bombesin, neurotensin, and neuropeptide-Y receptors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Morgat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Mishra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Varshney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Allard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Fernandez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Hindié</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Nucl Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1650" to="1657" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Peptide receptor radionuclide therapy: an overview</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dash</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chakraborty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Pillai</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Knapp</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Biother Radiopharm</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">First clinical evidence that imaging with somatostatin receptor antagonists is feasible</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wild</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Fani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Behe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Nucl Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1412" to="1417" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bombesin receptor antagonists may be preferable to agonists for tumor targeting</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cescato</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Maina</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Nock</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Nucl Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="318" to="326" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biochemical and pharmacological activities of SR 142948A, a new potent neurotensin receptor antagonist</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gully</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Labeeuw</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Boigegrain</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pharmacol Exp Ther</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">280</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="802" to="812" />
			<date type="published" when="1997">1997</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Biochemical and pharmacological profile of a potent and selective nonpeptide antagonist of the neurotensin receptor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Gully</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Canton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Boigegrain</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proc Natl Acad Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">90</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="69" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Osterkamp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Smerling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Reineke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Haase</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ungewiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">inventors; 3BP Pharmaceuticals GmbH, assignee. Neurotensin receptor ligands. European patent application EP20120008208</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012-12-07">December 7, 2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cloning and expression of a complementary DNA encoding a high affinity human neurotensin receptor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Vita</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Laurent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lefort</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">FEBS Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">317</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="142" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Stable expression of the mouse levocabastine-sensitive neurotensin receptor in HEK 293 cell line: binding properties, photoaffinity labeling, and internalization mechanism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Botto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Chabry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sarret</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Vincent</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Mazella</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biochem Biophys Res Commun</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">243</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="585" to="590" />
			<date type="published" when="1998">1998</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Synthesis and evaluation of a 18 F-labeled diarylpyrazole glycoconjugate for the imaging of NTS1-positive tumors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Maschauer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Hübner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Gmeiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Prante</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Med Chem</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9361" to="9365" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
