<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3361D19A39BB9B307E6EEA680608508D</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1055/s-0035-1545703</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:38+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Injury to the anorectal sphincter complex during vaginal birth is a significant risk factor for anal incontinence in women.</s><s>Between one and two thirds of women who sustained a third degree tear (classification based on <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>) detected immediately after delivery suffer from symptoms of anal incontinence <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s><s>In women who present with persistent symptoms of incontinence postpartum or who go on to develop anal incontinence at a later stage after delivery, the incidence for a defect of the external anal sphincter (EAS) muscle is 90 % while the incidence for a defect of the internal anal sphincter (IAS) muscle is 65 % <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s><s>One of the aims of obstetric care must therefore be to reduce the rates of high-grade perineal tears as much as possible.</s><s>In the chapter on Epidemiology, the guideline of the German Society for Gynecology and Obstetrics (DGGG) on the management of 3rd and 4th degree tears after vaginal delivery <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> therefore lists the odds ratios for the different risk factors, the factors which reduce the risk and the extent to which obstetric measures can change the rate of high-grade perineal tears.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Assessment for Quality Assurance</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>The indicator set "3rd or 4th degree perineal tear" is used in Germany as a quality indicator for clinical area 16/1 (Obstetrics) <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</s><s>The observed rate of 3rd and 4th degree perineal tears is calculated based on the number of documented 3rd and 4th degree perineal tears (numerator) in relation to all fully documented singleton births recorded in the Obstetrics score QI-ID 51181 (denominator).</s><s>Since 2011, calculations have additionally included risk adjustment.</s><s>The selected regression coefficients were risk factors recorded in the quality assurance documentation.</s><s>Factors include maternal height, birth weight of the child, maternal age at delivery, and parity.</s><s>Logistic regression analysis was used for risk adjustment.</s><s>The reference range calculated for 2013 for this risk-adjusted indicator was ≤ 2.25.</s></p><p><s>Obstetric sphincter damage is the most common cause of fecal incontinence in women.</s><s>Between one-third and two-thirds of women who sustain a recognized third-degree tear during delivery subsequently suffer from fecal incontinence.</s><s>We should therefore try to reduce the rate of highgrade tears as much as possible.</s><s>But this rate can only be used as an outcome indicator for the quality of obstetric departments if the recognition and classification of sphincter injury is similar across departments in different hospitals.</s><s>Is the Outcome Indicator "3rd/4th Degree Perineal Tear in Spontaneous Singleton Births" a Reliable Quality Parameter in Obstetrics?</s><s>For the risk adjustment, only 2 of the 10 risk factors listed in the new DGGG guideline on the management of high-grade perineal tears in spontaneous singleton births <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> were considered in the analysis.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Detection of High-grade Tears</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>Obvious injuries of the anal sphincter are detected on clinical examination after vaginal delivery in between 1.5 and 9% of cases <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>It should be noted that the detection rate for high-grade tears depends on a number of different factors.</s><s>Increased vigilance on the part of the examiner with regard to high-grade injuries can already increase the number of detected tears <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>.</s><s>Thus, the generally increased incidence of high-grade tears reported in the last few years is ascribed primarily to improved rates of detection <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref>.</s><s>Particularly women who have sustained only a partial tear of the anal sphincter (subgroup 3A according to the classification of Sultan et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>) require a "trained eye" to detect these injuries and ensure that they receive the necessary surgical treatment.</s><s>In their study, Andrews et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> showed that misclassification of the extent of injury to the anal sphincter complex occurred in 87 % of cases delivered by midwives, 27% of cases assisted by junior doctors in training, 14 % of cases treated by specialists and in only 1% of cases delivered by clinicians who had been specially trained in this area.</s><s>In addition to clinical experience, recognition of perineal trauma is made more difficult by blood at the site of injury or significant tissue edema <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The prevalence of sphincter injury is much higher if additional diagnostic tools are used such as endoanal ultrasound or anal manometry.</s><s>Using 2-dimensional endoanal ultrasound carried out postpartum, Sultan and colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> found that up to 35 % of women had an anal sphincter defect after uncomplicated vaginal birth.</s><s>Several studies have shown that postpartum use of endoanal ultrasound revealed occult anal sphincter defects in 12-44 % of primiparous women after vaginal birth (cf.</s><s><ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>).</s><s>The wide variation in the reported incidence of occult sphincter injury has been attributed to differences in ultrasound differentiation between defects of the puboanal muscle and the transverse perineal muscles from true EAS defects <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</s><s>In this study by Williams et al., use of an improved imaging technique, 3-dimensional endosonography, resulted in the detection of occult sphincter defects in 11 % of cases, a prevalence which appears to be relatively close to the real incidence as reported by Dudding and colleagues <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>It must be concluded that the documented numbers of highgrade perineal tears which are used to calculate the outcome indicators (see above) depend very much on the personal willingness to investigate, the individual level of training and the local site of injury at assessment, and therefore cannot be considered a reliable variable.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Prediction and Prevention of High-grade Tears in Spontaneous Singleton Deliveries</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>!</head><p><s>Despite numerous studies, it has not been possible to date to develop a risk-scoring system which can be used prior to delivery to identify patients who have an increased risk of sustaining an anal sphincter injury during vaginal birth <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>.</s><s>Risk estimation curves based on estimated fetal birth weight on prepartal ultrasound and maternal height could be used to predict the likelihood of perineal trauma <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>.</s><s>But the current data has not yet been taken into account in the new DGGG guideline <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>There are also currently no real evidence-based measures which could be used to prevent high-grade tears in spontaneous singleton births.</s><s>The motherʼs position during birth was not found to have any influence on the risk of high-grade intrapartal birth trauma <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>Prolonged second-stage labor has been associated with an increased risk of anal sphincter injury <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</s><s>One third of women with second-stage labor of more than 4 hours sustain a clinically verified 3rd or 4th degree tear.</s><s>However, measures to curtail second-stage labor such as uterine fundal pressure (the Kristeller maneuver) or early active pushing by the patient do not reduce the risk.</s></p><p><s>A training program specially designed to improve perineal support and reduce serious perineal injury appears to have had a positive effect <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>.</s></p><p><s>The data on the use of episiotomies as a preventative measure against high-grade perineal tear is inconsistent.</s><s>While median episiotomies increase the risk of 3rd and 4th degree tears, a restrictive use of mediolateral episiotomy appears to be acceptable <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">17,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">18]</ref>.</s><s>Overall, it must be concluded that to date there is no definite way of identifying those patients prepartum who have a higher risk of anal sphincter injury and who would potentially benefit from cesarean section as an alternative mode of delivery.</s><s>Only training programs to improve perineal support and a restrictive use of mediolateral episiotomy could have a positive impact on reducing the rate of 3rd and 4th degree perineal tears.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>! Injury of the anorectal sphincter complex results in fecal incontinence in more than one third of women.</s><s>One of the aims of obstetric care must therefore be to reduce the rate of high-grade perineal tears as much as possible.</s></p><p><s>As the rate of high-grade perineal tears depends very much on the personal willingness to investigate, the individual level of training and the local site of injury at assessment, it cannot therefore be considered as a variable which reliably reflects the quality of an obstetrical department.</s><s>Before and during delivery the ability of midwives and obstetricians to influence the rate of high-grade perineal tears directly is limited, with the possible exception of a restrictive use of episiotomies.</s></p><p><s>Implementing changes to bring down high rates of the risk-adjusted outcome indicator "ratio of observed to expected rate of 3rd and 4th degree perineal tears in spontaneous singleton births" are likely to result in only very limited improvements.</s><s>The validity and significance of this outcome indicator should therefore be questioned and not just when outcomes are abnormally high.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Zusammenfassung!</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Eine Verletzung des analen Sphinkters stellt einen wesentlichen Risikofaktor für die Entwicklung einer analen Inkontinenz bei Frauen dar.</s><s>Ein bis zwei Drittel der Frauen, bei denen unmittelbar nach der Entbindung ein Dammriss (DR) Grad III festgestellt wird, leiden an analen Inkontinenzsymptomen. Eine möglichst niedrige Rate höhergradiger Dammrisse ist deshalb anzustreben.</s><s>Diese Rate ist als Ergebnisindikator zur Beschreibung der Qualität einer geburtshilflichen Abteilung aber nur dann verwendbar, wenn eine vergleichbare Qualität der Wahrnehmung und Klassifizierung von analen Sphinkterverletzung in den Abteilungen besteht.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Ist der Ergebnisindikator "Dammriss Grad III/IV bei spontanen Einlingsgeburten" ein zuverlässiger geburtshilflicher Qualitätsparameter?</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Statement</cell><cell>145</cell></row><row><cell>Authors</cell><cell>H. B. G. Franz 1 , C. W. J. Erxleben 2</cell></row><row><cell>Affiliations</cell><cell>1 Frauenklinik Klinikum Braunschweig, Braunschweig</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2 Charité Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Berlin</cell></row><row><cell>Key words</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>l " delivery</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>l " fecal incontinence</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>l " tear</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>l " external anal sphincter</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>l " quality</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Schlüsselwörter</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>l " Geburt</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>l " anale Inkontinenz</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>l " Dammriss</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>l " externer analer Sphinkter</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>l " Qualität</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Deutschsprachige</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zusatzinformationen</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>online abrufbar unter:</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>www.thieme-connect.de/</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ejournals/toc/gebfra</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Bibliography</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>DOI http://dx.doi.org/</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>10.1055/s-0035-1545703</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Geburtsh Frauenheilk 2015; 75:</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>145-147 © Georg Thieme</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Verlag KG Stuttgart • New York •</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ISSN 0016-5751</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Correspondence</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PD Dr. med.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Heiko B. G. Franz</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Frauenklinik Klinikum</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Braunschweig</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Celler Straße 38</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>38114 Braunschweig</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>h.franz@</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>klinikum-braunschweig.de</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p><s>Franz HBG and Erxleben CWJ.</s><s>Is the Outcome … Geburtsh Frauenheilk 2015; 75: 145-147</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Franz HBG and Erxleben CWJ. Is the Outcome … Geburtsh Frauenheilk 2015; 75: 145-147</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Franz HBG and Erxleben CWJ. Is the Outcome … Geburtsh Frauenheilk 2015; 75: 145-147Statement</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conflict of Interest</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Cunningham</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Leveno</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">Williams</forename><surname>Bloom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Obstetrics</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill Professional</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>23rd ed</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Sultan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Thakar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Fenner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>Perineal and anal Sphincter Trauma</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anal sphincter defects and bowl symptoms in women with and without recognized anal sphincter trauma</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nichols</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">194</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1450" to="1454" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Management of 3rd and 4th degree perineal tears after vaginal birth. German guideline of the German Society of Gynecology and Obstetrics (AWMF Registry No. 015/079</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Aigmueller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Bader</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Beilecke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Geburtsh Frauenheilk</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="144" />
			<date type="published" when="2014-10">October 2014. 2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Qualitätsindikatoren Modul 16/1 -Geburtshilfe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Aqua-Institut</forename><surname>Gmbh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<publisher>Eigenverlag</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Göttingen</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Can we improve on the diagnosis of third degree tears?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Groom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Paterson-Brown</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Obstet Gynaecol Reprod Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">101</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="21" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Occult anal sphincter injuriesmyth or reality?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Andrews</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Sultan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Thakar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BJOG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="195" to="200" />
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Management of obstetric anal sphincter injury: a systematic review and national practice survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Fernando</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Sultan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Radley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Health Serv Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anal sphincter function after delivery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Sultan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kamm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Hudson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">329</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1905" to="1911" />
			<date type="published" when="1993">1993</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Obstetric anal sphincter injury: incidence, risk factors, and management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Dudding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Vaizey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kamm</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ann Surg</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">247</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="224" to="237" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Anal sphincter damage after vaginal delivery using three-dimensional endosonography</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Bartram</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Halligan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="770" to="775" />
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Risk scoring system for prediction of obstetric sphincter injury</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Tincello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>White</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BJOG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1066" to="1069" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Correlation of birth injury with maternal height and birthweight</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gudmundsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Henningsson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Lindquist</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BJOG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="764" to="767" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preventing perineal trauma during childbirth: a systematic review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Eason</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Labrecque</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wells</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="464" to="471" />
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How long is too long: does a prolonged second stage of labor in nulliparous women affect maternal and neonatal outcomes?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Cheng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Hopkins</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Caughey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">192</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1702" to="1706" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Incidence of obstetric anal sphincter injuries after training to protect the perineum: cohort study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Laine</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Skjedestad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Sandvik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMJ Open</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">e001649</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Episiotomy for vaginal birth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Carroli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Mignini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cochrane Database Syst Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">D000081</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Delivery method, anal sphincter tears and fecal incontinence: new information on a persistent problem</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Wheeler Tl 2nd</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Richter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Curr Opin Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="474" to="479" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Third-and fourth-degree perineal tears among primiparous women in England between 2000 and 2012: time trends and risk factors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Gurol-Urganci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cromwell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Edozien</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BJOG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1516" to="1525" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
