<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">PRM158 the iMPACt of seVeRe AsthMA on the QuAlity of life: A systeMAtC ReView</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Brandt</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Corporate Translations Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Chicago</settlement>
									<region>IL</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Corporate Translations Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>East Hartford</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Esam H, Badgujar L</roleName><forename type="first">Mothe</forename><surname>Rk</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Corporate Translations Inc</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>East Hartford</settlement>
									<region>CT</region>
									<country key="US">USA</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="laboratory">MarksMan Healthcare Solutions LLP (HEOR and RWE Consulting)</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Navi Mumbai</settlement>
									<country key="IN">India</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">PRM158 the iMPACt of seVeRe AsthMA on the QuAlity of life: A systeMAtC ReView</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">705A422848F232135EEEF12457668D66</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:39+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Objectives: Asthma is one of the most common long term medical conditions and an important contributor to the burden of illness.</s><s>People with asthma experience poor life satisfaction and require a range of health services to manage their condition.</s><s>There is a need to assess the instruments by disease concept and interpret the dimension scores.</s><s>The aim of this systematic review is to assess the impact of severe asthma on the quality of life (QoL).</s><s>MethOds: A systematic search was conducted of the relevant published evidence from Embase and MEDLINE.</s><s>Search limits were: articles in English, in human and published since year 2005.</s><s>Retrieved citations were screened by two independent reviewers according to inclusion criteria: severe asthma and baseline QoL data either measured on generic scale or disease-specific scale.</s><s>Results: A total 29 studies met the inclusion criteria.</s><s>The majority of studies were observational (14 studies) while seven studies had cross-sectional design.</s><s>The majority of studies were conducted in adult population (18 studies) while few studies were conducted in children (5 studies).</s><s>Asthma Quality of Life Questionnaire (AQLQ) was the most frequently used scale among the included studies, assessed in 13 studies followed by St. George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ) in six studies.</s><s>Seven studies reported total AQLQ data with mean scores ranging from 3.1-4.8,</s><s>which reflect poor QoL.</s><s>Across these domains, scores assessed on AQLQ -symptoms and AQLQ -activity limitations were lower as compared to AQLQ -emotional function and AQLQenvironmental stimuli.</s><s>Data also suggested that patients with severe asthma have rapid deterioration in overall health status as compared to patients with mildmoderate asthma.</s><s>cOnclusiOns: Patients with severe asthma had lower total QoL scores as assessed through different scales, indicating worse QoL.</s><s>Symptoms and activity limitations are the two main domains that potentially affect the QoL in patients with severe asthma.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Objectives: The objective of this study is to assess the translatability of "distressed" and to explore conceptually equivalent alternatives.</s><s>The term has been observed to cause difficulties during translation of Clinical Outcomes Assessments (COAs), thus warranting further investigation.</s><s>MethOds: Using Qualtrics, a web-based survey distribution service, a questionnaire was sent to 52 linguists who recently translated "distressed" in a questionnaire.</s><s>They were asked if they faced difficulties in translating the term, to elaborate on these difficulties if applicable and provide conceptually equivalent alternatives.</s><s>Additionally, cognitive debriefing results of "distressed" were analyzed.</s><s>Results: Out of 52 linguists, 29 responded to the questionnaire.</s><s>Sixtytwo percent (62%) of respondents (18 /29) stated that "distressed" was difficult to translate.</s><s>Synonyms presented by all sample members show that "distressed" lacks conceptual equivalency across languages.</s><s>The most common synonyms provided were "suffering," "affliction," and "sorrow," showing variation in the way respondents interpret emotional pain associated with "distress."</s><s>Four respondents indicated that "distressed" could refer to physical or emotional pain in their language.</s><s>Two respondents reported that their language had multiple terms which correspond to "distressed."</s><s>Nine languages were available for cognitive debriefing analysis.</s><s>"Distressed" appeared to be problematic for four out of the nine languages.</s><s>Although minimal issues were found with the term during debriefing, some subjects claim the term to be ambiguous or inappropriate for use in patient questionnaires, which is concordant with linguist feedback.</s><s>cOnclusiOns: Results show that "distressed" can be difficult to translate, due to its ambiguity in describing adverse effects.</s><s>When developing a source item measuring distress, it is recommended that multiple alternatives such as "despair," "mental suffering," and "anxiety" be measured in lieu of a single item on "distress," as the suggested alternatives can neither be ambiguous nor misconstrued.</s><s>Objectives: Health satisfaction may help predict adherence to T2DM self-care behaviors, a cornerstone of optimal T2DM management.</s><s>The CHES-Q was developed to assess T2DM-related health satisfaction and knowledge among people living with T2DM.</s><s>Because renal impairment is a frequent complication of T2DM, we aimed to better understand the experiences of people with T2DM and comorbid CKD and their interpretation of CHES-Q items.</s><s>MethOds: In-depth interviews were conducted with 20 adults with T2DM and CKD (stages 1-5) to explore the content and clarity of the 14-item CHES-Q.</s><s>Each interview included a brief discussion about the participant's experiences and impact of T2DM and CKD.</s><s>Then, participants were asked to "think out loud" about their process for answering each item and to identify words or concepts that were unclear.</s><s>Probes were used to obtain additional feedback about whether any important concepts were missing.</s><s>Interview responses were grouped and summarized.</s><s>Results: The mean age of participants was 59 years, half were female, 45% were white, and 75% completed at least some college.</s><s>Fifty-five percent had stage 5 CKD, 45% were on dialysis, and 2 had received a kidney transplant.</s><s>Average disease duration was 15 years for T2DM and 7.7 years for CKD.</s><s>All participants found the instructions and items clear and relevant.</s><s>Items that did not specifically refer to T2DM or blood sugar were interpreted by participants as relating to their health in general.</s><s>Concepts reported as missing from the CHES-Q included erectile dysfunction, concern with diet, and stress, which were each mentioned by 1 to 3 participants.</s><s>cOnclusiOns: Health satisfaction is an important concept to consider when developing individualized strategies for managing T2DM because it may predict adherence to self-care.</s><s>The CHES-Q assesses T2DM-related health satisfaction and is appropriate for use among people with T2DM and comorbid CKD.</s><s>item location range; number of items misfitting): 'Symptoms' <ref type="bibr">(-4.75 to 4.56; -3.38</ref> to 2.17; 3/14); 'Psychological' (-4.20 to 4.27; -2.53 to 2.65; 1/5); 'Limitations' (-4.50 to 4.55; -2.75 to 2.69; 3/10).</s><s>cOnclusiOns: Findings from the post-hoc analyses of the proposed revised MSIS-29 and MSWS-12 provide an initial evidence-base for the enhancement of their measurement performance in patients with SPMS.</s><s>Additional research is needed to determine the extent of improved scale-to-sample targeting and interpretability of the impact of MS. ).</s><s>Baseline characteristics were balanced between study arms; 52% employed.</s><s>CZP+MTX patients reported greater improvements vs PBO+MTX in household productivity (household work days missed per month BL vs Wk52: PBO+MTX= 10.4 vs 3.0, CZP+MTX= 8.8 vs 1.9; household work days with productivity reduced by ≥ 50%/month: PBO+MTX= 10.6 vs 3.0, CZP+MTX= 9.4 vs 2.1; level of arthritis interference with household work productivity/month: PBO+MTX= 6.4 vs 2.5, CZP+MTX= 6.0 vs 1.9).</s><s>CZP+MTX patients also reported lower need for assistance in usual activities from a relative/friend.</s><s>Employed CZP+MTX patients reported reductions in absenteeism and presenteeism vs PBO+MTX (work days missed/month BL vs Wk52: PBO+MTX= 4.0 vs 0.9, CZP+MTX= 4.4 vs 0.6; days with work productivity reduced by ≥ 50%/month: PBO+MTX= 8.8 vs 1.8, CZP+MTX= 6.4 vs 1.0; level of arthritis interference with work productivity/month: PBO+MTX= 5.8 vs 1.9, CZP+MTX= 5.5 vs 1.4).</s><s>cOnclusiOns: In DMARD-naïve patients with severe, active, progressive RA, CZP+MTX showed greater improvements at 1-year in workplace and household productivity and reduced need for assistance with regular activities vs PBO+MTX. 1. Emery.</s><s>Ann Rheum Dis 2015;74(S2):712</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PRM160</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PRM154 iMPRoVeMents in woRKPlACe</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PRM157 'how Does thAt MAKe you feel?' -the AMbiguity of tRAnslAting DePRession</head><p><s>Williams H, Welbeck E ICON Plc, Oxford, UK Objectives: To identify common translation issues occurring during linguistic validation of depression scales; to assess possible solutions that could be applied across target languages.</s><s>MethOds: We gathered back-translation reviews from linguistic validation projects comprising four depression scales and spanning thirteen languages; identified issues faced during discussion with lead linguistic validation consultants in-country; compared problems and solutions to find any patterns; highlighted challenges common to depression scales.</s><s>Results: There were three main challenges: 1. Colloquial expressions are frequently used.</s><s>Problematic items included 'I could not get going' and 'I could not shake off the blues'.</s><s>All languages reviewed had no colloquial equivalent for 'shake off the blues'; we resolved to create conceptual equivalence ('I could not get rid of my depression'/'I could not stop feeling sad') with a conversational register to reflect the source.</s><s>2. Some symptoms of depression are challenging to translate.</s><s>For example, 'worthless' and 'worthwhile' posed problems for 62% of languages.</s><s>Most often, the terms were confused with 'useless/useful'.</s><s>Where there was no direct translation, and when suitable for the clinical context, these terms were translated as 'worth nothing' and 'valuable'.</s><s>3. The marginally-nuanced ideas were no problem for a broad English vocabulary, however, during linguistic validation, there was difficulty differentiating between English source terms such as 'wound-up <ref type="bibr">', 'nervous', 'agitated', 'restless' and 'tense'.</ref></s><s>All target languages struggled to translate 'nervous' and 'wound-up' in two separate terms.</s><s>Project managers defined the latter as 'brought to a state of great tension', possibly including 'nervous movement', and the concept was rendered successfully.</s><s>cOnclusiOns: Attitudes towards depression vary across different cultures.</s><s>Verbatim translations are found to be risky for numerous reasons but, with careful discussion between lead linguists and project managers, conceptually-equivalent, culturally-adapted wording is found to allow for this.</s><s>To the issues reviewed, similar solutions were applied across languages and in different depression scales.</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Content VAliDity of the CuRRent heAlth sAtisfACtion QuestionnAiRe (Ches-Q) AMong PeoPle liVing with tyPe 2 DiAbetes Mellitus (t2DM) AnD CoMoRbiD ChRoniC KiDney DiseAse (CKD)</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Traina SB 1 , McQuarrie K 1 , Barrett A 2 , DiBenedetti D 2 , McLeod L 2</cell></row><row><cell>1 Janssen Global Services, LLC, Raritan, NJ, USA, 2 RTI Health Solutions, Research Triangle Park,</cell></row><row><cell>NC, USA</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>AnD householD PRoDuCtiVity following 52 weeKs of tReAtMent with CeRtolizuMAb Pegol in CoMbinAtion with MethotRexAte in DMARD-nAiVe PAtients with seVeRe, ACtiVe AnD PRogRessiVe RheuMAtoiD ARthRitis: Results fRoM the C-eARly RAnDoMizeD, Double-blinD, ContRolleD PhAse 3 stuDy</head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>To assess effects of CZP+MTX vs PBO+MTX on workplace and household productivity and need for help with daily activities in DMARD-naïve patients with severe, active, progressive RA.1 MethOds: Patients in this double-blind randomized study (NCT01519791) were DMARD-naïve with active RA &lt; 1yr diagnosis at baseline, fulfilling 2010 ACR/EULAR criteria; ≥ 4 swollen and ≥ 4 tender joints; DAS28[ESR]≥ 3.2; CRP≥ 10mg/L and/or ESR≥ 28mm/hr, RF/ACPA positive.Patients were randomized 3:1 to CZP (400mg Wks 0,2,4 then 200mg Q2W to Wk52)+MTX or PBO+MTX (MTX initiated at 10mg/wk, increased to 25mg/wk by Wk8, maximum tolerated dose maintained to Wk52).Workplace and household productivity (Work Productivity Survey [WPS]) were assessed; responses (LOCF imputation) compared using a non-parametric bootstrap-t method.Need for assistance was summarized descriptively.Results: 660 (CZP+MTX) and 219 (PBO+MTX) patients were randomized; 655 vs 213 in the full analysis set (pts with baseline and postbaseline DAS28[ESR]</s></p></div></figDesc><table><row><cell>Emery P 1 , Bingham C 2 , Burmester GR 3 , Bykerk VP 4 , Furst D 5 , Mariette X 6 , Purcaru O 7 ,</cell></row><row><cell>VanLunen B 8 , Weinblatt M 9</cell></row><row><cell>1 Leeds University, Leeds, UK, 2 Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA,</cell></row><row><cell>3 Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany, 4 Hospital for Special Surgery, New York, NY, USA,</cell></row><row><cell>5 UCLA, Los Angeles, CA, USA, 6 Paris-Sud University, Paris, France, 7 UCB Pharma, Brussels,</cell></row><row><cell>Belgium, 8 UCB Pharma, Durham, NC, USA, 9 Brigham and Women's Hospital, Boston, MA, USA</cell></row><row><cell>Objectives:</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
