<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">In vivo evidence of significant levator ani muscle stretch on MR images of a live childbirth</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MS</roleName><forename type="first">Nikhil</forename><surname>Sindhwani</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Christian</forename><surname>Bamberg</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Nele</forename><surname>Famaey</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Geertje</forename><surname>Callewaert</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Joachim</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Dudenhausen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>PhD</roleName><forename type="first">Ulf</forename><surname>Teichgräber</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>MD</roleName><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Deprest</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">In vivo evidence of significant levator ani muscle stretch on MR images of a live childbirth</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">9F40AD8E5CDBCB32D5A98CC992786E71</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ajog.2017.04.014</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:39+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>childbirth</term>
					<term>levator ani muscle</term>
					<term>magnetic resonance imaging</term>
					<term>pelvic floor dysfunction</term>
					<term>vaginal childbirth</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>OBJECTIVE: Vaginal childbirth is believed to be a significant risk factor for the development of pelvic floor dysfunction later in life.</s><s>Previous studies have explored the use of medical imaging and simulations of childbirth to determine the stretch in the levator ani muscle.</s><s>A report in 2012 has recorded magnetic resonance images of a live childbirth of a 24 year old woman giving birth vaginally for the second time, using a 1.0 Tesla open, high-field scanner.</s><s>Our objective was to determine the stretch ratios in the levator muscle using these magnetic resonance images of live childbirth.</s><s>STUDY DESIGN: Three-dimensional magnetic resonance image sequences were obtained to visualize coronal and axial planes before and after the childbirth.</s><s>These images were obtained before the expulsion phase without pushing and were used to reconstruct the levator muscle and the fetal head in 3 dimensions.</s><s>The fetal head was approximated to be an ellipsoid, and it is assumed that its middle section is visible in dynamic magnetic resonance images.</s><s>Assuming incompressibility, the full deformation field of the fetal head is then calculated.</s><s>Real-time cine magnetic resonance images were acquired for the during the expulsion phase, occurring over 2 contractions in the midsagittal plane.</s><s>The levator muscle stretch is estimated using a custom program.</s><s>The program calculates points of contact between the fetal head ellipsoid and the levator ani muscle model as the head descends down the birth canal and moves them orthogonal to its surface.</s><s>Circumferential stretch was calculated to represent the extension needed to allow the passage of the fetal head.</s><s>RESULTS: Starting from a position in the preexpulsion phase, the levator muscle experiences a maximum circumferential stretch of 248% on the posterior-medial portion of the levator ani muscle, as shown in previously published finite element simulations.</s><s>However, the maximal stretch was notably less than that predicted by finite element models.</s><s>This is because our baseline 3-dimensional model of the levator muscle is created from images taken shortly before expulsion and thus is already in a stretched state.</s><s>Furthermore, the finite element models are created from images of a healthy nulliparous woman, while this study uses images from a para 2 woman.</s><s>CONCLUSION: This study is the first attempt to estimate the stretch in levator ani muscle using magnetic resonance images of a live childbirth.</s><s>The stretch was significant and the locations corroborate with previous findings of finite element models.</s></p><p><s>P elvic organ prolapse (POP) is the descent of pelvic organs from their normal position resulting in protrusion of the vagina and/or the uterus. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> It affects almost half of all middle-aged women to some degree, and can have a significant impact on their quality of life. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref></s><s>The support to the pelvic organs is provided, next to the bony pelvis, by a complex interplay of pelvic floor musculature, the vaginal wall, connective tissue, fascia, and ligaments.</s><s>It is widely accepted that the loss of one or more support structures causes POP.</s></p><p><s>One event that inflicts direct trauma to the pelvic floor muscle support, the levator ani muscle (LAM), is pregnancy, labor, and in particular vaginal delivery. <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref></s><s>evator avulsion is a common form of trauma that has been directly associated with childbirth and causes significant changes in the shape and size of the urogenital hiatus. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref></s><s>n an attempt to visualize the mechanisms of this injury, theoretical computational models have been previously presented.</s><s>7]<ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> However, these predictions are difficult to corroborate experimentally because of the lack of real measurements that would require one to record the stretches during childbirth.</s></p><p><s>In 2012 magnetic resonance (MR) images of a live childbirth were recorded using a 1.0 Tesla open, high-field scanner. <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref></s><s>In this study, several MR images were collected, including a real-time cinematic MR imaging series in the midsagittal plane (see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>).</s><s>Also, multislice (3-dimensional [3D]) sequences in the sagittal, coronal, and axial planes were collected before the childbirth.</s><s>Using these images, Bamberg et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> described the relationship between fetal movements and position as the fetus passes through the birth canal.</s></p><p><s>This study aimed to interpret the stretch occurring in the LAM using this unique MR image data of a live childbirth.</s><s>With reasonable assumptions, this provides us a first insight into the mechanisms of the LAM stretch during childbirth, as corroborated with the MR images.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Materials and Methods</head><p><s>A 24 year old woman giving birth for the second time, at 37 5/7 weeks of gestation, was admitted with regular contractions to the Department of Obstetrics of the Charité University Hospital in Berlin, Germany.</s><s>Her height was 165 cm and</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Original Research</head><p><s>ajog.org weight 54 kg before pregnancy and 66 kg at term.</s><s>She had no diabetes and did not smoke.</s></p><p><s>After the administration of an epidural, 8 MR sequences were obtained.</s><s>The detailed image acquisition protocol was published earlier (Bamberg et al, 2012 <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> ).</s><s>In brief, the MR sequences included real-time dynamic MR images in the midsagittal plane (6 mm thickness, voxel size 1.4 Â 1.5 mm) in the active second stage of labor.</s><s>This dynamic sequence captures the entire duration of fetal head expulsion.</s></p><p><s>Also, T2-weighted multislice turbospin echo sequences were obtained to visualize the coronal and axial planes early in labor yet before expulsion (40 slices, 6 mm thickness, and 1 mm interslice gap with resolution 1.4 Â 1.6 mm).</s></p><p><s>Ethical approval of the study design was obtained, and written informed consent was obtained from the patient at 28 weeks of gestation.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3D model generation</head><p><s>MR images from the axial multislice sequence taken before birth were used to create 3D models of the LAM and the fetal head.</s><s>On each frame, the outline</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3D model generation process</head><p><s>Step 1 is to mark the outline contours of the levator ani muscle and the fetal brain on an axial image sequence (left panel).</s><s>Step 2 is to interpolate a surface using these curves (middle panel).</s><s>The resulting 3D models of the fetal brain and the levator ani are shown in the image on the right panel.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ajog.org</head><p><s>OBSTETRICS Original Research contour of the fetal brain and the LAM were drawn manually, and a 3D surface was extruded on these contours using the Mimics Innovation Suite (MIS version 16; Materialise NV, Leuven, Belgium; see Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</s><s>The extent of the LAM that could be extracted from the images may be seen from Appendix A.</s></p><p><s>The brain was chosen as a proxy to the brain because of its high contrast compared with the skull bones.</s><s>Also, it is assumed to have a finite unchanging volume.</s><s>The surface of the 3D models was then interpolated over these curves using design module of the MIS and exported as triangulated surfaces (STL).</s><s>The models were generated by the lead author (N.S.) and verified by a clinician (G.C.) for accuracy.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Interpretation of the fetal head</head><p><s>The dynamic MR sequence allows visualization of the fetal brain and, by proxy the fetal head, in the midsagittal plane but not in full 3 dimensions.</s><s>To calculate the stretch occurring in the LAM in 3 dimensions, it is necessary to estimate the 3D extent of the fetal head at each time point.</s><s>This is achieved by approximating the fetal head as an ellipsoid.</s><s>The 3D model of the fetal brain is used to get the initial dimensions of the ellipsoid.</s><s>The net volume of this ellipsoid is assumed to be constant throughout the birth process but can deform according to the changes observed in the fetal head because of head molding during childbirth.</s></p><p><s>Next, for each frame in the dynamic 2-dimensional midsagittal MR sequence, the brain of the fetus was manually outlined as shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>.</s><s>An ellipse fitted on these 2-dimensional outlines would be the midsagittal cross-section of the full 3D ellipsoid that represents the fetal head.</s><s>Thus, this ellipse provides the major and minor diameters of this ellipsoid.</s><s>Using the constant total volume assumption, the third (lateral) diameter of the fetal brain ellipsoid is approximated, giving an estimate of the full 3D extent of the fetal head at each frame.</s><s>The movement or the descent profile of the centroid of this ellipse, as observed in this midsagittal plane, is also recorded.</s></p><p><s>Thus, together with the changes in the ellipsoid diameters and the descent profile at each time frame, we obtain the full 3D deformational and translational fields of the fetal head throughout the birth process.</s></p><p><s>This interpretation process was performed using a custom program in Matlab (version 2013a; Mathworks Inc, Natick, MA).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Anatomical landmark placement</head><p><s>The position of the most inferior point of the pubic symphysis and the tip of the coccyx were marked on each frame.</s><s>These bony landmark points were used as reference for the position of the fetal head.</s><s>The final points' positions were averaged over the positions of the points placed by 2 experts (G.C. and C.B.).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Calculation of the LAM stretch</head><p><s>The LAM stretch is estimated by a custom process developed in Matlab.</s><s>A</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Manually outlined fetal brain and an ellipse fitted on it</head><p><s>The fetal brain is manually outlined (red crosses) and an ellipse is fitted on it (solid green).</s><s>The major axis and minor axes (a and b) are indicated in blue.</s><s>The process is repeated for each frame.</s><s>translation field is calculated using the anatomical reference points.</s><s>For each frame, the new position of the fetal head ellipsoid is calculated using the translational and deformation fields recorded from MR images described in the previous text.</s><s>After this new position is calculated if 1 or more of the vertices of the levator ani 3D object are inside the ellipsoid, they are displaced outward in the direction normal to the LAM's surface.</s><s>The process is described schematically in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">4</ref>.</s></p><p><s>To maintain a continuous surface topology, it was smoothed using the curvature flow smoothing technique after every deformation step. <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11</ref></s><s>Thus, the 3D model of the LAM morphs to allow the descent of the fetal head ellipsoid and provides the displacement values at every node of the model.</s></p><p><s>Once the nodal displacements are obtained, the circumferential stretch are visualized in Abaqus Finite element software (Simulia; Dassault Systèmes, Paris, France).</s><s>This is achieved by conducting a trivial simulation in which the displacement is explicitly applied to each node as a boundary condition to the corresponding nodes of the LAM 3D model.</s><s>The circumferential stretch map was then visualized.</s></p><p><s>To record the evolution of the lateral and transversal diameter of the LAM, a cross-section of the LAM 3D model was viewed in the plane of minimal hiatal dimensions.</s><s>An ellipse fitted on this cross-section and then gives the transverse and lateral diameters of the levator muscle.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Displacements of the LAM 3D model</head><p><s>The top, middle, and bottom rows show displacements of the LAM 3D model viewed in the isometric view, frontal view, and caudocranial view, respectively.</s><s>The left column shows the displacements when the fetal head is midpelvis, and the right column shows the displacements at the time of the expulsion of the head.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ajog.org</head><note type="other">OBSTETRICS Original Research</note></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p><s>The image acquisition took a total time of less than 1 hour in the magnet room, and any discomfort during labor was tolerated well.</s><s>A 2585 g boy was born with a head circumference of 33.5 cm.</s></p><p><s>The radii of the ellipsoid (A, B, and C) as measured at each image frame are shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">5</ref>.</s><s>For representation, the plot is smoothed temporally using a spline smoothing function.</s><s>The radius of the long axis of the fetal head ellipsoid was 65.84 (55.12, 71.87; mean [range]), that of the craniocaudal axis was 44.67 (39.47, 47.00), and that of the left-right axis was 44.33 (40.70 55.64).</s></p><p><s>Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">6</ref> shows the displacements occurring in the muscle at 2 different times during the birth, with the relative position of the fetal head ellipsoid.</s></p><p><s>The circumferential stretch in the levator muscle is shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_9">7</ref>  Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_11">8</ref> shows the evolution of the lateral and transversal diameter of the LAM as measured in the plane of minimal hiatal dimensions.</s><s>The lateral diameter extends from 63.6 mm to 83.8 mm, an increase of 31.7%, and the transversal diameter extends from 51.2 mm to 71.0 mm, an increment of 38.7%.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Comment</head><p><s>It is widely accepted that vaginal delivery is a major cause for POP and its symptoms.</s><s>LAM is a major biomechanical support structure and undergoes tremendous stretch during childbirth.</s><s>Abdool et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref> showed that in almost 21% of parous women with symptoms of POP, an avulsion of the levator muscle could be observed.</s></p><p><s>LAM trauma is believed to be a major reason for the onset of pelvic organ prolapse later in life. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12</ref></s><s>Furthermore, it has been shown that women who exhibit significant cystocele and who have a LAM injury, are at a higher risk of recurrence following surgical repair. <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13</ref></s><s>hile several computer models have been proposed to estimate the stretch that occur in this region, they have not been verified with data from a real human.</s></p><p><s>This study reports an estimate of the stretch in the LAM as interpreted directly from MR image data of a live childbirth.</s><s>To the best of our knowledge, this is a first study to describe the stretch in the LAM that solely relies on real MR image data.</s></p><p><s>We acknowledge several shortcomings of this study.</s><s>First, the analysis presented here is based on a dynamic MR sequence recorded in the midsagittal plane.</s><s>These dynamic images were taken in only 1 plane, as is the limitation of currently available MR imaging hardware.</s><s>We circumvented this problem by using an ellipsoid approximation of the fetal head and assuming incompressibility of the contents of this ellipsoid.</s><s>Furthermore, the 3D sequences taken before childbirth have a large interslice distance and relatively low resolution (voxel size is 1.5 mm).</s><s>This stems from the limiting need to scan using very fast MR protocols.</s><s>Because of these factors, the 3D models used here are interpolated and not extremely accurate.</s></p><p><s>Second, we note that the stretch reported in this study is not as high as presented by previous finite element studies.</s><s>Hoyte et al 6 reported a stretch factor of 3:1, and Lien et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref> reported a stretch factor of 3.26:1.</s><s>Nonetheless, the location of the maximum stretch region, ajog.org</s><s>OBSTETRICS Original Research found at the posterior-medial portion of the LAM, however, matches with that predicted by finite element simulations. <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">14</ref></s><s>ne must note, however, that both those studies used 3D models of the LAM generated from nulliparous women, while the subject in our study was delivering for the second time vaginally.</s><s>Shek et al <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15</ref> showed that in comparison with the nonpregnant nulliparous women, a para 1 woman in her third trimester is likely to have a hiatal area that is 27% larger at rest.</s><s>6]<ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref> Moreover, our starting LAM model is generated from MR images taken earlier in labor.</s><s>These reasons may account for the discrepancy that our measurements fail to match the stretch reported by earlier finite element studies.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p><s>The stretch occurring in LAM during childbirth has been reported before, using finite element simulations. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>In this study we calculated the stretch using MR image data of live childbirth.</s><s>The maximum circumferential stretch observed was about 250 %.</s><s>The location of the maximum stretch was at the posterior-medial portion of the LAM, as was also shown by finite element simulations.</s></p><p><s>n</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIGURE 1 Dynamic</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 1Dynamic MR image sequence of a live childbirth</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,37.98,103.13,499.86,209.59" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FIGURE 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 2</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,38.10,522.31,499.64,155.06" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>3D, 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>-dimensional.</s><s>Sindhwani et al.</s><s>Levator ani muscle stretch on MR images of a live childbirth.</s><s>Am J Obstet Gynecol 2017.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>FIGURE 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 3</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,36.96,114.58,159.14,206.19" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Sindhwani et al.</s><s>Levator ani muscle stretch on MR images of a live childbirth.</s><s>Am J Obstet Gynecol 2017.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>FIGURE 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 4Movement of model's nodes with the descent of ellipsoid head</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="3,208.52,103.13,330.12,203.58" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>FIGURE 6</head><label>6</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 6</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,208.63,103.13,329.99,501.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>3D, 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>-dimensional; LAM, levator ani muscle.</s><s>Sindhwani et al.</s><s>Levator ani muscle stretch on MR images of a live childbirth.</s><s>Am J Obstet Gynecol 2017.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>FIGURE 5 Long</head><label>5</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 5Long, craniocaudal, and left-right axes of fetal head</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,37.08,114.58,159.11,124.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>FIGURE 7</head><label>7</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 7Circumferential stretch in the levator muscle</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="5,37.98,103.13,499.86,555.53" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>from 3 different views.</s><s>Maximum stretch of 248% was recorded in the posterior caudal region of the LAM muscle.</s><s>A rendering showing the LAM stretch corresponding to the MR image frames is uploaded in the accompanying video file.</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>FIGURE 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIGURE 8Evolution of lateral and transversal diameter of the LAM</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,38.10,103.13,499.64,199.11" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Cite this article as: Sindhwani N, Bamberg C, Famaey N, et al.</s><s>In vivo evidence of significant levator ani muscle stretch on MR images of a live childbirth.</s><s>Am J Obstet Gynecol 2017;217:194.e1-8.</s></p></div></figDesc><table /><note><p><s>0002-9378/$36.00 ª 2017 Elsevier Inc.</s><s>All rights reserved.</s><s>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ajog.2017.04.014</s><s>Related editorial, page 110.</s><s>194.e1</s><s>American Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology AUGUST 2017</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="194">.e5 American Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology AUGUST 2017</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">AUGUST 2017 American Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology 194.e6</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="194">.e7 American Journal of Obstetrics &amp; Gynecology AUGUST 2017</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Author and article information</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pelvic organ prolapse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Jelovsek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Maher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Barber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">369</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1027" to="1038" />
			<date type="published" when="2007">2007</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Abdominal sacrocolpopexy: a comprehensive review</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Nygaard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Mccreery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Brubaker</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="805" to="823" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The aetiology of prolapse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dietz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int Urogynecol J Pelvic Floor Dysfunct</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1323" to="1329" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Levator trauma after vaginal delivery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dietz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Lanzarone</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">106</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="707" to="712" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of levator avulsion on hiatal dimension and function</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Abdool</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Shek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dietz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">201</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="89" to="e90" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Quantity and distribution of levator ani stretch during simulated vaginal childbirth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Hoyte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Damaser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Warfield</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">199</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="198" to="e199" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Levator ani muscle stretch induced by simulated vaginal birth</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K-C</forename><surname>Lien</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Mooney</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jol</forename><surname>Delancey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ashton</forename><forename type="middle">-</forename><surname>Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">103</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="40" />
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Deformation of the pelvic floor muscles during a vaginal delivery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mpl</forename><surname>Parente</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rmn</forename><surname>Jorge</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mascarenhas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Fernandes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jac</forename><surname>Martins</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int Urogynecol J Pelvic Floor Dysfunct</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="65" to="71" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human birth observed in real-time open magnetic resonance imaging</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bamberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Rademacher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Güttler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">206</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="505" to="e506" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Implicit fairing of irregular meshes using diffusion and curvature flow</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Desbrun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Schröder</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Barr</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="ftp://ftp.cis.upenn.edu/pub/cis610/public_html/Desbrun-DMSB_SIG99.pdf.Accessed" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-05-17">May 17, 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Available at: https://nl.mathworks. com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/26710-smoothtriangulated-mesh</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Kroon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005-06-10">2005. 2005. June 10. 2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Smooth triangulated mesh</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Does levator avulsion increase urethral mobility?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Shek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pirpiris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dietz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">153</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="219" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Levator avulsion is a risk factor for cystocele recurrence</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dietz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Chantarasorn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Shek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">36</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="80" />
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the biomechanics of vaginal birth and common sequelae</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ashton-Miller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jol</forename><surname>Delancey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annu Rev Biomed Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="163" to="176" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The effect of pregnancy on hiatal dimensions and urethral mobility: an observational study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Shek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kruger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dietz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int Urogynecol J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1561" to="1567" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Ultrasound imaging of the pelvic floor: changes in anatomy during and after first pregnancy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Veelen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Van</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Schweitzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Van Der Vaart</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">44</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="476" to="480" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The effect of childbirth on hiatal dimensions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Shek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Dietz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">113</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1272" to="1278" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
