<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Evanescence wave-based technology for the rapid and sensitive quantification of biological analytes</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Evanescence wave-based technology for the rapid and sensitive quantification of biological analytes</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">2396C3A8A33786B5442A9F344D64CBFB</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2022-05-18T11:40+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>To the Editor:</s></p><p><s>Time has become the most crucial factor in modern precision medicine.</s><s>The quick availability of the results of diagnostic procedures has direct economic consequences in all clinical settings, and especially in emergency-medicine laboratories, where results are required as soon as possible to ensure an immediate initiation of the correct medical treatments. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1</ref> Currently immunoassays are powerful and sensitive technologies widely used for in vitro diagnostics (IVD), analyses of biomarkers for the prediction of outcomes and disease endotyping as tools of precision medicine, as well as in research and development. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref></s><s>nce the first description of a radioimmunoassay in 1959, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3</ref> many modifications of the radioimmunoassay in different formats including enzyme-, chemiluminescence-, or fluorescence-linked assays have been described. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>Classical ELISAs are still eminently suitable for both research and development and IVD applications due to a high flexibility, sensitivity, and specificity.</s><s>They represent the criterion standard for the detection of many biomarkers and include numerous heterogeneous assay formates. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4</ref></s><s>Technical aspects of ELISA such as antigen or antibody coating, buffer compositions, detection chemistry, substrates, automation, and assay standardization have been developed thoroughly, making ELISA a well-characterized and validated technology.</s><s>Despite excellent performance in terms of sensitivity and specificity, ELISA suffers from a time-to-results of several hours due to the long incubation time and multiple washing steps.</s><s>Moreover, the technology relies on end-point measurements, which depend on Here, we present a novel evanscence wave-based fluorescence (EVA) biosensor technology <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> comparable to ELISA in terms of specificity and sensitivity, allowing a 10-minute time-to-result with a single pipetting step and avoiding any washing steps and is, therefore, about 10 times faster than conventional immunoassays.</s><s>The EVA technology consists of 2 elements: (1) an 8-well biosensor chip (EVA chip) produced by injection molding of polystyrene identical to the material used to produce maxisorb ELISA plates activated with a Co-60-g source to obtain a high-density binding surface (see Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">E1</ref>, left panel, in this article's Online Repository at www.jacionline.org)</s><s>and (2) the EVA reader to detect evanescence excitation of fluorophors bound to the EVA chip surface (Fig E1, right panel).</s><s>Each well of the EVA chip can be biofunctionalized for the detection of an analyte preconfigured according to the needs of the users in any format based on fluorescence-linked immunosorbent assay in analogy to, and following the principles used for the development of state-of-the-art immunoassays. <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8</ref></s><s>To produce ready-to-use tests, all reagents needed are added to the wells, washed, blocked, dried at room temperature (RT), and packaged on a special blister for long-term storage.</s><s>The only manipulation needed to be done by the end user is to add a few microliters of the biological sample to be tested ( The EVA reader is based on evanescence excitation of fluorophors bound to the EVA chip surface.</s><s>A diode laser light beam with a wavelength of 635 nm is directed against the side wall of the prism, where it is refracted as a function of the refractive index of air (n 5 1.000) and polystyrene (n 5 1.595) according to classical geometrical optics (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">1, A</ref>).</s><s>The laser light does not enter the liquid and only fluorescently labeled molecules present in the thin 200 nm evanescence layer at the bottom of the well adsorb the 635 nm leaser beam photons and subsequently emit light of longer wavelength (Fig 1 <ref type="figure">, B</ref>).</s><s>The design of the EVA reader allows only photons emitted through the bottom of the prism to be collected, filtered, and counted in a time-dependent mode.</s><s>The instrument moves the EVA chip from well to well, measures photons for 1 second, and records them; 30 such cycles are measured, and recorded as kinetic raw data (Fig 1 <ref type="figure">, C</ref>), which are automatically converted to the concentration of the analyte in the assay plotting the EVA signal (U/s) versus the concentration best fitted as sigmoidal 4 parametric curve (Fig 1 <ref type="figure">, D</ref>).</s><s>This implicates that the EVA chip has to be measured immediately after the addition of the patient's sample.</s><s>All parameters required for the evaluation of the tests are stored on the bar code of the EVA chip and additional specific controls by the end user are not needed.</s><s>Quality controls for each of the newly developed assays can be included in the chip.</s></p><p><s>As proof of concept we compared the performance of the EVA technology for the 1-step determination of total serum IgE and allergen-specific IgE to the recombinant allergen rAsp f 1 <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9</ref> to the results obtained with the ImmunoCAP system, 10 considered the criterion standard for the in vitro diagnosis of allergic sensitizations.</s><s>To prepare EVA chips for the detection of total serum IgE, wells were coated with a murine IgG anti-human IgE mAb, blocked, followed by addition of a matched fluorescently labeled murine IgG anti-human IgE mAb, and dried at RT (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2, A</ref>).</s><s>After addition of 20 mL undiluted serum samples, the EVA chip was inserted into the EVA reader and measurements for the detection of total serum IgE immediately started.</s><s>Because the antibody and analyte binding takes place at the bottom of the well, the assay is not affected by the volume (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">E2</ref>).</s><s>The EVA signals showed a strong linear correlation (R 2 5 0.96, P &lt; .001)</s><s>with the ImmunoCAP total IgE assay over concentrations ranging from 20 to 800 kU/L (Fig 2 <ref type="figure">, B</ref>).</s><s>To prepare EVA chips for the detection of serum IgE raised against rAsp f 1, the wells were directly coated with the allergen (10 mg/mL), washed, and blocked.</s><s>Thereafter, fluorescently labeled murine IgG anti-human IgE mAb as detection antibody was added and the chips dried at RT (Fig 2 <ref type="figure">, C</ref>). Measurements for the detection of Asp f 1-specific IgE were performed as described for total serum IgE and showed an excellent correlation with the rAsp f 1-specific ImmunoCAP measurements (R 2 5 0.92; P &lt; .01)</s><s>(Fig 2 <ref type="figure">, D</ref>).</s><s>The lower and upper limits of detection (&gt;0.26, &lt;100 KU A /L) are comparable to those of ImmunoCAP (&gt;0.35, &lt;100 KU A /L), and for values exceeding 100 KU A /L, dilution of the serum samples is required for both technologies.</s><s>Measurements of allergen-specific IgE using EVA chips coated with the major allergens of A fumigatus (rAsp f 1, rAsp f 2, rAsp f 4, and rAsp f 6), birch (Bet v 1), cat (Fel d 1), dog (Can f 1 and Can f 2), mugwort (Art v 1), and bee venom (Api m 1) showed strong correlations with ELISA and ImmunoCAP determinations in terms of specificity and sensitivity ranging from R 2 values of 0.8389 to 0.9127.</s></p><p><s>The EVA technology presented has been shown to be powerful not only for the detection of total and allergen-specific serum IgE but also for a fast and quantitative detection of serum cortisol levels in a competitive assay (see Fig E3 in  The technology is robust, allowing the use in a mobile setting, for example, an ambulance as well as in a point of care setting for assays using whole blood and for patient's samples that do not require further processing, such as urine or saliva.</s><s>In addition, the hands-on time is low and the use is easy; thus, the technology can also be used by health care professionals outside a laboratory setting.</s><s>The number of tests that can be run simultaneously depends only on the size of the plate.</s><s>Currently, 8-well plates have been used but larger plate readers, for example, for 96-well plates, can be constructed, offering an alternative to ELISA also for large commercial laboratories offering economical advantages.</s><s>The device and the first tests are expected to be ready for use in the clinical settings by the end of 2017 after completing the ongoing ISO certification at a highly competitive price compared with standard ELISA.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cat ownership, cat allergen exposure, and trajectories of sensitization and asthma throughout childhood</head><p><s>To the Editor:</s></p><p><s>For almost 2 decades, cat exposure has been linked to a number of different and often contradictory outcomes.</s><s>2]<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> In contrast, a protective effect of high allergen exposure on cat sensitization, with a bell-shaped dose-response relationship, has been reported in cross-sectional studies in older children and adults. <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5</ref></s><s>imilar inconsistencies have been reported on the association between cat ownership and cat-specific sensitization. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7</ref></s><s>We hypothesized that the effect of early-life cat exposure on sensitization differs (1) over time, rendering the generalization of effects from cross-sectional analyses at specific age points potentially misleading; (2) for different allergenic proteins from cat; and (3) between children with different risk of allergy.</s></p><p><s>To address our hypotheses, we investigated the effect of cat exposure in the first year of life on longitudinal trajectories of sensitization and asthma throughout childhood in a populationbased birth cohort in which skin prick tests (SPTs) and IgE to cat</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>METHODS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>EVA-biosensor chips and readers</head><p><s>The EVA chips are produced by injection molding of polystyrene (BASF, Ludwigshafen, Germany) according to the geometry described in the patent EP 193719967, E1 fitting to the inlet of the EVA reader.</s><s>EVA readers are manufactured by Hamilton (Hamilton AG, Bonaduz, Switzerland).</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Labeling of detection reagents with fluorophors</head><p><s>Standard conjugation of detection reagents with allophycocyanin (APC) is performed by mixing an mAb or an antigen with a 50-fold molar excess of N-succinimidyl S-acetylthioacetate (SATA, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Uppsala, Sweden) followed by incubation for 30 minutes at RT.</s><s>After removal of excess SATA over an NAP-5 desalting column (GE Healthcare, Life Sciences, Glattbrugg, Switzerland), the SATA-derivatised thiol group is deacethylated with 50 mM NH 2 OH for 2 hours at RT.</s><s>The resulting antibody respective antigen-thiol derivative is directly coupled to (succinimidyl 4-(Nmaleimidomethyl)cyclohexane-1-carboxylate)-activated APC (SMCC-APC, Columbia Biosciences) for 2 hours at RT.</s><s>The reaction is quenched by addition of cysteine to a final concentration of 10 mM followed by incubation for 15 minutes at RT.</s><s>The resulting conjugate is purified over a Superdex 200 10/300 GL (GE Healthcare) in PBS at a flow of 0.5 mL/min.</s><s>The OD of purified conjugate is finally measured at 280 nm for total protein content and at 630 nm for APC content.</s><s>Typically, the efficiency of the labeling procedure results in 1.5 M APC per mol coupled detection reagent.</s><s>Alternatively, detection reagents are labeled with Cy5 (GE Healthcare) following the standard protocol recommended by the manufacturer.</s><s><ref type="bibr">E2</ref></s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Development of immunoassays</head><p><s>Each of the 8 wells of an EVA chip can be biofunctionalized for the detection of an analyte basically following the standard procedures and assay formats used to obtain ELISA tests.</s></p><p><s>A sandwich assay was developed for the detection of human IgE by coating purified anti-human IgE mouse mAb to the sensor surface 5 mg/mL in PBS, 20 mL per well for 2 hours at RT. Wells were washed 4 times with PBS and blocked by 1-hour incubation with 30 mL of 1% BSA (Roche Applied Science, Rotkreuz, Switzerland) in PBS containing 0.25% Tween 20 (Sigma-Aldrich, Buchs, Switzerland).</s><s>Blocking buffer was removed and wells were washed twice with PBS followed by 2 washes with 1% sucrose solution.</s><s>After addition of 20 mL per well of a matched APC-labeled purified anti-human IgE mouse mAb in 1% sucrose solution, the chips were let drying at RT under normal atmospheric pressure and packaged into blisters for long-time storage.</s></p><p><s>For the measurement of allergen-specific anti-Asp f 1 serum IgE, the direct assay described elshewhere <ref type="bibr">E3</ref> with following modifications was used: rAsp f 1 was directly coated to the wells at 10 mg/mL in PBS, 20 mL per well for 2 hours at RT. Washing and blocking steps were as described above for total serum IgE and in a last step APC-labeled purified mouse IgG anti-human IgE mAb in 1% sucrose solution the ready-to-use chips were air dried at RT and packaged into blisters as described above.</s></p><p><s>The cortisol assay was developed by coating 20 mL per well of cortisol-3carboxymethyloxime-BSA conjugate (Fitzgerald, Acton, Mass) at 10 mg/mL in PBS as described above.</s><s>After washing with PBS and blocking followed by washing with PBS and sucrose 20 mL per well anticortisol mAb (clone XM210, HyTest, FI), APC conjugated at 50 mg/mL was added as detection reagent, air dried at RT, and packaged into waterproof blisters.</s><s>The antigen used as competitor for test measurement was cortisol titrated in PBS (1 mg/mL stock solution in dimethyl sulfoxide [Sigma-Aldrich]) (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_5">E3</ref>).</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>FIG 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIG 1. Schematic representation of the EVA-assay principle, kinetic raw data record, and analyte quantification.</s><s>A, Surface-coated antigen or antibody ( ), evanescent surface (-------), analyte in biological sample ( ), allophycocyanin-labeled reagent ( ), excitation light ( ), emitted light ( ), interference filter ( ), filtered light ( ).</s><s>B, Correlation between penetration depth (y-axis) and emitted evanescence signal (x-axis).</s><s>Only fluorophors present at the bottom of the wells (ca.</s><s>200 nm, -------) are excited by the laser beam and able to emit photons.</s><s>C, Record of the fluorescence intensity (y-axis) as function of the time (x-axis).</s><s>D, Conversion of the fluorescence signal (y-axis) into analyte concentration fitted as sigmoid 4 parametric curves (x-axis).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>FIG 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIG 2. Quantitative detection of total serum IgE.</s><s>A, Sandwich assay with coated mouse monoclonal IgG anti-human IgE as catching antibody ( ) and a matched allophycocyanin-labeled mouse monoclonal IgG anti-human IgE developing antibody ( ) provided as ready-to-use dry EVA chip.</s><s>The only manipulation required is the addition of undiluted serum ( ).</s><s>B, Correlation between the ImmunoCAP values (x-axis) and EVA signal (y-axis) in 25 serum samples.</s><s>Quantitative detection of rAsp f 1-specific serum IgE.</s><s>C, Direct assay with coated rAsp f 1 allergen ( ) and allophycocyanin-labeled monoclonal mouse IgG anti-human IgE developing antibody ( ) provided as ready-to-use dry EVA chip.</s><s>The only manipulation required is the addition of undiluted serum ( ).</s><s>D, Correlation between the ImmunoCAP values (x-axis) and EVA signal (y-axis) in 18 serum samples.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="2,404.96,318.49,72.01,210.07" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>this article's Online Repository at www.jacionline.org)</s><s>and for the detection of b-HCG in different biological fluids (Fig E4).</s><s>In conclusion, the EVA technology has the potential to substitute all ELISA-based immunoassays with tests requiring only a single pipetting step by the end user and delivers reproducible high-quality quantitative results in 10 minutes or less when applied to the same sample over multiple days (data not shown).</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>FIG 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIG 1. Longitudinal trajectories of cat sensitization among children who lived in a home with a cat in early life and those who did not.</s><s>Predicted value of mean response is shown in graphical format along with 95% CIs.</s><s>A, SPT sensitization.</s><s>B, CRD sensitization to cat.</s><s>C, CRD components.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="4,304.27,65.59,232.55,498.05" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>FIG E1 .FIG E2 .</head><label>E1E2</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIG E1.</s><s>EVA chip (left panel): The chip (76 3 9.3 3 10.6 mm) has 2 areas: the upper part consists of 8 separated polystyrene wells and the lower part of a prism with surfaces of high optical quality.</s><s>EVA reader (right panel): Compact medical device (21.2 3 26.5 3 21.7 cm) with external barcode for automated patients' sample recognition, internal barcode for test recognition, electronics, and proprietary software for automated interpretation of the test results.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="6,109.08,65.59,370.75,162.99" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>FIG E3 .</head><label>E3</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIG E3.</s><s>Quantitative determination of serum cortisol levels in a competitive assay.</s><s>A, Coated cortisol-BSA conjugate ( ), free cortisol in a biological sample ( ); allophycocyanin-labeled anticortisol mAb ( ); (x) lack of binding.</s><s>B, Graph showing the correlation between concentration of cortisol (x-axis) and EVA signal (y-axis).</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="8,265.16,192.85,125.32,95.23" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>FIG E4 .</head><label>E4</label><figDesc><div><p><s>FIG E4.</s><s>Detection of b-HCG in plasma (:), urine (C), and saliva (n).</s><s>Chip were coated streptavidin followed by incubation with a biotinilated anti-b-HCG mAb, washing, and blocking.</s><s>After the addition of a matched allophycocyanin-labeled anti-b-HCG mAb, chips were air dried at RT and packaged into blisters to obtain ready-to-use tests.</s></p></div></figDesc><graphic coords="9,210.08,65.29,64.98,189.19" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>plasma, urine, saliva, see Fig E4 in this article's Online Repository at www.jacionline.org)</s><s>because the test is volume independent (see Fig E2 in this article's Online Repository at www.jacionline.org),</s><s>and insert the EVA chip into the EVA reader to obtain quantitative results in 10 minutes or less.</s><s>(Details are listed in this article's Online Repository at www.jacionline.org.)</s></p></div></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>Rhyner is employed by the Swiss Institute for Allergy and Asthma Research and Davos Diagnostics, has received grants from Kommission f€ ur technologische Innovation (KTI), and has stock/stock options in DDX.</s><s>M. Wiki has received grants from EU FP 7 (RaptaDiag 304814) and KTI (PFLS-LS 13066.1,</s><s>PFLS-LS 16009.1).</s><s>G. Quapil has patents paid to Davos Diagnostics licensed to Leuze Electronic.</s><s>T. Zuberbier has consultant arrangements with ALK, Almirall, Abbvie, Astellas, Bayer Health Care, Bencard, Berlin Chemie, FAES, HAL, Henkel, Kryolan, Leti, Meda, Menarini, Merck, MSD, Novartis, Pharmasquire, Quintiles, Serono, Stallergenes, Takeda, Teva, and UCB; and has the following organizational affiliations: Committee member, WHO-Initiative ''Allergic Rhinitis and its Impact on Asthma'' (ARIA); Member of the Board, German Society for Allergy and Clinical Immunology (DGAKI); Head, European Centre for Allergy Research Foundation; Secretary General, Global Allergy and Asthma European Network (GA 2 LEN); and Member, Committee on Allergy Diagnosis and Molecular Allergology, World Allergy Organisation.</s><s>C. A. Akdis has received grants from Actellion, EU FP 7 Projects Medall and Predicta, Allergopharma, the Swiss National Science Foundation, and the Christine K€ uhne Center for Allergy Research and Education.</s><s>R. Crameri has received a grant and travel support from the Swiss National Science Foundation and is cofounder and shareholder of Davos Diagnostics AG.</s></p></div></figDesc><table /><note><p><s>C.</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">J ALLERGY CLIN IMMUNOL VOLUME 141, NUMBER 2 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR 817</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">J ALLERGY CLIN IMMUNOL VOLUME 141, NUMBER 2</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">J ALLERGY CLIN IMMUNOL VOLUME 141, NUMBER 2 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR 820.e2</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="820">.e5 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>We thank Mrs Marion Kenk, Mrs Katharina Romer, Dr Carly Huitema, and Dr Judith Olzhausen for their excellent technical assistance.</s></p><p><s>Manfred Schawaller, PhD</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Blood donors</head><p><s>Blood was obtained from informed consented patients who were recruited from the outpatient clinic from the Department of Dermatology and Allergy, University of Z€ urich, Switzerland.</s><s>The study had been approved by the local ethic committee of the University of Z€ urich and was conducted according to the Declaration of Helsinki principles.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical analyses</head><p><s>Statistical analysis was performed using Wilcoxons signed rank test or Mann-Whitney U test (GraphPad Prism, San Diego, Calif).</s><s>*P &lt; .05;</s><s>**P &lt; .01;</s><s>***P &lt; .001.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Trends in in vitro diagnostics and mobile healthcare</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Vashist</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Luong</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biotechnol Adv</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="137" to="342" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Precision medicine in patients with allergic diseases: airway diseases and atopic dermatitis-PACTALL document of the European Academy of Allergy and Clinical Immunology and the American Academy of Allergy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Muraro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Lemanske</surname><genName>Jr</genName></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Hellings</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Akdis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bieber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Casale</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Asthma &amp; Immunology. J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">137</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1347" to="1358" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Assay of plasma insulin in human subjects by immunological methods</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Yaslow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Berson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">159</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1648" to="1649" />
			<date type="published" when="1959">1959</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Radioimmunoassay, enzyme and nonenzyme-based immuoassays</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Grange</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Lambert</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Br J Anesth</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="213" to="216" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new immunoassay based on fluorescence excitation by internal reflection spectroscopy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Kronick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Little</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Immunol Methods</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="240" />
			<date type="published" when="1975">1975</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The crux with a reliable in vitro and in vivo diagnosis of allergy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Crameri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Allergy</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="693" to="694" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evanescent wave fluorescence biosensors</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Taitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ligler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biosens Bioelectron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2470" to="2487" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evanescent wave fluorescence biosensors: advances of the last decade</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Taitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ligler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biosens Bioelectron</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">76</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="103" to="112" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diagnostic value of recombinant Aspergillus fumigatus allergen I/a for skin testing and serology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Crameri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Brust</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Suter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Menz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A new tool in the field of in-vitro diagnosis of allergy: preliminary results in the comparison of ImmunoCAPÓ 250 and the ImmunoCAPÓ ISAC</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gadisseur</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Chapelle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cavalier</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Chem Lab Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="277" to="280" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Available online</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jaci.2017.08.037</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jaci.2017.08.037" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-10-23">October 23. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A cuvette for a reader device for assaying substances using the evanescence field method</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>References E1</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Schawaller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Quapil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>EP 1&apos;371&apos;967 B1, 12.06.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cyanine dyelabelling reagents-carboxymethylindocyanine succinimidyl esters</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Southwick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Ernst</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tauriello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Parker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Mujumdar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Mujumdar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cytometry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="418" to="430" />
			<date type="published" when="1990">1990</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Diagnostic value of recombinant Aspergillus fumigatus allergen I/a for skin testing and serology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Moser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Crameri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Brust</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Suter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Menz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Allergy Clin Immunol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">93</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="11" />
			<date type="published" when="1994">1994</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
